<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0714-2799-0229-05" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">MANDEVILLE, Sir John</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 14, page 229</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:829774">Bees</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166263">Vices</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166236">Vice</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hn2p">Bees</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m6290g">Vice</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49p2wf9z">Travel</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194202799" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">MANDEVILLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir John</hi></label>, a
                    physician celebrated on account of his travels, was born at St Alban’s, about
                    the beginning of the fourteenth century. He received a liberal education, and
                    applied himself to the study of physic; but being at length seized with an
                    invincible desire of visiting distant parts of the globe, he left England in
                    1332, and did not return till thirty-four years thereafter. His friends, who had
                    long supposed him dead, did not know him when he re-appeared amongst them. He
                    had travelled throughout almost all the East, and had made himself master of a
                    great variety of languages. In particular, he had visited Scythia, Armenia,
                    Egypt, Arabia, Syria, Media, Mesopotamia, Persia, Chaldaea, Greece, Dalmatia,
                    and various other countries. He afterwards went to Liège, where he appears to
                    have passed under the name of <hi rend="italic">Joannes de</hi><hi rend="italic">Barbam,</hi> and died in November 1372. His design seems to have
                    been to commit to writing whatever he had heard, read, or learned, concerning
                    the places which he visited. Hence he has taken descriptions of monsters from
                    Pliny, copied accounts of miracles from legends, and related fabulous stories
                    upon the authority of authors who are now classed as mere romancers; so that
                    many, perhaps most, of the falsehoods in his work properly belong to preceding
                    writers, who, however much they may now be despised or disregarded, were
                    considered as of good credit at the time when he wrote. But there does not
                    appear to be any good reason why be should not be believed in regard to
                    circumstances which he relates from his own observation. Mandeville was a good
                    linguist, and wrote his Travels in Latin, from which he translated them into
                    French, then into English, and lastly into Italian. The English edition is
                    entitled “The Voiyage and Travaile of Ser John Maunde-ville, knight,” London,
                    1568, 4to, reprinted in 1684 in the same form, and again in 1727, 8vo. The
                    original English manuscript is in the Cotton Library. The English editions are
                    the more valuable to us, from having been written in the language used by our
                    countrymen three hundred years ago, when the orthography of English was so
                    little fixed that it seems to have been a fashionable affectation amongst
                    writers to spell the same words in the greatest variety <hi rend="italic">of</hi> ways imaginable. Addison’s pretended discovery of Sir John Mandeville’s
                    manuscripts, and the pleasant fiction of the freezing and thawing of several
                    short speeches made by Sir John in the territories of Nova Zembla, must be known
                    to most of our readers. (See <hi rend="italic">Tatler,</hi> with annotations,
                    vol. iv. No. 254, edition of 1806.)</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mandeville,</hi><hi rend="italic">Bernard,</hi> an author
                    of very considerable celebrity in his day, was born about the year 1670, in
                    Holland, where he studied physic, and took the degree of doctor in that faculty.
                    He afterwards came to England, and wrote several works which, though not devoid
                    of ingenuity, inculcate principles little calculated to advance the interests of
                    society. In 1709, he published his Virgin Unmasked, in the form of a dialogue
                    between an old maiden aunt and her niece, upon love, marriage, and other topics
                    therewith connected, which are treated in a manner not calculated to promote
                    female virtue and innocence. In 1711, appeared his Treatise on the Hypochondriac
                    and Hysteric Passions; a work which is divided into three dialogues, and
                    contains some shrewd remarks on the modern practice of physicians and
                    apothecaries. In 1714, he published a poem entitled the Grumbling Hive, or
                    Knaves turned Honest, upon which he afterwards wrote remarks, and enlarged the
                    whole into his well-known publication, The Fable of the Bees, or Private Vices
                    made Public Virtues, which was printed at London in 1723. In the preface to this
                    book be observes that, having met with several who, since the first publication
                    of his poem, had wilfully or ignorantly affirmed that it was intended as a
                    satire upon virtue and morality, and written for the encouragement of vice, he
                    had resolved, whenever it should be reprinted, to apprise the reader of the real
                    intent with which it had been composed, and of the object which he had in view
                    in the composition of the poem. In this, however, he was not by any means
                    fortunate; for the book was in the same year proscribed by the grand jury of
                    Middlesex, and severely animadverted on in a letter printed in the London
                    Journal of the 27th July 1723. Mandeville endeavoured to vindicate his book from
                    the imputations cast upon it both in the letter just mentioned and in the
                    presentment of the grand jury; though, as it appears, with but little success.
                    He was attacked by various writers, who all united in denouncing the principles
                    therein inculcated, and in representing them as equally hostile to morality and
                    pernicious <pb break="no" facs="nls:194202812" xml:id="kp-eb0714-2812-0230"/>to society. To these, however, he made no reply
                    until 1728, when he published, in one volume 8vo, the second part of the Fable
                    of the Bees, intended to illustrate the design and defend the intention of the
                    first. In 1720, appeared his Free Thoughts on Religion, founded on what is
                    called the rational system; and, in 1732, came out his Inquiry into the Origin
                    of Honour, and the Usefulness of Christianity in War, a work abounding in
                    questionable doctrines and paradoxical opinions. Mandeville died on the 21st of
                    January 1733, in the sixty-third year of his age. He is said to have been coarse
                    and overbearing in his manners, where he durst be so, yet a flatterer of the
                    great, and also of “some vulgar Dutch merchants who allowed him a pension.” He
                    lived in obscure lodgings in London, and never had much practice as a physician;
                    but he was patronised, it is said, by the first Earl of Macclesfield, at whose
                    table he was a frequent guest, and had there an unlimited license to indulge his
                    wit as well as his appetite, both of which appear to have been sufficiently
                    unscrupulous. In his writings there are many remarks equally ingenious and just;
                    he was a shrewd observer of men and manners, and often singularly happy in
                    recording the results of his experience; but the general principles inculcated
                    in some of his works have been almost universally reprobated, as calculated to
                    depress the standard of morality, if not to encourage vice and irréligion.
                    Amongst the assailants of the Fable of the Bees may be mentioned Dr Fiddes, in
                    the preface to his General Treatise of Morality, printed in 1724; Mr John
                    Dennis, in his Vice and Luxury Public Mischiefs, 1724; Mr William Law, in
                    Remarks upon the Fable of the Bees, 1724; Mr Bluet, in his Inquiry whether the
                    general Practice of Virtue tends to the Wealth or Poverty, Benefit or
                    Disadvantage of a People, 1725; Mr Hutcheson, author of an Inquiry into the
                    Original of our Ideas of Beauty and Virtue; and Mr Archibald Campbell, in his ’
                    <hi rend="italic">Aigiroaoγ∕a.</hi> Mandeville’s notions were likewise
                    animadverted on by Bishop Berkeley in his Alciphron, or the Minute Philosopher,
                    printed in 1732. This drew from Mandeville a reply, which was published the same
                    year in the form of a letter to Dion, occasioned by his book called Alciphron;
                    and there also appeared a pamphlet containing some Remarks on the Minute
                    Philosopher, in a Letter to a Country Clergyman from his friend in London, the
                    anonymous author of which (supposed to have been John Lord Harvey) interposes in
                    the controversy with much apparent impartiality. It is not necessary, however,
                    to multiply details respecting a work which is no longer read except by the
                    learned. The leading error in the Fable of the Bees consists in the author not
                    sufficiently distinguishing between what is and what ought to be; between vices
                    properly so called, and mere superfluities or articles of luxury and refinement,
                    which are the natural and useful accompaniments of certain conditions of life,
                    and, in themselves, neither objects of praise nor of censure. As to his
                    propensity to trace good actions to bad motives, and his disposition to exhibit
                    on all occasions the dark side of human nature, no apology can be offered for
                    it; and the best test of public estimation is the general neglect into which his
                    writings have fallen. (See the <hi rend="italic">Eirst Preliminary
                    Dissertation,</hi> prefixed to this work.) <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>