<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0256-0235-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VINCENT of Beauvais, or Vincentius Bellovacensis (9th
                    edition, volume 24, page 235)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q15g">Angels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t32v">Lion</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:999328">Lions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n256/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VINCENT <hi rend="smallcaps">of Beauvais</hi>, or <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Vincentius Bellovacensis</hi></label> (c. 1190-c. 1264), the
                    encyclopaedist of the Middle Ages, was probably a native of Beauvais.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>He is sometimes styled
                    Vincentius Burgundus; but, according to Μ. Daunou, this appellation cannot be
                    traced back further than the first half of the 15th century.</p></note> The
                    exact dates of his birth and death are unknown. A tolerably old tradition,
                    preserved by Louis a Valleoleti (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>. 1413), gives the
                    latter as 1264;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Apparently confirmed by the few enigmatical lines preserved by Échard from
                    his epitaph—</p><p><hi rend="italic">“Pertulit iste necem post annos mille
                    ducentos, Sexaginta decem sex habe, sex mihi retentos.”</hi></p></note> but
                    Tholomaeus de Luca, Vincent’s younger contemporary <hi rend="italic">(ob.</hi>
                    1321), seems to reckon him as living during the pontificate of Gregory X.
                    (1272-1276). If we assume 1264 as the year of his death, the immense volume of
                    his works forbids us to think he could have been born much later than 1190. Very
                    little is known of his career. A plausible conjecture makes him enter the house
                    of the Dominicans at Paris between 1215 and 1220, from which place a second
                    conjecture carries him to the Dominican monastery founded at Beauvais in
                    1228-29. There is no evidence to show that the Vincent who was sub-prior of this
                    foundation in 1246 is the encyclopaedist; nor indeed is it likely that a man of
                    such abnormally studious habits could have found time to attend to the daily
                    business routine of a monastic establishment. It is certain, however, that he at
                    one time held the post of “reader” at the monastery of Royaumont <hi
                    rend="italic">(Mons Regalis),</hi> not far from Paris, on the Oise, founded by
                    St Louis between 1228 and 1235. St Louis read the books that he compiled, and
                    supplied the funds for procuring copies of such authors as he required for his
                    compilations. Queen Margaret, her son Philip, and her son-in-law Theobald V. of
                    Champagne and Navarre are also named among those who urged him to the
                    composition of his “little works,” especially the <hi rend="italic">De
                    Institutione Principum.</hi> Though Vincent may well have been summoned to
                    Royaumont even before 1240, there is no actual proof that he lived there before
                    the return of Louis IX. and his wife from the Holy Land, early in the summer of
                    1254. But it is evident that he must have written his work <hi rend="italic">De
                    Eruditione Filiorum Regalium</hi> (where he styles himself as “Vincentius
                    Belvacensis, de ordine praedicatorum, qualiscumque lector in monasterio de
                    Regali Monte”) after this date and yet before January 1260, the approximate date
                    of his <hi rend="italic">Tractatus Consolatorius.</hi> When he wrote the latter
                    work he must have left Royaumont, as he speaks of returning from the funeral of
                    Prince Louis (15th January 1260) “ad nostram domum,” a phrase which can hardly
                    be explained otherwise than as referring to his own Dominican house, whether at
                    Beauvais or elsewhere.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Μαjus Speculum,</hi> the great compendium of all the
                    knowledge of the Middle Ages, as it left the pen of Vincent, seems to have
                    consisted of three parts only, viz., the <hi rend="italic">Speculum Naturale,
                    Doctrinale,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Historiale.</hi> Such, at least, is
                    Échard’s conclusion, derived from an examination of the earliest extant MSS. All
                    the printed editions, however, consist of four parts, the additional one being
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Speculum Morale.</hi> This has been clearly shown to
                    be the production of a later hand, and is ascribed by Échard to the period
                    between 1310 and 1325. In arrangement and style it is quite different from the
                    other three parts, and indeed it is mainly a compilation from Thomas Aquinas,
                    Stephen de Bourbon, and two or three other contemporary writers.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Speculum Naturale</hi> fills a bulky folio volume of 848
                    closely-printed double - columned pages. It is divided into thirty-two books and
                    3718 chapters. It is a vast summary of all the natural history known to western
                    Europe towards the middle of the 13th century. It is, as it were, the great
                    temple of mediaeval science, whose floor and walls are inlaid with an enormous
                    mosaic of skilfully-arranged passages from Latin, Greek, Arabic, and even Hebrew
                    authors. To each quotation, as he borrows it, Vincent prefixes the name of the
                    book and author from whom it is taken, distinguishing, however, his own remarks
                    by the word “actor.” The <hi rend="italic">Speculum Naturale</hi> is so
                    constructed that the various subjects are dealt with according to the order of
                    their creation; it is in fact a gigantic commentary on Genesis i. Thus bk. i.
                    opens with an account of the Trinity and its relation to creation; then follows
                    a similar series of chapters about angels, their attributes, powers, orders,
                    &amp;c., down to such minute points as their methods of communicating thought,
                    on which matter the author decides, in his own person, that they have a kind of
                    intelligible speech, and that with angels to think and to speak are not the same
                    process. The whole book, in fact, deals with such things as were with God “in
                    the beginning.” Bk. ii. treats of our own world, of light, colour, the four
                    elements, Lucifer, and his fallen angels, thus corresponding in the main with
                    the sensible world and the work of the first day. Bks. iii. and iv. deal with
                    the phenomena of the heavens and of time, which is measured by the motions of
                    the heavenly bodies, with the sky and all its wonders, fire, rain, thunder, dew,
                    winds, &amp;c. Bks. v.-xiv. treat of the sea and the dry land: they discourse of
                    the seas, the ocean, and the great rivers, agricultural operation's, metals,
                    precious stones, plants, herbs, with their seeds, grains, and juices, trees wild
                    and cultivated, their fruits and their saps. Under each species, where possible,
                    Vincent gives a chapter on its use in medicine, and he adopts for the most part
                    an alphabetical arrangement. In bk. vi. c. 7 he incidentally discusses what
                    would become of a stone if it were dropped down a hole, pierced right through
                    the earth, and, curiously enough, decides that it would stay in the centre. Bk.
                    xv. deals with astronomy—the moon, stars, and the zodiac, the sun, the planets,
                    the seasons, and the calendar. Bks. xvi. and xvii. treat of fowls and fishes,
                    mainly in alphabetical order and with reference to their medical qualities. Bks.
                    xviii.-xxii. deal in a similar way with domesticated and wild animals, including
                    the dog, serpents, bees, and insects; they also include a general treatise on
                    animal physiology spread over bks. xxi.-xxii. Bks. xxiii.-xxviii. discuss the
                    psychology, physiology, and anatomy of man, the five senses and their organs,
                    sleep, dreams, ecstasy, memory, reason, &amp;c. The remaining four books seem
                    more or less supplementary; the last (xxxii.) is a summary of geography and
                    history down to the year 1250, when the book seems to have been given to the
                    world, perhaps along with the <hi rend="italic">Speculum Historiale</hi> and
                    possibly an earlier form of the <hi rend="italic">Speculum Doctrinale.</hi></p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Speculum Doctrinale,</hi> in seventeen books and 2374
                    chapters, is a summary of all the scholastic knowledge of the age and does not
                    confine itself to natural history. It is intended to be a practical manual for
                    the student and the official alike; and, to fulfil this object, it treats of the
                    mechanic arts of life as well as the subtleties of the scholar, the duties of
                    the prince, and the tactics of the general. The first book, after defining
                    philosophy, &amp;c., gives a long Latin vocabulary of some 6000 or 7000 words.
                    Grammar, logic, rhetoric, and poetry are discussed in bks. ii. and iii., the
                    latter including several well-known fables, such as the Lion and the Mouse. Bk.
                    iv. treats of the virtues, each of which has two chapters of quotations allotted
                    to it, one in prose and the other in verse. Bk. v. is of a somewhat similar
                    nature. With bk. vi. we enter on the practical part of the work; it deals with
                    the <hi rend="italic">ars oeconomica,</hi> and gives directions for building,
                    gardening, sowing, reaping, rearing cattle, and tending vineyards; it includes
                    also a kind of agricultural almanac for each month in the year. Bks. vii. -ix.
                    have reference to the <hi rend="italic">ars politica</hi>: they contain rules
                    for the education of a prince and a summary of the forms, terms, and statutes of
                    canonical, civil, and criminal law. Bk. xi. is devoted to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >artes mechanicas,</hi> namely, those of weavers, smiths, armourers, merchants,
                    hunters, and even the general and the sailor. Bks. xii.-xiv. deal with medicine
                    both in practice and in theory: they contain practical rales for the
                    preservation of health according to the four seasons of the year, and treat of
                    various diseases from fever to gout. Bk. XV. deals with physics and may be
                    regarded as a summary of the <hi rend="italic">Speculum Naturale.</hi> Bk. xvi.
                    is given up to mathematics, under which head are included music, geometry,
                    astronomy, astrology, weights and measures, and metaphysics. It is noteworthy
                    that in this book Vincent shows a knowledge of the Arabic numerals, though he
                    does not call them by this name. With him the unit is termed “digitus”; when
                    multiplied by ten it becomes the “articulus”; while the combination of the
                    articulus and the digitus is the “numerus compositus.” In this chapter (xvi. 9),
                    which is superscribed “actor,” he clearly explains how the value of a number
                    increases tenfold with every place it is moved to the left. He is even
                    acquainted with the later invention of the “cifra” or cipher. The last book
                    (xvii. ) treats of theology or (as we should now say) mythology, and winds up
                    with an account of the Holy Scriptures and of the fathers, from Ignatius and
                    Dionysius the Areopagite to Jerome and Gregory the Great, and even of later
                    writers from Isidore and Bede, through Alcuin, Lanfranc, and Anselm, down to
                    Bernard of Clairvaux and the brethren of St Victor.</p>
                <p>As the fifteenth book of the <hi rend="italic">Speculum Doctrinale</hi> is a
                    summary of the <hi rend="italic">Speculum Naturale,</hi> so the <hi
                    rend="italic">Speculum Historiale</hi> may be regarded as the expansion of the
                    last book of the same work. It consists of thirty-one books divided into 3793
                    chapters. The first book opens with the mysteries of God and the angels, and
                    then passes on to the works of the six days and the creation of man. It includes
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n257/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0257-0236"/> dissertations on the various vices and virtues,
                    the different arts and sciences, and carries down the history of the world to
                    the sojourn in Egypt. The next eleven books (ii.-xii.) conduct us through sacred
                    and secular history down to the triumph of Christianity under Constantine. The
                    story of Barlaam and Josaphat occupies a great part of bk. xv.; and bk. xvi.
                    gives an account of Daniel’s nine kingdoms, in which account Vincent differs
                    from his professed authority, Sigebert of Gembloux, by reckoning England as the
                    fourth instead of the fifth. In the chapters devoted to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >origines</hi> of Britain he relies on the Brutus legend, but cannot carry his
                    catalogue of British or English kings further than 735, where he honestly
                    confesses that his authorities fail him. Seven more books bring us to the rise
                    of Mohammed (xxiii. ) and the days of Charlemagne (xxiv. ). Vincent’s
                    Charlemagne is a curious medley of the great emperor of history and the champion
                    of romance. He is at once the gigantic eater of Turpin, the huge warrior eight
                    feet high, who could lift the armed knight standing on his open hand to a level
                    with his head, the crusading conqueror of Jerusalem in days before the crusades,
                    and yet with all this the temperate drinker and admirer of St Augustine, as his
                    character had filtered down through various channels from the historical pages
                    of Eginhard. Bk. xxv. includes the first crusade, and in the course of bk.
                    xxix., which contains an account of the Tartars, the author enters on what is
                    almost contemporary history, winding up in bk. xxxi. with a short narrative of
                    the crusade of St Louis in 1250. One remarkable feature of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Speculum Historiale</hi> is Vincent’s constant habit of devoting several
                    chapters to selections from the writings of each great author, whether secular
                    or profane, as he mentions him in the course of his work. The extracts from
                    Cicero and Ovid, Origen and St John, Chrysostom, Augustine, and Jerome, are but
                    specimens of a useful custom which reaches its culminating point in bk. xxviii.,
                    which is devoted entirely to the writings of St Bernard. One main fault of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Speculum Historiale</hi> is the unduly large space devoted to
                    miracles. Four of the mediaeval historians from whom he quotes most frequently
                    are Sigebert of Gembloux, Hugh of Fleury, Helinand of Froidmont, and William of
                    Malmesbury, whom he uses for Continental as well as for English history.</p>
                <p>Vincent has thus hardly any claim to be reckoned as an original writer. But it is
                    difficult to speak too highly of his immense industry in collecting,
                    classifying, and arranging these three huge volumes of 80 books and 9885
                    chapters. The undertaking to combine all human knowledge into a single whole was
                    in itself a colossal one and could only have been born in a mind of no mean
                    order. Indeed more than six centuries passed before the idea was again
                    resuscitated; and even then it required a group of brilliant Frenchmen to do
                    what the old Dominican had carried out unaided. The number of writers quoted by
                    Vincent is almost incredible: in the <hi rend="italic">Speculum Naturale</hi>
                    alone no less than 350 distinct works are cited, and to these must be added at
                    least 100 more for the other two <hi rend="italic">Specula.</hi> His reading
                    ranges from Arabian philosophers and naturalists to Aristotle, Eusebius, Cicero,
                    Seneca, Julius Caesar (whom he calls Julius Celsus), and even the Jew Peter
                    Alphonso. But Hebrew, Arabic, and Greek he seems to have known solely through
                    one or other of the popular Latin versions.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">A list of Vincent’s works, both MS. and printed, will be found
                    in the</hi> Histoire Littéraire de France, <hi rend="italic">vol. xviii., and in
                    Echard. The</hi> Tractatus Consolatorius pro Morte Amici <hi rend="italic">and
                    the</hi> Liber de Eruditione Filiorum Regalium <hi rend="italic">(dedicated to
                    Queen Margaret) were printed by Amerbach at Basel in December 1480. The</hi>
                    Liber de Institutione Principum <hi rend="italic">has never yet been printed,
                    and the only MS. copy the writer of this article has been able to consult does
                    not contain in its prologue all the information which Échard seems to imply is
                    to be found there. The so-called first edition of the</hi> Speculum Majus, <hi
                    rend="italic">including the</hi> Speculum Morale, <hi rend="italic">ascribed to
                    Mentelin and long celebrated as the earliest work printed at Strasburg, has
                    lately been challenged as being only an earlier edition of Vincent’s three
                    genuine</hi> Specula <hi rend="italic">(</hi> c <hi rend="italic">. 1468-70),
                    with which has been bound up the</hi> Speculum Morale <hi rend="italic">first
                    printed by Mentelin (c. 1473-76). (T. A. A.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
