<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0131-0116-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VAUQUELIN (9th edition, volume 24, page 116)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w950p9z">Chemists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f285">Parents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86t6p">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:853570">Chemists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1053407">Parenting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n131/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VAUQUELIN</label>, Louis <hi rend="smallcaps">Nicolas</hi>
                    (1763-1829), French analytical chemist, was born at Saint-André-d’Hébertot in
                    Normandy on 16th May 1763. His parents, although very poor, sent him to school
                    to fit him for the coveted post of a gentleman’s servant at the chateau. At the
                    age of thirteen or fourteen Vauquelin went to Rouen as laboratory boy with an
                    apothecary. He did not remain long there; but his interest in chemistry was
                    fairly aroused, and he began to make experiments and take notes. His master,
                    finding him so engaged on one occasion, tore up his note-book and ordered him to
                    keep to his menial work for the future. Vauquelin had spirit enough to resent
                    this treatment: he borrowed six francs from a friend and walked to Paris to seek
                    his fortune. For a time his prospects were very dark: after getting and losing
                    two situations he became ill, was sent to the public hospital, and when
                    convalescent found himself once more without money or friends. At length,
                    however, he met a humane apothecary, Cheradame, who took him in and treated him
                    with kindness. Vauquelin at once resumed his studies, and devoted every spare
                    minute to learning. Cheradame introduced him to Fourcroy, who had himself worked
                    his way up from poverty, and from this time Vauquelin’s fortune was made.
                    Henceforward he devoted his attention to chemical analysis without intermission
                    or variety until his death, which occurred at his birthplace on 14th November
                    1829. At first his work appeared as that of his friend and patron, then in their
                    joint names; but in 1790 he commenced to publish on his own authority, and wrote
                    perhaps more papers than any other chemist has ever done. Either together or
                    successively Vauquelin held the offices of inspector of mines, professor at the
                    School of Mines and at the Polytechnic School, assayer of gold and silver goods,
                    professor of chemistry in the College of France, member of the Council of
                    Industry and Commerce, commissioner on the pharmacy laws, examiner to the
                    Polytechnic School, and, finally, was successor to Fourcroy himself; at this
                    last step all the other candidates retired in his favour.</p>
                <p>Vauquelin’s life was uneventful; his nature was quiet and retiring; he never
                    desired to mix with the world; and even in the turmoil of the Revolution his
                    interest centred in the laboratory. He was emphatically one who lived for his
                    work alone. He never married. He does not appear to have communicated with his
                    parents after he became wealthy. The one bright feature in the somewhat
                    colourless character of his later life was the fact that he supported Fourcroy’s
                    aged sisters after his old friend died.</p>
                <p>As an analyst Vauquelin came at the right time. The theory of chemistry was being
                    built afresh on a basis of experiment; all substances, natural and artificial,
                    were being classified by their compositi .n; and it would be hard to mention any
                    mineral or any plant or animal or product of life that Vauquelin did not
                    examine. With Fourcroy he drove the piles on which the first theories in pure
                    chemistry were founded; with Haüy he put mineralogy on a satisfactory footing;
                    but he himself was neither chemist nor mineralogist. Vauquelin’s name is
                    associated with 376 papers published between 1790 and 1833, and, with the
                    exception of one or two criticisms and claims for priority, these were all
                    simple records of patient and laborious analytical operations. He propounded no
                    theories, was guided by no generalizations, and was troubled by no problems save
                    those of his methods. Given a substance, he did his best to find its
                    composition, devising new processes where these seemed necessary, but this was
                    all. Considering the amount of work he did, one is surprised that only two new
                    elements are associated with his name. He detected glucina in beryl when
                    analysing that mineral for Haiiy, and in a red lead ore from Siberia he
                    discovered chromium, although, strange to say, eight years elapsed between his
                    first examination of the ore and his separation of chromic acid. It is even more
                    extraordinary that he never suspected the existence of alkaloids in the
                    vegetable and animal juices he was continually analysing. Cuvier in his <hi
                    rend="italic">éloge</hi> argues from this that without the concurrence of a
                    happy chance the greatest perseverance and the most admirable patience often
                    miss the mark; a more legitimate inference might be that work carried on “for
                    work’s ignoble sake” is fruitless in higher results, and that perseverance apart
                    from a definite aim can accomplish little.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
