<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0066-0053-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VAN (9th edition, volume 24, page 53)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r753">Lying</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h77">Mohammedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c552">Nestorians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4280544r">Kurds</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1164079">Vans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814767">Armenians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1036176">Nestorians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:989403">Kurds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937895">Gardens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204622">Georgia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n66/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VAN</label>, a city of Asiatic Turkey, capital of a vilayet,
                    is situated two miles to the east of the lake to which it gives its name, in 38°
                    30' N. lat. and 43° 18' E. long. It lies on the ill-defined borderland between
                    Armenia and Kurdistan, in an extremely fertile plain some 40 miles in circuit,
                    which is described as one of the gardens of the East, whence the local saying:
                    “Van in this world, heaven in the next.” Its low flat-roofed houses are grouped
                    irregularly at the southern base of a nummulitic limestone eminence, somewhat
                    resembling a camel’s back, which rises 100 feet sheer above the plain and is
                    crowned by the so-called citadel, the fortifications of which are mostly in a
                    dilapidated state. But it is naturally a position of great strength and of
                    considerable strategic importance, standing at the junction of two military
                    routes, which here diverge westwards through Mush and Kharpút to Asia Minor and
                    southwards to Mosul and Mesopotamia, besides commanding the approaches to the
                    Persian frontier at Kotúr and Bayezid. The town itself, which contains four
                    mosques, two large churches, an Armenian bazaar, baths, and caravanserais, is
                    enclosed within a double line of crenellated walls and ditches on the three
                    sides not protected by the rock; and beyond these enclosures lies the suburban
                    district of Baghlar, or the “Gardens.” The population, estimated at from 30,000
                    to 35,000, are Turks, except about 2000 Armenians and a few hundred Mohammedan
                    and Nestorian Kurds. Besides trade and agriculture, the inhabitants are engaged
                    in a few industries, such as the making of coarse cotton chintzes, a highly
                    prized goat-hair waterproof moire antique, a thick woollen cloth called <hi
                    rend="italic">shayak,</hi> and an excellent soap, prepared from the saline
                    efflorescences of Lakes Van and Erchek, which consist in about equal proportions
                    of the carbonate and sulphate of soda.</p>
                <p>Armenian tradition derives the name of Van from an Armenian king who reigned a
                    little before Alexander the Great, and speaks of an older city founded by
                    Semiramis (Shemiramagerd). This is of course fable; but the Vannic inscriptions
                    (vol. xiii. p. 116) show that the region was the seat of an Armenian kingdom,
                    whose native name was Biaina, as early as the 9th century <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi> In the isolated rock towering above the plain there are numerous
                    galleries, flights of steps, crypts, and cuneiform rock inscriptions, one of
                    which is trilingual, like that of Behistún, and like it relates the deeds of
                    Xerxes, son of Darius. Others are in the Haikan or Old Armenian language; while
                    for others scattered over the district a solution has been sought by Prof. Sayce
                    with doubtful success in the present language of Georgia.</p>
                <p>The vilayet of Van, one of the finest but also one of the least developed regions
                    of Asiatic Turkey, lies on the Persian frontier between Erzerum (north) and
                    Baghdad (south). It has an area of 15,000 square miles, with a population of
                    over 1,000,000.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lake Van.</hi></p>
                <p>Lake Van, called <hi rend="italic">Arsissa Palus</hi> by the ancients, and also
                    <hi rend="italic">Thos-pitis,</hi> from its Armenian name Tosp, is 80 miles long
                    and 30 broad, with a total area of 1500 square miles. Although of smaller extent
                    than Lake Urmia, it contains a much larger volume of water owing to its much
                    greater depth, which is at least 80 feet near Van and still more along the south
                    side. The lake stands about 5400 feet above sea-level on the south Armenian
                    plateau, which is encircled by the lofty ranges that bifurcate west and south
                    from Ararat and culminate in the Sipan-Dagh (12,000 feet) on the north side of
                    the lake. These mountains are clad with dense forests of beech, chestnut, ash,
                    and walnut, while the broad fertile belt between their base and the lake is
                    planted with melon gardens and orchards of plums, peaches, apricots, figs, and
                    pomegranates, festooned with a vine which yields a palatable wine.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n67/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0067-0054"/>
                <p>Lake Van, which is too brackish to be drinkable for man or beast, is inhabited by
                    a species of blay or bleak, which abound especially about the mouths of the
                    influents, and come to the surface when the spring floods spread over the
                    heavier saline layers. This lake is a completely land-locked basin, or at least
                    has no visible outlet. But the natives speak of underground channels through
                    which it communicates south-westwards with the head-waters of the Tigris,
                    attributing to the occasional obstruction of these channels the great
                    oscillations of level that have undoubtedly occurred in past and recent times.
                    In the 17th century and again about 1840 the water rose from 10 to 12 feet, and
                    is even now (1888) rising. Lake Erchek perhaps marks its extreme eastern limit
                    in former times. Lake Van is also indirectly connected with the Euphrates
                    through the little Lake of Nazik, which lies west of the Sipan-Dagh, on the
                    water-parting between the lacustrian and fluvial basins, and which by a rare
                    phenomenon sends emissaries to both. The narrow part of Lake Van, which runs for
                    nearly 40 miles towards the north-east, and gives the lake somewhat the
                    appearance of a frying-pan, is very shallow, and was once, according to
                    tradition, a fertile plain. The lake is not regularly navigated. Scattered along
                    the south-east shore are a few picturesque islets, one of which, Aktamar, is the
                    seat of an Armenian patriarch.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
