<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0132-0117-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VEDANTA (9th edition, volume 24, page 117)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77z92">Brahmanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gk13">Vedas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20s16z">Vedanta</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k64b29t">Upanishads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sn03">Rope</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4377609d">Intellect</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:837525">Brahmanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837522">Brahman</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837534">Brahmans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1164683">Vedanta</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n132/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VEDANTA</label>. The Vedanta is the first and most impressive
                    structure of Indian philosophy, the creed of intellectual Hindus, and the basis
                    of the popular Hindu religions. Its earliest germs lie in the Mantra portion of
                    the Veda. The Nāsadīyasūkta <hi rend="italic">(Rigveda,</hi> x. 129) propounds
                    the genesis of the world from an inscrutable principle, darkness, neither
                    existent nor non-existent, and from “one that breathed without afflation, other
                    than which there was nothing, beyond it nothing.” The genesis of things from a
                    universal soul is taught in the Purushasūkta <hi rend="italic">(Rigveda,</hi> x.
                    90). The unreality of the internal and external orders of things, and the sole
                    reality of a supreme spirit, or impersonal self, are set forth in the Upanishads
                    or later portions of the Veda. The teaching of these Upanishads explicated and
                    systematized, with little or no addition, constitutes the Vedānta. It has
                    innumerable expositors among the Indian schoolmen, of whom the most illustrious
                    is Śankarāchārya (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Sanskrit Literature,</hi> vol. xxi.
                    p. 290), a philosopher of Kerala or Malabar, who lived, it is supposed, between
                    650 and 740.</p>
                <p>The term “vedānta,” end of the Veda, is a synonym of “upanishad.” Upanishad is
                    said by the Indian scholiasts to denote, in the first place, the knowledge of
                    the impersonal self, the science of absolute being, <hi rend="italic"
                    >paramātmajnāna, brahmavidyā,</hi> in the second place, any treatise imparting
                    that knowledge. The doctrines of the Upanishads constitute the <hi rend="italic"
                    >jnānakānda,</hi> or gnostic portion of the Veda, as distinguished from the <hi
                    rend="italic">karmakānda, or</hi> ritual portion, comprised in the Samhitās and
                    Brāhmanas. They constitute also the <hi rend="italic">parāvidyā,</hi> or
                    superior science, dealing with cessation from volition and action, and leading
                    to extrication from metempsychosis, as distinguished from the <hi rend="italic"
                    >aparāvidyā,</hi> or inferior science, of the Samhitās, Brāhmanas, and Vedāngas,
                    which deals with action, and prolongs metempsychosis, leading only to higher
                    embodiments in this world or in the paradises of the deities. The Vedanta
                    philosophy is also called Aupanishadī Mīmānsā, Brāhmī Mīmānsā, Śārīrakī Mīmānsā.
                    The Sūtras or mnemonic formulas in which the system is developed are the
                    Vedāntasūtra, Brahmasūtra, and Śārīrakasūtra. They are ascribed to Vyāsa or
                    Bādarāyana. The system is further styled the Uttaramīmānsā, as an investigation
                    of the later portion of the Veda, as distinguished from the Pūrvamī-mānsā of
                    Jaimini, which is an investigation of the earlier portion of the Veda. The
                    purport of the Pūrvamīmānsā is <hi rend="italic">dharmajijn</hi> ā <hi
                    rend="italic">s</hi> ā <hi rend="italic">,</hi> inquiry into sacred
                    prescription; the purport of the Uttaramīmānsā, or Vedanta, is <hi rend="italic"
                    >brahmajijnāsā,</hi> inquiry into the real nature of the soul.</p>
                <p>There is, according to the Vedānta, but one substance or reality, ingenerable,
                    immutable, incorruptible, eternal, and this is the supreme spirit, the
                    impersonal self, the spiritual absolute, <hi rend="italic">ātman, paramātman,
                    brahman.</hi> The series of bodies and of environments through which the soul
                    appears to pass in its <hi rend="italic">μετεvσωμάτωσιs</hi> are illusive,
                    unreal, the figments of a fictitious illusion, <hi rend="italic">māyā, prakriti,
                    avyakta, avyākrita.</hi> The individual soul, <hi rend="italic">jīvātman,
                    vijnānātman,</hi> is personal only in fictitious semblance, only so long as it
                    is implicated in the series of transmigratory states, and is in truth
                    impersonal, one with the undifferenced self or Brahman. Its apparent and
                    fictitious individuality, and its apparent action and suffering, are the
                    individuality, the action, and the suffering of its illusory adjuncts, the
                    organism and the faculties. The unity of all souls in the one soul is the
                    highest truth, or, properly speaking, the only truth. On reaching and realizing
                    this truth the individual soul returns to its isolation or state of pure
                    indetermination. The duality of experience is fictitious and is surmounted by
                    the true intuition, <hi rend="italic">samyagjnāna.</hi> On the side of this
                    intuition there abides only “the existent, the intelligence, the beatitude.”</p>
                <p>Indian philosophy, and in particular its earliest form, the philosophy of the
                    Upanishads, or Vedānta, is governed throughout by two needs. First, there is the
                    need to give consistency and coherence to existing imagery, physical and
                    hyperphysical, to work out a conception of the totality of things. Secondly,
                    there is the need to put a stop to the miseries of metempsychosis. The idea of
                    transmigration, foreign to the Indo-Aryans of the Vedic hymns, appears to have
                    been taken up by their successors from the lower races with which they
                    intermingled, while retaining their supremacy among them. The Indo-Aryans of the
                    Vedic hymns found life pleasurable and exciting. They prayed to the gods for
                    their hundred years of it, and for an after-life with the whole body. This view
                    of life was replaced by one of horror and aversion, pervading everything Indian
                    with its gloom,—the expectation of care, bereavement, sickness, pain, and death,
                    in body after body, and through aeon after aeon.</p>
                <p>The effort to work out a coherent and complete idea by means of some principle of
                    unity appears in the following passages.</p>
                <p>In the Mundaka Upanishad: “Śaunaka, the householder, approached Angiras and Said,
                    ' Holy sir, by knowing what may all this universe be known ?’ Angiras replied,
                    ‘Two sciences are to be known which they that transmit the Veda propound, a
                    superior and an inferior science. Of these the inferior is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Rigυeda,</hi> Ac. The superior is that by which that undecaying being is
                    attained. That which none can see, none can handle, which is without kindred,
                    without colour, which has neither eyes nor ears, neither hands nor feet, which
                    is imperishable, infinitely diversified, everywhere present, wholly
                    imperceptible,—that is the immutable, that it is that <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n133/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0133-0118"/> sages behold as the source of all.’” In reference
                    to this text the scholiast Ānandagiri says, “If we know the <hi rend="italic"
                    >principium,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">upā-dāna,</hi> of things, we shall know
                    all things, inasmuch as all things have pre-existed in and are identical with
                    their causes.” Śankarāchārya says: “In daily life things are known to ordinary
                    people, if the unities are known under which those things are contained. For
                    example, individual pieces of gold are known under the nature of gold. Thus the
                    question of the text is, what is the one cause or emanatory principle of the
                    diversity of the universe, which known everything else is known ?”</p>
                <p>In the Chhāndogya Upanishad: “His father said to him, ‘ Svetaketu, thou art
                    high-minded, wise in thy own conceit, and proud. Tell me, hast thou asked for
                    that instruction by which the unheard is heard, the unthought thought, the
                    unknown known? ’ He answered, ‘ How is that instruction given, sir? ’ His father
                    said, ‘ Dear son, as by one lump of clay all that is made of clay becomes known,
                    being a modification of speech only, a change, a name, and the clay being the
                    only reality; as by one piece of iron all that is made of iron becomes known,
                    being a modification of speech only, a change, a name, and the iron being the
                    only reality; as by a pair of scissors all that is made of steel becomes known,
                    being a modification of speech only, a change, a name, and the steel being the
                    only reality :—such is the method of that instruction.’ Śvetaketu said, ‘ Sir,
                    doubtless my teacher knew not that, for, had he known it, how could he have
                    failed to tell me of it? Do thou therefore tell me of it.’ His father said, ‘ Be
                    it so, my dear son. Existent only, fair youth, was this in the beginning, one
                    only, without duality. Some indeed have said, non-existent only was this in the
                    beginning, one only, without duality. From that non-existent the existent
                    proceeded. But how could this be so? how could entity proceed out of non-entity?
                    ’”</p>
                <p>In the Śvetāśvatara Upanishad: “Those that proclaim Brahman say, What is the <hi
                    rend="italic">principium?</hi> Is it the impersonal self? From what have we
                    proceeded into life? into what do we return? By what are we upheld as we pass
                    through pleasures and pains? Is time the <hi rend="italic">principium?</hi> Is
                    the inherent property of things their <hi rend="italic">principium?</hi> Is
                    chance? Are the elements? Or is the individual soul the origin of all things? Or
                    is the sum of these the <hi rend="italic">principium?</hi> Neither is any one of
                    these, nor are all of these, the <hi rend="italic">principium,</hi> for it is
                    the impersonal self. It is not the individual self, for that is not independent,
                    being subject to pleasures and to pains.”</p>
                <p>The most powerful incentive to speculation was the yearning to escape the
                    miseries of transmigration. The soul has to pass through hunger and thirst,
                    sorrow, bereavement, decrepitude, death, in body after body, through age after
                    age. The individual soul has to look forward to continual suffering through a
                    countless series of embodiments. The series is without beginning, and, until the
                    individual learns his impersonal nature, without end. The series of
                    transmigratory spheres is projected and retracted, projected and retracted, from
                    before all time. Periods of evolution and of dissolution follow each other from
                    and to eternity. Any intervals of pleasure in the series of states through which
                    the soul passes are fugitive and unsatisfying. Even the pleasures of the
                    paradises of the deities are tainted with the fear of their expiry, and with the
                    inequalities amongst the participants. They also are part of the darkness in
                    which everything appears to be involved.</p>
                <p>The transmigratory series, or <hi rend="italic">samsara,</hi> is said to consist
                    of agents, actions, and fruits of action. The fruits of action are the bodies
                    and the environments allotted according to good or evil works. It is described
                    as an unbroken succession of evils,—birth, death, bereavement, and other
                    sorrows,—arising from transition from body to body. The individual soul floats
                    down the stream, “like a gourd upon the waters,” through embodiment after
                    embodiment, “from a patch of grass to the first of the divinities,” through
                    forms, inorganic and organic, vegetable, animal, human, ultrahuman, infernal,
                    and celestial. Each later stage is determined by the good or evil actions of the
                    individual in his earlier embodiments, by a blindly, a fatally operating law of
                    retribution, <hi rend="italic">adrishta.</hi> It is in conformity to this
                    principle that the <hi rend="italic">opifex aedificatorquc mundi deus,</hi> the
                    Demiurgus, Īśvara, puts together and rules the transmigratory series through the
                    successive aeons. It is this principle that clears the Demiurgus of the charge
                    of cruelty and injustice on account of the miseries and inequalities of life. In
                    all that it does and suffers the soul is reaping the fruits of its own actions.
                    Its actions proceed from preferences and aversions; its preferences and
                    aversions proceed from illusion, from its identifying itself with its <hi
                    rend="italic">per se</hi> unconscious senses, faculties, and organism. Merit, no
                    less than demerit, prolongs the series, and must be shunned as sin by the
                    aspirant to extrication.</p>
                <p>The world, then, was pictured by the Indian sages as a series, beginningless and
                    endless, of bodies and environments, through which personal souls—that is, the
                    one soul illusively viewing itself as many—pass. They pass through it for the
                    fruition of their works, <hi rend="italic">bhoga.</hi> The material of which it
                    is built up at each period of evolution is the cosmical illusion, <hi
                    rend="italic">ajnāna, aυidyā</hi>, <hi rend="italic">māyā, prakriti.</hi> This
                    is the principle by which soul mistakes itself for not-self, identifies itself
                    with fictitious adjuncts, <hi rend="italic">upādhi,</hi> with the organs, the
                    faculties, the organism. It is this illusion that gives rise to the unreal world
                    of duality, generable, mutable, corruptible, <hi rend="italic"
                    >avidyāparikalpitam dυaitam.</hi> It is illusion that projects the manifold of
                    experience, <hi rend="italic">nānātvapratyupasthāpikā māyā.</hi> As the flow of
                    transmigratory experiences is a succession of pleasures, pains, and neutral
                    states, the world-projecting illusion is defined to be pleasure, pain, and
                    indolence in equilibrium, <hi rend="italic">gunatrayasāmya.</hi> Pleasure, pain,
                    indifference, are the three <hi rend="italic">primordia rerum,</hi> the factors
                    of experience, the three strands of the rope that holds the soul in bondage. The
                    world-projecting illusion is further spoken of as the power of the Demiurgus,
                    his all-creative power, “the power of the divine spirit latent in its
                    constituent <hi rend="italic">primordia.”</hi> Thus Śankarāchārya in his Bhāshya
                    on the Vedāntasūtra says: “Name and form <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> all that
                    is heard and seen), the fictitious products of illusion, and the body of the
                    omniscient Demiurgus,— name and form, inexplicable as entity and as nonentity,
                    the germs of the transmigratory series,—are called the illusion, the power, the
                    productiveness <hi rend="italic">(prakriti)</hi> of the Demiurgus.” This
                    illusion is “neither existent nor non-existent, nor both in one, neither to be
                    explained as entity or as nonentity, fictitiously proceeding from and to all
                    eternity.” It is the illusory adjunct, <hi rend="italic">upādhi,</hi> of
                    Brahman. The internal and the external order of things are illusorily superposed
                    <hi rend="italic">(adhyasta, adhyāropita)</hi> upon the one and only real, the
                    impersonal self, by an illusion that has imagined itself from all eternity.</p>
                <p>To illustrate this in the figures of the Vedanta :—“As a spider extends and
                    retracts his threads, as plants grow up upon the earth, as the hairs of the head
                    and body spring from the living man, so the world arises from the imperishable.”
                    “As from the blazing fire its kindred sparks proceed in thousands, so the
                    diverse creatures proceed from that imperishable principle and into it return.”
                    All that presents itself to the soul in life after life, in sphere after sphere,
                    lies in fictitious semblance above the real, like the blueness seen in the sky,
                    though in the sky it has no existence; like the waters of a mirage; like the
                    bubbles on the surface of a river; like the airy fabric of a day-dream; like the
                    visions of a dream; like the silver seen, or seeming to be seen, on the shell of
                    the pearl-oyster; like the snake seen by the. belated traveller in a piece of
                    rope; like the gloom that surrounds the owl amidst the noontide glare. The soul
                    is confined to the body as within a prison. Its doings and sufferings are as
                    unreal as the apparent motion of the trees upon the bank to one sailing down the
                    river. The experience of life after life is the phantasmagory of a waking dream.
                    The unreality, the fictitious nature, of the things of experience is implied
                    everywhere in the Upanishads, and explicated with a profusion of imagery, by the
                    Indian schoolmen.</p>
                <p>The contents of this transmigratory series are supplied from the popular
                    religion, the earlier imagery being built up into the new conception. A place is
                    found in it for the deities and their paradises; only these deities and their
                    paradises, up to the Demiurgus himself, the Īśvara, and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >brahmaloka,</hi> the sphere of Brahma, are <hi rend="italic">per se</hi>
                    fictitious, unreal, illusory. A sojourn in these paradises is promised to the
                    religionist; assimilation to these deities is promised to those that worship
                    them with knowledge as well as with rites. Every man, the Indian schoolmen say,
                    shall be assimilated to the deity he worships. The highest reward of obedience
                    to sacred prescription and of worship of the deities is continuance in the <hi
                    rend="italic">brahmaloka</hi> till the end of an aeon, “relative immortality,”
                    <hi rend="italic">āpekshikam nityatvam.</hi> The only real immortality is
                    extrication from metempsychosis, reunion with the impersonal self, to be reached
                    not by works but by knowledge. They that delight in works, in rites, and the
                    spheres won by works, wander in darkness, are like the blind led by the blind.
                    Works and worship are, however, necessary to purify the intellect of the
                    aspirant to extrication. The process of purification may go on through several
                    successive lives. Good works performed without a view to recompense, and as an
                    offering to the Demiurgus, produce that purity of the internal faculties which
                    is requisite to the knowledge that terminates in liberation from metempsychosis.
                    They are thus instrumental to emancipation. Good works are necessary, says
                    Śankarāchārya, to the rise of the spiritual intuition; they are unnecessary when
                    it has once arisen. The qualified aspirant to liberation, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >adhikārin,</hi> must renounce all works, the good as well as the evil, for they
                    serve only to prolong the series of his embodiments. It is thus that the popular
                    religion is taken up and fitted into the Vedānta philosophy. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Karmavidyā</hi> is preliminary to <hi rend="italic">brahmavidyā.</hi></p>
                <p>Māyā, the inexplicable illusion, self-imagined, has been the unreal adjunct, <hi
                    rend="italic">upādhi,</hi> illusorily overspread upon Brahman from all eternity.
                    Brahman in its first connexion with ignorance or illusion is the Demiurgus,
                    Īśvara, Parameśvara, the constructive and superintending deity of the Vedāntins.
                    Before describing the process of things at a period of evolution, the conception
                    of Brahman, the impersonal self, must be unfolded in the terms of the
                    Vedānta.</p>
                <p>Brahman is the one and real that underlies the many and apparent. It is
                    ingenerable, immutable, incorruptible. It is the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n134/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0134-0119"/> ultimate residuum of abstraction, to be spoken of
                    only under negative predicates, <hi rend="italic">sarvanishedhāvadhi.</hi> It
                    transcends duality, the world of subject and object, <hi rend="italic"
                    >jnātrijneyabhāvātirikta.</hi> It is one only without internal and external
                    differences. “There is nothing before it, nor after it, nor within it, nor
                    without it.” It is everlasting, objectless cognition, <hi rend="italic">nityam
                    nirvishayam jhānam.</hi> “Of the sight of the seer there is no intermission, for
                    it is imperishable.” It is no object of the understanding, and it cannot be
                    expounded in language. “From it words turn back, with the thinking faculty, not
                    reaching it.” And this Brahman, this impersonal self, is I, <hi rend="italic"
                    >aham brahmāsmi.</hi></p>
                <p>The impersonal self, Brahman, is “existent, intelligence, beatitude,” <hi
                    rend="italic">sachchīdānanda</hi>:—existent, as imparting existence and
                    manifestations to everything that is known and seems to be, <hi rend="italic"
                    >sat-tāsphūrtipradatayâ</hi>; intelligence, as being self-luminous, as giving
                    light to all things, making to appear all things that do appear, <hi
                    rend="italic">svaprākāśaka, sarvāvabhāsaka</hi>; beatitude, as exempt from all
                    the miseries of metempsychosis, from evil, pain, and sorrow, a beatitude in
                    which there is no distinction between the bliss and the blissful subject, <hi
                    rend="italic">ananda</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ānandin,</hi> a beatitude like
                    the repose of dreamless sleep. It is “ever pure, intelligent, and free,” <hi
                    rend="italic">nitya-śuddhabuddhamukta</hi>:—pure, as free from desire and
                    aversion, and passionless, and as unaffected by illusory limitations, <hi
                    rend="italic">nirupādhika;</hi> intelligent, as irradiating all things,
                    illuminating the otherwise dark or unconscious modifications of the sensories
                    and intellects of personal spirits, and as illuminating the objects of those
                    modifications; free, as unaffected by the experiences of those spirits, exempt
                    from implication in the unreal. It is unmodifiable, and therefore neither knows,
                    nor acts, nor suffers. All cognition, action, and passion belong to the unreal
                    world of duality, and are the modifications of the sensory and intellect of
                    personal souls. These modifications would be dark, that is unconscious, but for
                    the light of the underlying real self, in which they shine forth. In the absence
                    of that real self the whole transmigratory order would be involved in blindness,
                    <hi rend="italic">tadabhāve jagadāndhyam prasajyeta.</hi> It is the
                    witness,—that is, the inner light—of the cognitions of the intellects of all
                    personal souls, <hi rend="italic">sarvabuddhipratyayasākshin.</hi> It is “the
                    light of lights beyond the darkness.” “To it the sun gives no light, nor the
                    moon and the stars, nor the lightning,—how then this fire? That, as it shines,
                    all the world shines after. By the light of that all this world shines
                    forth.”</p>
                <p>Brahman is said to abide especially within the heart, for it is there that the
                    internal faculties are lodged, and it is by the light of Brahman that they are
                    illumined. It is “the one spirit internal to all sentiencies,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >ekah sarvabhūtāntarātmā.</hi> It is present to them all, as the one sun is
                    mirrored upon many watery surfaces, as the ether one and indivisible in many
                    water-jars. The personal self, <hi rend="italic">the jīvātman,</hi> is said to
                    be resolved into the impersonal Brahman in three states,—in dreamless sleep, in
                    a period of dissolution between two aeons, and in emancipation. Dreamless sleep
                    is called a “daily dissolution,” <hi rend="italic">dainandinah
                    pralayah.</hi></p>
                <p>To Brahman alone belongs existence in the strict sense of the term, <hi
                    rend="italic">pāramārthikī sattā.</hi> It is; everything else appears to be. The
                    things of daily life have a conventional existence, sufficient for acting upon,
                    insufficient to the reason, <hi rend="italic">vyāvahārikī sattā.</hi> The silver
                    seen upon the shell, the snake seen in the piece of rope, have an apparent
                    existence, <hi rend="italic">prātibhāsikī sattā.</hi> For the sage conventional
                    existence is only apparent existence. At the foot of the scale of being stand
                    things impossible or absurd, <hi rend="italic">tuchcha,</hi> as the flowers of
                    the sky, the horns of the hare.</p>
                <p>Brahman is both the real and the operative cause of the world, the <hi
                    rend="italic">upādāna</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">nimitta.</hi> It is the
                    real cause, inasmuch as the transmigratory series fictitiously overlies it.
                    “Over this the sky, the earth, the welkin, are woven.” “Illusion,” says
                    Śankar-</p>
                <p>āchārya, “the aggregate of the powers of all causes and effects, reposes upon
                    Brahman, woven across and across it, as the potentiality of the banyan-tree
                    reposes in the seed of the tree.” “A fictitious object,” says Ānandagiri, “such
                    as the snake seen in a piece of rope, has a relatively real substratum in the
                    piece of rope; the transmigratory series, unreal because phenomenal, has a real
                    substance beneath it.” Brahman is the operative cause of the world, inasmuch as
                    the world-projecting illusion, inert of itself, becomes active by proximity to
                    Brahman, as iron is set in motion by the loadstone, the iron being inert of
                    itself, and the loadstone unmoved and unchanged.</p>
                <p>A process of evolution is called a “differentiation under name and form,” <hi
                    rend="italic">nāmarūpavyākarana.</hi> Processes of evolution and of dissolution
                    follow one another from eternity to eternity. Embodiments have proceeded from
                    works, and works from embodiments, in a series without beginning, as plants
                    proceed from seeds and seeds from plants. The series must proceed for each
                    individual until he learns his real nature, and becomes re-immersed in the
                    fontal unity. The one, the ultimate spiritual reality, is knowledge. The many is
                    ignorance, the semblance of knowledge, fictitious cognition, illusion. Ignorance
                    is not mere privation of knowledge: it has a kind of being; it is a false
                    identification of self with not-self, <hi rend="italic">bhāvarūpam ajnānam,
                    viparītajnānam ajnānam.</hi></p>
                <p>A process of evolution is as follows :—</p>
                <p>(1) Brahman overspread with illusion manifests itself as Īśvara, the Demiurgus.
                    The illusion of Īśvara is one with the illusion of each and every sentiency, and
                    of all sentiencies, or <hi rend="italic">jīvas.</hi> It is at once one and many.
                    As one it is the causal body of the Demiurgus; as many it is the beatific <hi
                    rend="italic">involucra</hi> of sentiencies, their <hi rend="italic"
                    >ānandama-yakosha.</hi> The Demiurgus and the sentiencies are one. Their state
                    is a state of dreamless sleep, a state of beatitude. Īśvara, the Demiurgus, is
                    the first figment of the cosmical illusion. The Demiurgus allots to
                    transmigrating spirits their several bodies and spheres of fruition, in
                    accordance with the law of retribution, and retracts them into himself at the
                    dissolution of the aeon. Knowledge of the real nature of his soul frees a man
                    from all fear of Īśvara.</p>
                <p>(2) Brahman overspread with illusion next manifests itself as Hiranyagarbha. As
                    one it manifests itself as Hiranyagarbha; as many it is the sentiencies or <hi
                    rend="italic">jivas</hi> in the state of dreaming sleep, <hi rend="italic"
                    >taijasa.</hi> Illusion has two powers,—that with which it envelops the soul,
                    hiding from it its proper nature, the <hi rend="italic">āvarana</hi> ś <hi
                    rend="italic">akti,</hi> and that with which it projects the seeming bodies and
                    their seeming spheres, the <hi rend="italic">vikshepaśakti.</hi> The elements,
                    as yet imperceptible, come into being. Out of these the tenuous <hi
                    rend="italic">involucra,</hi> the vestures of the spirit in its passage from
                    body to body, are evolved. Out of the imperceptible elements the perceptible are
                    afterwards evolved. The soul clothed upon with a tenuous <hi rend="italic"
                    >involucrum,</hi> and passing with it from body to body, from sphere to sphere,
                    is the individual soul, the <hi rend="italic">jīvātman.</hi> Hiranyagarbha is
                    spirit identifying itself w’ith the as yet imperceptible elements, and with the
                    tenuous <hi rend="italic">involucra.</hi> It passes through them as a thread
                    passes through the beads of a necklace, and is called the thread-soul,
                    Sūtrātman.</p>
                <p>(3) Brahman overspread with illusion finally manifests itself as Vaiśvānara or
                    Virāt. As one it is Vaiśvānara, as many it is the sentiencies or <hi
                    rend="italic">jivas</hi> in the waking state, <hi rend="italic">visva.</hi>
                    Vaiśvānara is the Purusha of the Purushasūkta: “A thousand heads has Purusha, a
                    thousand eyes, a thousand feet.” Purusha is Brahman, illusorily identifying
                    itself with the perceptible elements, and w’ith the bodies of all transmigrating
                    spirits. Every sentiency, every man, in the waking state, is Brahman illusively
                    identified with this or that visible and tangible organism. The perceptible are
                    evolved out of the imperceptible elements by the process of quintuplication, <hi
                    rend="italic">panchīkarana.</hi> Each of the later of the five elements has the
                    property of the earlier elements in addition to its own. Ether has the property
                    of sound; air the properties of sound and tangibility; fire the properties of
                    sound, tangibility, and colour; water the properties of sound, tangibility,
                    colour, and taste; earth the properties of sound, tangibility, colour, taste,
                    and smell. Of these elements the bodies of transmigrating spirits, and their
                    several spheres of fruition, are composed.</p>
                <p>Such is the order of evolution. An evolution is conceived by the Vedāntins as an
                    instantaneous process, rapid as a flash of light.</p>
                <p>There are, then, three orders of intelligence in three states of experience—(1)
                    the Demiurgus, and the individual soul in the state of dreamless sleep; (2)
                    Hiranyagarbha, and the individual soul in the state of dreaming sleep; (3)
                    Vaiśvānara, and the individual soul in the waking state.</p>
                <p>There are for these three orders of bodies—(1) the causal body of the Demiurgus,
                    and the wrapper of bliss; (2) the tenuous <hi rend="italic">involucra</hi> of
                    transmigrating spirits—(these are made up of three wrappers, laid above the
                    wrapper of bliss, viz., the cognitional wrapper, or the intellect and the organs
                    of sense; the sensorial wrapper, or the common sensory and the organs of action;
                    the respiratory wrapper, or the five vital airs, and the organs of action);—(3)
                    the gross <hi rend="italic">involucra,</hi> the visible and tangible bodies of
                    transmigrating spirits, or nutrimentitious wrapper. Invested in these five
                    successive wrappers, one above the other, the impersonal self manifests itself
                    in the shape of innumerable sentiencies, as beast, as man, as god. It is present
                    in all, as the one sun reflects itself upon many pools, as the one ether spreads
                    itself through many water-jars. It is at the same time, apart from these
                    illusory adjuncts, untouched with mundane sorrows, as the sun looks dow n upon
                    the impurities of the earth without defilement.</p>
                <p>Out of these successive <hi rend="italic">involucra</hi> the individual soul, to
                    extricate itself from metempsychosis, has to extract itself “like the pith out
                    of a reed.” It extracts itself by returning to its proper nature. And to learn
                    and recover his proper nature, his real self, a man must purify his intellect,
                    perhaps through several lives, and must put himself under a spiritual preceptor
                    to whom the Vedantic doctrine has descended through an unbroken line of
                    authorized exponents. Brahman is to be known by traditional exponents, not by
                    the mere exercise of the intellect. “Not he that has not ceased from evil, not
                    he that rests not from sensations, not he that is not concentrated, not he whose
                    faculties are not quiescent, can reach that self by the intuition.” “This
                    spiritual reality is not to be reached by learning, by memory, by much spiritual
                    study. But if he choose this reality it may be reached by him; to him the self
                    unfolds its own essence.”</p>
                <p>The aspirant to extrication, the <hi rend="italic">mumukshu,</hi> must renounce
                    everything<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n135/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0135-0120"/> in this and in future spheres of fruition. He
                    must become a <hi rend="italic">sannyāsin.</hi> In the words of the
                    Brihadāranyaka Upanishad: " They that know the breath of the breath, the eye of
                    the eye, the ear of the ear, the thought of the thought, they have seen this
                    fontal spirit, primeval, existing from before all time. It is to be seen with
                    the intellect only. In it there is nought that is manifold. From death to death
                    he goes that looks on this as manifold. It is to be seen in one way only. It is
                    unthinkable, imperishable, unsullied, beyond illusion. Unborn, infinite,
                    imperishable, is Self. Let the patient Brahman know that and learn wisdom. Let
                    him not learn many words, for that is a weariness of the voice. This indeed is
                    the great, Unborn Self. This it is that holy mendicants yearn after in setting
                    out upon their wandering life. Yearning after this it was that the ancient sages
                    desired no offspring, saying, ‘ What have we to do with children, we to whom
                    this spiritual reality belongs in the real sphere? They arose, and forsook the
                    desire of children, of wealth, and of worldly existence, and set out as holy
                    mendicants.’” The tardy aspirant, <hi rend="italic">mandādhikārin,</hi> who
                    seeks for gradual emancipation, <hi rend="italic">kramamukti,</hi> is enjoined
                    to mutter and to ponder incessantly upon the mystic syllable Om. This is said to
                    be the nearest image of Brahman, to be identical with all words, and with all
                    things.</p>
                <p>“They make mistake who leave me out, Me, when they fly, I am the wings;</p>
                <p>I am the doubter and the doubt, And I the hymn the Brahman sings."</p>
                <p>The spiritual preceptor proceeds by the way of “illusory superposition, and the
                    sublation of that superposition,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >adhyāropāpavā-danyâyena.</hi> Illusory superposition is the viewing of the
                    unreal, the fictitious series of souls and their environments, upon the one and
                    only real. The sublation of this superposition is the position of the impersonal
                    self, Brahman, as the sole reality, and the recognition of the falsity of the
                    fictitious illusion and of all its figments. The doctrine of sublation is
                    expounded as follows in Nrisinhasaras-vati’s Subodhinī: "Sublation is the
                    annulment of the series proceeding from illusion. The states in this series are
                    illusory emanations, <hi rend="italic">vivartta,</hi> of Brahman, and to annul
                    them is to abide as pure, undifferenced spirit. The apparent snake of the
                    familiar example, seen by the belated wayfarer, illusorily proceeds from, or is
                    fictitiously produced upon, the piece of rope, without any change of nature
                    taking place in the rope itself. It is sublated when the piece of rope resumes
                    its proper shape. A thing may retain its own nature, and become otherwise than
                    it was, in two manners, viz., by modification, <hi rend="italic">parināma,</hi>
                    and by illusory emanation, <hi rend="italic">vivartta.</hi> Modification is when
                    a thing really quits its proper form and takes another shape. Milk, for example,
                    quits its proper form to take the form of curds and whey. Illusory emanation is
                    where a thing, without quitting its proper form, takes another and a fictitious
                    shape. The piece of rope takes the fictitious appearance of a snake without
                    quitting its proper form: it remains a piece of rope. The transmigratory series
                    is not allowed in the Vedānta to be a modification of Brahman. Brahman, if
                    modified as the milk is modified, would be mutable, and therefore perishable.
                    The doctrine of illusory emanation is not exposed to this difficulty. The series
                    superposed on Brahman being fictitious, Brahman remains unchanged. A fictitious
                    thing, then, is said to be sublated when only the real thing abides upon which
                    it was imposed. The transmigratory series is sublated when only the pure
                    intelligence remains upon which it was fictitiously outspread.”</p>
                <p>By continuous contemplation the aspirant refunds each entity into the entity from
                    which it emanated, till he passes beyond illusion to the fontal unity of
                    undifferenced spiritual existence. He follows the order of dissolution, the
                    inverse of the order of evolution, till he arrives at Brahman. He thus realizes
                    the import of the great text, the <hi rend="italic">mahāvākya,</hi> “that art
                    thou,” <hi rend="italic">tat tvam asi</hi> (Chhān-dogya Upanishad, sixth
                    Prapāthaka). Particular souls are one with the universal soul, the Demiurgus,
                    and the universal soul is one with Brahman. This knowledge is the last and
                    highest of cognitions, the final modification of the aspirant’s intellect as it
                    melts away into the fontal unity. This is the <hi rend="italic">phalitam brahma,
                    “</hi> the resultant impersonal self.” The <hi rend="italic">phalitam
                    brahma</hi> is a modification of the aspirant’s sensorium, his <hi rend="italic"
                    >antahkarana,</hi> and passes away, that the impersonal self, the supreme
                    spirit, may alone remain. He to whose inner faculties this vision is present has
                    the spiritual intuition, <hi rend="italic">samyagdarśana.</hi> He is extricated
                    but alive, <hi rend="italic">jīvanmukta,</hi> and remains in the body till those
                    merits are exhausted which have led to his present life. Disengaged from
                    metempsychosis, and still in the body, the perfected sage is said to be
                    untouched by merit and demerit, unsoiled by sin, uninjured by anything he does
                    or leaves undone. No evil, the scholiasts say, arises from this freedom, as the
                    purificatory virtues of the aspirant cling to the accomplished seer,—his
                    humility, his sincerity, his tenderness to all, remaining upon him like
                    ornaments even after the rise of the spiritual intuition. Finally his body falls
                    away, and his spirit is freed for ever. It abides in itself. It is undifferenced
                    existence, undifferenced intelligence, undifferenced beatitude. This is the
                    consummation of <hi rend="italic">brahmavidyā.</hi></p>
                <p>The soul has found itself, has loosed itself, not that in verity it is ever
                    loosed or bound. From the highest point of view bondage and liberation,
                    implication and extrication, are unreal. The Vedāntins compare the individual
                    spirit seeking to regain its impersonal nature to one searching for that which
                    he unwittingly carries about with him, to a man trembling at his own shadow. The
                    soul of the finished sage knows itself, and therefore is itself. In the words of
                    the Mundaka Upanishad: “Burst are his heart’s ties, broken his doubts, his
                    merits spent, when he has seen the principle supreme at once and not supreme. In
                    the golden, perfect <hi rend="italic">involucrum</hi> is the unsullied Self,
                    without parts, luminous, which they know that know the soul.” “As all rivers
                    flowing onwards disappear in the sea, quitting name and form, so the sage
                    extricated from name and form enters into the self-luminous spirit beyond the
                    last of things, beyond illusion.” In the words of the Brihadāranyaka: “He that
                    knows it is no longer sullied by evil deeds. Repressing his senses, quiescent,
                    free from all desires, ready to suffer all things, his thoughts fixed, he sees
                    within himself the Self, the universal soul. Imperfection reaches him no more;
                    he passes beyond imperfection. He burns up all his imperfection. He that knows
                    Brahman becomes free from imperfection, free from uncertainty, insphered in
                    Brahman. This same great, unborn, Self is undecaying, undying, imperishable,
                    beyond all fear. Brahman is beyond all fear. He that knows this becomes the
                    spiritual reality beyond all fear.” (A. E. G. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
