<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0080-0065-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VANE, Sir Henry (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    65)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sb3x770">Vanes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07378">Covenanters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90242v">Puritans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1084357">Puritans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993547">Laude</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881906">Covenanters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n80/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VANE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Henry</hi></label>
                    (1612-1662), the younger, was the son of Sir Henry Vane and Frances Darcy. His
                    father, of an ancient family in Durham, was secretary of state and comptroller
                    of the household under Charles I. Henry was born in 1612 at Hadlow in Kent; and
                    after an education at Westminster, where he was noted for his high and reckless
                    spirits, and at Magdalen, Oxford, where he neither matriculated nor took his
                    degree, he was sent to France and Geneva. Here he no doubt acquired the strongly
                    Puritan views for which he had been prepared by a remarkable change of mind when
                    quite a boy. In spite of the personal efforts of Laud, who made the attempt at
                    the king’s request, he refused to give them up, and fell especially under the
                    influence of Pym. In 1635 he emigrated to Massachusetts, where he was elected
                    governor in 1636, though only twenty-four years of age. After two years of
                    office, during which he showed striking administrative ability, he was defeated
                    by Winthrop, the former governor, chiefly on account of the protection he had
                    given to Mrs Hutchinson in the religious controversies which she raised.</p>
                <p>Vane returned to England in August 1637. Being elected to the Short Parliament
                    for Kingston-upon-Hull, he speedily became a leader of the Independents and a
                    marked man. In order to secure him for the court he was made joint-treasurer of
                    the navy with Sir W. Russell, and was knighted. In November 1640 he was again
                    elected for Hull to the Long Parliament. Accidentally finding among his father’s
                    papers some notes of Strafford’s advice to the king after the dissolution of the
                    Short Parliament, in which Strafford justified the use of force, he handed them
                    to Pym, and on 10th April 1641 was examined upon them by the House; this
                    disclosure was largely instrumental in bringing about Strafford’s downfall. He
                    carried up the impeachment of Laud from the Commons, was a strong supporter,
                    when on the committee of religion, of the “Root and Branch” bill, and in June
                    1641 put forward a scheme of church government by which commissioners, half lay
                    and half cleric, were to assume ecclesiastical jurisdiction in each diocese. He
                    was, in fact, foremost in all the doings of the Long Parliament. When war broke
                    out he surrendered his office of treasurer of the navy, but was replaced in it
                    by the Parliament. Hereupon he gave a rare example of disinterestedness by
                    relinquishing all the profits of the office, stated at £30,000 a year,
                    stipulating only that £1000 should be paid to a deputy. In August 1642 he was on
                    the committee of defence. In 1643 he was the leading man among the commissioners
                    sent to treat for a league with the Scots. Vane, who was bitterly opposed to the
                    tyranny of the Presbyterian system, was successful in two important points. The
                    aim of the Scots was chiefly the propagation of their discipline in England and
                    Wales, and for this they wanted only a “covenant.” The English desired a
                    political “league.” Vane succeeded in getting the bond termed the Solemn League
                    and Covenant, and further in substituting the expression <hi rend="italic"
                    >“according to the word of God</hi> and the example of the best Reformed
                    churches” for the latter phrase alone. In the Westminster Assembly, too, he
                    joined Cromwell in insisting upon full religious liberty, and in opposing the
                    view that the taking of the Covenant should be necessary for ordination. In 1644
                    he was charged by Essex with holding communication with the court, but explained
                    that he had done so in order to acquire information of the Royalist plans, and
                    was fully acquitted by the House of Lords. He was on the committee of two
                    kingdoms, and was engaged in the negotiations with Charles at Uxbridge in 1645.
                    He was, with Cromwell, a prime mover in the Self-Denying Ordinance and the New
                    Model, and it was he who suggested the filling up of the vacant seats in
                    parliament. His views of government at this time and throughout his life may be
                    best studied in an important paper, the <hi rend="italic">People's Case
                    Stated,</hi> written shortly before his death. “The power which is directive,
                    and states and ascertains the morality of the rule of obedience, is in the hand
                    of God; but the original, from whence all just power arises, which is
                    magistratical and coercitive, is from the will or free gift of the people, who
                    may either keep the power in themselves or give up their subjection and will in
                    the hand of another.” The king, then, having transgressed the condition, and
                    having been conquered, the people were free to change their form of government
                    and, if they pleased, resort to a republic. In 1646 Vane was one of the English
                    commissioners for the preservation of peace with Scotland, and in 1648 was
                    appointed with others to negotiate with Charles at the Isle of Wight. Radical as
                    were his views, he refused all participation in Pride’s “purge ”—the point where
                    he first broke with Cromwell—and remained in privacy at Raby Castle in Durham
                    until after the king’s death, a measure in which he took no part. In 1649,
                    however, he returned to London and was placed on the council of state, though he
                    refused to take the oath which expressed approbation of the king’s execution. He
                    was chairman of the committee appointed to consider the mode of election of
                    future parliaments, and his proposals were brought forward in January 1650. He
                    acknowledged the Commonwealth only so far as he found it “consonant to the
                    principles which have given rise to the law and the monarchy itself in England,”
                    and he recognized in a parliament, conforming in other respects to the ancient
                    laws, the supreme authority of the state, whether there were a king at the head
                    of it or not. He wished to reform the franchise on the property basis, to
                    disfranchise some of the existing boroughs, and to give increased representation
                    to the large towns; the sitting members, however, were to retain their seats. In
                    this he was opposed by Cromwell, who desired an entirely new parliament and the
                    supremacy of the army representation; and Vane stands henceforward as the
                    champion of the doctrine of pure parliamentary government. His most useful
                    qualities were exhibited, however, when in March 1653 he became the head of the
                    commission for managing the army and navy. It was by his exertions in
                    organization that Blake was fitted out with the fleet with which Van Tromp was
                    defeated and the supremacy of England at sea assured. It was at this time that
                    Milton’s sonnet was addressed to him. On 20th April Cromwell forcibly dissolved
                    the Long Parliament, when Vane especially received from the Protector studied
                    insult. He was, however, almost at once invited to rejoin the Government. “He
                    answered the invitation by a letter extracted from the Apocalypse wherein the
                    reign of the saints is mentioned, which faith he believes will now begin.” In
                    his retirement at Raby he now wrote the <hi rend="italic">Retired Man’s
                    Meditations.</hi> In 1656 he proposed in <hi rend="italic">A Healing
                    Question</hi> a new form of government, insisting as before upon a Puritan <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n81/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0081-0066"/> parliament supreme over the army. This he sent to
                    Cromwell, and so alarmed was the Protector at the interest it excited that Vane
                    was summoned on 12th August to the council in consequence. Refusing to give
                    security not to disturb the public peace, he was on 9th September sent prisoner
                    to Carisbrooke Castle, and there remained until 31st December. He had
                    previously, according to his opponents, excited the jealousy of the Government
                    by “going up and down among the Quakers, and endeavouring to withdraw them from
                    their submission to the Government.” After the death of Cromwell he stood for
                    Kingston and Bristol successively, and was elected, but the court managers gave
                    the certificate of election to the defeated candidates; finally, however, he was
                    chosen for Whitchurch and took his seat on 27th January 1659, at the head of the
                    small body of forty republicans. He was at once urgent in pressing that, before
                    Richard Cromwell, for whom he had a great contempt, was acknowledged protector,
                    the limitations of his power, and the full security of parliament and subjects,
                    should be settled. Upon Richard’s abdication he joined the army leaders in
                    reviving the Rump; and, when the breach occurred between it and the army, he
                    adhered to the latter, accepting a commission from them. He was one of the
                    committee of safety and also of the council of state appointed in May; he was,
                    too, chairman of the army and navy commission, and soon afterwards of another
                    special commission for the navy. In September he was made president of the
                    council. He had, morever, in May, been appointed with Lambert and others to
                    treat with the Dutch ambassador for freeing the commerce of the Baltic. When
                    Monk arrived in London Vane was ordered to his seat in Lincolnshire, having been
                    discharged from the parliament for espousing the cause of the army.</p>
                <p>At the Restoration Vane was imprisoned in the Tower by the king’s order. After
                    several conferences between the Houses of Parliament it was agreed that he
                    should be excepted from the indemnity bill, but that a petition should be sent
                    to Charles asking that his life might be spared. The petition was granted.
                    During the conferences he had been moved from prison to prison, and was finally
                    placed in a castle in the Scilly Isles. In his captivity he wrote the <hi
                    rend="italic">People's Case Stated,</hi> with many other political and religious
                    works of the highest eloquence and beauty. On 7th March 1662, the Convention
                    Parliament being no longer in existence, he was taken to London, and on 2d June
                    put upon his trial, which was conducted with a shameless absence of equity. He
                    was refused the assistance of counsel and was not allowed to see the indictment
                    before it was read. In his own behalf he spoke courageously and well, pleading
                    the authority of the Long Parliament for his acts, and maintaining that the
                    House of Commons, “representing the whole body of the people in case of a
                    difference between the authority, royal and politic, possessed a just power to
                    defend the right of the people, and to authorize the people of England and every
                    one of them to defend them.” Charles, however, was determined that he should
                    die, and, in spite of his answer to the petition mentioned above, wrote himself
                    to Clarendon declaring that Vane was “too dangerous a man to let live, if we can
                    honestly put him out of the way.” He was therefore sentenced on 11th June to
                    death. On the 14th he was taken out to execution, and died with the serenity and
                    courage which had marked his life. (O. A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
