<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0713-0133-0670-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MADEIRA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 13, page 670</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:827893">Basalt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193210133" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MADEIRA</label>, an island situated off the western coast of
                    Africa, about fifty-four miles in length by twenty-one in breadth. It is a
                    country of rocks, consisting of a number of lofty mountains, on the declivities
                    of which all the productions of the island are raised. The best account of the
                    island is that by the late Mr Edward Bowdich, whose journey over the island we
                    shall follow. The country at the back and sides of Funchal, the capital,
                    presents the broken outline of a segment of a vast natural amphitheatre of
                    basaltic peaks and mountains, rising to 3800 feet behind the Mount Church, which
                    is the most striking edifice in this beautiful landscape, and is elevated 1900
                    feet above the sea, presenting the most picturesque breaks and vistas,
                    intersected by ravines and torrents, and covered with undulating and rugged
                    ridges and sheets of basalt, diverging from the more central heights, and
                    descending boldly to the sea. The basalt is both columnar and granular; the
                    former is, generally speaking, compact, of a broad conchoidal fracture,
                    splitting in horizontal laminae, or at right angles to the prism, dark gray
                    within or on the surface of a fresh fracture, which becomes covered with a
                    superficial decomposing coat of brownish red, with age-inducing brittleness, and
                    passing ultimately into yellowish white and dull brown; a moderately thin plate
                    of the columnar basalt, when covered exteriorly with red powder, will snap
                    between the fingers. The next place of importance is the Peak of Ariero, about
                    three hours’ ride from Funchal. The latter part of the ascent is along the
                    barren rocks of basalt and red tuffa, which form the highest outline of the view
                    behind from Funchal, and are 3700 feet above the sea. The peak is 5446 feet
                    above the level of the sea, and is covered with vegetation to the top. The
                    Coural, or sheepfold, is an immense valley near the village of Comera de Lobos,
                    completely surrounded with almost perpendicular hills, and in no part less than
                    1000 feet in height. Round a part of three cliffs is a narrow road, winding
                    along the brink of the precipices, often cut out of the solid rock, across peaks
                    and gaps which were formerly impassable. This road has been of great importance
                    in connecting the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193210146"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0713-0146-0671"/>interior of the island with the sea coast, and
                    useful for transporting the productions of the country to the capital.</p>
                <p>The soil in every part is extremely fertile; the hills are covered with a
                    luxuriant vegetation; and the finest flowers, sometimes of aquatic species, are
                    found growing on the summits, being supplied with a moisture from the constant
                    vicinity of the clouds. Trees and shrubs of the finest kinds are everywhere
                    found in great abundance; and tropical plants which have strayed from the
                    gardens soon become perfectly naturalized to the soil. The Portuguese formerly
                    procured their principal supplies of sugar from this place; but not being able
                    to compete with the West Indian planters, the inhabitants betook themselves to
                    the culture of the vine, which has since become the chief product of the island.
                    It is said that plants of the vine were conveyed from Crete to Madeira in 1421,
                    and have since succeeded extremely well. There is considerable difference in the
                    flavour and other qualities of the wines of Madeira; the best are produced on
                    the south side of the island. The method of cultivation most generally followed
                    is to trench the ground from three to seven and even nine feet deep, according
                    to the nature of the soil, and lay a quantity of loose or stony earth at the
                    bottom, to prevent the roots from reaching the clayey soil beneath, which would
                    otherwise oppose their growth. The ground is watered three times if the summer
                    has been very dry, the sluices being left open until the ground is pretty well
                    saturated; the less the ground is watered the stronger the wine, but the
                    quantity is diminished in proportion. The vines are found to bear fruit as high
                    as 2700 feet, but no wine can be made from it. Wheat, barley, and rye are
                    produced, but scarcely amount to one fifth of the quantity annually consumed.
                    Wheat is sown in October and reaped in June; and the crop is followed by beans
                    or sweet potatoes. The chestnut-tree has been introduced, and forms the
                    principal timber of the island, and affords the chief food of the peasantry.
                    Rice is cultivated, but more as ornamental grass than for any useful purpose.
                    Pine and custard apples, and various other fruits, are grown in the open air in
                    considerable quantities. In consequence of the land rising to a great elevation,
                    this island presents great diversity of climate, though, upon the whole, it is
                    mild and healthy. The rainy season comprehends the months of October, November,
                    December, and January, although the dry weather during the first two months
                    generally exceeds the rainy. The prevailing winds during this season are from
                    the west and the south-west. In the dry season the prevailing winds are from the
                    north-east, and they are not saturated with humidity like those which blow over
                    the equinoctial seas. Although vegetation is so great, the pasture is scanty,
                    and only capable of maintaining a small number of cows, which renders the
                    productions of the dairy objects of luxury. A few oxen are used in the towns;
                    but the mule is the most common beast of burden, and is best adapted for
                    carrying goods along the narrow paths of the mountains. There are abundance of
                    goats and hogs, which being allowed to run wild, acquire a resemblance to
                    venison in taste; rabbits are very common in mountainous districts. Myriads of
                    lizards inhabit the gardens and vineyards, and do considerable damage amongst
                    the refined grapes. Bees abound in hills and valleys, and produce a honey of
                    peculiar delicacy, from the numerous aromatic herbs on which they feed. The
                    population is thought to be at present (1816) about 100,000, though some
                    accounts represent it as much greater. From the extent of the island, and the
                    rocky nature of the land, this census is very great. The inhabitants have
                    evidently sprung from various sources. Amongst the richer inhabitants and
                    merchants are found natives of almost every commercial country, but the greatest
                    number are British. These hold little intercourse with the other inhabitants,
                    but live in a state of luxury among themselves, and show great hospitality to
                    strangers visiting the island. The peasants are generally of Portuguese descent,
                    who, amidst the plenty which surrounds them, live in a state of great poverty.
                    In appearance they are tall, well made, but meagre, with gloomy looks and long
                    black hair; and they are very polite. Their dress consists of white linen
                    trousers, made very wide, over which are drawn boots of buff leather; a coarse
                    white shirt open at the neck, displaying their sun-burnt breasts; a blue cap and
                    jacket, ornamented with silver buttons; and in winter they wear long cloaks. The
                    females are condemned to severe labour: whilst the males are engaged in the
                    vineyards, it is their duty to procure fuel, and often to carry loads of it to
                    the city to dispose of for their subsistence, besides other households toils.
                    They are generally of hard, yet not disagreeable features, with high
                    cheek-bones, dark complexions, and rather large feet; their bodies, however, are
                    well proportioned, and their eyes are lively, large, and black. The want of
                    animal food is severely felt by the peasantry, the most hard-working labourer
                    being constrained to live almost entirely upon bread, roots, and fruits. They
                    extract from the husks and stalks of the grape, after they have passed through
                    the wine-press, a kind of small beer called <hi rend="italic">aqua pe</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> which, when fermented, acquires some degree of
                    tartness, but will not keep.</p>
                <p>The capital, Funchal, is a considerable town, situated in the centre of a large
                    bay. It is built on the declivity of a hill, and the streets are kept clean,
                    being watered by streams from the mountains. The bay is not very secure for
                    anchorage, and is even dangerous during south winds. The landing is difficult,
                    owing to the great surf which breaks upon the shore. It is strongly fortified
                    towards the sea; but the defences on the land side have been greatly neglected.
                    The wealthier inhabitants are generally British merchants, engaged in the wine
                    trade. It is situated in long. 17. 6. W. and lat. 32. 37. N.</p>
                <p>Adjacent to Madeira is the island of Porto Santo, about six miles long and two
                    and a half broad. It is high and rocky, composed principally of sandstone, and a
                    calcareous tuffa of a greenish-gray colour. The vine is cultivated in
                    considerable quantities, and the soil yields good crops of wheat, Indian corn,
                    barley, and beans. The population is estimated at 1400, and there are 300
                    militia. It possesses a good roadstead, but the landing place is bad. The
                    Desertas are small uninhabited islands, which, with Madeira and Porto Santo,
                    form the group called the Madeiras.</p>
                <p>These islands were first settled by the Portuguese; but a tradition exists of
                    their having been visited by an English gentleman, and lady to whom he was
                    attached, who were left behind by accident, and both died there soon afterwards.
                    It has belonged to the Portuguese ever since, and was considered as of such
                    importance to the commerce of this country, that, during the late war, it was
                    held in trust by Great Britain for her ally.</p>
                <p>Its commerce consists almost entirely in the export of its wine. The principal
                    quantity is sent to Great Britain, the East and West Indies, and America; but
                    from frequent adulteration, and the preference of French wines, the trade is not
                    now so great as it formerly was, the growth of the island not exceeding 20,000
                    pipes. The best is that known by the name of London particular, the second
                    London market; and there is also a very rich sweet wine called Malmsey. The
                    quantity of Madeira wines imported into Great Britain in 1833 was 301,057
                    gallons; of this, 161,042 gallons were retained for home consumption, and
                    209,194 exported. The price of these wines in London varies from L.18 to L.80
                    per pipe, according to the quality· There is also a considerable trade carried
                    on in supplying with provisions ships which generally call at this place on the
                    voyage to India.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
