<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0764-0719-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">XENOPHANES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 719</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1161461">Unitarians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:868495">Colophons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1161454">Unitarianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:915906">Ethiopians</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1176240">Wisdom</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45t3g226">Unitarianism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6g77p">Colophons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z984">Thracians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n764/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">XENOPHANES</label> of Colophon, tho reputed founder of the
                    Eleatic school of philosophy, is supposed to have been born in the third or
                    fourth decade of the 6th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> An exile from
                    his Ionian home, he resided for a time in Sicily, at Zancle and at Catana, and
                    afterwards established himself in southern Italy, at Elea, a Phocaean colony
                    founded in the sixty-first Olympiad (536-533). In one of the extant fragments he
                    speaks of himself as having begun his wanderings sixty-seven years before, when
                    he was twenty-five years of age, so that he was not less than ninety-two when he
                    died. His teaching found expression in poems, which he recited rhapsodically in
                    the course of his travels. In the more considerable of the elegiac fragments
                    which have survived he ridicules the doctrine of the migration of souls
                    (xviii.), asserts the claims of wisdom against the prevalent athleticism, which
                    seemed to him to conduce neither to the good government of states nor to their
                    material prosperity (xix.), reprobates the introduction of Lydian luxury into
                    Colophon (xx.), and recommends the reasonable enjoyment of social pleasures
                    (xxi.). Of the epic fragments the more important are those in which he attacks
                    the “anthropomorphic and anthropopathic polytheism” of his contemporaries.
                    According to Aristotle, “this first of Eleatic Unitarians was not careful to say
                    whether the unity which he postulated was finite or infinite, but, contemplating
                    the whole firmament,” (or perhaps “the whole world,” for the word <hi
                    rend="italic">οὑρανός</hi> is ambiguous), “declared that the One is God.”
                    Whether Xenophanes was a monotheist, whose assertion of the unity of God <hi
                    rend="italic">suggested</hi> to Parmenides the doctrine of the unity of Being,
                    or a pantheist, whose assertion of the unity of God was also a declaration of
                    the unity of Being, so that he <hi rend="italic">anticipated</hi> Parmenides,—in
                    other words, whether Xenophanes’s teaching was purely theological or had also a
                    philosophical significance,—is a question about which authorities have differed
                    and will probably continue to differ. The silence of the extant fragments, which
                    have not one word about the unity of Being, favours the one view; the voice of
                    antiquity, which proclaims Xenophanes the founder of Eleaticism, has been
                    thought to favour the other.</p>
                <p>Of Xenophanes’s utterances about (1) God, (2) the world, (3) knowledge, the
                    following survive. (1) “There is one God, greatest among gods and men, neither
                    in shape nor in thought like unto mortals. . . . He is all sight, all mind, all
                    ear (i.e., not a composite organism). . . . Without an effort ruleth he all
                    things by thought. . . . He abideth ever in the same place motionless, and it
                    befitteth him not to wander hither and thither. . . . Yet men imagine gods to be
                    born, and to have senses, and voice, and body, like themselves. . . . Even so
                    the gods of the Ethiopians are swarthy and flat-nosed, the gods of the Thracians
                    are fair-haired and blue-eyed. . . . Even so Homer and Hesiod attributed to the
                    gods all that is a shame and a reproach among men—theft, adultery, deceit, and
                    other lawless acts. . . . Even so lions and horses and oxen, if they had hands
                    wherewith to grave images, would fashion gods after their own shapes and make
                    them bodies like to their own. (2) From earth all things are and to earth all
                    things return. . . . From earth and water come all of us. . . . The sea is the
                    well whence water springeth. . . . Here at our feet is the end of the earth
                    where it reacheth unto air, but, below, its foundations are without end. . . .
                    The rainbow, which men call Iris, is a cloud that is purple and red and yellow.
                    (3) No man hath certainly known, nor shall certainly know, aught of that which I
                    say about the gods and about all things; for, be that which he saith ever so
                    perfect, yet doth he not know it; all things are matters of opinion. . . . That
                    which I say is opinion like unto truth. . . . The gods did not reveal all things
                    to mortals in the beginning; long is the search ere man findeth that which is
                    better.”</p>
                <p>There is very little secondary evidence to record. “The Eleatic school,” says the
                    Stranger in Plato’s <hi rend="italic">Sophist,</hi> 242 D, “beginning with
                    Xenophanes, and even earlier, starts from the principle of the unity of all
                    things.” Aristotle, in a passage already cited, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Metaphysics,</hi> A5, speaks of Xenophanes as the first of the Eleatic
                    Unitarians, adding that his monotheism was reached through the contemplation of
                    the <hi rend="italic">οὑρανός.</hi> Theophrastus (in Simplicius’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Ad Physica,</hi> 5) sums up Xenophanes’s teaching in the
                    propositions, "The All is One and the One is God.” Timon (in Sext. Empir., <hi
                    rend="italic">Pyrrh.,</hi> i. 224), ignoring Xenophanes’s theology, makes him
                    resolve all things into one and the same unity. The demonstrations of the unity
                    and the attributes of God, with which the treatise <hi rend="italic">De Melisso,
                    Xenophane, et Gorgia</hi> (now no longer ascribed to Aristotle or Theophrastus)
                    accredits Xenophanes, are plainly framed on the model of Eleatic proofs of the
                    unity and the attributes of the Ent, and must therefore be set aside. The
                    epitomators of a later time add nothing to the testimonies already
                    enumerated.</p>
                <p>Thus, whereas in his writings, so far as they are known to us, Xenophanes appears
                    as a theologian protesting against an anthropomorphic polytheism, the ancients
                    seem to have regarded him as a philosopher asserting the unity of Being. How are
                    we to understand these conflicting, though not irreconcilable, testimonies?
                    According to Zeller, the discrepancy is only apparent. The Greek <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n765/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0765-0720"/> gods being the powers of nature personified,
                    pantheism lay nearer to hand than monotheism. Xenophanes was then a pantheist.
                    Accordingly his assertion of the unity of God was at the same time a declaration
                    of the unity of Being, and in virtue of this declaration he is entitled to rank
                    as the founder of Eleaticism, inasmuch as the philosophy of Parmenides was his
                    forerunner’s pantheism divested of its theistic element. This reconciliation of
                    the internal and the external evidence, countenanced as it is by Theophrastus,
                    one of the best-informed of the ancient historians, and approved by Zeller, one
                    of the most acute of the modern critics, is more than plausible; but there is
                    something to be said on the contrary part. In the first place, it may be doubted
                    whether to a Greek of the 6th century pantheism was nearer than monotheism.
                    Secondly, the external evidence does not bear examination. The Platonic
                    testimony, if it proved anything, would prove too much, namely, that the
                    doctrine of the unity of Being originated, not with Xenophanes, but before him;
                    and, in fact, the passage from the <hi rend="italic">Sophist</hi> no more proves
                    that Plato attributed to Xenophanes the philosophy of Parmenides than <hi
                    rend="italic">Theaetetus,</hi> 160 D, proves that Plato attributed to Homer the
                    philosophy of Heraclitus. Again, Aristotle’s description of Xenophanes as the
                    first of the Eleatic unitarians does not necessarily imply that the unity
                    asserted by Xenophanes was the unity asserted by Parmenides; the phrase,
                    “contemplating the firmament (or the world), he declared that the One is God,”
                    leaves it doubtful whether Aristotle attributed to Xenophanes any philosophical
                    theory whatever; and the epithet άγ <hi rend="italic">ροικότεροs</hi>
                    discourages the belief that Aristotle regarded Xenophanes as the author of a new
                    and important departure. Thirdly, when Xenophanes himself says that his theories
                    about gods and about things are not knowledge, that his utterances are not
                    verities but verisimilitudes, and that, so far from learning things by
                    revelation, man must laboriously seek a better opinion, he plainly renounces the
                    “disinterested pursuit of truth.” If then he was indifferent to the problem, he
                    can hardly be credited with the Eleatic solution. In the judgment of the present
                    writer, Xenophanes was neither a philosopher nor a sceptic. He was not a
                    philosopher, for he despaired of knowledge. He was not a sceptic, if by
                    “sceptic” is meant the misologist whose despair of knowledge is the consequence
                    of disappointed endeavour, for he had never hoped. Rather he was a theologian
                    who arrived at his theory of the unity of God by the rejection of the
                    contemporary mythology. But, while he thus stood aloof from philosophy,
                    Xenophanes influenced its development in two ways: first, his theological monism
                    led the way to the philosophical monism of Parmenides and Zeno; secondly, his
                    assertion that so-called knowledge was in reality no more than opinion taught
                    his successors to distinguish knowledge and opinion, and to assign to each a
                    separate province.</p>
                <p>Apart from the old controversy about Xenophanes’s relations to philosophy, doubts
                    have recently arisen about his theological position. In fragments i., xiv.,
                    xvi., xxi., &amp;c., he recognizes, thinks Freudenthal, a plurality of deities;
                    whence it is inferred that, besides the One God, most high, perfect, eternal,
                    who, as immanent intelligent cause, unifies the plurality of things, there were
                    also lesser divinities, who govern portions of the universe, being themselves
                    eternal parts of the one all-embracing Godhead. Whilst it can hardly be allowed
                    that Xenophanes, so far from denying, actually affirms a plurality of gods, it
                    must be conceded to Freudenthal that Xenophanes’s polemic was directed against
                    the anthropomorphic tendencies and the mythological details of the contemporary
                    polytheism rather than against the polytheistic principle, and that, apart from
                    the treatise <hi rend="italic">De Melisso, Xenophane, et Gorgia,</hi> now
                    generally discredited, there is no direct evidence to prove him a consistent
                    monotheist. The wisdom of Xenophanes, like the wisdom of the Hebrew Preacher,
                    showed itself, not in a theory of the universe, but in a sorrowful recognition
                    of the nothingness of things and the futility of endeavour. His theism was a
                    declaration not so much of the greatness of God as rather of the littleness of
                    man. His cosmology was an assertion not so much of the immutability of the One
                    as rather of the mutability of the Many. Like Socrates, he was not a
                    philosopher, and did not pretend to be one; but, as the reasoned scepticism of
                    Socrates cleared the way for the philosophy of Plato, so did Xenophanes’s
                    “abnormis sapientia” for the philosophy of Parmenides.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi> S. Karsten, <hi rend="italic">Xenophanis
                    Colophonii Carminum Reliquite,</hi> Brussels, 1830; F. W. A. Mullach, <hi
                    rend="italic">Frag. Phil. Graec.,</hi> Paris, 1860, i. 99-108; G. Teichmüller,
                    <hi rend="italic">Studien z</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Gesch. d. Begriffe,</hi>
                    Berlin, 1874, pp. 589-623; E. Zeller, <hi rend="italic">Phil. d. Griechen,</hi>
                    Leipsic, 1877, i. 486-507; J. Freudenthal, <hi rend="italic">Ueber d. Theologie
                    d. Xenophanes,</hi> Breslau, 1886, and “Zur Lehre d. Xen.,” in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Archiv f. Gesch. d. Philos.,</hi> Berlin, 1888, i. 322-347. For a fuller
                    bibliography, including the controversy about the <hi rend="italic">De Melisso,
                    Xen., et Gorgia,</hi> see Ueberweg, <hi rend="italic">Grundriss d. Gesch. d.
                    Philos.,</hi> Berlin, 1871, i. § 17. See also art. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Parmenides.</hi> (H. JA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
