<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0761-0716-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">XAVIER, Francisco (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    716)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1023771">Missions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025853">Months</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2md37">Missions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n761/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">XAVIER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Francisco</hi></label>
                    (1506-1552), surnamed the “Apostle of the Indies,” was the youngest son of Juan
                    de Jasso, privy councillor to Jean d’Albret, king of Navarre, and his wife Maria
                    Azpilcueta Xavier, sole heiress of two noble Navarrese families. He was born at
                    his mother’s castle of Xavero or Xavier, at the foot of the Pyrenees and close
                    to the little town of Sanguesa, on 7th April 1506, according to a family
                    register, though his earlier biographers fix his birth in 1497. Following a
                    Spanish custom of the time, which left the surname of either parent optional
                    with children, he was called by his mother’s family name, and grew up tall,
                    strong, healthy, and active both in mind and body, with a lively, cheerful
                    disposition. He showed no taste, however, for the career of arms, and early
                    disclosed a preference for literary pursuits. His father accordingly strained
                    his slender resources to send him, in 1524, to the university of Paris, then
                    much frequented by Spaniards, where he entered the College of St Barbara, and
                    made such rapid progress that he was appointed in 1528 lecturer in Aristotelian
                    philosophy at the Collége de Beauvais. In 1530 he took his degree as master of
                    arts. The same year which saw his nomination as lecturer at the university saw
                    also the arrival there of the man who was to mould his destiny and that of his
                    chamber-mate Pierre le Fèvre, namely, Ignatius Loyola, even then meditating the
                    foundation of his celebrated institute (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Jesuits,</hi>
                    vol. xiii. p. 652). Ignatius speedily recognized in Xavier the qualities which
                    made him the first missionary of his time, —and set himself to win him as an
                    associate in his vast enterprise. Xavier, after a protracted resistance, yielded
                    to the spell, and was one of the little band of seven persons, including Loyola
                    himself, who took the original Jesuit vows and founded the company, on 15th
                    August 1534, in the crypt of Notre Dame de Montmartre. They continued in Paris
                    for two years longer, though there is some uncertainty whether Xavier retained
                    his chair; but on 15th November 1536 they started for Italy, to concert with
                    Ignatius (then in Spain, but purposing to join them) plans for a mission to
                    convert the Moslems of Palestine. About Epiphany-tide 1537, after a journey
                    attended with much fatigue and some danger, owing to the disturbed <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n762/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0762-0717"/> posture of political affairs, they arrived in
                    Venice, where they found Ignatius awaiting them. As some months must needs
                    elapse before they could sail for the Holy Land, Ignatius determined that the
                    time should be spent partly in hospital work at Venice and later in the journey
                    to Rome, there to obtain their credentials. Accordingly, Xavier devoted himself
                    for nine weeks to the care of the patients in the hospital for incurables, at
                    the end of which time he set out with eight companions for Rome, where Pope Paul
                    III. received them favourably, sanctioned their enterprise, and gave them
                    facilities for obtaining ordination. Returning to Venice, Xavier was ordained
                    priest on Midsummer Day 1537; but the outbreak of war between Venice and Turkey
                    put an end to the Palestine expedition. Hereupon the companions agreed to
                    disperse for a twelvemonth’s home mission work in the Italian cities, and
                    Bobadilla and Xavier betook themselves, first to Monselice, thence to Bologna,
                    where they remained till summoned to Rome by Ignatius at the close of 1538, to
                    consider his plans for erecting the company into a religious order, with a
                    formal constitution under papal sanction. The draft rules were signed by the
                    whole number on 15th April 1539, though it was not till 1540 that the pope’s
                    confirmation was given, nor was it published till 1541. While the remaining
                    members dispersed anew for work in various parts of Italy, Ignatius retained
                    Xavier at Rome as secretary to the new institute. Meanwhile John III., king of
                    Portugal, had resolved on sending a mission to his East Indian dominions, and,
                    at the instance of his minister Govea, applied through his envoy Pedro de
                    Mascarenhas to the pope for six Jesuits to undertake the task. Ignatius could
                    spare but two, and chose Rodriguez and Bobadilla for the purpose; and the former
                    set out at once for Lisbon to confer with the king. Bobadilla, sent for to Rome,
                    arrived there just before Mascarenhas was about to depart, but fell too ill to
                    respond to the call made on him. Hereupon Ignatius on 15th March 1540 told
                    Xavier to leave Rome the next day with Mascarenhas, in order to join Rodriguez
                    in the Indian mission. Xavier complied, merely waiting long enough to obtain the
                    pope’s benediction, and set out for Lisbon, where he was presented to the king,
                    and soon won his entire confidence, attested notably by procuring for him from
                    the pope four briefs, one of them appointing him papal nuncio in the Indies. On
                    7th April 1541, his thirty-fifth birthday, he sailed from Lisbon with Martin
                    Alphonso de Souza, governor of India, and, refusing all accommodations for the
                    voyage offered him, except a few books and some clothing, lived amongst the
                    common sailors on board, ministering to their religious and temporal needs,
                    especially during an outbreak of scurvy. After five months’ voyage the ship
                    reached Mozambique, where the captain resolved to winter, and Xavier was
                    prostrated with a severe attack of fever. When the voyage was resumed, the ship
                    touched at the Mohammedan town of Melinde, whose sultan told Xavier of the
                    marked decline of Islam. But neither there nor at the island of Socotra, the
                    next point of arrival, where Christianity was equally declining, was the
                    missionary able to remain long enough to attempt any work; and he finally
                    reached Goa on 6th May 1542. Exhibiting his brief to João d’ Albuquerque, bishop
                    of Goa, he asked his permission to officiate in the diocese, and at once began a
                    mission, walking through the streets ringing a small bell, and telling all those
                    attracted by its sound to come themselves, and send their children and servants,
                    to the “Christian doctrine” or catechetical instruction in the principal church.
                    He spent five months actively employed in Goa, where he is stated to have
                    effected much reformation in morals, and then turned his attention to the
                    fishery coast, extending from Cape Comorin to the Paumbum Pass, where he had
                    heard that the Paravas, a tribe engaged in the pearl-fishery, had relapsed into
                    heathenism after having professed Christianity. He laboured assiduously amongst
                    them for fifteen months, and at the end of 1543 returned to Goa to procure
                    colleagues for the mission. Travancore was his next field of action, and there
                    he is said to have succeeded in founding no fewer than forty-five Christian
                    settlements, each with numerous converts. It is to be noted that his own letters
                    contain, both at this time and later on, express disproof of his possession of
                    that miraculous gift of tongues with which he was credited even in his lifetime,
                    and which is attributed to him in the <hi rend="italic">Breviary</hi> office for
                    his festival. Not only was he obliged to employ interpreters, but he relates
                    that in their absence he was compelled to use signs only, and he never appears
                    to have displayed any special aptitude for acquiring new languages. He sent a
                    missionary to the isle of Manaar, and himself visited Ceylon, where he proved
                    unsuccessful in an effort to invoke Portuguese interference in a dynastic
                    dispute, and betook himself thence to Meliapur, the traditionary tomb of St
                    Thomas the apostle, which he reached in April 1544, continuing there four
                    months. His next sphere of active work was Malacca, which he reached on 25th
                    September 1545, and where he remained another four months, but had comparatively
                    little success, and abandoned it at last as wholly intractable. While there he
                    addressed a letter to King John of Portugal, urging him to set up the
                    Inquisition in Goa to repress Judaism, and was readily listened to, although the
                    actual erection of the tribunal did not take place till 1560, some years after
                    his own death. After a missionary expedition to Amboyna and other isles of the
                    Molucca group, he returned to Malacca in July 1547, and found three Jesuit
                    recruits from Europe awaiting him. An attack upon Malacca by the sultan of
                    Acheen, which the governor was disinclined to punish, aroused the warlike temper
                    which slumbered in Xavier’s breast, and he compelled the organization of an
                    expedition to chastise the invaders, which proved a triumph and much increased
                    his local influence. While in Malacca he met one Han-Siro, a Japanese exile
                    (known to the biographies as Anger), whose conversation fired him with zeal for
                    the conversion of Japan. But he first paid a series of visits to the scenes of
                    his former labours, and then, returning to Malacca, took ship for Japan,
                    accompanied by Han-Siro, now known as Paul of the Holy Faith. After a perilous
                    voyage they reached Kagoshima, at the south of Kiusiu, the southernmost of the
                    larger Japanese islands, and in the territory of the daimio of Satsuma.
                    Kagoshima was Han-Siro’s birthplace, and he was himself heartily welcomed by his
                    friends, whom he induced to extend their good-will to his companions. The
                    daimio, who desired to secure the Portuguese trade, was friendly at first; but,
                    finding that the merchant vessels preferred the safer anchorage of Firando (or
                    Hirado) far to the north of his fief, he withdrew his permission to preach and
                    threatened converts with the penalty of death. Xavier judged it well to move
                    elsewhither, and travelled on foot to Firando, making some converts on the road,
                    and proving far more successful at Firando itself than in Kagoshima. Thence he
                    proceeded to the capital of the empire, the city then known as Miako,
                    subsequently as Kioto, and now as Saikio or “western capital.” But the mikados
                    or emperors had been little more than puppets under the control of the shoguns
                    or hereditary commanders-in-chief for some centuries before this time, so that
                    Xavier judged that he could work more effectually at the courts of the great
                    daimios than at that of their nominal sovereign. He also noticed that asceticism
                    and poverty had no such attractive power in Japan as they had exercised in
                    India, and determined to try the effect of some measure of pomp and display on
                    his return from Miako. Making but a brief stay <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n763/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0763-0718"/> at Firando, he went to Amanguchi (Yamaguchi),
                    capital of Suwo, and there presented himself to the daimio in some state,
                    bringing him valuable presents. He was allowed to preach, and had some success,
                    which encouraged him to proceed to Fucheo, capital of the fief of Bungo (Bugo),
                    where his mission prospered more than anywhere else in Japan; and, feeling that
                    he could now safely leave the work in other hands, he quitted that empire in
                    1551, intending to attempt next the conversion of China. On board the “Santa
                    Cruz,” the vessel in which he sailed to Malacca, he discussed this project with
                    Diego Pereira, the captain, and devised the plan of persuading the viceroy of
                    Portuguese India to despatch an embassy to China, in whose train he might enter,
                    in despite of the law which then excluded foreigners from that empire. He
                    reached Goa in February 1552, and after settling some disputes which had arisen
                    in his absence obtained from the viceroy consent to the plan of a Chinese
                    embassy and to the nomination of Pereira as envoy. Large sums for the necessary
                    expenses were contributed by the treasury, by Pereira himself, and by
                    subscriptions from private persons interested in the missionary part of the
                    scheme. Xavier left India on 25th April 1552 and betook himself to Malacca,
                    there to meet Pereira and to re-embark on the “Santa Cruz.” But Alvaro d’
                    Ataide, governor of Malacca, had a private grudge against Pereira, and besides
                    desired the Chinese embassy for himself, and therefore threw difficulties in the
                    way of the expedition, though Xavier, anticipating something of the kind, had
                    procured for him the high office of captaincy of the neighbouring seas, and had
                    also provided himself with stringent orders from the viceroy for the furtherance
                    of his object, with threats of punishment for disobedience. Ataide, however,
                    paid no attention to them, and laid an embargo on the “Santa Cruz.” Xavier, who
                    with characteristic modesty had kept his dignity as papal nuncio private (save
                    for exhibiting the brief to the bishop at Goa on his first arrival in India),
                    determined to avail himself of it now, and desired the vicar-general of Malacca
                    to inform the governor, and to remind him that such as impeded a nuncio in the
                    discharge of his office were subject to excommunication by the pope himself.
                    Ataide paid no more regard to the papal brief than he had done to the viceroy’s
                    letter, and even charged Xavier with having forged it,—if not both
                    documents,—while the people of Malacca sided with him against Xavier and
                    Pereira. At last, however, he agreed to a compromise. The embassy was stopped
                    and Pereira detained, while some of the governor’s people were substituted for
                    as many of the crew of the “Santa Cruz,” in which Xavier and two companions were
                    allowed to proceed. The vicargeneral asked him to take formal leave of the
                    governor; but he refused, saying that they would meet no more till the day of
                    judgment, when Ataide must give account for his resistance to the spread of the
                    gospel, and, shaking the dust of Malacca from his shoes, he embarked 16th July
                    1552. After a short stay at Singapore, whence he despatched several letters to
                    India and Europe, the ship at the end of August 1552 reached San-chan
                    (Chang-chuang), an island at no great distance from Canton, which served as port
                    and rendezvous for Europeans, not then admitted to trade directly with China.
                    Xavier was seized with fever soon after his arrival, and was, in addition,
                    delayed by the failure of the interpreter he had engaged, as well as by the
                    reluctance of the Portuguese to attempt the voyage to Canton for the purpose of
                    landing him. He arranged for his passage in a Chinese junk and had made all
                    other preparations for starting, when he was again attacked by fever, and died
                    on 2d December 1552. He was buried close to the cabin where he had died, but his
                    body was later transferred to Malacca, and thence to Goa, where it still lies.
                    He was beatified by Paul V. in 1619 and canonized by Gregory XV. in 1621.</p>
                <p>The chief authorities for the life of St Francis Xavier are <hi rend="italic">Be
                        Vita Sancti Francisci Xaverii Libri VI.,</hi> by the Jesuit Torsellino
                    (Tur-sellinus), Rome, 1596, of which there is a vigorous English version, Paris,
                    1632; another biography by Lucena, Lisbon, 1600; his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Letters,</hi> published in seven books by the Jesuit Poussines (Pos-sinus),
                    Rome, 1667; a fuller collection of the <hi rend="italic">Leiters</hi> by another
                    Jesuit, Menchacha, Bologna, 1795, translated into French by Léon Pagès, Paris,
                    1854; Faria y Souza, <hi rend="italic">Asia Portuguesa,</hi> Lisbon, 1655;
                    Bouhours, <hi rend="italic">Vie de St François Xavier,</hi> Paris, 1684;
                    Bartoli, <hi rend="italic">Asia,</hi> part i., Rome, 1653; H. J. Coleridge, <hi
                        rend="italic">Life and Letters of St Francis Xavier,</hi> London, 1872;
                    while a graphic sketch of the more striking episodes is to be found in Sir James
                    Stephen’s article on the “Founders of Jesuitism,” reprinted in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Essays in Ecclesiastical Biography,</hi> London, 1849. (R. F.
                    L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
