<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0713-5921-0346-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LIMA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:954023">Heating</term>
                    <term ref="fast:953778">Heat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058953">Peruvians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067051">Plazas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166257">Viceroys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx4522p">Peruvian</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52ff6p">Heat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hr3b">Heating</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193205921?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">LIMA</label>, a department of the republic of Peru,
                    in South America, bounded on the north by Truxillo, on the east by Junin and
                    Ayacucho, on the south by Arequipa, and on the west by the Pacific Ocean. The
                    Cordillera of the Andes ranges along its eastern side. The climate is considered
                    as fine; and although the atmosphere is cloudy and humid, it seldom rains
                    throughout the whole year. The heat is excessive along the coast; but as the
                    country becomes more elevated towards the interior, the air becomes purer and
                    more temperate. Earthquakes are frequent, from six to twelve occurring annually;
                    and these convulsions of nature on a large scale seem to observe a periodical
                    return at intervals of fifty years. It is watered by several streams, but none
                    of any considerable size, the largest being the river Rimae, which, during the
                    summer months, is much swollen by torrents from the Andes. The soil is good, and
                    agricultural pursuits are followed to a considerable extent. The chief wealth of
                    the country <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi>, however, consists in the produce of
                    the mines, which are worked by proprietors in Lima. Next to Lima in importance
                    is the sea-port of Callao, situated in the bay of that name, and containing a
                    population of about 8000. The port is defended by three castles, which are
                    surrounded with thick walls, a moat, and batteries of great strength. It is
                    connected with the city of Lima by a straight road, about six indes in length.
                    It was entirely destroyed by an earthquake in 1746, when upwards of 3000 of the
                    inhabitants are said to have perished, and nineteen ships sunk in the harbour.
                    Trade has lately much increased, and the town has greatly improved. Its
                    appearance, however, is mean and unfavourable.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Lima,</hi> a city in the department of that name,
                    and capital of the republic of Peru, is situated in a spacious plain, on the
                    southern bank of the river Rimae, about ten miles from the sea. Long. 76. 56.
                    45. ∖V . Lat. 12. 3. S. The population, according to the latest accounts, is
                    40,000 inhabitants. It was founded in 1553 by Pizarro, who called it La Ciudad
                    de les Reyes, or City of Kings; but the name has been since changed to Linιa, a
                    corruption of Rimae. The city is built in an amphitheatre formed by sierras of
                    the great chain of the Andes, which shelter it from the northerly <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193205934?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0713-5934-0347"/>and
                    easterly winds. The figure of the city is nearly semicircular, the river being
                    the diameter, and is two miles long from east to west, and one and a quarter in
                    breadth. It consists of 157 squares, and 355 streets, built at right angles, and
                    about twenty-five feet wide. The streets are well paved, and furnished with
                    streams of water, which are arched over, and rendered subservient to cleanliness
                    and other conveniences. It stands nearly 700 feet above the level of the sea,
                    and, when seen from Callao roads, presents a beautiful appearance, owing to its
                    numerous domes and spires rising from so elevated a situation. The entrance is
                    by a fine avenue Or public walk called the Almeda, <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi>
                    at the termination of which are the ruins of a handsome gate. It is surrounded
                    by a brick wall, flanked with thirty-four bastions, but without embrasures. At
                    the south-eastern extremity of the city is a small citadel, called Santa
                    Catalina; and on the right side of the river, connected with the city by a
                    bridge, is the suburb of San Lazarro, which is inhabited by the lower classes.
                    The city having suffered much from earthquakes, the houses are generally built
                    of one story, the walls being composed of mud and cut straw, formed into bricks
                    by the heat of the sun, and strengthened by pieces of timber. The houses of the
                    wealthy inhabitants, built in a Moorish style, generally consist of a square
                    pile, two stories in height, enclosing a quadrangular court, which is surrounded
                    with piazzas, and sometimes contains a second, or even third inner court. The
                    Plaza, or great square, in the centre of the city, is surrounded partly with
                    shops and private houses, and partly with public buildings. On the eastern side
                    is the cathedral, to the north of which is the principal parish church, adorned
                    with a beautiful façade, and adjoining it is the archiépiscopal palace, part of
                    which is now occupied by the Peruvian synod. On the north side are the viceroy’s
                    palace and the city hall, under which is the city jail. In the centre of the
                    square is a fine brass fountain, erected in 1653, the water of which being the
                    best in Lima, is conveyed to all parts of the city. In this square the principal
                    market is held. The cathedral is a noble edifice, and at each corner is a tower,
                    nearly 200 feet in height. The interior is very rich, and the high altar has a
                    magnificent appearance. The roofs of the houses, and domes and spires of the
                    churches, are built of wood, covered with stucco-work, variously ornamented,
                    which presents a splendid appearance when viewed from a distance; but the
                    traveller is apt to feel disappointed upon a nearer inspection. Formerly the
                    number of monks was reckoned at 1200, but they have now decreased nearly one
                    fifth in amount. There are fourteen convents for females, and a number of
                    religious houses, into which ladies retire for a short period. Some of the
                    conventual churches are remarkably beautiful; that of St Domingo having a tower
                    about 180 feet high, which is the loftiest in the city. There are several
                    hospitals of a charitable and benevolent description. The university, founded in
                    1549, and possessing peculiar privileges, is a handsome building, with several
                    good halls, and an extensive library.</p>
                <p part="N">The higher classes of the inhabitants are generally well educated,
                    though in a limited sense; and the females are equally celebrated for their
                    vivacity and beauty. They are said, however, to be somewhat licentious in their
                    manners; and their walking-dress, consisting of a petticoat fitted close to the
                    body, and a hood thrown over the head, seems peculiarly favourable to intrigue.
                    Both sexes are addicted to smoking; but the females do not practise it openly.
                    All classes of the inhabitants are extravaganten their dress, the richest stuffs
                    of Europe being used even on ordinary occasions. Music, cards, and dancing, are
                    the principal sources of amusement; bull-fights having been abolished. Gambling
                    formerly prevailed in the higher circles; but this vice has of late sensibly
                    diminished. The</p>
                <p part="N">Spaniards of Lima are at present almost all creoles; the European
                    Spaniards having quitted the country at the period of the revolution. There were
                    formerly 15,000 slaves; but slavery was abolished in 1828 by the new
                    constitution. Lima has been repeatedly laid in ruins by earthquakes, the most
                    destructive of which were those of 1678 and 1746, when, out of 3000 houses, not
                    more than twenty were left standing. In 1822 and 1828 also very destructive
                    earthquakes occurred. The political events which have occurred in Lima will be
                    fully detailed under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Peru.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
