<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0713-2887-0114-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LARES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43r0pw1h">Protectorates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd61">Dog</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tt4h">Highways</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v88x">Mania</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079666">Protectorates</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896265">Dogs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916316">Etruscans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:886684">Dactylis</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193202887?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">LARES</label>, amongst the ancients, derived by
                    Apuleius from <hi rend="italic">lar familiaris,</hi> a kind of domestic genii or
                    divinities, worshipped in houses, esteemed the guardians and protectors of
                    families, and supposed to reside more immediately in the chimney corner. The
                    Lares were distinguished from the Penates, as the former were supposed to
                    preside over housekeeping, the servants in families, and domestic affairs;
                    whilst the latter were the protectors of the masters of families, their wives,
                    and children. Accordingly the Lares were dressed in short, succinct habits, to
                    show their readiness to serve; and they held a sort of cornucopia in their
                    hands, as a signal of hospitality and good housekeeping. According to Ovid,
                    there were generally two of them, who were sometimes represented with a dog at
                    their feet. Plutarch distinguishes good and evil Lares, as he had before done
                    good and evil genii. There are also some public, others private Lares. Apuleius
                    tells us the domestic Lares were no more than the souls of departed persons, who
                    had lived well, and had discharged the duties of their station; <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193202900?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0713-2900-0115"/>whereas
                    those who had done otherwise were vagabonds, wandering about and frightening
                    people, called <hi rend="italic">Larvae</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lemures.</hi>
                    The Lares were also called <hi rend="italic">Penates,</hi> and were worshipped
                    under the figures of little marmosets, or images of wax, silver, or earthen
                    ware. The public Lares were also called <hi rend="italic">Compitales,</hi> from
                        <hi rend="italic">compitum,</hi> a cross-way; and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Viales,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">via,</hi> a way or public road; as
                    being placed at the meetings of roads and in the highways, and esteemed the
                    patrons and protectors of travellers. The private Lares took care of particular
                    houses and families, and were also called <hi rend="italic">Proestites,</hi>
                    from <hi rend="italic">proesto.</hi> The Lares were likewise genial gods, and
                    were supposed to take care of children from their birth. It is for this reason
                    that, when Macrobius tells us the Egyptians had four gods who presided over the
                    births of children, viz. Genius, Fortune, Love, and Necessity, called <hi
                        rend="italic">Proestites,</hi> some interpret him as if he had said the
                    Egyptians had Lares, and they have mentioned that there was a great difference
                    between the Lares of the Romans and the Proestites of the Egyptians. However,
                    the learned Mr Bryant affirms that they were the same. The ancients differ
                    extremely about the origin of the Lares. Varro and Macrobius say that they were
                    the children of Mania; Ovid makes them the issue of Mercury, and the Naiad Lara
                    or Larunda; Apuleius assures us that they were the posterity of the Lemures;
                    Nigridius, according to Arnobius, makes them sometimes the guardians and
                    protectors of houses, and sometimes the same with the Curetes of Samothracia,
                    which the Greeks call <hi rend="italic">Idoei Dactyli.</hi> Nor was Varro more
                    consistent in his opinion of these gods; sometimes making them the manes of
                    heroes, and sometimes gods of the air. Titus Tatius, king of the Sabines, was
                    the first who built a temple to the Lares. The chimney and fire-place in the
                    house were particularly consecrated to them. Tertullian is of opinion that the
                    custom of worshipping the Lares arose from this, that they anciently interred
                    their dead in their houses; and hence the credulous people took occasion to
                    imagine that their souls continued there also, and thus proceeded to pay them
                    divine honours. To this it may be added, that the custom being afterwards
                    introduced of burying in the highways, they might hence take occasion to regard
                    them as gods of the highways. The victim offered to the Lares in the public
                    sacrifices was a hog; but in private they were offered wine, incense, a crown of
                    wool, and a little of what was left at the table. They also crowned them with
                    flowers, particularly the violet, myrtle, and rosemary. Their symbol was a dog,
                    which was usually represented by their side, on account of its fidelity and the
                    service it does to a man in watching his house. They were sometimes also
                    represented as clothed in a dog’s skin. The term <hi rend="italic">Lares,</hi>
                    according to Mr Bryant, was formed from <hi rend="italic">laren,</hi> an ancient
                    word by which the ark was represented. He supposes that the Lares and Manes were
                    the same domestic deities under different names; and that by these terms the
                    Etruscans and Latins denoted the <hi rend="italic">dii arkitae,</hi> who were no
                    other than their arkite ancestors, or the persons preserved in the laren or ark,
                    the genius of which was Isis, the reputed parent of the world, He observes
                    further, that they are described as demons and genii, who once lived upon earth,
                    and were gifted with immortality. Arnobius styles them <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lares</hi><hi rend="italic">quosdam genios et functorum</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">animas</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and he says that,
                    according to Varro, they were the children of Mania. Huetius <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Demonst. Prop.</hi> iv. p. 139) adds, that Mania had also the name of
                    Larunda; and that she is styled the mother <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the demons.
                    By some she is called Lara, and was supposed to preside over families; and
                    children were offered at her altar in order to procure her favour. Instead of
                    these, they offered in after times the heads of poppies and pods of garlic.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
