<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0069-0058-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">KHÁSI AND JÁINTIA HILLS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 58</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f430">Timber</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wm7s">Coal</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9h942">Coaling</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40k26g4w">Hinduism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:990476">Lac</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1938968">Aryans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:957121">Hinduism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n69/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KHÁSI AND JÁINTIA HILLS</label>, a district in Assam, India,
                    lying between 25° Γ and 26° 14' N. lat., and 90° 47' and 92° 52' E. long., and
                    bounded on the N. by Kâmrùp and Nowgong districts, E. by Cachar and the Nâgâ
                    Hills, S. by Sylhet, and W. by the Gâro Hills. Its approximate area is 6157
                    square miles.</p>
                <p>The district consists of a succession of steep ridges running east and west, with
                    elevated table-lands between. On the southern side, towards Sylhet, the
                    mountains rise precipitously from the valley of the Bârâk. The first plateau is
                    about 4000 feet above sea-level. Farther north is another plateau, on which is
                    situated the station of Shillong, 4900 feet above the sea; behind lies the
                    Shillong range, of which the highest peak rises to 6449 feet. On the north side,
                    towards Kâmrüp, are two similar plateaus of lower elevation. The general
                    appearance of all these table-lands is that of undulating downs, covered with
                    grass, but destitute of large timber. At 3000 feet elevation the indigenous pine
                    predominates over all other vegetation, and forms almost pure pine forests. The
                    highest ridges are clothed with magnificent clumps of timber trees, which
                    superstition has preserved from the axe of the woodcutter. The characteristic
                    trees in these sacred groves chiefly consist of oaks, chestnuts, magnolias,
                    &amp;c. Beneath the shade grow rare orchids, rhododendrons, and wild cinnamon.
                    The streams are merely mountain torrents. As they approach the plains, they form
                    rapids and cascades, and many of them pass through narrow gorges of wild beauty.
                    From time immemorial, Lower Bengal has drawn its supply of lime from the Khâsi
                    Hills, and the quarries along their southern slope are literally inexhaustible.
                    Coal of excellent quality crops out at several places, but has not yet been
                    remuneratively worked. Ironstone exists in abundance, and in former days the
                    Khâsias were renowned as smelters of iron. Among other natural products may be
                    mentioned beeswax, lac, and caoutchouc. Wild animals abound, including the
                    elephant, rhinoceros, tiger, buffalo, <hi rend="italic">mithun</hi> or wild cow,
                    and many varieties of deer.</p>
                <p>Both as regards history and administration the Khâsi (Khasiâ or Cossya) and
                    Jaintia or Jayntiyâ Hills constitute two separate tracts. The Khâsi Hills are
                    occupied by a collection of petty states, each governed by an elective ruler.
                    The chiefs have not been brought completely under British administration, and
                    still retain marks of semi-independence. The headquarters of the British
                    political agent for the Khâsi Hills is at Châra Pùnji (Cherra Poonjee). The
                    Jâintia Hills, on the other hand, are purely British territory. The inhabitants
                    call themselves Syntengs, and first became British subjects in 1835 (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Jaintia Hills,</hi> vol xiii. p. 554).</p>
                <p>An enumeration in 1872 disclosed a total population in the Khâsi and Jâintia
                    Hills of 141,838—aboriginal tribes, 141,283; Hindus, 365; Mohammedans, 62;
                    Christians, 128. The two races of Khâsias and Syntengs have succeeded in
                    preserving to the present day their primitive isolation, free from the
                    interference of Hinduism. They have only given way somewhat to Hindu prejudices
                    as regards purity of food. The Khâsias have no written character or literature,
                    nor even any traditions of their own. The most curious of their social customs
                    is the importance attached to female descent and female authority. The husband
                    marries into the wife’s family, the wife or her mother is regarded as the head
                    of the household, and all property descends in the female line—a survival of the
                    polyandrie institutions still kept up in full force by the Nairs, and other
                    non-Aryan tribes of India. The ashes of the dead are buried under cromlechs
                    consisting of four upright slabs of stone, covered over by a fifth slab. The
                    only places in the Khâsi and Jâintia Hills above the rank of hamlets are
                    Shillong, the headquarters station, Jowâi, and Châra Pûnji.</p>
                <p>The principal cereal crop is rice, but even of this they do not grow sufficient
                    for their own consumption. Sugar cane, cotton, and potatoes are also grown; and
                    fruits such as oranges, limes, and pine-apples are raised in large quantities
                    for export to Calcutta. The land is the absolute property of the cultivators,
                    who pay no rent or revenue either to the British Government or to their own
                    chiefs. Blights, floods, and droughts are almost unknown. Of a total area of
                    6157 square miles, only 286 are estimated as under cultivation, but other 3898
                    are returned as available for tillage. The trade of the hills is considerable.
                    The estimated exports in 1876-77 were valued at £160,000, chiefly potatoes,
                    limestone, cotton, stick-lac, bay leaves, oranges, and betel nuts. The imports
                    were valued at £157,000. By far the greater portion of the trade is conducted at
                    a row of markets along the southern foot of the hills, of which Chhatak in
                    Sylhet district is the most important.</p>
                <p>The Khâsi and Jâintia Hills constitute a political agency, independent of the
                    ordinary jurisdiction. The Khasi petty states, twenty-five in number, are
                    presided over by elective chiefs, having jurisdiction over their own subjects in
                    all cases except homicide. The British Government undertakes the management of
                    the natural products of the country, such as lime, coal, timber, and elephants,
                    and pays over to the chiefs a half share of the profits. Their other sources of
                    revenue are market dues, court fines, and various cesses. Their aggregate income
                    is approximately estimated at £5000, of which £2300 is derived from lime
                    quarries. The total revenue of the district to the British Government in 1875
                    was £13,383, of which the larger portion came from royalties on lime quarries
                    and the house tax; the expenditure was £9692. Education is conducted through the
                    agency of the Welsh Calvinistic mission, and in 1874-75 there were seventy-three
                    schools open, attended by 1666 pupils. Female education is making progress among
                    the Khâsias. The climate of the district is mild and equable, though in some
                    parts excessively humid. At Shillong the thermometer rarely exceeds 80° Fahr.,
                    and falls as low as 38°. Shallow water occasionally freezes, but snow never
                    falls. The rainfall at Châra Pιinji is the heaviest recorded in the world. The
                    average during the three years ending 1876 is returned at 368 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 41 inches; and 805 inches are said to have fallen in
                    1861, including 366 inches in the single month of July. At Shillong the annual
                    rainfall declines to about 85 inches; and at Jowâi, which occupies an
                    intermediate position, the average is 150 inches. The district is liable to
                    shocks of earthquake. Generally speaking, the climate is healthy, both for
                    natives and Europeans. Cholera never prevails, unless directly imported from the
                    plains.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n70/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0070-0059"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
