<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0152-0141-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KÖRNER, Karl Theodor (9th edition, volume 14, page
                    141)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896788">Dominoes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46w96c3p">Dominoes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sb3x70m">Stockings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f223">Stocks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n152/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KÖRNER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Karl Theodor</hi></label>
                    (1791-1813), German patriot and poet, was born at Dresden, September 23, 1791.
                    His father, a prosperous lawyer, made his house in Dresden a centre of literary,
                    musical, and artistic society, and was an intimate friend of Schiller; and his
                    mother, a daughter of the copper-plate engraver Stock of Leipsic, enjoyed
                    Goethe’s friendship through life, and in her later years claimed it for her son.
                    Theodor Körner was at first so delicate a child that his parents made the
                    paternal vineyard—the same in which Schiller sat and wrote <hi rend="italic">Don
                        Carlos</hi> a few years before—his summer schoolroom. They prescribed for
                    lessons, gymnastics, riding, swimming, fencing, and the like, till the delicate
                    boy grew into a young athlete, with a joyous, affectionate disposition which won
                    the hearts of all who knew him. Partly at the Kreuzschule in Dresden, but
                    chiefly with private tutors at home, Körner now studied languages, history, and
                    mathematics. He was an adept at various kinds of fine wood-turning, could
                    sketch, and play the guitar; but his happiest hours were spent over the volumes
                    of Goethe and Schiller—the household gods; and under their influence the boy
                    began to write verses which his parents forbore to praise, but which displayed,
                    even then, much of the facility and grace of his later poems. At the age of
                    seventeen he went to the school of mines in Freiberg, and worked
                    enthusiastically for two years at mathematics, mineralogy, and chemistry. The
                    poems he wrote during this period were collected and published under the title
                        <hi rend="italic">Knospen.</hi> From Freiberg Körner went to the university
                    of Leipsic, where for some months he studied philosophy, history, and anatomy.
                    He founded there a poetical association, and became a member of the “Macaria”
                    and more than one student club; but he was unfortunately drawn into the
                    hostilities then rife between two parties in the university, and, after fighting
                    several party duels, was at last forced to leave the town to escape the results
                    of a street fray in which he took part. From Leipsic he went to Berlin, and then
                    to Vienna, with letters to his father’s old friends, the Prussian ambassador Von
                    Humboldt and Friedrich Schlegel. Two little pieces which he wrote for the stage,
                        <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Braut</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Der grüne</hi><hi rend="italic">Domino,</hi> were acted at the Vienna Court
                    Theatre in July 1812 with great success; and, with the consent of his parents,
                    he gave up all his former plans, with the hope of being able to make a living by
                    literature alone. His other works followed with astonishing rapidity. In some
                    fifteen months appeared some dozen dramatic pieces and the librettos of a few
                    operas <hi rend="italic">(Das Fischermädchen, Der vierjährige Posten,</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">Die Bergknappen),</hi> besides many short poems. One after
                    the other all his plays were received at the Vienna Theatre with applause. <hi
                        rend="italic">Zriny,</hi> founded on an heroic incident in Hungarian
                    history, was the favourite with the public; but Goethe praised <hi rend="italic"
                        >Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Braut, Der grüne</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Domino,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Die Sühne.</hi> In January 1813, at the
                    age of one and twenty, Körner was appointed poet to the court theatre in Vienna.
                    With the preparation of the libretto of an opera, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Rückkehr</hi><hi rend="italic">des Ulysses,</hi> for
                    Beethoven, and with the writing, printing, and stage preparation of his plays,
                    the young poet’s hands were now full; very busy and very happy he describes
                    himself in his letters. His betrothal to a young Viennese lady, known now only
                    as the “Toni” of his correspondence, was another source of happiness; but this
                    bright career came suddenly to an end. In the early spring of 1813 there was
                    published the <hi rend="italic">Fatherland:s Call to Arms in the Struggle for
                        Liberation,</hi> and Körner was one of the first to answer the summons. He
                    left Vienna in March, and at Breslau joined the Prussian free-corps then forming
                    under the command of Lützow. When the corps was solemnly consecrated in the
                    village church at Rogau a few days later, the service was opened with a chorale,
                    set to Körner’s words, “Dem Herrn Allein die Ehre”; and almost immediately
                    afterwards, when Petersdorf was sent on a mission to Dresden, to try to unite
                    the Saxons in the common cause, the young poet was sent with him, and on this
                    occasion published his spirited prose <hi rend="italic">Address to the People of
                        Saxony.</hi> Here Körner saw his parents and friends for the last time. In
                    April he was made lieutenant by the vote of his comrades; and a little later,
                    having left the infantry, he was made adjutant to Lützow himself. At Kitzen,
                    near Leipsic, during the three weeks’ armistice, he was severely wounded through
                    the treachery of the enemy, but after several adventures escaped to Carlsbad,
                    where he remained till he was well enough to resume his former post. Lützow’s
                    free corps was in almost daily action when the young adjutant was welcomed back.
                    His cheerful zeal and self-denying helpfulness had endeared him to all his
                    comrades, and it was his wild war songs, sung by many voices to old national
                    melodies round the camp <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n153/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0153-0142"/> fires at night, that helped to spread that
                    fervour in the corps which made it peculiarly terrible to the enemy. The poems
                    written by him at this time are published under the title <hi rend="italic"
                        >Leyer</hi><hi rend="italic">und Schwert.</hi> They include the lines
                    “Abschied vom Leben,” which were composed during the night when he lay wounded
                    in the wood by Kitzen. The letters written by Körner to his parents at this time
                    are tender and thoughtful—often aflame with patriotic fervour, but with now and
                    then a ring of intense sadness which forebodes the end. This was very near. His
                    last poem, “Das Schwertlied,” was scribbled in his pocket-book at dawn on the
                    26th of August, when the corps was prepared for action; and he was reading it to
                    a friend when the order to attack was given. It is the wildest of all his
                    warsongs, a love-rhapsody to his sword,—the soldier’s bride; and it was this
                    poem that suggested the refrain of Mrs Hemans’s beautiful verses to his memory.
                    In the engagement that followed, on the high road between Gadebusch and
                    Schwerin, Körner, as adjutant, fought at Liitzow’s side. The French were in
                    great force, but were overcome and fled. Among the hottest in pursuit was
                    Körner, who was mortally wounded, as he rode through a wood, by a shot from one
                    of the fugitive <hi rend="italic">tirailleurs</hi> who lay hidden there. He was
                    buried with full military honours under an old oak on the road from Lübelow to
                    Dreikrug, by the village of Wöbbelin, where there is now a monument to his
                    memory.</p>
                <p>Körner’s position in the literature of his country is a peculiar one. He was not
                    quite two and twenty when he died, and his works are necessarily but
                    first-fruits—might all be included in the modest title <hi rend="italic"
                        >Knospen</hi> —-^plentiful indeed, and full of promise of flowers to come.
                    His earlier poems were hardly more than graceful and pleasing, and even his
                    popular dramas scarcely entitle him to a nigh place in the literature of his
                    country. It was with the war that Korner ’ s true inspiration came. Had he lived
                    a lifetime, he could never have excelled the productions of those few
                    impassioned weeks; but the homage which all Germany paid, and still pays, to the
                    young poet’s memory is due, not to his lyric genius alone, but to his bright
                    youth also, and heroic death. His works have passed through many editions. That
                    published in one volume, with a preface by Karl Streckfuss (Berlin, 1879),
                    includes a sketch of his life, extracts from his letters, a few English
                    translations of his poems, and stanzas to his memory by German and English
                    poets, of which last Felicia Hernans is the chief. There is an indifferent
                    English translation of the life of Körner by his father, with selections from
                    his works, by G. F. Richardson, 2 vols., 1827. . . (F. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
