<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0042-0033-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KEN, Thomas (9th edition, volume 14, page 33)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45v4z">Hymns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz36">Inns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp12">Prayer</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756s76">Prayers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173723">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:808921">Anglicans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1074680">Prayer</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:965486">Hymns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n42/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KEN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi></label> (1637-1711),
                    the most eminent of the non-juring bishops, and one of the fathers of modern
                    English hymnology, was born at Little Berkhampstead, Herts, in 1637. He was the
                    son of Thomas Ken of FurnivaΓs Inn, who belonged to an ancient stock,—that of
                    the Kens of Ken Place, in Somersetshire; his mother was a daughter of the now
                    forgotten poet, John Chalkhill, who is called by Walton an “acquaintant and
                    friend of Edmund Spenser.” It may be mentioned that Ken’s stepsister, Anne, was
                    married to Izaak Walton in 1646, a connexion which brought Ken from his boyhood
                    under the refining influence of this gentle and devout man. In 1652 he entered
                    Winchester College, and in 1656 became a student of Hart Hall, Oxford. He gained
                    a fellowship at New College in 1657, and proceeded B.A. in 1661 and M.A. in
                    1664. He was for some time tutor of his college; but the most characteristic
                    reminiscence of his university life is the mention made by Anthony Wood that in
                    the musical gatherings of the time “Thomas Ken of New College, a junior, would
                    be sometimes among them, and sing his part.” Ordained in 1662, when he was
                    twenty-five years old, he successively held the livings of Little Easton in
                    Essex, Brighstone (sometimes called Brixton) in the Isle of Wight, and East
                    Woodhay in Hampshire; in 1672 he resigned the last of these, and returned to
                    Winchester, being by this time a prebendary of the cathedral, and chaplain to
                    the bishop, as well as a fellow of Winchester College. He remained there for
                    several years, <pb facs="mdp.39015074635338_0042.jp2"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0042-0034"/> acting as curate in one of the lowest
                    districts, and fulfilling other duties in the city, but, above all, preparing
                    his <hi rend="italic">Manual of Prayers for the use of the Scholars of
                        Winchester College,</hi> which was first published in 1674, and composing
                    hymns. It was at this time that he wrote, primarily for the same body as his
                    prayers, his morning, evening, and midnight hymns, the first two of which,
                    beginning “Awake, my soul, and with the sun” and “Glory to Thee, my God, this
                    night,” are now household words wherever the English tongue is spoken. The
                    latter is often made to begin with the line “All praise to Thee, my God, this
                    night,” but in the earlier editions over which Ken had control, the line is
                    given as above.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                            fact, however, that in 1712—only a year after Ken’s death— his
                            publisher, Brome, published the hymn with the opening words “All praise”
                            has been deemed by such a high authority as Lord Selborne sufficient
                            evidence that the alteration had Ken’s authority.</p></note> In 1674 Ken
                    paid a visit to Rome in company with young Izaak Walton, and this journey seems
                    mainly to have resulted in confirming his regard for the Anglican communion. In
                    1679 he was appointed by Charles II. chaplain to the Princess Mary, wife of
                    William of Orange. While with the court at the Hague, he incurred the
                    displeasure of William by insisting that a promise of marriage, made to an
                    English lady of high birth by a relative of the prince, should be kept; and he
                    therefore gladly returned to England in 1680, when he was immediately appointed
                    one of the king’s chaplains. He was once more residing at Winchester in 1683
                    when Charles came to the city with his doubtfully composed court, and his
                    residence was chosen as the home of Nell Gwynne; but Ken stoutly objected to
                    this arrangement, and succeeded in making the favourite find quarters elsewhere.
                    We find him in August of this same year accompanying Lord Dartmouth to Tangiers
                    as chaplain to the fleet, and Pepys, who was one of the company, has left on
                    record some quaint and kindly reminiscences of him and of his services on board.
                    The fleet returned in April 1684, and a few months after, upon a vacancy
                    occurring in the see of Bath and Wells, Ken, now Dr Ken, was appointed bishop.
                    It is said that, upon the occurrence of the vacancy, Charles, mindful of the
                    high and pure spirit he had shown at Winchester, exclaimed, “Where is the good
                    little man that refused his lodging to poor Neill” and determined that no other
                    should be bishop. The consecration took place at Lambeth, January 25, 1685; and
                    one of Ken’s first duties was to attend the death-bed of Charles, where his wise
                    and faithful ministrations won the admiration of everybody except Bishop Burnet.
                    In this year he published his <hi rend="italic">Exposition on the Church
                        Catechism,</hi> which is perhaps better known by its sub-title, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Practice of Divine Love.</hi> His public life as bishop is
                    mainly remembered from the stand he took upon two memorable occasions. In 1688,
                    when James reissued his “Declaration of Indulgence,” Ken was one of the “seven
                    bishops” who refused to publish it. He was probably influenced by two
                    considerations :—first, by his profound aversion to Roman Catholicism, to which
                    he felt he would be giving some episcopal recognition by compliance; but, second
                    and more especially, by the feeling that James by his arbitrary action was
                    compromising the spiritual freedom of the church. Along with his six brethren,
                    Ken was committed to the Tower, June 8, 1688, on a charge of high misdemeanour;
                    the trial, which took place on the 29th and 30th of the month, and which
                    resulted in a verdict of acquittal, is matter of history. With the revolution
                    which speedily followed this impolitic trial, new troubles encountered Ken; for,
                    having sworn allegiance to James, he thought himself thereby precluded from
                    taking the oath to William of Orange. Accordingly, he took his place among the
                    non-jurors, and, as ho stood firm to his refusal, he was, in August 1691,
                    superseded in his bishopric by Dr Kidder, dean of Peterborough. From this time
                    he lived mostly in retirement, finding a congenial home with Lord Weymouth, his
                    friend from college days, at Longleat in Somersetshire; and, though pressed to
                    resume his diocese in 1703, upon the death of Bishop Kidder, he declined, partly
                    on the ground of growing weakness, but partly no doubt from his love for the
                    quiet life of devotion which he was able to lead at Longleat. His death took
                    place there upon the 19th of March 1711.</p>
                <p>Although Ken wrote much poetry, besides his hymns, he cannot be called a great
                    poet; but he had that fine combination of spiritual insight and feeling with
                    poetic taste which marks all great hymnwriters. As a hymn-writer he has had few
                    equals in England; it can scarcely be said that even Kcble, though possessed of
                    much rarer poetic gifts, surpassed him in his own sphere (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Hymns,</hi> vol. xιi. p. 592). In his own day he took high
                    rank as a pulpit orator, and even royalty had to beg for a seat amongst his
                    audiences; but bis sermons are now forgotten. He lives in history, apart from
                    his three hymns, mainly as a man of unstained purity and invincible fidelity to
                    conscience, weak only in a certain narrowness of view which is a frequent
                    attribute of the intense character which he possessed. As an ecclesiastic he was
                    α High Churchman of the old school.</p>
                <p>Ken’s poetical works were published in collected form by W. Hawkins, his relative
                    and executor, in 1721, and extended to four volumes; his prose works were issued
                    in 1838 in one volume, under the editorship of J. T. Round. A brief memoir was
                    prefixed by Hawkins to a selection from Ken’s works which he published in 1713;
                    and a life, in two volumes, by the Rev. W. L. Bowles, appeared in 1830. But the
                    standard biography of Ken is that of J. Lavieount Anderdon (<hi rend="italic"
                        >The Life of Thomas Ken, Bishop of Bath and Wells, by a Layman,</hi> 1851;
                    2d ed., 1854).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
