<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0011-0002-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">KARAITES, or Caraites</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 2</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2sf6k">Talmud</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45d8np3k">Kale</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n36h">Pentateuch</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mv15">Sects</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h6r">Risk</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1104504">Samaritans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:985798">Kale</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1110714">Sects</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1098241">Ritual</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1064447">Pioneers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:800130">Age</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n11/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KARAITES, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Caraites</hi></label>, a
                    Jewish sect of the Middle Ages, claiming to be distinguished by adherence to
                    Scripture as contrasted with oral tradition, whence the name (from K"∣p, as if
                    “readers,” <hi rend="italic">scripturarii·,</hi> sometimes also N∏ρo 'J5). They
                    have frequently been identified with the Sadducees or with the Samaritans, with
                    neither of whom have they any historical connexion or much spiritual affinity.
                    The schism arose at Baghdad about the middle of the 8th century, when the
                    hereditary claims of Anan, a learned Talmudist, to the office of Resh Galutha
                    were set aside by the Gaonim or heads of rabbinical schools at Sura and
                    Pumbeditha because he was believed to undervalue the authority of the Talmud. An
                    appeal by Anan to the caliph proved unsuccessful, and he appears even to have
                    been. imprisoned for some time; but ultimately he was permitted to migrate along
                    with his followers to Palestine, where they erected in Jerusalem a synagogue
                    which continued to be maintained until the time of the crusades. From this
                    centre the sect diffused itself thinly over Syria, spread into Egypt, and
                    ultimately reached south-eastern Europe. Anan, who is said to have died in 765
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">a,d.,</hi> was the author of a commentary on the Pentateuch
                    and other works in Talmudic Hebrew and Arabic,—all of which unfortunately are
                    lost; for our knowledge of the distinctive principles maintained by him we are
                    thus left entirely dependent on the hostile indications of opponents. In general
                    we know that he showed great bitterness against the Talmud and its upholders
                    (the “Rabbanites ”) for their falsification of the written law by arbitrary
                    additions and subtractions, but there is nothing to indicate that he himself had
                    the insight or the fervour by which he could have become the pioneer of any
                    really great reformation in religion or morals. The questions in dispute appear
                    to have turned entirely on points of very minute detail. Several of them related
                    to the regulation of the calendar, the new moon, for example, being fixed by the
                    Karaites by direct observation, not by astronomical calculation, and the
                    intercalary year also being determined empirically; others related to paschal
                    and pentecostal ritual, such as the precise hour for killing the lamb or for
                    burning its remains. The differences which affected social life most deeply were
                    those relating to Sabbath observance and the forbidden degrees of marriage, the
                    Karaites not recognizing any distinction between relationships of consanguinity
                    and those of affinity, while in their zeal to avoid all risk of infringement of
                    the sacredness of the day of rest they prohibited the burning of any light at
                    all in their houses from sunset to sunset. Little information as to the Karaites
                    can be derived from their liturgies, which are comparatively modern; though
                    differing from those used by the Rabbinical Jews, they are not characterized by
                    any marked divergence in principle. The controversies as to the rule of faith
                    which so deeply divided the Christian church in the 16th century gave to this
                    obscure sect an illusory and passing importance, the Catholics frequently
                    hurling the epithet Karaei, in token of contempt, at the Protestants, who in
                    their turn willingly accepted it as sufficiently descriptive of their attitude
                    towards Scripture. The Karaites never have been numerous; the present community
                    in Jerusalem numbers only about ten families. They occur in Constantinople and
                    elsewhere in Turkey, but are chiefly met with in southern Russia, and especially
                    in the Crimea, where in 1874 they numbered some 6000, chiefly in Eupatoria,
                    Theodosia, and Sebastopol. In the Crimea their historical capital and chief
                    synagogue was formerly the “Jews’Castle” (Tshufut-Kale), near Bakhchisarai. The
                    place is now deserted; its cemetery was the seat of Firkowitsch’s notorious
                    forgeries (inscriptions of 1st century), by which he sought to establish a
                    fabulous antiquity for his sect. According to Strack <hi rend="italic">(A.
                    Firkowitsch u. seine</hi><hi rend="italic">Entdeckungen,</hi> 1876) the oldest
                    tombstones do not go back beyond the 14th century. The modern Karaites are
                    generally well spoken of for their honesty, perseverance, and simple habits of
                    life; but their enslavement to tradition is quite as complete as that of any
                    Talmudist could possibly be.</p>
                <p>Among the older authorities maybe mentioned Morinus, <hi rend="italic">Exercit.
                    Bibl.,</hi> lib. ii. ex. 7, 1669; and Triglandius, <hi rend="italic">Diatribe
                    de</hi><hi rend="italic">Secta</hi><hi rend="italic">Karaeorum,</hi> 1703. See·
                    Grätz, <hi rend="italic">Gesch.</hi><hi rend="italic">der Juden,</hi> especially
                    in vol. v., 1860; and Fürst, <hi rend="italic">Gesch. des Karderthurns,</hi>
                    1865.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
