<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0151-0140-05" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KORDOFAN (9th edition, volume 14, page 140)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49p2wf9z">Travel</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j96094w">Seasons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204591">Sudan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173723">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106735">Schists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110447">Seasons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:985568">Kababish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n151/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KORDOFAN</label>, a province of the Egyptian Sudan, which,
                    though marked off from the surrounding territory by no very definite confines,
                    may be said to lie between 12° and 16° N. lat. and between 29° 30' and 32° 30'
                    E. long. On the east it does not reach the Nile, and on the west it is usually
                    held to be separated from Darfur by a neutral strip of country. It consists for
                    the most part of a rolling steppe in which a hill of 50 feet is a landmark for a
                    day’s journey; but towards the west there are a few isolated peaks such as Jebel
                    Abu Senun and Jebel Kordofan, which rise to a height of 150 to 800 feet above
                    the plain, and in the north-west there are two considerable groups, Jebel Katul
                    and Jebel Kagga. The general elevation of the country above sea-level is given
                    as from 1410 to 1840 feet. A granitic sand with abundance of mica and felspar
                    forms the upper stratum throughout the greater part of the area; but an
                    admixture of clay, which is observable in the north, becomes strongly marked in
                    the south, where there are also stretches of black vegetable mould. Beneath
                    there appears to unfold itself an unbroken surface of mica schist. River or
                    stream there is really none, though a few temporary watercourses or <hi
                        rend="italic">khhrs</hi> exist in the rainy season; and the only permanent
                    lakes are El Birkeh, El Rahad, and Shirkeleh, which are formed by the great Khor
                    Abu Hable in the south. During the rainy season the water collects in myriads of
                    little depressions, but owing partly to rapid evaporation and partly to the
                    porous character of the soil the surface of the country is soon as dry as
                    before. The water which has found its way through the granitic sand flows over
                    the surface of the mica schist and settles in the hollows. Wells consequently
                    sunk so as to reach the solid rock obtain a supply of water more or less
                    abundant according to the spot which they happen to strike; and it is the
                    existence of these which renders human life possible in Kordofan. It is
                    estimated that (apart from those in a few areas of depression—Cagmar, Abu
                    Haraze, Bara, and Mulbes—where the sand stratum is very thin and water is
                    reached at the depth of a few feet) there are about 900 of these wells. They are
                    narrow shafts going down from 75 to 150 or 200 feet, and supported “from the
                    bottom to a little above the water-level” by the long roots of the mimosa, wound
                    round so as to form a complete casing. The water ⅛ raised by rope and bucket at
                    the cost of enormous labour, and none is available for irrigation. The very
                    cattle are trained to go a long time without drinking. Entire villages migrate
                    after harvest to the neighbourhood of some plentiful well; and in El Obeyd water
                    becomes a regular article of trade soon after the close of the rains. As there
                    is no highland area draining into Kordofan, the underground reservoirs are
                    dependent on the local rainfall, and a large number of the wells are dry during
                    many months. The rainy season lasts from June to September, rain falling every
                    three or four days in brief but violent showers. The wind during that period is
                    from the south or southwest; the air is extremely oppressive; and fevers prevail
                    among the foreign residents. In September the north winds begin to take their
                    turn, and from the middle of October they blow steadily throughout the winter,
                    and produce what Europeans consider a delightful climate. With March begins the
                    dry and sultry summer. The settled population of Kordofan is estimated at
                    164,740, the nomadic at 114,000. The former, who are scattered over the country
                    in about eight hundred and sixty villages, are of very mingled blood, especially
                    in the neighbourhood of the capital, but the Ghodiat, Gilledat, and Gowanieh
                    appear to be the original stock. Of the nomadic tribes the most noteworthy are
                    the Hasanieh, the Kababish, and the Bagara. The last-mentioned—who roam about
                    the southern parts of the country—are a dark red-bronze race remarkable for
                    their magnificent physique. The staple crop in Kordofan is the dokhn or <hi
                        rend="italic">Penicillaria typhoides.</hi> Eaten both uncooked and in
                    various culinary conditions, it forms the main food of nine-tenths of the
                    population, and <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n152/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0152-0141"/> furnishes the raw material for the sweetish
                    Kordofan beer or merissa. Cattle are largely bred by the Bagara, and camels by
                    the Kababish; aud horses, goats, donkeys, and sheep are kept in small numbers.
                    Since the ostrich has been almost hunted out of the country the chief article of
                    importance for trade is the gum yielded by the many mimosa trees, which along
                    with the hijlij, the tamarisk, and the talh tend to relieve the monotony of the
                    steppe. Salt and iron ore exist within the province, but they have not become of
                    any practical value.</p>
                <p>Of the movements by which the present composite ethnology of Kordofan was
                    attained little record is recoverable. In 1790 Sheikh Nasib of Sennaar
                    subjugated the district; and under his rule the inhabitants prospered. But,
                    piqued by his neighbour’s success, Ibn Fadhl of Darfur invaded Kordofan with a
                    powerful army numbering no less than 12,000 or 14,000 camels, and completely
                    defeated the Sennaar governor Melek il Hashma. The Darfur supremacy continued
                    till 1821 when Mohammed Aly undertook the conquest of Nubia and Sennaar. The
                    defterdar, Mohammed Aly’s son-in-law, subjugated Kordofan, and continued to rule
                    it with worse than a rod of iron till he was recalled on account of his
                    cruelties.</p>
                <p>See the Travels of Sultan Teima (1821), Ruppell (1824), Holroyd (1837), Rus-seger
                    (1837), Pallme (1844), Brehm (1848), Graf von Schlieffen (1853); Petherick,
                    Egypt, the Sudan, and Central Africa, London, 1861; Major H. G. Prout, General
                    Report on Province of Kordofan, Cairo, 1877; Marno, Reise in der egypt. Equat.
                    Provinz, Yienna, 1879. 'lhe Italian travellers Matteucci and Massari traversed
                    Kordofan in 1880, in their great journey across the continent. The geographical
                    nomenclature is still in many cases uncertain.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
