<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0166-0155-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">KUMAUN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 155</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h77">Mohammedanism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f430">Timber</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4251ft9s">Tea</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vd7z">Graining</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1144120">Tea</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1150988">Timber</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1137272">Sugar</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1150682">Tibetans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n166/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KUMAUN</label>, a district in the North-Western Provinces of
                    India, lying between 28° 55' and 30° 50' N. lat., and 78° 52' and 80° 56' E.
                    long. It consists of two distinct tracts—the sub-Himalayan ranges, and the <hi
                    rend="italic">bhdbhar</hi> or waterless forest, averaging from 10 to 15 miles in
                    breadth, which stretches between the forests and the Tarâi. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Himalaya,</hi> vol. xi.∙p. 824. Of the entire area of the
                    highlands, only 500 square miles are returned as cultivated and 100 square miles
                    as cultivable. The southern or <hi rend="italic">bhdbhar</hi> portion was up to
                    1850 an almost impenetrable forest, given upto wild animals; but since then the
                    numerous clearings have attracted a large population from the hills, who
                    cultivate the rich soil during the hot and cold seasons, returning to the hills
                    in the rains. The rest of Kumâun is a maze of mountains, some of which are among
                    the loftiest known. In fact, in a tract not more than 140 miles in length and 40
                    in breadth, there are over thirty peaks rising to elevations exceeding 18,000
                    feet (see vol. xi. p. 825). The rivers rise chiefly in the southern slope of the
                    Tibetan watershed north of the loftiest peaks, amongst which they make their way
                    down valleys of rapid declivity and extraordinary depth. The principal are the
                    Kâli or Gogra, and the Pindar and Kâilganga, whose waters join the Alaknanda.
                    The valuable timber of the yet uncleared forest tracts in Kumâun is now under
                    official supervision. The chief trees are the <hi rend="italic">chip</hi> or
                    three-leaved Himalayan pine, the cypress, fir, alder, <hi rend="italic">sal</hi>
                    or iron-wood, and <hi rend="italic">saindan.</hi> Limestone, sandstone, slate,
                    gneiss, and granite constitute the principal geological formations of the
                    district. Mines of iron, copper, gypsum, lead, asbestos, and coral exist; but
                    they are not thoroughly worked.</p>
                <p>The census of 1872 disclosed a population of 433,314, of whom 425,963 were
                    returned as Hindus and 5569 as Mohammedans. The Kumâunis are a tolerably fair,
                    good-looking race, active, cheerful, honest, and industrious. Polyandry is
                    unknown, but polygamy is frequent. The 4606 villages of the district are
                    scattered about the hillsides, the houses being built of stone laid in mud, and
                    roofed with slates, or with planks or thatch. The only native town is Almora.
                    There are large bazaars at the European stations of Naini Tai and Ranikhet. The
                    area available for cultivation is small; but wherever possible the hill sides
                    have been terraced. The soil except in some of the valleys is poor and stony,
                    and requires much manure. On the better kinds of land rice, wheat, and tobacco
                    are grown; on the others wheat, barley, mustard, vetches, flax, Indian corn,
                    millets, pulses, sugar-cane, cotton, oil-seeds, &amp;c. The staple food of the
                    peasantry is <hi rend="italic">mαηduα</hi><hi rend="italic">{Eleusine</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">corocana).</hi> Potatoes are becoming common. Fruit is very
                    plentiful, and the oranges are of excellent quality. The tea plantations form
                    now an important and valuable feature in the district, but are almost entirely
                    in the hands of European owners. In 1876-77 the gardens covered an area cf 2222
                    acres, yielding 261,060 ft of tea. The only other manufacture is the weaving of
                    coarse woollen clothing. The imports from Tibet include beasts of burden, salt,
                    coarse cloths, and Chinese silk. The exports to Tibet are grain, cotton goods,
                    broadcloth, quilts, hardware, tobacco, sugar, spices, dyes, tea, and timber. To
                    the plains of India Kumâun sends grain, clarified butter, tea, ginger, turmeric,
                    red'pepper, drugs, spices, bark, honey, wax, a little iron and copper timber,
                    and wild jungle produce. The roads in the hills are for the most part only
                    bridle-paths, more or less well laid out, but all now well bridged. Except in
                    the <hi rend="italic">bhabhar</hi> and deep valleys, the climate is mild. The
                    rainfall of the outer Himalayan range, which is first struck by the monsoon, is
                    double that of the central hills, in the average proportion of 80 iuches to 40.
                    No winter passes without snow on the higher ridges, and in some years it is
                    universal throughout the mountain tract. Frosts, especially in the valleys, are
                    often severe. Kumâun is occasionally visited by epidemic cholera. Leprosy is
                    most prevalent in the east of the district. Goitre and cretinism afflict a small
                    proportion of the inhabitants. The hill fevers at times exhibit the rapid and
                    malignant features of plague. The <hi rend="italic">rnahdmari</hi> pestilence,
                    which was formerly confined to Garhwâl, has of late years extended its ravages
                    to Kumâun.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
