<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0099-0088-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">KINGSLEY, Charles</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 88</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1113216">Sermons</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h10">Sermons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kw57q5f">Yeast</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bd1d">Poor</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n99/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KINGSLEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi></label>
                    (1819-1875), an English clergyman, poet, and novelist, was born on the 12th June
                    1819, at Holne vicarage, Dartmoor, Devon. His early years were spent at his
                    father’s living in the Fen country, and afterwards in North Devon. The scenery
                    of both made a great impression on his mind, and was afterwards described with
                    singular vividness in his writings. He was educated at private schools and at
                    King’s College, London, after his fither’s promotion to the rectory of Chelsea.
                    In 1838 he entered Magdalene College, Cambridge, where he took his degree in
                    1842, first-class in classics, and senior optime in mathematics. In the same
                    year he was ordained to the curacy of Eversley in Hampshire, to the rectory of
                    w4ιich he was not long afterwards presented, and this was his home for the
                    remaining thirty-three years of his life, although his residence there was much
                    broken by various domestic circumstances as well as, in later years, by
                    promotion to other offices in the church.</p>
                <p>In 1844 he married Fanny, daughter of Pascoe Grenfell, and in 1848, when aged
                    twenty-nine, he published his first volume, <hi rend="italic">The Saint's
                    Tragedy.</hi> In 1860 he was appointed to the professorship of modern history in
                    the university of Cambridge, which he resigned in 1869, and was soon after
                    appointed to a canonry at Chester. In 1873 this was exchanged for a canonry at
                    Westminster. He died at Eversley, after a short illness, on the 23d January
                    1875.</p>
                <p>It will be seen that his life had but few incidents. With the exception of
                    occasional changes of residence in England, generally for the sake of his wife’s
                    health, one or two short holiday trips abroad, a tour in the West Indies, and
                    another in America to visit his ’eldest son settled there as an engineer, his
                    life was spent in the peaceful, if active, occupations of a clergyman who did
                    his duty earnestly, and of a vigorous and prolific writer. But in spite of this
                    outward peace he was for many years one of the most prominent men of his time,
                    who both personally and by his works had no little influence on the thought of
                    his generation. Though at no time profoundly learned, he was a man of wide and
                    various information, whose interests and sympathies embraced almost all branches
                    of human knowledge as well as speculations on subjects on which men but slowly
                    learn that speculation avails them nothing. Gifted with great powers of
                    language, both written and in conversation, with a keen wit, and a fund of
                    knowledge far above the average, there were few subjects in which he did not
                    shine, and many in which he excelled. The inherited peculiarities of his
                    opinions and temperament, which made him seemingly though not really
                    inconsistent, excited curiosity, and were in part the reason of his great
                    attractiveness. Sprung on the father’s side from an old English race of country
                    squires, and on his mother’s side from a good West Indian family who had been
                    slaveholders for generations, he had the keen love of sport and the exceeding
                    sympathy with country folk often fostered by such pursuits, while he had at the
                    same time much of the aristocratic scorn for lower races to be found among those
                    who have been in a dominant position among them.</p>
                <p>With the sympathetic organization which made him keenly sensible of the wants of
                    the poor, he threw himself heartily into the movement known as Christian
                    Socialism, of which Mr Maurice was the recognized leader, and for many years he
                    was considered as an extreme radical in a profession which holds as a rule but
                    few such. While in this phase of mind he wrote his novels <hi rend="italic"
                    >Yeast</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Alton Locke,</hi> in which, though he pointed
                    out unsparingly the folly of extremes, his sympathies were unmistakably shown to
                    be, not only with the poor as in their strife against the rich, but with much
                    that was done and said by the leaders in the Chartist movement. Yet even then he
                    considered that the true leaders of the people were a peer and a dean, and there
                    was no real inconsistency in the fact that at a later period he was among the
                    most strenuous defenders of Governor Eyre in the measures adopted by him to put
                    down the Jamaican disturbances. In politics he might therefore have been
                    described as a Tory aristocrat tempered by sympathy, or as a Radical tempered by
                    hereditary scorn of subject races. The like seeming but not real inconsistencies
                    were to be found in his attitude as a clergyman. He was a man of earnest piety,
                    and lived so near in his own mind to the great realities of the unseen world
                    that he could even afford to speak of serious subjects in a way which in one
                    less reverent than he would have seemed to lack reverence; and, while he held in
                    many respects what would be called a liberal theology, the church, its
                    organization, its creed, its dogma, had ever an increasing hold upon him.
                    Although at one period he certainly shrunk from reciting the Athanasian creed in
                    church, he was towards the close of his life found ready to join an association
                    for the defence of this symbol. With these two influences at work in his mind,
                    it was not unnatural that the more orthodox and conservative should gain the
                    upper hand as time went on, but the careful students of him and his writings
                    will find a deep conservatism underlying all the most radical utterances of his
                    earlier years, while a passionate sympathy for the poor, the afflicted, and the
                    weak held possession of him till the last hour of his life.</p>
                <p>Both as a writer and in his personal intercourse with men Kingsley was a
                    thoroughly stimulating teacher. He would not probably have wished to found a
                    school, and most certainly never did so. As with his own teacher Mr Maurice, his
                    influence on other men rather consisted in the fact of his inducing them to
                    think for themselves than that he led them to adopt his own views. Perhaps these
                    were at no time quite definite enough to have been reduced to such system as is
                    demanded for one who would make his disciples think as himself. But his healthy
                    and stimulating influence went far beyond the boundaries of his parish, his
                    canonries, and his wide circle of friends, and was largely attributable to the
                    fact that he gave utterance to the thoughts which were stirring in many minds
                    during the time of his own most vigorous life. His originality, which was great,
                    lay rather in his manner of crystallizing the current thoughts of men, and
                    giving them apt expression, than in any new discoveries in the matters of which
                    he treated. Just because he was completely the product and the mouthpiece of his
                    own time, it may be doubted whether his influence on the future will be very
                    great, and it is possible that men who may read his works by chance some years
                    hence will fail to understand how wide was the influence he exercised.</p>
                <p>As a preacher he was vivid, eager, and earnest, equally plain-spoken and
                    uncompromising when preaching to a courtly congregation or to his own village
                    poor. One of the very best of his writings is a sermon called <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Message of the Church to Working Men·,</hi> but as a rule his sermons
                    cannot be read with the interest with which they were heard, and none of his
                    later published sermons equal the little volume of <hi rend="italic">Twenty-five
                    Village Sermons</hi> which he preached in the early years of his Eversley
                    life.</p>
                <p>As a novelist his chief power lay in his descriptive faculties. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Yeast</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Alton Locke</hi> were written out of the heat
                    of strong conviction, and dealt in a brilliant manner with great social
                    questions, but the later novels seem to have been written rather because he
                    wished to say something than because he had something to say, and in spite of
                    new and ever new editions it may be doubted whether the real interest felt in
                    these works is considerable. Few persons <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n100/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0100-0089"/> read them twice, although it is fair to say that
                    this may partially arise from the fact that the story is so vividly told that it
                    is not forgotten, and therefore needs no second reading. But the descriptions of
                    South American scenery in <hi rend="italic">Westward Ho,</hi> of the Egyptian
                    desert in <hi rend="italic">Hypatia,</hi> of the North Devon scenery in <hi
                    rend="italic">Two Years Ago,</hi> are among the most brilliant pieces of
                    word-painting in English prose writing, and the American scenery is even more
                    vividly and more truthfully described when he had seen it only by the eye of his
                    imagination than in his work <hi rend="italic">At Last,</hi> which was written
                    after he had visited the tropics.</p>
                <p>As a poet he wrote but little, but that little he wrote with singular facility,
                    and there are passages in the <hi rend="italic">Saines</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Tragedy,</hi> and many isolated lyrics, which ought to take their place in all
                    future standard collections of English literature. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Andromeda</hi> is a very successful attempt at naturalizing the hexameter as a
                    form of English verse, and reproduces with great skill the sonorous roll of the
                    Greek original.</p>
                <p>In person Charles Kingsley was tall and spare, sinewy rather than powerful, and
                    of a restless excitable temperament. His complexion was swarthy, his hair dark,
                    and his eye bright and piercing. His temper was hot, kept under rigid control,
                    his disposition tender, gentle, and loving as that of a woman, with flashing
                    scorn and indignation against all that was ignoble and impure; he was a good
                    husband, father, and friend.</p>
                <p>Kingsley’s life has been written by his widow, in two volumes, entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Charles Kingsley, his Letters and Memories of his Life,</hi> and
                    presents a very touching and beautiful picture of her husband, but perhaps
                    hardly does justice to his humour, his wit, his overflowing vitality and boyish
                    fun.</p>
                <p>The following is a list of Kingsley’s writings :— <hi rend="italic">Saint's
                    Tragedy,</hi> a drama, 1848; <hi rend="italic">Alton Locke,</hi> a novel, 1849;
                    <hi rend="italic">Yeast,</hi> a novel, 1849; <hi rend="italic">Twenty-five
                    Village Sermons,</hi> 1849; <hi rend="italic">Phaeton, or Loose Thoughts for
                    Loose Thinkers,</hi> 1852; <hi rend="italic">Sermons on National Subjects,</hi>
                    1st series, 1852; <hi rend="italic">Hypatia,</hi> a novel, 1853; <hi
                    rend="italic">Glaucus,</hi><hi rend="italic">or the Wonders of the Shore,</hi>
                    1854; <hi rend="italic">Sermons on National Subjects,</hi> 2d series, 1854; <hi
                    rend="italic">Alexandria and her Schools,</hi> 1854; <hi rend="italic">Westward
                    Ho!</hi> a novel, 1855; <hi rend="italic">Sermons for the Times,</hi> 1855; <hi
                    rend="italic">The Heroes,</hi> Greek fairy tales, 1856; <hi rend="italic">Two
                    Years Ago,</hi> a novel, 1857; <hi rend="italic">Andromeda and other Poems,</hi>
                    1858; <hi rend="italic">The Good News of God,</hi> sermons, 1859; <hi
                    rend="italic">Miscellanies,</hi> 1859; <hi rend="italic">Limits of Exact Science
                    applied to History</hi> (Inaugural Lectures), 1860; <hi rend="italic">Town and
                    Country Sermons,</hi> 1861; <hi rend="italic">Sermons on the Pentateuch,</hi>
                    1863; <hi rend="italic">Water-babies,</hi> 1863; <hi rend="italic">The Roman and
                    the Teuton,</hi> 1864; <hi rend="italic">David and other Sermons,</hi> 1866; <hi
                    rend="italic">Hereward the Wake,</hi> a novel, 1866; <hi rend="italic">The
                    Ancient</hi><hi rend="italic">Régime</hi> (Lectures at the Royal Institution),
                    1867; <hi rend="italic">Water of Life and other Sermons,</hi> 1867; <hi
                    rend="italic">The Hermits,</hi> 1869; <hi rend="italic">Madam Hoιo and Lady
                    Why,</hi> 1869; <hi rend="italic">At Last,</hi> 1871; <hi rend="italic">Town
                    Geology,</hi> 1872; <hi rend="italic">Discipline and other Sermons,</hi> 1872;
                    <hi rend="italic">Prose Idylls,</hi> 1873; <hi rend="italic">Plays and
                    Puritans,</hi> 1873; <hi rend="italic">Health and Education,</hi> 1874; <hi
                    rend="italic">Westminster Sermons,</hi> 1874; <hi rend="italic">Lectures
                    delivered in America,</hi> 1875. He was a large contributor to periodical
                    literature; many of his essays are included in <hi rend="italic">Prose
                    Idylls</hi> and other works in the above list. But no collection has been made
                    of some of his more characteristic writings in the <hi rend="italic">Christian
                    Socialist</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Politics for the People,</hi> many of them
                    signed by the pseudonym he then assumed, “Parson Lot.” (C. K. P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
