<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0163-0152-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KUCH BEHAR, or Coosh Behar (9th edition, volume 14,
                    page 152)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:970716">Indos</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1939163">Jute</term>
                    <term ref="fast:985280">Jutes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h77">Mohammedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47659j0m">Descent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c24qr4p">Jute</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gm3d">Tobacco</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n163/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KUCH BEHAR, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Coosh Behar</hi></label>,
                    a native state in Bengal, India, lying between 25° 57' and 26° 32' N. lat., and
                    88° 48' and 89° 55'E. long. It is entirely surrounded by British territory,
                    being bounded on the N. by Jalpâigurf, on the E. by Goâlpâra, on the S. by
                    Rangpur, and on the W. by Purniah districts. The state forms a level plain of
                    triangular shape, intersected by numerous rivers. The greater portion is fertile
                    and well cultivated, but tracts of jungle are to be seen in the north-east
                    corner, which abuts upon Assam. The soil is uniform in character throughout,
                    consisting of a light, friable loam, varying in depth from 6 inches to 3 feet,
                    superimposed upon a deep bed of sand. The whole is detritus, washed down by
                    torrents from the neighbouring Himâlayas. The rivers all pass through the state
                    from north to south, to join the main stream of the Brahmaputra. Some half dozen
                    are navigable for small trading boats throughout the year, and are nowhere
                    fordable; and there are about twenty minor streams which become navigable only
                    during the rainy season. The streams have a tendency to cut new channels for
                    themselves after every annual flood, and they communicate with one another by
                    cross-country water-courses. There are no embankments or artificial canals, nor
                    are any mineral products known to exist.</p>
                <p>The population in 1872 was 532,565, distributed over an area of 1307 square
                    miles. The Hindus numbered 127,928; the Mohammedans, 48,086. The Koch or
                    Râjbansi tribe numbered 111,125 adult males, or 63 per cent, of the whole. This
                    is a widely spread tribe, evidently of aboriginal descent, which is found
                    throughout all northern Bengal, from Purniah district to the Assam valley. They
                    are akin to the Indo-Chinese races of the north-east frontier; but they have now
                    become largely Hinduized, especially in their own home, where the appellation ‘
                    ‘ Koch” has come to be used as a term of reproach. Kuch Behar town, which
                    contains the palace of ti e râjâ, and has 7132 inhabitants, is the only populous
                    place in tl.e state. Even villages, in the ordinary sense of the word, are
                    unknown, each well-to-do family living apart in its own homestead. Rice is grown
                    on three-fourths of tlιe total cultivated area. Jute and tobacco are largely
                    grown for exportation over an increasing area; year by year. The only special
                    industries are the weaving of a strong silk from worms fed on the castor-oil
                    plant, and of a coarse jute cloth, used for screens and bedding. The external
                    trade is chiefly in the hands of Mârwâri immigrants from Upper India. The chief
                    exports are jute, tobacco, oil, timber; salt, sugar, and piece goods are
                    imported. The net revenue in 1870-71 amounted to&gt; £112,093, of which £25,719
                    was derived from <hi rend="italic">zαminddri</hi> estates in British territory.
                    The climate is damp and malarious, but not so hot as in other parts of Bengal.
                    The average annual rainfall is 123 inches.</p>
                <p>As in the case of many other small native states, the royal family of Kuch Behar
                    lays claim to a divine origin in order to conceal an impure aboriginal descent.
                    The greatest monarch of the dynasty was Nar Narayan, the son of Visu Sinh, who
                    began to reign about 1550. He conquered the whole of Kamπip, built temples in
                    Assam, of which ruins still exist bearing inscriptions with his name, and
                    extended his power southwards over what is now part of the British districts of
                    Rangpur and Purniah. To his reign also is attributed the introduction of the
                    well-known Nârâyani currency, the privilege of coining which has not yet been
                    entirely abolished. His son, Lakshmi Narayan, who succeeded him in Kuch Behar,
                    became tributary to the Mughal empire. In 1772 a competitor for the throne,
                    having been driven out of the country by his rivals, applied for assistance to
                    Warren Hastings. A detachment of sepoys was accordingly marched into the state;
                    the Bbutias, whose interference had led to this intervention, were expelled, and
                    forced to sue for peace through the mediation of the lama of Tibet. By the
                    treaty made on this occasion, April 1773, the raja acknowledged subjection to
                    the Company, and made over to it one half of his annual revenues. But, though
                    the Bhutiâs were driven out, the rivalry of domestic faction continued. In 1863,
                    on the death of the râjâ, leaving a son and heir only ten months old, a British
                    commissioner was appointed to undertake the direct management of affairs during
                    the minority of the prince, and many important reforms have thus been
                    successfully introduced.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
