<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0012-0003-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">KARAMZIN, Nikolai Mikhailovich</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 3</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n12/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KARAMZIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Nikolai
                    Mikhailovich</hi></label> (1765-1826), Russian historian, critic, novelist, and
                    poet, was born at the village of Mikhailovka, in the government of Orenburg, and
                    not at Simbirsk as many of his English and German biographers incorrectly state,
                    on the 1st of December (old style) 1765. His father, an officer in the Russian
                    army, of Tartar extraction, was anxious that his son should follow his own
                    profession. The idea was not, however, persevered in, and the future author was
                    sent to Moscow to study under Professor Schaden, whence he afterwards removed to
                    St Petersburg, where he made the acquaintance of Dmitrieff, a Russian poet of
                    some merit, and occupied himself with translating essays by foreign writers into
                    his native language. After residing some time at St Petersburg, he went to
                    Simbirsk, where he lived in retirement till induced by a friend to revisit
                    Moscow. There, finding himself in the midst of the society of learned men, he
                    again betook himself to literary work. In 1789 he resolved to travel, and
                    visited Germany, France, Switzerland, and England. On his return he published
                    his <hi rend="italic">Letters of a Russian Traveller,</hi> which met with great
                    success. They are elegantly written, and show the feeling of a poet for the
                    scenery of the countries through which he passed, but to many readers of the
                    present day they will appear insipidly sentimental. These letters were first
                    printed in the <hi rend="italic">Moscow Journal,</hi> but were afterwards
                    collected and issued in 6 vols. (1797-1801). In the same periodical Karamzin
                    also published translations of some of the tales of Marmontel, whose sickly
                    elegance was then in fashion, and some of his own original stories, among which
                    may be mentioned <hi rend="italic">Poor Liza</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Natalia
                    the Boyar’s Daughter.</hi> To judge by the cheap editions which are continually
                    appearing, these tales still find readers in Russia. The best of them is <hi
                    rend="italic">Marfa the Posadnitza of Novgorod,</hi> but all are more or less
                    disfigured by the sentimentalism already referred to. In 1794 and 1795 Karamsin
                    abandoned his literary journal, and published a miscellany in two volumes,
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Aglaia,</hi> in which appeared, among other things,
                    “The Island of Bornholm” and “Ilia Mourometz,” a story based upon the adventures
                    of the well-known hero of many a Russian legend. In 1797-99 he issued another
                    miscellany or poetical almanac, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Aonides,</hi> in conjunction with Der-zhâvin and Dmitrieff. In 1798 he compiled
                    the <hi rend="italic">Pantheon,</hi> a collection of pieces from the works of
                    the most celebrated authors ancient and modern, translated into Russian. Many of
                    his lighter productions were subsequently printed by him in a volume entitled
                    <hi rend="italic">My Trifles.</hi> In 1802 and 1803 Karamzin edited the journal
                    <hi rend="italic">The European Messenger.</hi> It was not till after the
                    publication of this work that he realized where his strength lay, and commenced
                    his <hi rend="italic">History of the Russian Empire.</hi> In order to accomplish
                    the task, he secluded himself for some years; and, on the cause of his
                    retirement becoming known to the emperor Alexander, Karamzin was invited to
                    Tver, where he read to the emperor the first eight volumes of his history. In
                    1816 he removed to St Petersburg, where he spent the happiest days of his life,
                    enjoying the favour of Alexander, and submitting to him the sheets of his great
                    work, which the emperor read over with him in the gardens of the palace of
                    Tzarskoë Selo. He did not, however, live to carry his work further than the
                    eleventh volume, terminating it at the accession of Michael Romanoff in 1613. In
                    1825 the health of Karamzin began to decline, and the emperor Nicholas, who had
                    succeeded to the throne in that year, and continued the favours which his
                    brother had bestowed on the historian, ordered a frigate to be got ready, that
                    he might visit a warmer climate to recruit his failing powers. It was, however,
                    too late; on the 22d of May (old style) 1826, Karamzin died in the Taurida
                    palace. A monument was erected to his memory at Simbirsk in the year 1845.</p>
                <p>As an historian Karamsin has deservedly a very high reputation. Till the
                    appearance of his work little had been done in this direction in Russia. The
                    preceding attempt of Tatistcheff was merely a rough sketch, inelegant in style,
                    and without the true spirit of criticism. Karamzin was most industrious in
                    accumulating materials, and the notes to his volumes are mines of curious
                    information. The style of his history is elegant and flowing, modelled rather
                    upon the easy sentences of the French prose writers than the long periodical
                    paragraphs of the old Slavonic school. Perhaps Karamzin may justly be censured
                    for the false gloss and romantic air thrown over the early Russian annals,
                    concealing the coarseness and cruelty of the native manners; in this respect he
                    reminds us of Sir Walter Scott, whose writings were at this time creating a
                    great sensation throughout Europe, and probably had their influence upon our
                    author. Karamzin appears openly as the panegyrist of the autocracy; indeed, his
                    work has been styled the “Epic of Despotism.” He does not hesitate to avow his
                    admiration of Ivan the Terrible, and considers him and his grandfather Ivan III.
                    as the builders up of Russian greatness, a glory which in his earlier writings,
                    perhaps at that time more under the influence of Western ideas, he had assigned
                    to Peter the Great. In the battle-pieces <hi rend="italic">lp.g.,</hi> the
                    description of the field of Koulikovo, the taking of Kazan, &amp;c. ) we find
                    considerable powers of description; and the characters of many of the chief
                    personages in the Russian annals are drawn in firm and bold lines. The study of
                    ethnology and historical criticism has advanced so much since the days of
                    Karamzin that some of his work has necessarily become obsolete, but it will
                    always be read with pleasure and advantage. No translation into English of this
                    <hi rend="italic">opus magnum</hi> has appeared, although even modern Greek
                    boasts its version. Of the French translation by MM. Saint Thomas and Jauffret
                    Karamzin himself had a mean opinion; he declared that the average number of
                    mistakes in each of the many volumes was two hundred. As a critic Karamzin was
                    of great service to his countιy; in fact he may be regarded as the founder of
                    the review and essay (in the Western style) among the Russians. He had read
                    extensively, and modelled himself upon Addison and others of our best writers.
                    As a novelist and writer of tales he imitated the sentimental school then in
                    vogue throughout Europe. As a poet he occupies a subordinate place, but his
                    productions are above mediocrity. Many of his lyrics are graceful and melodious,
                    and the sentiments expressed are those of a benevolent and healthy-minded man.
                    The little poem entitled <hi rend="italic">The Grave</hi> deserves special
                    mention.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
