<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0118-0107-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOMBERG, Wilhelm (9th edition, volume 12, page
                    107)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153279">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998853">Limes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998827">Lime</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1063025">Physics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z7110r">Lime</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44x4f">Doctors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gx2h">Physics</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n118/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOMBERG, <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilhelm</hi></label> (1652
                    -1715), an eminent natural philosopher, born at Batavia, January 8,1652, was
                    educated in Holland, studied law at Jena and Leipsic, and became an advocate at
                    Magdeburg in 1674. In that town he interested himself in botany and astronomy,
                    and made the acquaintance of Otto von Guericke, under whose influence,
                    renouncing his profession, he finally devoted himself exclusively to the natural
                    sciences. Having travelled in Italy, France, and England, and profited by the
                    instructions of the anatomist Graaf in Holland, he took the degree of doctor of
                    medicine at Wittemberg; and, after visiting Germany, Hungary, Bohemia, and
                    Sweden, he in 1685 settled in Rome, where he practised physic with great
                    success. At Paris, whither he repaired in 1691, he was elected a member of the
                    Academy of Sciences, and became (1702) teacher of physics and (1705) private
                    physician to the duke of Orleans. He died at Paris, September 24, 1715. In 1702
                    Homberg discovered boracic acid, termed at first the <hi rend="italic"
                    >sal</hi><hi rend="italic">sedativum</hi><hi rend="italic">Hombergi,</hi> the
                    true nature of which was ascertained by Bergman in 1775. What is known as
                    “Romberg’s phosphorus” is a mixture of calcium chloride and lime, which, after
                    heating in a sealed tube and exposure to sunlight, phosphoresces in the
                    dark.</p>
                <p>Numerous treatises by Homberg, chiefly chemical, were published in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Recueil</hi><hi rend="italic">de l</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">Academie</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                    Sciences,</hi> 1692, &amp;c. See Chauffepié, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dictionnaire,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> vol. v. p. 461.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">HOMBURG-vor-der-Höhe,</hi> chief town of the circle of
                    Obertaunus in the Wiesbaden government district of the Prussian province of
                    Hesse-Nassau, is prettily situated on a small stream at the foot of a spur of
                    the Taunus mountains, about 11 miles north of Frankfort-on-the-Main, with which
                    it is connected by rail. Homburg consists of an old and a new town, the latter,
                    founded by the landgrave Frederick II., being regular and well-built. Besides
                    the palatial edifices erected in connexion with the mineral water-cure, the most
                    important buildings are the theatre, the synagogue, and the various churches,
                    schools, and benevolent institutions. On a neighbouring hill stands the castle
                    of the former landgraves, built in 1680, and subsequently enlarged and improved.
                    The White Tower, 183 feet in height, is said to date from Roman times, and
                    certainly existed under the lords of Eppstein, who held the district in the 12th
                    century. The castle is surrounded by extensive grounds, laid out in the manner
                    of an English park. The woollen and linen manufactures of Homburg are
                    unimportant, the prosperity of the town being almost entirely due to the annual
                    influx of visitors, which in the season lasting from May to October inclusive
                    averages 9000 or 10,000. The five mineral springs which form the chief
                    attraction to strangers are very salipe, and contain a considerable proportion
                    of carbonate of lime. Their use is beneficial for diseases of the stomach and
                    intestines, and externally for diseases of the skin and rheumatism. The
                    population of the town in 1875, including the garrison, was 8294.</p>
                <p>Homburg first came into repute as a watering-place in 1834, and owing to its
                    gambling-tables, which were set up soon after, it rapidly became one of the
                    favourite and most fashionable health-resorts of the Continent. In 1849 the town
                    was occupied by Austrian troops for the purpose of enforcing the imperial decree
                    against gambling establishments, but immediately on their withdrawal the bank
                    was again opened, and play continued unchecked till 1872, when the Prussian
                    Government refused to renew the lease for gambling purposes which then expired.
                    As the capital of thy former landgraviate of Hesse-Homburg the town shared the
                    vicissitudes of that state.</p>
                <p>See Schudt’s <hi rend="italic">Homburg</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">seine</hi><hi rend="italic">Umgebungen,</hi> 11th ed., 1875.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
