<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0422-0407-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HUSSITES (9th edition, volume 12, page 407)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:835564">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1076268">Priests</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079934">Protestants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kn07">Priests</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rv0d77h">Protestants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b6k">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n422/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HUSSITES</label>. The arbitrary arrest and imprisonment of
                    Huss at Constance in November 1415 created a very painful impression among all
                    classes in Moravia and Bohemia, and called forth angry remonstrances as soon as
                    it was known. While the nobles resorted to diplomacy, the masses rioted and in
                    many instances attacked the clergy. The excitement was immensely intensified by
                    the tidings of his death, which was freely characterized as a judicial murder;
                    several priests were put to death by the infuriated populace, who cherished the
                    memory of Huss as that of a patriot and a saint; and the archbishop himself,
                    after having been beset in his own palace, with difficulty saved his life by
                    flight. Public feeling found its first organized expression in a diet which was
                    hastily summoned to meet at Prague early in September; there a solemn protest,
                    ultimately signed by 452 magnates and barons, was drawn up, in which the
                    personal character of Huss as man, teacher, preacher, and author was warmly
                    upheld, and the freedom of Bohemia and Moravia from error and heresy was as
                    energetically asserted. Three days later the nobles who had signed this document
                    formed themselves into a league, headed by two Bohemian barons and one from
                    Moravia, by which they bound themselves to protect liberty of preaching on their
                    estates, and to yield obedience to bishop or pope only in so far as might be in
                    accordance with Scripture and the will of God. Matters of dispute were to be
                    subjected to the arbitration of the rector and doctors in theology of the
                    university of Prague. Soon afterwards a counter league was formed for the
                    support of the council and curia; and civil war appeared to be imminent. The
                    tension was further increased by the arrival of the bishop of L·eitomischl, long
                    the enemy of Huss, as legate from the council for the extirpation of heresy; and
                    by the pressure of the interdict under which the city of Prague continued to
                    lie. In February 1416 the 452 nobles who had signed the protest in favour of
                    Huss were summoned to appear before the council, while the anti-Hussite league
                    was encouraged to prepare for a crusade; and the burning of Jerome of Prague in
                    the following May still further revealed the prevailing disposition of Catholic
                    Christendom. Owing to the slowness, however, with which matters moved at
                    Constance, it was not until February 1418 that the new pope, Martin V. (Otto di
                    Colonna), was able to issue various bulls and briefs, in which he laid all
                    obstinate Hussites under the ban, and called upon all the ecclesiastical and
                    civil authorities to proceed against them. The council also, shortly before its
                    dissolution, drew up twenty-four articles for withdrawing the Bohemians from the
                    prevailing heresy, bidding King Wenceslaus protect the rights of the Romish
                    Church in his dominion, restore the banished clergy to their benefices, repress
                    the Hussite preaching and hymn singing, dissolve the Hussite associations, and
                    take the ringleaders into custody. To this policy the king after much
                    vacillation began to give effect early in 1419, and forthwith the more prominent
                    Hussites withdrew from court; among these were Nicolaus of Pistna, an able
                    statesman, and the famous John Zizka, a practised soldier, who placed themselves
                    at the head of the malcontents. By the end of the year the war, though it is
                    usually reckoned from 1420, may be said to have begun. It divides itself into
                    two periods—the defensive, which lasted from 1420 to 1425, and the offensive,
                    which began with Procopius’s invasion of Germany in 1427, and lasted until the
                    commencement of negotiations with the council of Basel in 1431. The struggle had
                    not proceeded very far, however, before it became manifest that the Hussite
                    party was itself sharply divided in views and aims. All were agreed in warm and
                    tender reverence for the memory of Huss, the evangelical preacher and the
                    faithful servant of Christ; equally unanimous were they in holding the
                    distinctive doctrine of the supreme authority of Holy Scripture, and in urging
                    the reformation of the church. But all were not prepared to go equally far in
                    the amount of reform they proposed. While the more radical section rejected such
                    doctrines as those of purgatory and of the mediation of saints, held that
                    priests in mortal sin could validly administer no sacrament, disapproved of
                    penances, imnges, relics, mass in a foreign tongue, maintained the right of the
                    pious laity, even of women, to preach, and regarded every building as in itself
                    at least suitable for acts of divine worship, the more moderate or conservative
                    section formulated their much simpler programme in the famous four articles of
                    Prague (July 1420). These were—(1) free preaching of the word of God throughout
                    the kingdom of Bohemia; (2) the administration of the eucharist to all believers
                    not in mortal sin, under both species according to the institution of Christ;
                    (3) deprivation of the clergy of the secular lordship they had assumed and of
                    the secular property they had acquired to their own injury and to the prejudice
                    of the civil power; (4) prohibition and repression of all mortal sins and public
                    scandals. The supporters of these articles, who were led by Baron Czenko of
                    Wartenberg, and had in their number such men as Jakob von Mies, were strong in
                    the town and university of Prague, and occasionally received the name of the
                    Praguers, but ultimately came to be more generally known as Calixtines (from
                    “calix”) or Utraquists (from their claim to receive the communion “sub utraque
                    specie ”). The more radical party, from having taken up their headquarters at a
                    stronghold which had been fortified by Zizka and called Mount Tabor, some 65
                    miles southwards of Prague, received the name of Taborites. Whatever
                    differences, however, may have separated the Hussites, all were united in
                    offering resistance to the efforts made by Sigismund to crush them; and at
                    Deutschbrod in 1422, at Aussig in 1426, and finally at Taus (August 14, 1431),
                    they inflicted signal defeats on his troops. Negotiations begun in 1431 with the
                    council of Basel reached a termination only in November 1433, when the so-cilled
                    “Compactata” or articles of agreement were signed by which the Calixtines
                    were'satisfied, communion under both species being granted to all who desired
                    it, although the other concessions in the direction of the four articles of
                    Prague were made in a somewhat illusory manner. The Taborites, or “Orphans” (as
                    the followers of Zizka were sometimes called after his death in 1424), failed,
                    however, to find in the Compactata all that they required, and they speedily
                    took the field again in a campaign which terminated disastrously for them at
                    Hrib near Böhmischbrod on May 30,1434. In this battle both Procopius and his
                    brother perished; and soon afterwards the Taborites were compelled to surrender
                    all the fortresses to which they had betaken themselves. Thenceforward they
                    rapidly disappeared as a political party, although as a religious body they can
                    be traced to about the middle of the century, when they gradually became merged
                    in the so-called Moravians, or United Brethren of Bohemia. The Calixtines
                    obtained from Sigismund in 1436 the formal recognition of the Compactata, which
                    from that time had the force of law. Satisfied with this somewhat empty
                    achievement (which, however, was jealously guarded against the hostile attack of
                    Pius II. in 1462), they gradually subsided into an inert conformity, so as to be
                    but little distinguished from the Catholics around them At the time of the
                    Reformation some returned to the Roman Church, while the rest attached
                    themselves either to the Lutheran or to the Reformed creed, and Hussitism as a
                    distinct form of Christian profession became extinct.</p>
                <p>See Cochlaeus, <hi rend="italic">Hist. Hussitarum</hi> (1549); Palacky, <hi
                    rend="italic">Urkundliche Beiträge zur</hi><hi rend="italic">Gesch. d.
                    Husitenkrieges</hi> (1872-74). (J. S. BL.) <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n423/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0423-0408"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
