<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0146-0135-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HONE, William (9th edition, volume 12, page
                    135)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q74d">Athanasianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z981">Abbots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s33k">Creeds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:959995">Honing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882694">Creeds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:819945">Athanasianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100524">Roses</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n146/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HONE, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label> (1780-1842),
                    a political satirist and a writer on antiquarian and miscellaneous subjects, was
                    born at Bath, June 3, 1780. His father, a man of deep spiritual experience in
                    that time of religious revival, brought up his children in strictness and
                    reverence, but not without the sectarian narrowness that so frequently produces
                    reaction. The parodist of the litany and of the Athânasian creed was taught to
                    read from the Bible only. Hone received no systematic education. His father
                    having removed to London in 1783, he was in 1790 placed in an attorney’s office.
                    Becoming connected with the London Corresponding Society, which was given to
                    freethought and to political agitation, he was removed by his father to the
                    office of a solicitor at Chatham, but after two years and a half he returned to
                    London and became clerk to a solicitor in Gray’s Inn. Having no liking for the
                    study of the law, and apparently no hope of succeeding in it, Hone, being then
                    married, started in 1800 a book and print shop and a circulating library in
                    Lambeth Walk, and he soon after removed to St Martin’s Churchyard, where he
                    brought out his first publication, Shaw’s <hi rend="italic">Gardener,</hi> and
                    suffered much loss from a fire. It was at this time that Hone matured and with a
                    friend endeavoured to realize a plan for the establishment of popular savings
                    banks, and even had an interview on the subject with the Right Hon. George Rose,
                    then president of the Board of Trade. This scheme, however, fell through from
                    lack of support. His partner in the savings bank became next his partner in a
                    bookseller’s business; but Hone’s habits were not those of a tradesman, and
                    bankruptcy was the result. After several removals, having compiled an index to
                    Lord Berner’s translation of Froissart, he was in 1811 chosen by the booksellers
                    as auctioneer to the trade, and had an office in Ivy Lane. Independent
                    investigations carried on by him into the condition of lunatic asylums led again
                    to difficulties and failure, but, struggling bravely under his burdens, he took
                    a small lodging in the Old Bailey, and kept himself and his now large family by
                    contributions to magazines and reviews. He hired a small shop (or rather box) in
                    Fleet Street, but this was on two separate nights broken into, and valuable
                    books lent for show were stolen. In 1815 he started the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Traveller</hi> newspaper, and endeavoured vainly to exculpate Eliza Fenning, a
                    poor girl, apparently quite guiltless, executed on a charge of poisoning. From
                    February 1 to October 25, 1817, he published the <hi rend="italic"
                    >liefen</hi><hi rend="italic">mist</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">s Register,</hi>
                    writing in it as the serious critic of the state abuses, to which he soon after
                    applied the lash of satire in those political squibs and parodies that made his
                    name known throughout the land, and that first gave notoriety to George
                    Cruikshank, who was his artistic collaborator. In April 1817 three <hi
                    rend="italic">ex officio</hi> informations were filed against him by the
                    attorney-general, Sir William Garrow, and he was seized while reading in the
                    street and hurried to the lock-up. Three separate trials took place in the
                    Guildhall before special juries on the 18th, 19th, and 20th of December 1817.
                    The first, for publishing Wilkes’s <hi rend="italic">Catechism of a Ministerial
                    Member,</hi> was before Mr Justice Abbot (afterwards Lord Tenterden); the
                    second, for parodying the litany and libelling the prince regent, and the third,
                    for publishing the <hi rend="italic">Sinecurist's Creed,</hi> a parody on the
                    Athanasian creed, were before Lord Ellenborough. The prosecuting officials,
                    among whom we must include the judges, took the ground that the prints were
                    calculated to injure public morals, and to bring the prayer-book and even
                    religion itself into contempt. But there can be no doubt that the real motives
                    of the prosecution were political; Hone had ridiculed the habits and exposed the
                    corruption of the prince regent and of other persons in power. He went to the
                    root of the matter when he wished the jury “to understand that, had he been a
                    publisher of ministerial parodies, he would not then have been defending himself
                    on the floor of that court.” In spite of illness and exhaustion Hone displayed
                    great courage, ability, dignity, and presence of mind. On each of the three days
                    he spoke on an average seven hours. Notwithstanding the powerful prosecution and
                    the bias of the judges, he was acquitted on each count, and the result on each
                    occasion was received with enthusiastic cheers by immense crowds within and
                    without the court. Soon after the trials a public meeting, in which Aiderman
                    Waithman, Sir F. Burdett, and Lord Cochrane took part, was held, and a
                    subscription was begun, by which a large sum was soon collected to enable Hone
                    to get over the difficulties caused by his prosecution.</p>
                <p>Hone’s most successful political satires were published within a few years after
                    his trial. Among them we may mention <hi rend="italic">The Political House that
                    Jack built, The Queen's Matrimonial Ladder</hi> (in favour of Queen Caroline),
                    <hi rend="italic">The Man in the Moon, The Political Showman,</hi> all
                    illustrated by Cruikshank. Many of his squibs are directed against a certain “Dr
                    Slop,” a nickname given by him to Dr (afterwards Sir John) Stoddart, a writer in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Times.</hi> In researches for his defence he had come upon
                    some curious and at that time little trodden literary ground, and the results
                    were shown by his publication in 1820 of his <hi rend="italic">Apocryphal New
                    Testament,</hi> and in 1823 of his <hi rend="italic">Ancient Mysteries
                    Explained.</hi> He proposed in 1820 to write a <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Parody,</hi> but this never appeared. In 1826 he published the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Every-day Book,</hi> in 1827-8 the <hi rend="italic">Table-Book,</hi> and in
                    1829 the <hi rend="italic">Year-Book ∙,</hi> all three were collections of
                    curious information on manners, antiquities, and various other subjects.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>According to a recent writer
                    in <hi rend="italic">Notes and Queries</hi> (6th S. i. 171), Hone remarked in
                    conversation that he took the idea of the <hi rend="italic">Everyday Book</hi>
                    in 1814 from Defoe’s <hi rend="italic">Times Telescope.</hi></p></note> These
                    are the works by which Hone is best remembered. In preparing them he had the
                    warm approval of Southey and the assistance of Charles Lamb, but pecuniarily
                    they were not successful, and Hone was lodged in King’s Bench prison for debt.
                    Friends, however, again came to his assistance, and he was established in a
                    coffee-house in Gracechurch Street; but this again, like most of his
                    enterprises, ended in failure. Hone’s attitude of mind had gradually changed to
                    that of extreme devoutness, and during the latter years of his life he
                    frequently preached in Weigh House Chapel, Eastcheap. In 1830 he edited Strutt’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Sports and Pastimes,</hi> and, on the starting in 1832 of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Penny Magazine,</hi> he contributed to the first number. He
                    was also for some years sub-editor of the <hi rend="italic">Patriot.</hi> He
                    died at Tottenham, 8th November 1842.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n147/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0147-0136"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
