<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0165-0154-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOOPING-COUGH, or Whooping-Cough (9th edition, volume
                    12, page 154)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:881175">Cough</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140998">Symptoms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:848912">Catarrh</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1003744">Lungs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v30g">Symptoms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45t3g156">Catarrh</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62820">Lungs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bw55">Cough</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n165/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOOPING-COUGH, or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Whooping-Cough</hi></label> (syn. <hi rend="italic">Pertussis,</hi>
                    Chin-Cough), an infectious disease of the respiratory mucous membrane,
                    manifesting itself by frequently recurring paroxysms of convulsive coughing
                    accompanied with peculiar sonorous inspirations. It occurs for the most part
                    among children, and only once in a lifetime.</p>
                <p>The specific cause of hooping-cough is unknown, but the view which ascribes it to
                    some atmospheric condition appears to derive support from the frequency of this
                    disease as an epidemic; whether, however, that be the presence of a peculiar
                    form of germ, as is held by some, remains as yet undetermined. Although
                    specially a disease of childhood, hooping-cough is by no means limited to that
                    period, but may occur at anytime of life, even to old age, should there have
                    been no previous attack. It is most common between the ages of one and four, and
                    is rare after ten. Dr Edward Smith’s statistics showed that it was the most
                    fatal of all diseases of children under one year, that 68 per cent, of the
                    deaths from hooping-cough occurred under the age of two, and that only 6 per
                    cent, of the deaths were recorded after five years. It has been occasionally
                    observed in newly-born infants. It is more common in female than in male
                    children. Hooping-cough is highly contagious during auy stage of its progress,
                    but apparently more so in its commencement. It is not only communicated by the
                    breath, but may, as has been clearly proved, be conveyed by the medium of
                    clothing and by persons who have been in contact with those affected. It is said
                    to be favoured by cold and damp weather, and to prevail mostly in spring and
                    autumn, doubtless owing to these seasons increasing the predisposition to
                    affections of the respiratory passages. Epidemics of hooping-cough have often
                    been noticed to succeed or even to accompany those of measles or scarlet fever,
                    although no causal connexion between these diseases can be admitted.</p>
                <p>With respect to the symptoms of hooping-cough, three stages of the disease are
                    recognized, viz., (1) the catarrhal stage, (2) the spasmodic stage, (3) the
                    stage of decline.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">first stage</hi> is characterized by the ordinary phenomena
                    of a catarrh, with sneezing, watering of the eyes, irritation of the throat,
                    feverishness and cough, but in general there is nothing in the symptoms to
                    indicate that they are to develop into hooping-cough. The catarrhal stage
                    usually lasts from ten to fourteen days. The <hi rend="italic">second
                    stage</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">s&gt;</hi> marked by the
                    abatement of the catarrhal symptoms, but at the same time by increase in the
                    cough, which now occurs in irregular paroxysms both by day and by night. Each
                    paroxysm consists in a series of violent and rapid expiratory coughs, succeeded
                    by a loud sonorous or crowing inspiration—the “whoop.” During the coughing
                    efforts the air is driven with great force out of the lungs, and as none can
                    enter the chest the symptoms of impending asphyxia appear. The patient grows
                    deep-red or livid in the face, the eyes appear as if they would burst from their
                    sockets, and suffocation seems imminent till relief is brought by the “whoop ”—
                    the louder and more vigorous the better. Occasionally blood bursts from the
                    nose, mouth, and ears, or is extravasated into the conjunctiva of the eyes. A
                    single fit rarely lasts beyond from half to three-quarters of a minute, but
                    after the “whoop” another recurs, and of these a number may come and go for
                    several minutes. The paroxysm ends by the coughing or vomiting up of a viscid
                    tenacious secretion, and usually after this the patient seems comparatively
                    well, or, it may be, somewhat wearied and fretful. The frequency of the
                    paroxysms varies according to the severity of the case, being in some instances
                    only to the extent of one or two in the whole day, while in others there may be
                    several in the course of a single hour. Slight causes serve to bring on the fits
                    of coughing, such as the acts of swallowing, talking, laughing, crying, &amp;c.,
                    or they may occur without any apparent exciting cause. In general children come
                    to recognize an impending attack by a feeling of tickling in the throat, and
                    they cling with dread to their mothers or nurses, or take hold of some object
                    near them for support during the paroxysm; but although exhausted by the severe
                    fit of coughing they soon resume their play, apparently little the worse. The
                    attacks are on the whole most severe at night. This stage of the disease usually
                    continues for thirty to fifty days, but it may be shorter or longer. It is
                    during this time that complications are apt to arise which may become a source
                    of danger greater even than the malady itself. The chief of these are
                    inflammatory affections of the bronchi and lungs, and convulsions, any of which
                    may prove fatal. When, however, the disease progresses favourably, as it usually
                    does, the <hi rend="italic">third</hi> or <hi rend="italic">terminal stage</hi>
                    is announced by the less frequent paroxysms of the cough, which generally loses
                    in great measure its “whooping” character. The patient’s condition altogether
                    undergoes amendment, and the symptoms disappear in from one to three weeks. It
                    is to be observed, however, that for a long period afterwards in any simple
                    catarrh from which the patient suffers the cough often assumes a spasmodic
                    character, which may suggest the erroneo as notion that a relapse of the
                    hooping-cough has occurred.</p>
                <p>In severe cases it occasionally happens that the disease leaves behind it such
                    structural changes in the lungs (emphysema, &amp;c.), as entail permanent shoι
                    tness of breathing or a liability to attacks of asthma. Further, hooping-cough
                    is well known to be one of those diseases of early life which are apt to give
                    rise to a weakened and vulnerable state of the general health, or to call into
                    activity any inherited morbid tendency, such as that towards consumption.</p>
                <p>As regards the treatment of hooping-cough in mild cases, little is necessary
                    beyond keeping the patient warm and carefully attending to the general health.
                    The remedies applicable in the case of catarrh or the milder forms of bronchitis
                    are of service here, while gentle counter-irritation to the chest by stimulating
                    liniments may be employed all through the attack. In mild weather the patient
                    may be in the open air. In the more severe forms efforts have to be employed to
                    modify the severity of the paroxysms. Numerous remedies are recommended, the
                    chief of which are the bromides of ammonium or potassium, hydrocyanic acid,
                    chloral, chloric ether, &amp;c. These can only be safely administered under
                    medical advice, and with due regard to the symptoms in individual cases. During
                    convalescence, where the cough still continues to be troublesome, a change of
                    air will often effect its removal. <hi rend="smallcaps">(j.</hi> o. A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
