<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0165-0154-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOOPOE (9th edition, volume 12, page 154)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1209332">Madagascar</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k06x333">Crests</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn85">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10z9f">Nests</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785p59">Autumn</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25p07">Winter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086351k">Larks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fb7f">Falcons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:992706">Larks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882872">Crests</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950030">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833880">Blacks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833576">Black</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1036179">Nests</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n165/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOOPOE</label> (French <hi rend="italic">Huppe,</hi> Latin
                    <hi rend="italic">Upupa,</hi> Greek <hi rend="italic">eπ-οψ—</hi> all names
                    bestow ed apparently from its cry), a bird long celebrated in literature, and
                    conspicuous by its variegated plumage and its large erectile crest,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Hence the secondary meaning
                    of the French word <hi rend="italic">huppe</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> a crest
                    or tuft (c∕ Littré, <hi rend="italic">Diet.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Française,</hi> i. 2067).</p></note> the <hi rend="italic">Upupa</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">epops</hi> of naturalists, which is the type of the very peculiar
                    Family <hi rend="italic">Upupidoe,</hi> placed by Prof. Huxley in his group <hi
                    rend="italic">Coccygomorphas</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n166/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0166-0155"/> but considered by Dr Murie <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Ibis,</hi> 1873, p. 208) to deserve separate rank as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Epopomorphoe.</hi> This species has an exceedingly wide range in the Old World,
                    being a regular summervisitant to the whole of Europe, in some parts of which it
                    is abundant, as well as to Siberia, mostly retiring southwards in autumn to
                    winter in equatorial Africa and India, though it would seem to be resident
                    throughout the year in North-Eastern Africa and in China. Its power of wing
                    ordinarily seems to be feeble; but it is capable of very extended flight, as is
                    testified by its wandering habits (for it occasionally makes its appearance in
                    places very far removed from its usual haunts), and also by the fact that when
                    pursued by a Falcon it will rapidly mount to an extreme height and frequently
                    effect its escape from the enemy. About the size of a Thrush, with a long,
                    pointed, and slightly arched bill, its head and neck are of a golden-buff—the
                    former adorned by the crest already mentioned, which begins to rise from the
                    forehead and consists of broad feathers, gradually increasing in length, tipped
                    with black, and having a subterminal bar of yellowish-white. The upper part of
                    the back is of a vinous-grey, and the scapulars and flight-feathers are black,
                    broadly barred with white tinged in the former with buff. The tail is black with
                    a white chevron, marking off about the distal third part of its length. The legs
                    and feet are as well adapted for running or walking as for' perching, and the
                    scutellations are continued round the whole of the tarsi. Chiefly on account of
                    this character, which is also possessed by the Larks, Sundevall <hi
                    rend="italic">{Tentamen,</hi> pp. 53-55) united the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Upupidoe</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Alaudidoe</hi> in the same “cohors” <hi
                    rend="italic">Holaspideoe.</hi> Comparative anatomy, however, forbids its being
                    taken to signify any real affinity between these groups, and the resemblance on
                    this point, which is by no means so striking as that displayed by the form of
                    the bill and the coloration in certain Larks (of the genus <hi rend="italic"
                    >Certhilauda,</hi> for instance), must be ascribed to analogy merely, though at
                    present no explanation of the why and the wherefore can be offered.</p>
                <p>Pleasing as is the appearance of the Hoopoe as it fearlessly parades its showy
                    plumage, its habits are much the reverse. All observers agree in stating that it
                    delights to find its food among filth of the most abominable description, and
                    this especially in its winter-quarters. But where it breeds, its nest, usually
                    in the hole of a tree or of a wall, is not only partly composed of the foulest
                    material, but its condition becomes worse as incubation proceeds, for the hen
                    scarcely ever leaves her eggs, being assiduously fed by the cock as she sits;
                    and when the young are hatched, their faeces are not removed by their
                    parents,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This indeed is
                    denied by Naumann, but by him alone; and the statement in thé text is confirmed
                    by many eye-witnesses.</p></note> as is the case with most birds, but are
                    discharged in the immediate neighbourhood of the nest, the unsanitary condition
                    of which can readily be imagined. Worms, grubs, and insects generally, form the
                    Hoopoes’ food, and upon it they get so fat in autumn that they are esteemed a
                    delicate morsel in some of the countries of Southern Europe, and especially by
                    the Christian population of Constantinople.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Under the name of <hi rend="italic">Dulcipαth,</hi> in the
                    authorized version of the Bible translated “Lapwing” (Lev. xi. 19, Deut. xiv.
                    18), the Hoopoe was accounted unclean by the “Jewish law.” Arabs have a great
                    reverence for the bird, imparting to it marvellous medicinal and other
                    qualities, and making use of its head in all their charms (c∕ Tristram, <hi
                    rend="italic">Nat. Hist, of the Bible,</hi> pp. 208, 209).</p></note></p>
                <p>Not a year passes but the Hoopoe makes its appearance in some part or other of
                    the British Islands, most often in spring, and if unmolested would doubtless
                    stop to breed in them, and a few instances are known in which it has done so.
                    But its remarkable plumage always attracts attention, and it is generally shot
                    down so soon as it is seen, and before it has time to begin a nest, which there
                    is reason to think would not in a temperate climate become so offensive a
                    nuisance as it is in more southern latitudes. Eight or nine so-called species of
                    the genus have been described, but of them the existence of five only has been
                    recognized by the writers who have most lately investigated them— Messrs Sharpe
                    and Dresser <hi rend="italic">{Birds of Europe,</hi> pt. vii.). Besides the <hi
                    rend="italic">Upupa epops</hi> above treated, these are <hi rend="italic">U.
                    indica,</hi> resident in India and Ceylon; <hi rend="italic">U.
                    longirostris,</hi> which seems to be the form of the Indo-Chinese countries <hi
                    rend="italic">; U.</hi><hi rend="italic">marginata,</hi> peculiar to Madagascar;
                    and <hi rend="italic">U. africana</hi> cr <hi rend="italic">J7. minor</hi> of
                    some writers, which inhabits South Africa to the Zambesi on the east and
                    Benguela on the west coast. In habits and appearance they all resemble the
                    best-known and most widely-spread species, and their particular differences
                    cannot, for want of space, be here pointed out.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The genera <hi rend="italic"
                    >Rhinοpοrnastus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Irrisor</hi> are generally placed in
                    the Family <hi rend="italic">Upupidoe,</hi> but Dr Murie (Z.c.), after an
                    exhaustive examination of their osteology, regards them as forming a group of
                    equal value.</p></note><hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
