<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0341-0330-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HUDDERSFIELD (9th edition, volume 12, page 330)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:880656">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836750">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010167">Marketing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010316">Markets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tw1v">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q67d">Costs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gs41">Marketing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp32">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n341/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HUDDERSFIELD</label>, a municipal and parliamentary borough
                    and market-town of England, in the West Riding of Yorkshire, is beautifully
                    situated on the slope of a hill in the valley of the Colne, a tributary of the
                    Calder, 15 miles south of Bradford, and 16 J south-west of Leeds. It is
                    surrounded by a network of railways, and is connected with the extensive canal
                    system of Lancashire and Yorkshire. The town is built principally of stone, and
                    has undergone within late years very extensive improvements, in regard to both
                    its external appearance and its sanitary arrangements. The older portions of the
                    town, where the streets were mean-looking and narrow, have almost disappeared,
                    making way for handsome, spacious, and well-paved thoroughfares, whilst many of
                    the business premises possess considerable architectural merit. Among the
                    churches deserving special mention are St Peter’s, the parish church, in the
                    Perpendicular style, rebuilt in 1837 at a cost of £10,000, possessing chancel,
                    nave, aisles, transept, and tower with peal of ten bells; Trinity Church,
                    erected in 1819 at a cost of £12,000, in the Pointed style, with an embattled
                    tower at the west end; St Paul’s, built by the parliamentary commissioners in
                    1831, in the Early English style, with a tower surmounted by a light spire; St
                    Thomas’s, in the Transition Early English style, completed in 1859 at a cost of
                    £10,000. Of the numerous Nonconformist places of worship, Ramsden Street
                    (Congregational), Queen Street and Buxton Road (Wesleyan), and Brunswick Street
                    (Free Methodist) chapels are remarkable for their capacity, whilst High Street
                    (New Connexion Methodist), New North Road (Baptist), and Highfield and Hillhouse
                    (Congregational) have considerable architectural beauty. The principal other
                    buildings, in addition to the many fine warehouses, are the Cloth-Hall, erected
                    by Sir Thomas Ramsden in 1768, and extended in 1780,—a circular two-storied
                    brick building, having a diameter of 80 yards, now fallen almost into disuse;
                    the Armoury, erected as a ridingschool, but now the headquarters of the rifle
                    volunteers, and also used for concerts and large public meetings; the Victoria
                    Hall, a capacious building recently erected by the Huddersfield Temperance
                    Society; the Philosophical Hall, in the Grecian style, originally used for
                    lectures and public meetings, afterwards converted into a theatre, and burnt
                    almost to the ground February 15,1880; the Gymnasium Hall, erected in 1847,
                    capable of accommodating 1000 persons, and transformed into public baths in
                    1879; the Infirmary, erected in 1831, a large and elegant stone edifice of the
                    Doric order with wings and a portico, the latter supported by four fluted
                    columns, a large ward and medicated baths being added later; the General Railway
                    Station, in the Grecian style, erected in 1848, having in front a handsome
                    statue of Sir Robert Peel; the Huddersfield College, in the Baronial style,
                    established in 1838 for sons of gentlemen and tradesmen; the Collegiate School,
                    in the Gothic style, erected in 1839; the Huddersfield Club; the Borough Club;
                    the Masonic Hall (1838); the Corporation offices, in the Classic style (1877);
                    the Town-Hall, also in the Classic style, but much richer (1880); the Guardians’
                    offices (1880); the Ramsden Estate buildings, a handsome and extensive block of
                    the mixed Italian order; the Chamber of Commerce; and a remarkably fine new
                    markethall, in the Gothic style, with a clock-tower and spire 106 feet in
                    height, founded in 1878, and opened in 1880.</p>
                <p>The cost of the building was £28,000, and the sum paid by the corporation to Sir
                    J. W. Ramsden, Bart., for the market-rights and site, was £25,790, in addition
                    to £15,273 for the site and rights of the cattle-market. A public cemetery, off
                    New North Road, the property of the corporation, with mortuary chapels for
                    Churchmen and Nonconformists, was completed in 1855; and the cemetery at
                    Almondbury was taken over by the corporation in 1868. The extensive gas-works
                    are the property of the corporation, as are also the water-works, which afford
                    an ample supply of excellent water, the reservoirs being capable of storing
                    900,000,000 gallons. The cost has been over £750,000. A public park of 21 acres,
                    called the Beaumont Park, is the gift of Mr H. F. Beaumont; the first sod was
                    cut on May 29, 1880. There are fourteen handsome board schools, erected at a
                    cost of about £120,000, twenty-one national schools, and one Roman Catholic
                    school. The principal public societies are the mechanics’ institution, the
                    building for which, a large edifice in the Italian style, was opened in 1861,
                    and the mechanics’ institutes at Lindley and Lockwood, each possessing handsome
                    buildings. Huddersfield is a place of considerable antiquity, being mentioned in
                    Domesday, and is supposed by some to derive its name from <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n342/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0342-0331"/> Oder or Hudard, a Saxon chief; but its importance
                    dates from the establishment of the woollen manufacture within the last century.
                    It is the principal seat of the fancy woollen trade in England; and it exceeds
                    every other place in the variety of its manufacture of this class of textile
                    fabrics, which includes doeskins, angolas, tweeds, worsted coatings and
                    trouserings, Ulster cloths, mohairs, cashmeres, sealskins, fancy dress
                    skirtings, kerseys, woollen cords, quiltings, a few broad cloths, and a large
                    number of union materials. It also possesses silk and cotton spinning mills,
                    iron foundries, engineering works for steam-engines, steam-engine boilers, and
                    the machinery used in the various manufactures, chemical works, dye-houses,
                    lead-piping and <hi rend="italic">t</hi>.nitary tube manufactories, and three
                    organ factories. Handloom weaving is carried on in the surrounding villages, but
                    to a much less extent than formerly. A market for woollen goods is held weekly.
                    Coal is abundant in the vicinity. There is a sulphurous spa in the Lockwood
                    ward, with warm, cold, vapour, and shower baths. At Almondbury, 2 miles distant
                    from the centre of the town, there was at one time a Saxon fortress, and by some
                    writers the Roman station <hi rend="italic">Cambodunum,</hi> mentioned by
                    Antonine, is believed to have been situated there; recent excavations, however,
                    have proved almost conclusively that at Slack, just outside the opposite
                    boundary of the borough, was the real <hi rend="italic">Cambodunum.</hi>
                    Kirklees park, 3 miles from Huddersfield, is popularly supposed to have been the
                    burial-place of Robin Hood. Since 1832 Huddersfield has returned one member to
                    parliament, and it became a municipal borough in 1868, with 12 wards, and a town
                    council of 56 members. The area of the town was greatly increased at the time of
                    its incorporation. The area of the parliamentary borough is 10,998 acres, and
                    that of the municipal borough 10,498 acres. The population of the parliamentary
                    borough in 1861 was 34,877; and in 1871, owing chiefly to the increased area, it
                    was 74,358. The population of the municipal borough ip 1880 was estimated at
                    81,780.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
