<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0160-0149-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOOKE, Robert (9th edition, volume 12, page
                    149)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:885665">Cutlers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1181567">Wrens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885666">Cutlery</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804885">Algebra</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm44">Cutlers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736mb9b">Wrens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0wt00">Cutlery</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4901zk6v">Springs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n160/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOOKE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label> (1635-1703),
                    an original and ingenious experimental philosopher, was born at Freshwater, in
                    the Isle of Wight, July 18, 1635. His father, who was minister of the parish,
                    destined him for the church; but his constitutional ill-health precluded study,
                    and threw him instead on the resources afforded by his precocious mechanical
                    genius. From the workshop of Sir Peter Lely, where he was placed after his
                    father’s death in 1648, he was transferred to the house of Dr Busby, master of
                    Westminster School; and there his education progressed with surprising rapidity
                    both in its classical and mathematical branches. In 1653 he entered Christ
                    Church, Oxford, as servitor; and ten years later he took his M.A. degree by
                    special recommendation of Lord Clarendon, then chancellor of the university.
                    After 1655 he was employed and patronized by the Hon. Robert Boyle, who turned
                    his skill to account in the construction of his celebrated air-pump. Hooke’s
                    inventive faculty exercised itself, between 1657 and 1659, in devising tlιirty
                    different methods of flying, and more profitably in regulating the movement of
                    watches by the application of the balance spring. In 1675 a lively controversy
                    arose between him and Huygens respecting their rival claims to this ingenious
                    invention. The truth seems to be that the original idea belonged to Hooke, but
                    that the coiled form of the spring, on which its practical utility depends, was
                    due to Huygens. On the 12th of November 1662 Hooke was appointed curator of
                    experiments to the Royal Society, and filled the office with extraordinary
                    diligence and skill during the remainder of his life. In 1664 Sir John Cutler
                    instituted for his benefit a mechanical lectureship of £50 a year, and in the
                    following year he was nominated professor of geometry in Gresham College, where
                    he subsequently resided. After the great fire of 1666 he constructed a model for
                    the rebuilding of the city, which was highly approved, although the design of
                    Wren was preferred. During the progress of the works, however, Hooke acted as
                    surveyor, aud accumulated in that lucrative employment a sum of several thousand
                    pounds, discovered after his death in an old iron chest, which had evidently
                    lain unopened for above thirty years. He fulfilled the duties of secretary to
                    the Royal Society during five years after the death of Oldenburg in 1677,
                    publishing in 1681-82 the papers read before that body under the title of <hi
                    rend="italic">Philosophical Collections.</hi> A protracted controversy with
                    Hevelius, in which Hooke urged the advantages of telescopic over plain sights,
                    brought him little but discredit. His reasons were good; but his offensive style
                    of argument rendered them unpalatable and himself unpopular. Many circumstances
                    concurred to embitter the latter years of his life. The death, in 1687, of his
                    niece, Mrs Grace Hooke, who had lived with him for many years, caused him deep
                    affliction; a law suit with Sir John Cutler about his salary (decided, however,
                    in his favour in 1696) occasioned him prolonged anxiety; and the repeated
                    anticipation of his discoveries inspired him with a morbid jealousy. Marks of
                    public respect were not indeed wanting to him. A degree of M.D. was conferred on
                    him at Doctors’ Commons, December 7, 1691, and the Royal Society made him, in
                    1696, a grant to enable him to complete his philosophical inventions. While
                    engaged on this task he died, worn out with disease and toil, March 3, 1703, and
                    was buried in St Helen’s Church, Bishopsgate Street.</p>
                <p>In personal appearance Hooke made but a sorry show. His figure was crooked, his
                    limbs shrunken; his hair hung in dishevelled locks over his haggard countenance.
                    His temper was irritable, his habits penurious and solitary. He was, however,
                    blameless in morals, and reverent in religion. His scientific performances would
                    probably have been more striking if they had been less varied. He originated
                    much, but perfected little. His optical investigations<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n161/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0161-0150"/> led him to adopt in an imperfect form the
                    undulatory theory of light, to anticipate the doctrine of interference, and to
                    observe, independently of though subsequently to Grimaldi, the phenomenon of
                    diffraction. He was the first to state clearly that the motions of the heavenly
                    bodies must be regarded as a mechanical problem, and he approached in a
                    remarkable manner the discovery of universal gravitation. He suggested a method
                    of meteorological forecasting and a system of telescopic signalling, anticipated
                    Chladni’s experiment of strewing a vibrating bell with flour, investigated the
                    nature of sounds and the function of· the air in respiration and combustion, and
                    originated the idea of using the pendulum as a measure of gravity.</p>
                <p>His principal writings are <hi rend="italic">Micrographin,</hi> 1664; <hi
                    rend="italic">Lectiones</hi><hi rend="italic">Cutleri-</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >anae,</hi> 1674-79; and <hi rend="italic">Posthumous lVorks,</hi> containing a
                    sketch of his “Philosophical Algebra,” published by Waller in 1705.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
