<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0912-0333-0322-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOWE, John (9th edition, volume 12, page 322)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90242v">Puritans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f5v">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v131">Pastors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1097947">Righteousness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1084357">Puritans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1053582">Parishes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n333/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOWE, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1630-1706), one
                    of the greatest of the later Puritan divines, was born May 17, 1630, at
                    Loughborough, Leicestershire, of which parish his father was minister. When
                    hardly five years old he was removed to Ireland by his father, who, unable to
                    support the ecclesiastical policy of Archbishop Laud, had been ejected from his
                    living. On the outbreak of the Irish rebellion in 1641, the exiles returned to
                    England; and, fixing his abode in Lancashire, the elder Howe conducted in person
                    the studies of his son, who in his seventeenth year (May 19, 1647) entered
                    Christ’s College, Cambridge, as a sizar, and in the following year took his
                    degree of B.A. During his residence in this university he made the acquaintance
                    of Cudworth, More, and Smith, from intercourse with whom, doubtless, as Calamy
                    suggests, as well as from direct acquaintance with the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dialogues</hi> themselves, his mind received that “Platonic tinge” which is so
                    perceptible in his writings. Immediately after graduation at Cambridge, he
                    removed to Oxford, where he took the same degree in the following year, and,
                    after becoming a fellow of Magdalen College, proceeded M A. in 1652. On leaving
                    Oxford in that year he returned to his father’s retreat in Lancashire, and
                    received ordination at Win wick from the hands of Mr Herle, the minister of the
                    parish, who was assisted by the ministers of the neighbouring chapelries.
                    Sometime afterwards “an unexpected conduct of divine providence” bore him to
                    Great Torrington in Devonshire, where he spent some years as pastor. It was
                    there that he preached those discourses v·diich at a later period took shape in
                    his treatises on <hi rend="italic">The Blessedness of the Righteous</hi> and on
                    <hi rend="italic">Delighting in God.</hi> There also it was that he married the
                    daughter of “his inner friend” Mr George Hughes. In the beginning of 1657 a
                    journey to London accidentally brought Howe under the notice of Cromw'ell, who,
                    struck by his appearance and preaching, made him his domestic chaplain. In this
                    prominent position, -which he had accepted with very great reluctance, his
                    conduct as the almoner and confidential adviser of the Protector was such as to
                    win the praises of even the bitterest enemies of his party. Without overlooking
                    the due claims of the Puritans, he omitted no opportunity of helping pious and
                    learned men of other denominations, Ward (afterwards bishop of Exeter) and
                    Thomas Fuller having been among the number of those who profited by How⅛ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> s kindness, and who were not ashamed subsequently to
                    express their gratitude for it. On the deposition of Richard Cromwell, Howe
                    returned to Great Torrington, where, like all who had played a conspicuous part
                    under the Commonwealth, he soon after the Restoration found himself an object of
                    suspicion and hatred; in 1662 the passing of the Act of Uniformity drove him
                    from his parish. For several years he now led a wandering and uncertain life,
                    preaching in secret as occasion offered to handfuls of trusted hearers. More
                    than once his liberty was in imminent peril; and it is alleged by Calamy, though
                    on doubtful grounds, that for two months in 1665 he was imprisoned in the Isle
                    of St Nicholas in Plymouth Sound. Impelled by the demands of pressing want, he
                    in 1668 published the treatise entitled <hi rend="italic">The Blessedness of the
                    Righteous;</hi> the reputation which he had acquired by it procured for him in
                    1669 an invitation from Lord Massarene of Antrim Castle, Ireland, to become his
                    domestic chaplain. At Antrim, where he was soon joined by his family, he
                    accordingly spent six years of quiet, during which he frequently preached in
                    public, with the approval of the bishop of the diocese, and also found time <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n334/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0334-0323"/> to produce the most eloquent of his shorter
                    treatises, <hi rend="italic">The Vanity of Man as Mortal,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">On Delighting in God</hi>; there too he planned the largest (and
                    also in some respect the greatest) of his works, <hi rend="italic">The Living
                    Temple.</hi> In the beginning of 1676 he accepted an invitation to become pastor
                    of a nonconformist congregation in Silver Street, London; and in the same year
                    he published the first part of <hi rend="italic">The Living Temple,</hi>
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Concerning God's Existence and His Conversableness
                    with Man: Against Atheism or the Epicurean Deism.</hi> In 1677 appeared his
                    tractate <hi rend="italic">On the Reconcileable-ness of God's Prescience of the
                    Sins of Men with the Wisdom and Sincerity of His Coιιnsels, Exhortations, and
                    whatsoever means He uses to prevent them,</hi> which was attacked from various
                    quarters, and had Andrew Marvel for oneof its defenders. His work <hi
                    rend="italic">On Thoughtfulness for the Morrow</hi> followed in 1681; those on
                    <hi rend="italic">Self-Dedication</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Union among
                    Protestants</hi> in 1682; and that on <hi rend="italic">The Redeemer's Tears
                    wept over Lost Souls</hi> in 1684. During the earlier years that followed his
                    settlement in London Howe had enjoyed comparative freedom from annoyance on the
                    ground of his nonconformity, and had been on intimate terms with many who
                    already were or who afterwards became eminent in the Established Church, such as
                    Stillingfieet, Tillotson, Sharp, and Kidder; but the greater severity which
                    began to be manifested in 1681, and which continued to be shown during the
                    following years, so interfered with his liberty that in 1685 he gladly accepted
                    the invitation of Philip Lord Wharton to travel abroad with him. The tour
                    extended over the greater part of a year. In 1686, matters still seeming
                    hopeless in England, he determined to settle for a time at Utrecht, where he
                    officiated along with Mead and others in the English chapel, and also read
                    privately with English students at the university. Among his friends there was
                    Burnet, the future bishop of Salisbury, by whose influence he obtained several
                    confidential interviews with the prince of Orange. In 1687 Howe availed himself
                    of the publication by James II. of the declaration for liberty of conscience to
                    return to England, and in the following year he headed the procession of
                    nonconformist ministers who went to congratulate William on his accession to the
                    English throne. The remainder of his life, so far as recorded, was extremely
                    uneventful. In 1693 he published three admirable discourses <hi rend="italic">On
                    the Carnality of Religious Contention,</hi> suggested by the disputes and
                    divisions that had so abundantly occurred among the nonconformists as soon as
                    liberty of doctrine and worship had been granted. In 1694 and 1695 he published
                    various treatises on the subject of the Trinity, the principal being <hi
                    rend="italic">A Calm and Solemn Inquiry concerning the Possibility of a Trinity
                    in the Godhead.</hi> The second part of <hi rend="italic">The Living
                    Temple,</hi> entitled <hi rend="italic">Animadversions on</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Spinosa</hi><hi rend="italic">and a French Writer pyretending to confute him,
                    with a recapitulation of the former part and an account of the destitution and
                    restitution of God's Temple among Men,</hi> appeared in 1702. About this time he
                    appears to have fallen into shattered health, but he was able in 1705 to give to
                    the world a discourse <hi rend="italic">On Patience in the Expectation of Future
                    Blessedness,</hi> which proved to be his last work. He died in London on April
                    2, 1706.</p>
                <p>Though excelled by Baxter as a pulpit orator, and by Owen in exegetieal ingenuity
                    and in almost every department of theological learning, Howe compares favourably
                    with either as a sagacious and profound thinker, while he was much more
                    successful in combining religious earnestness and fervour of conviction with
                    large-hearted tolerance and cultured breadth of view. His style, moreover,
                    though not altogether free from the literary faults which may almost be called
                    characteristic of Puritanism, has often a stately yet graceful flow which the
                    modern reader will look for in vain in most of Howe’s theological
                    contemporaries. The works published in his life-time, including a number of
                    sermons and other occasional pieces besides those specified above, were
                    collected into 2 vols. fol. m 1724, and again reprinted in 3 vols. 8vo. in 1848.
                    A complete edition of the <hi rend="italic">Whole Works,</hi> including much
                    posthumous and additional matter, appeared with a Memoir in 8 vols, in 1822;
                    this was reprinted in 1 vol. in 1838. The <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> of Howe
                    by Calamy, originally published in 1724, have been more than once reprinted, and
                    form the basis of <hi rend="italic">The Life and</hi><hi rend="italic">Character
                    of Howe, with</hi><hi rend="italic">an Analysis</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 0</hi><hi rend="italic">f hi</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> s</hi><hi rend="italic">Writings,</hi> by Henry Rogers (1836; new
                    ed∙,</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
