<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0708-0687-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EDWARDES, Sir Herbert Benjamin (9th edition, volume 7,
                    page 687)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h12vb7j">Frontiers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4901zk6v">Springs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh0c">Afghans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62g2p">Sikhs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:798948">Afghans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1006241">Majorities</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952743">Health</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205406">Afghanistan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n708/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EDWARDES, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Herbert
                    Benjamin</hi></label> (1819-1868), major-general in the East Indian army, one of
                    the noblest names on the roll of the soldier-statesmen of the British Indian
                    empire, was born at Frodesley, in Shropshire, November 12, 1819. The family was
                    of high standing. Sir Herbert’s father was Benjamin Edwardes, rector of
                    Frodesley, and his grandfather Sir John Edwardes, baronet, eighth holder of the
                    title, which was conferred on one of his ancestors by Charles I. in 1644. After
                    receiving his early education at a private school, he was sent to King’s
                    College, London, to complete his studies. Through the influence of his uncle,
                    Sir Henry Edwardes, he was nominated in 1840 to a cadetship in the East India
                    Company; and on his arrival in India, at the beginning of 1841, he was posted as
                    ensign in the First Bengal Fusileers. He remained with this regiment about five
                    years, and during this period gave proof of that “great capacity for taking
                    pains” which is the characteristic of genius. He mastered the lessons of his
                    profession, obtained a good knowledge of Hindustani, Hindi, and Persian, and
                    attracted attention by the political and literary ability displayed in a series
                    of letters which appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Delhi Gazette.</hi> In
                    November 1845, on the breaking out of the first Sikh war, Edwardes was appointed
                    aide-de-camp to Sir Hugh (afterwards Viscount) Gough, then commanderin-chief in
                    India. On the 18th of the following month he served at the battle of Moodkee,
                    and was severely wounded. He soon recovered sufficiently to resume his duties,
                    and fought by the side of his chief at the decisive battle of Sobraon (February
                    10, 1846), which closed the war. He was soon afterwards appointed third
                    assistant to the commissioners of the Trans-Sutlej Territory; and in January
                    1847 was named first assistant to Sir Henry Lawrence, the resident at Lahore.
                    Lawrence became the great exemplar of the young hero, who looked up to him with
                    the affectionate reverence of a disciple and a son, and in later years was
                    accustomed to attribute to the influence of this “father of his public life”
                    whatever of great or good he had himself achieved. He took part with Lawrence in
                    the suppression of a religious disturbance at Lahore in the spring of 1846, and
                    soon afterwards assisted him in reducing, by a rapid movement to Jummoo, the
                    conspirator Imaum-ud-din. In the following year a more difficult task was
                    assigned him,—the conduct of an expedition to Bunnoo, a tributary Afghan
                    district, in which the people would not tolerate the presence of a collector,
                    and the revenue had consequently fallen into arrear. By his rare tact and
                    fertility of resource, Edwardes succeeding in completely conquering the wild
                    tribes of the valley without firing a shot, a victory which he afterwards looked
                    back upon with more satisfaction than upon other victories which brought him
                    more renown. His fiscal arrangements were such as to obviate all difficulty of
                    collection for the future. In the spring of 1848, in consequence of the murder
                    of Mr Vans Agnew and Lieutenant Anderson at Mooltan, by order of the Dewan
                    Moolraj, and of the raising of the standard of revolt by the latter, Lieutenant
                    Edwardes was authorized to march against him. He set out immediately with a
                    small force, occupied Leia on the left bank of the Indus, was joined by Colonel
                    Cortlandt, and, although he could not attack Mooltan, held the enemy at bay and
                    gave a check at the critical moment to their projects. He won a great victory
                    over a greatly superior Sikh force at Kineyree (June 18), and received in
                    acknowledgment of his services the local rank of major. In the course of the
                    operations which followed near Mooltan, Edwardes lost his right hand, by the
                    explosion of a pistol in his belt. On the arrival of a large force under General
                    Whish the siege of Mooltan was formed, but was suspended for several months in
                    consequence of the desertion of Shere Singh with his army and artillery.
                    Edwardes distinguished himself by the part he took in the final operations,
                    begun in December, which ended with the capture of the city, January 4, 1849 For
                    his services he received the thanks of both houses of parliament, was promoted
                    major by brevet, and created C.B. by special statute of the order. The directors
                    of the East India Company conferred on him a gold medal and a good service
                    pension of £100 per annum. After the conclusion of peace Major Edwardes came to
                    England for the benefit of his health, married during his stay there, and wrote
                    and published his fascinating account of the scenes in which he had been
                    engaged, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Ä</hi><hi rend="italic">Year on
                    the Punjab Frontier in</hi> 1848-1849. His countrymen gave him fitting welcome,
                    and the university of Oxford conferred on him the degree of D.C.L. In 1851 he
                    returned to India and resumed his civil duties in the Punjab under Sir Henry
                    Lawrence. In November 1853, he was entrusted with the responsible post of
                    commissioner of the Peshawur frontier, and this he held when the Mutiny or Sepoy
                    War of 1857 broke out. It was a position of enormous difficulty, and momentous
                    consequences were involved in the way the crisis might be met. Edwardes rose to
                    the height of the occasion. He saw as if by inspiration the facts and the need,
                    and by the prompt measures which he adopted he rendered a service of
                    incalculable importance, by effecting a reconciliation with Afghanistan, and
                    securing the neutrality of the Amir and the tribes during the war. So effective
                    was his procedure for the safety of the frontier that he was able to raise a
                    large force in the Punjab and send it to co-operate in the siege and capture of
                    Delhi. In 1859 Edwardes once more came to England, his health so greatly
                    impaired by the continual strain of arduous work that it was doubtful whether he
                    could ever return to India. During his stay he was created K.C.B., with the rank
                    of brevet colonel; and the degree of LL.D, was conferred upon him by the
                    university of Cambridge. Early in 1862 he again sailed for India, and was
                    appointed commissioner of Ambala and agent for the Cis-Sutlej states. He had
                    been offered the governorship of the Punjab, but on the ground of failing health
                    had declined it. In February 1865, he was compelled finally to resign his post
                    and return to England. A second good service pension was at once conferred on
                    him; in May 1866, he was created K.C. of the Star of India, and early in 1868
                    was promoted majorgeneral in the East Indian army. It was known that he had been
                    for some time engaged on a life of Sir Henry Lawrence, and high expectations
                    were formed of the work; but he did not live to complete it. He died in London,
                    December 23, 1868. Sir Herbert Edwardes, great in council and great in war, was
                    singularly beloved by personal friends, and was generous and unselfish to a high
                    degree. He was also a man of deep religious convictions, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n709/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0709-0688"/> and naturally desired and hoped for the
                    evangelization of India. But his zeal was under the restraint of knowledge, and
                    he knew how to reconcile private aspiration with public duty. Like Sir John
                    Lawrence, he advocated toleration for the native religious systems, and at the
                    same time deprecated Government support of them in any way. “India,” says a
                    writer in the <hi rend="italic">Pall Mall Gazette,</hi> “has produced many great
                    men, some of whom have done more for their country, but there were few upon whom
                    the stamp of genius was more visibly impressed than upon Herbert Edwardes.” The
                    life of Sir Henry Lawrence w as completed by Mr Herman Merivale, and was
                    published in 1873.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
