<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0610-0589-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EAGLE (9th edition, volume 7, page 589)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903849">Eggs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174597">White</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:843192">Buzzards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205290">Greenland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1226682">Albania</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3d540">Eggs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4610vs6b">Buzzards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xp3b">Mayos</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80q7z">Ospreys</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n610/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EAGLE</label> (French <hi rend="italic">Aigle,</hi> from the
                    Latin <hi rend="italic">Aquila),</hi> the name generally given to the larger
                    Diurnal Birds-of-prey which are not Vultures; but tne limits of the subfamily
                    <hi rend="italic">Aquilinoe</hi> have been very variously assigned by different
                    writers on systematic ornithology, and, as before observed <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(Buzzard,</hi> vol. iv. p. 603), there are Eagles smaller than certain
                    Buzzards. By some authorities the <hi rend="italic">Lämmergeier</hi> of the
                    Alps, and other high mountains of Europe, North Africa, and Asia, is accounted
                    an Eagle, but by others the genus <hi rend="italic">Cypaetus</hi> is placed with
                    the <hi rend="italic">Vulturidoe,</hi> as its common English name (Bearded
                    Vulture) shows. There are also other forms, such as the South-American <hi
                    rend="italic">Harpyia</hi> and its allies, which though generally called Eagles
                    have been ranked as Buzzards. In the absence of any truly scientific definition
                    of the family <hi rend="italic">Aquilinoe</hi> it is best to leave these and
                    many other more or less questionable members of the group—such as the genera <hi
                    rend="italic">Spizaetus, Circaetus, Spilorηis, Helotarsus,</hi> and so
                    forth—and, so far as space will allow, to treat here of those whose position
                    cannot be gainsaid.</p>
                <p>True Eagles inhabit all the Regions of the world, and some seven or eight species
                    at least are found in Europe, of which two are resident in the British Islands.
                    In England and in the Lowlands of Scotland Eagles only exist as stragglers; but
                    in the Hebrides and some parts of the Highlands a good many may yet be found,
                    and their numbers appear to have rather increased of late years than diminished;
                    for the foresters and shepherds, finding that a high price can be got for their
                    eggs, take care to protect the owners of the eyries, which are nearly all well
                    known, and to keep up the stock by allowing them at times to rear their young.
                    There are also now not a few occupiers of Scottish forests who interfere so far
                    as they can to protect the king of birds. But hardly twenty years ago trapping,
                    poisoning, and other destructive devices were resorted to without stint, and
                    there was then every probability that before long not an Eagle would be left to
                    add the wild majesty of its appearance to the associations of the mountain or
                    the lake.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The late Lord
                    Breadalbane was perhaps the first large landowner who set the example that has
                    been since followed by others. On his unrivalled forest of Black Mount,
                    Eagles—elsewhere persecuted to the death—were by him ordered to be unmolested so
                    long as they were not numerous enough to cause considerable depredations on the
                    farmers’ flocks. He thought, and all who have an eye for the harmonies of nature
                    will agree with him, that the spectacle of a soaring Eagle was a fitting adjunct
                    to the grandeur of his Argyllshire mountainscenery, and a good equivalent for
                    the occasional loss of a lamb, or the slight deduction from the rent paid by his
                    tenantry in consequence. How faithfully his wishes were carried out by his
                    head-forester, Mr Peter Robertson, the present writer has abundant means of
                    knowing.</p></note> In Ireland the extirpation of Eagles seems to have been
                    carried on almost unaffected by the prudent considerations which in the northern
                    kingdom have operated so favourably for the race, and except in the wildest
                    parts of Donegal, Mayo, and Kerry, Eagles in the sister-island are said to be
                    almost birds of the past.</p>
                <p>Of the two British species the Erne (Icel. <hi rend="italic">(Ern)</hi> or
                    Sea-Eagle<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n611/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0611-0590"/> (by some called also the White-tailed and
                    Cinereous Eagle)— <hi rend="italic">Haliaetus albicilla—</hi> affects chiefly
                    the coast aud neighbourhood of inland waters, living in great part on the fish
                    and refuse that is thrown up on the shore, though it not unfrequently takes
                    living prey, such as iambs, hares, and rabbits. On these last, indeed, young
                    examples mostly feed when they wander southward in autumn, as they yearly do,
                    and appear in England. The adults (fig. 1) are distinguished by their prevalent
                    greyish-brown colour, their pale head, yellow beak, and white tail—characters,
                    however, wanting in the immature, which do not assume the perfect plumage for
                    some three or four years. The eyry is commonly placed in a high cliff or on an
                    island in a lake— sometimes on the ground, at others in a tree—and consists of a
                    vast mass of sticks, in the midst of which is formed a hollow lined with <hi
                    rend="italic">Luzula sylvatica</hi> (as first observed by the late Mr John
                    Wolley) or some similar grass, and here are laid the two or three white eggs. In
                    former days the Sea-Eagle seems to have bred in several parts of England—as the
                    Lake district, and possibly even in the Isle of Wight and on Dartmoor. This
                    species inhabits all the northern part of the Old World from Iceland to
                    Kamchatka, and breeds in Europe so far to the southward as Albania. In the New
                    World, hotvever, it is only found in Greenland, being elsewhere replaced by the
                    White-headed or Bald Eagle, <hi rend="italic">H. leucocephalus,</hi> a bird of
                    similar habits, and the chosen emblem of the United States of America. In the
                    far east of Asia occurs a still larger and finer Sea-Eagle, <hi rend="italic"
                    >H.</hi><hi rend="italic">pelagicus,</hi> remarkable for its white thighs and
                    upper wingcoverts. South-eastern Europe and India furnish a much smaller
                    species, <hi rend="italic">11. leucoryρhus,</hi> which has its representative,
                    <hi rend="italic">II. leucogaster,</hi> in the Malay Archipelago and Australia,
                    and, as allies in South Africa and Madagascar, <hi rend="italic">H. νocifer</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">II. vociferoides</hi> respectively. All these Eagles may
                    be distinguished by their scaly tarsi, while the group next to be treated of
                    have the tarsi feathered to the toes.</p>
                <p>The Golden or Mountain-Eagle, <hi rend="italic">Aquila chrysaetus,</hi> is the
                    second British species. This also formerly inhabited England, and a nest, found
                    in 1668 in the Peak of Derbyshire, is well described by Willughby, in whose time
                    it was said to breed also in the Snowdon range. It seldom if ever frequents the
                    coast, and is more active on the wing than the Sea-Eagle, being able to take
                    some birds as they fly, but a large part of its sustenance is the flesh of
                    animals that die a natural death. Its eyry is generally placed and built like
                    that of the other British species,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>As already stated, the site chosen varies greatly.
                    Occasionally placed in a niche in what passes for a perpendicular cliff to which
                    access could only be gained by a skilful cragsman with a rope, the writer has
                    known a nest to within ten or fifteen yards of which he rode on a poDy. Two
                    beautiful views of as many Golden Eagle’s nests, drawn on the spot by Mr Wolf,
                    are given in the <hi rend="italic">OoUwcα JVolleyana,</hi> and a fine series of
                    eggs is also figured in the same work.</p></note> but the neighbourhood of water
                    is not requisite. The eggs, from two to four in number, vary from a pure white
                    to a mottled, and often highly-coloured, surface, on which appear different
                    shades of red and purple. The adult bird (fig. 2) is of a rich, dark brown, with
                    the elongated feathers of the neck, especially on the nape, light tawny, in
                    which imagination sees a “golden” hue, and the tail marbled with brown and
                    ashy-grey. In the young the tail is white at the base, and the neck has scarcely
                    any tawny tint. The Golden Eagle does not occur in Iceland, but occupies
                    suitable situations over the rest of the Palaearctic Region and a considerable
                    portion of the Nearctic—though the. American bird has been, by some, considered
                    a distinct species. Domesticated, it has many times been trained to take prey
                    for its master in Europe, and to this species is thought to belong an Eagle
                    habitually used by the Kirgiz Tartars, who call it <hi rend="italic">Pergut</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">Pearcoot,</hi> for the capture' of antelopes, foxes, and
                    wolves. It is carried hooded on horseback or on a perch between two men, and
                    released when the quarry is in sight. Such a bird, when well trained, is valued,
                    says Pallas, at the price of two camels. It is quite possible, however, that
                    more than one kind of Eagle is thus used, and the services of <hi rend="italic"
                    >A. heliaca</hi> (which is the Imperial Eagle of some writers<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Which species may have been
                    the traditional emblem of lιotnan power, and the <hi rend="italic">Ales
                    Jονis,</hi> is very uncertain.</p></note>) and of <hi rend="italic">A.
                    mogilnue—</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n612/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0612-0591"/> both of which are found in Central Asia, as well
                    as in South-eastern Europe—may also be employed.</p>
                <p>Of the other more or less nearly allied species or races want of room forbids the
                    consideration, but there is a smaller form on which a few words may be said.
                    This has usually gone under the name of <hi rend="italic">A.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">noevia,</hi> but is now thought by the best authorities to include
                    three local races, or, in the eyes of some, species. They inhabit Europe, North
                    Africa, and Western Asia to India, and two examples of one of them— <hi
                    rend="italic">A. clanga,</hi> the form which is somewhat plentiful in
                    North-eastern Germany—have occurred in Cornwall. The smallest true Eagle is <hi
                    rend="italic">A. pennata,</hi> which inhabits Southern Europe, Africa, and
                    India. Differing from other Eagles of their genus by its wedge-shaped tail,
                    though otherwise greatly resembling them, is the <hi rend="italic">A.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">audax</hi> of Australia. Lastly may be noticed here a small group
                    of Eagles, characterized by their long legs, forming the genus <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nisaetus,</hi> of which one species, A <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi>. <hi
                    rend="italic">fasciatus,</hi> is found in Europe. The Osprey <hi rend="italic"
                    >lf*andion),</hi> though placed by many among the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aquilince,</hi> certainly does not belong to that subfamily. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
