<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0707-0686-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EDWARD the Black Prince (9th edition, volume 7, page
                    686)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836682">Borings</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830788">Berries</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xg2s">Boring</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pz51m4r">Borings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rj8h">Berries</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n707/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EDWARD <hi rend="smallcaps">the Black Prince</hi></label>
                    (1330-1376), son of Edward III. of England, and of Philippa, was born at
                    Woodstock, June 15, 1330. In 1337 he was created duke of Cornwall. He was
                    appointed guardian of the kingdom during the king’s absences in France in 1338,
                    1340, and 1342, and on his return in 1343 was created prince of Wales. In 1346
                    he accompanied his father’s fourth expedition against France, when the division
                    led by him bore the chief brunt in the battle of Crécy. In 1350 ho shared with
                    his father the glory of defeating the Spanish fleet at the battle of
                    “L’Espagnols-sur-Mer.” In 1355 he commanded the principal of the three armies
                    raised by the English for the invasion of France, and landing at Bordeaux
                    captured and plundered the chief of its southern towns and fortresses. In the
                    year following he gained the great victory of Poitiers, and took King John
                    prisoner; and returning to England in 1357, he entered London in triumphant
                    procession, accompanied by his illustrious captive. During the pause of arms
                    which followed the treaty of Bretigny he was married to his cousin Joan,
                    commonly called the Fair Maid of Kent, of whom he was the third husband. This
                    event took place in 1361. Shortly after, he was created duke of Aquitaine, and
                    he set sail for his new dominions in February 1363. Here his life was spent in
                    comparative quietude until Pedro, the deposed monarch of Castile, sought his
                    assistance to remount the Spanish throne. Trusting to Pedro’s promises to defray
                    the cost of the expedition, the Black Prince agreed to his request. He marched
                    across the Pyrenees, defeated Don Henry with great slaughter at the battle of
                    Navarette, and two days afterwards, along with Don Pedro, entered Bourges in
                    triumph. Don Pedro, however, speedily forgot the promise of payment which his
                    distresses had induced him to make, and after the Black Prince had waited some
                    months in vain for its fulfilment, he was compelled to return to his duchy,
                    having lost four-fifths of his army by sickness alone. To defray his expenses he
                    found it necessary to impose on Aquitaine a hearth tax, and the Gascon lords
                    having complained to the king of France, he was summoned in 1369 to Paris to
                    answer the complaint. He replied that he was willing and ready to come, but it
                    would be with “helm on head, and with 60,000 men.” War was consequently again
                    declared between England and France. Two simultaneous invasions of English
                    territory were planned by the French—the one under the duke of Anjou, the other
                    under the duke of Berri. The latter laid* siege to Limoges, which by the
                    treachery of its bishop basely surrendered. Enraged almost to madness, the
                    prince swore by the “soul of his father” that he would recover the city, and
                    after a month’s siege fulfilled his oath. Surprising the garrison by the
                    springing of a mine, he carried the city by assault, and massacred without mercy
                    every man, woman, and child found within its walls. This terrible act of
                    cruelty, attributable, it is <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n708/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0708-0687"/> only charitable to suppose, partly to the
                    irritation of ill health, and possibly to chagrin arising from the presentiment
                    that the English power in France was now on the wane, is the one blot on his
                    fair fame. It closed also his military career, for he was compelled in 1371, by
                    the advice of his physicians, to return to England. From this time his
                    constitution was utterly broken, but he lingered on to witness the loss of his
                    duchy to England, and also to originate the measures of the “Good Parliament,”
                    although his death prevented their completion. He died at Westminster, 8th June
                    1376. He was buried at Canterbury Cathedral, where his mailed effigy may still
                    be seen.</p>
                <p>See Longman’s <hi rend="italic">Life and Times of Edward III.; Edward III.</hi>
                    by Rev. W. Warburton, Μ. A.; Pauli’s <hi rend="italic">Aufsätze zur Englischen
                    Geschichte</hi> (Edward, Der Schwarze Prinz), Leipsic, 1869; and Creighton’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Edward</hi><hi rend="italic">the</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Black</hi><hi rend="italic">Prince.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
