<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0617-0596-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EARLE, John (9th edition, volume 7, page 596)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nz3s">Hunting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964162">Hunting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852224">Chaplains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n617/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EARLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (16011-1665),
                    bishop of Worcester and afterwards of Salisbury, was born at York about 1601. He
                    completed his education at Oxford, first entering Christ Church, and taking his
                    degree of B.A. in 1619. He afterwards passed to Merton College, and graduated
                    M.A. in 1624. He was appointed in 1631 proctor of the university, and the same
                    year became chaplain to Philip, earl of Pembroke, then chancellor of the
                    university. He was soon after presented by this nobleman to the rectory of
                    Bishopstone, in Wiltshire, and, having been introduced to the king, Charles I.,
                    was appointed chaplain and tutor to Prince Charles. In 1642 Earle took his
                    degree of D.D., and in the following year was elected one of the famous Assembly
                    of Divines at Westminster. But his sympathies with the king and with the Church
                    of England were so strong that he declined to sit. Early in 1643 he was chosen
                    chancellor of the cathedral of Salisbury; but of this preferment he was soon
                    after deprived. After Cromwell’s great victory at Worcester, Earle went abroad,
                    and was named clerk of the closet and chaplain to Charles II. He spent a year at
                    Antwerp in the house of Izaak Walton’s friend Dr Morley, who became afterwards
                    bishop of Winchester. He next joined the duke of York (James II.) at Paris,
                    returning to England at the Restoration. He was at once appointed dean of
                    Westminster, and in 1661 was one of the commissioners for revising the liturgy.
                    At the end of November 1662 he was consecrated bishop of Worcester, and was
                    translated, ten months later, to the see of Salisbury. During the plague of
                    London Bishop Earle attended the king and queen at Oxford, and there he died,
                    November 17, 1665. Earle’s chief title to remembrance is his witty and humorous
                    work entitled <hi rend="italic">Microcosmography, or a Piece of the World
                    discovered, in Essays and Characters,</hi> which throws light on the manners of
                    the time. First printed in 1628, it became very popular, and ran through eight
                    editions in the lifetime of the author. A new edition with notes and appendix,
                    containing much interesting matter, by Philip Bliss, was published in 1811. The
                    style is quaint and epigrammatic; and the reader is frequently reminded of
                    Thomas Fuller by such passages as this: “A university dunneris a gentlemen
                    follower cheaply purchased, for his own money has hyr’d him.” Several reprints
                    of the book have been issued since the author’s death; and in 1671 a French
                    translation by J. Dymock appeared with the title of <hi rend="italic">Le</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">vice ridicule.</hi> Earle was employed by Charles II. to make the
                    Latin translation of the <hi rend="italic">Eikon Bαsiliko,</hi> published in
                    1649.</p>
                <p>“Dr Earle,” says Lord Clarendon in his <hi rend="italic">Life,“</hi> was a man of
                    great piety and devotion, a most eloquent and powerful preacher, and of a
                    conversation so pleasant and delightful, so very innocent, and so very
                    facetious, that no man’s company was more desired and loved. No man was more
                    negligent in his dress and habit and mien, no man more wary and cultivated in
                    his behaviour and discourse. He was very dear to the Lord Falkland, with whom he
                    spent as much time as he could make his own.”</p>
                <p>See especially Bliss’s edition of the <hi rend="italic">Hicrocosmographie,</hi>
                    and Arber’s Keprint, London, 1868.</p>
                <p>EΛRLOM, <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard</hi> (1742-1822), English mezzotint
                    engraver, was born in London in 1742. His natural faculty for art appears to
                    have been first called into exercise by admiration for the lord mayor’s state
                    coach, just decorated by Cipriani. He tried to copy the paintings, and was sent
                    to study under Cipriani. He displayed great skill as a draughtsman, and at the
                    same time acquired without assistance the art of engraving in mezzotint. In 1765
                    he was employed by Aiderman Boydell, then one of the most liberal promoters of
                    the fine arts, to make a series of drawings from the pictures at Houghton Hall;
                    and these he afterwards engraved in mezzotint. His most perfect works as
                    engraver are perhaps the fruit and flower pieces after the Dutch artists Van Os
                    and Van Huysum. Amongst his historical and figure subjects are—Agrippina, after
                    West · Love in Bondage, after Guido Reni; the Royal Academy, the Embassy of
                    Hyderbeck to meet Lord Cornwallis, and a Tiger Hunt, the last three after
                    Zoffany; and Lord Heathfield, after Sir Joshua Reynolds. Earlom also executed a
                    series of 200 facsimiles of the drawings and sketches of Claude Lorraine, which
                    was published in 3 vols, folio, under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Liber</hi><hi rend="italic">Veritatis</hi> (1777-1819). Earlom died in London,
                    October 9, 1822.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
