<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0049-0040-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DELAMBRE, Jean Baptiste Joseph (9th edition, volume 7,
                    page 40)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n49/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DELAMBRE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jean Baptiste
                    Joseph</hi></label> (1749-1822), an eminent mathematician and astronomer, was
                    born at Amiens, September 19, 1749. He commenced his studies in the gymnasium of
                    that town under the celebrated poet IJplille, with whom he maintained an
                    intimate friendship till his death. Having obtained an exhibition founded by one
                    of his ancestors for the benefit of the town of Amiens, he was enabled to
                    prosecute his studies for a time at the Collège du Plessis in Paris. The expiry
                    of this privilege, however, left him to struggle with great privations. During
                    the interval in which he was awaiting permanent employment he devoted himself to
                    historical and literary studies. He undertook extensive translations from Latin,
                    Greek, Italian, and English, and at the same time entered on the study of the
                    mathematical sciences. For about a year he supported himself by teaching at
                    Compiègne. On his return to Paris in 1771 he obtained the situation of tutor in
                    the family of D’Assy, the receiver-general of finance. By this time he had
                    resolved to give himself specially to the study of physics and astronomy.</p>
                <p>At the College of France he attended the lectures of Lalande, on whose works he
                    had even at that time made a complete commentary. This was first remarked when,
                    in the course of instruction, an occasion presented itself of citing from memory
                    a passage of Aratus. Lalande immediately intrusted to him the most complicated
                    astronomical calculations, and prevailed on D’Assy to establish an observatory
                    at his house, where Delambre applied himself to astronomical observations. In
                    1781 the discovery of the planet Uranus by Herschel led the Academy of Sciences
                    to propose the determination of its orbit as the subject of one of its annual
                    prizes. Delambre undertook the formation of tables of its motion, and the prize
                    was awarded to him. His next effort was the construction of solar tables, and
                    tables of the motions of Jupiter and Saturn. He took part in the sitting of the
                    Academy of Sciences when Laplace communicated his important discoveries on the
                    inequalities of Jupiter and Saturn; and he formed the design of applying the
                    result of that profound analysis to the completion of tables of the two planets.
                    Delambre turned his attention more especially to the satellites of Jupiter—an
                    undertaking of great difficulty and extent. He had been engaged for several
                    years in the composition of his ecliptical tables, when the Academy of Sciences
                    offered a prize for the subject, wh <hi rend="superscript">;</hi> ch was awarded
                    to him. In the same year (1792) he was elected a member of the Academy.</p>
                <p>Immediately afterwards he was appointed, along with Méchain, by the French
                    section of the joint English and French commission to measure an arc from
                    Dunkirk to Barcelona as a basis for the metric system. This undertaking, in
                    itself laborious, was rendered highly dangerous to the personal safety of those
                    engaged in it by the events of the Revolution. Méchain died whilst the work was
                    proceeding; and its successful termination in 1799 was due to the ability and
                    the prudence of Delambre. A full and interesting account of the work was
                    published in his <hi rend="italic">Base</hi><hi rend="italic">du Système
                    Métrique</hi><hi rend="italic">Decimal</hi> (3 vols. 1806-10), for which he
                    obtained, by a unanimous vote, the prize awarded by the National Institute of
                    France to the most important work in physical science of the preceding ten
                    years.</p>
                <p>Delambre, who had been chosen as an associate of almost every scientific body in
                    Europe, was appointed in 1795 a member of the French Board of Longitude, and in
                    1803 perpetual secretary for the mathematical sciences in the Institute. In 1807
                    he succeeded Lalande in the chair of astronomy of the College of France, and he
                    was appointed one of the principal directors <hi rend="italic">(titulaires)</hi>
                    of the university.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n50/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0050-0041"/>
                <p>For twenty years he performed faithfully and impartially the duties of his office
                    in one of the classes of the Institute. His annual reports, his historical <hi
                    rend="italic">éloges,</hi> which have been published, and his exposition of the
                    progress of science are eminently distinguished by profound erudition, literary
                    skill, and, above all, by generous appreciation of the works of others. His
                    literary and scientific labours were very numerous, and, in respect of
                    excellence, of the highest order. His <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Astronomy,</hi> published at intervals, and forming when complete six quarto
                    volumes, is a work of prodigious research. It puts the modern astronomer in
                    possession of all that had been done, and of the methods employed by those who
                    lived before him.</p>
                <p>His <hi rend="italic">Méthodes Analytiques pour la Détermination d'un Arc du
                    Méridien,</hi> his numerous memoirs in the additions to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Connaissances</hi><hi rend="italic">des Temps,</hi> and his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Astronomie Théorique et</hi><hi rend="italic">Pratique</hi> exhibit the finest
                    applications of modern analysis to astronomy and geography.</p>
                <p>It is a remarkable fact that Delambre did not apply himself to astronomical
                    observations until he had reached the comparatively late age of thirty-five. He
                    was appointed a member of the Royal Council of Public Instruction in 1814; but
                    he lost the place in 1815. He was in Paris when it was taken by the allied
                    armies; and, in a letter written at that time to a friend and pupil, he says
                    that on the day of the siege, in the hearing of the cannonade, he laboured with
                    tranquillity in his study from eight in the morning till midnight. He had a
                    happier fate than Archimedes in a like position, for he was not molested by the
                    victors, and no one was billeted on him, probably from respect to his high
                    reputation. At the creation of the Legion of Honour in 1802 Delambre was made a
                    member of that order. He was appointed chevalier of St Michael in 1817, an
                    officer in the Legion of Honour in 1821; but a long time before, he had been
                    created an hereditary chevalier, with an endowment, which was decreed as a
                    national reward.</p>
                <p>The life of continued and hard study which Delam,bre led at last affected his
                    health. The disease by which he was cut off became apparent in the month of July
                    1822. His total loss of strength, with frequent and long continued
                    fainting-fits, gave warning of a fatal result, which occurred on the 19th August
                    1822.</p>
                <p>The following is a list of his works which appeared separately :— <hi
                    rend="italic">Tables de Jupiter</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >de Saturn</hi> (1789); <hi rend="italic">Tables</hi><hi rend="italic">du
                    Soleil,</hi><hi rend="italic">de Jupiter, de Saturn,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >d'</hi><hi rend="italic">Uranus,</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >des Satellites de Jupiter, pour</hi><hi rend="italic">servir à</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">la</hi><hi rend="italic">3me</hi><hi rend="italic">édition V
                    Astronomie de Lalande</hi> (1792); <hi rend="italic">Méthodes Analytiques pour
                    la Détermination d’un Arc du Méridien</hi> (1799); <hi rend="italic">Tables
                    Trigonométriques Décimales, par Borda, revues, augmentées, et publiées par Μ.
                    Delambre,</hi> (1801); <hi rend="italic">Tables du Soleil, publiées par le
                    Bureau des Longitudes</hi> (1806); <hi rend="italic">Base du Système Métrique
                    Décimal,</hi> &amp;c. (3 vols, in 4to, 1806-1810); <hi rend="italic">Rapport
                    Historique sur les Progrès des Sciences Mathématiques depuis</hi> 1789, &amp;c.
                    (1810); <hi rend="italic">Abrégé d’Astronomie, ou Leçons Élémentaires
                    d'Astronomie Théorique et Pratique,</hi> in 8vo; <hi rend="italic">Astronomie
                    Théorique et Pratique</hi> (3 vols, in 4to, 1814); <hi rend="italic">Tables
                    Ecliptiques des Satellites de Jupiter</hi> (1817); <hi rend="italic">Histoire de
                    VAstronomie Ancienne</hi> (2 vols, in 4to, 1817); <hi rend="italic">Histoire
                    de</hi><hi rend="italic">l’</hi><hi rend="italic">Astronomie du Moyen Age</hi>
                    (1819, 1 vol. in 4to); <hi rend="italic">Histoire de VAstronomie Moderne</hi>
                    (1821, 2 vols, in 4to); <hi rend="italic">Histoire de VAstronomie au Dixhuitième
                    Siècle</hi> (1 vol. 4to, 1827). In addition to these, he furnished a very
                    considerable number of memoirs (about 28) on various points of astronomy to the
                    <hi rend="italic">Connaissances</hi><hi rend="italic">de Temps,</hi> beginning
                    with the year 1788. He also contributed to the Memoirs of the Academies of
                    Stockholm, St Petersburg, Berlin, and Turin, and to those of the first class of
                    the French Institute; and he composed <hi rend="italic">éloges</hi> on many of
                    his contemporaries at their death.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
