<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0046-0037-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DEKKER, Thomas (9th edition, volume 7, page 37)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:958730">Holidays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897549">Dramatists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1158235">Truth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942866">Girls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176346">Witches</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952093">Hawks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785r56">Holidays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vs7f">Dramatists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9789n">Girls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tw3f">Hawking</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qj2t">Hawks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n46/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DEKKER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi></label>, dramatist.
                    It is impossible to make out, from the scanty records of Dekker’s personal life,
                    what manner of man he was. His name occurs frequently in Henslowe’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Diary</hi> during the last year of the 16 th century; he is
                    mentioned there as receiving loans and payments for writing plays in conjunction
                    with Ben Jonson, Chettle, Haughton, and Day, and he would appear to have been
                    then in the most active employment as a playwright. The titles of the plays on
                    which he was engaged from April 1599 to March 1599-1600 are <hi rend="italic"
                    >Troilus</hi><hi rend="italic">and Cressida, Orestes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Fures,</hi><hi rend="italic">Agamemnon, The Stepmother’s Tragedy, Bear a Brain,
                    Pagge of Plymouth, Robert the Second, Patient Grissel, The Shoemaker's Holiday,
                    Truth's Supplication to Candlelight, The Spanish Moor's Tragedy, The Seven Wise
                    Masters.</hi> At that date it is evident that Dekker’s services were in great
                    request for the stage. He is first mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">Diary</hi>
                    two years before, as having sold a book; the payments in 1599 are generally made
                    in advance, “in earnest” of work to be done. In the case of three of the above
                    plays, <hi rend="italic">Orestes</hi><hi rend="italic">Fures,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Truth's Supplication,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Shoemaker’s
                    Holiday,</hi> Dekker is paid as the sole author. Only the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Shoemaker's Holiday</hi> has been preserved; it was published in 1600. It would
                    be unsafe to argue from the classical subjects of some of these plays that
                    Dekker was then a young man from the university, who had come up like so many
                    others to make a living by writing for the stage. Classical knowledge was then
                    in the air; playwrights in want of a subject were content with translations, if
                    they did not know the originals. However educated, Dekker was then a young man
                    just out of his teens, if he spoke with any accuracy when he said that he was
                    threescore in 1637; and it was not in scholarly themes that he was destined to
                    find his true vein. The call foi the publication of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Shoemaker's Holiday,</hi> which deals with the life of the city, showed him
                    where his strength lay. To give a general idea of the substance of Dekker’s
                    plays, there is no better way than to call him the Dickens of the Elizabethan
                    period. The two men were as unlike as possible in their habits of work, Dekker
                    having apparently all the thriftlessness and impecunious shamelessness of
                    Micawber himself. Dekker’s Bohemianism appears in the slightness and hurry of
                    his work, a strong contrast to the thoroughness and rich completeness of every
                    labour to which Dickens applied himself; perhaps also in the exquisite freshness
                    and sweetness of his songs, and the natural charm of stray touches of expression
                    and description in his plays. But he was like Dickens in the bent of his genius
                    towards the representation of the life around him in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n47/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0047-0038"/> London, as well as in the humorous kindliness of
                    his way of looking at that life, his vein of sentiment, and his eye for odd
                    characters. There is a passage in Ben Jonson’s caricature of Dekker under the
                    name of “Crispinus,”—an allusion to his <hi rend="italic">Shoemaker's
                    Holiday,—</hi> from which it would appear that Dekker prided himself on his
                    powers of observation. The less is included in the greater; the random pickings
                    of Dekker, hopping here and there in search of a subject, give less complete
                    results than the more systematic labours of Dickens. Dekker’s Simon Eyre, the
                    good-hearted, mad shoemaker, and his Orlando Frisco-baldo, are touched with a
                    kindly humour in which Dickens would have delighted; his Infelices, Fiamettas,
                    Tormiellas, even his Bellafronta, have a certain likeness in type to the
                    heroines of Dickens; and his roaring blades and their gulls are prototypes of
                    Sir Mulberry Hawk and Lord Frederick Verisopht. Only there is this great
                    difference in the spirit of the two writers, that Dekker wrote without the
                    smallest apparent wish to reform the life that he saw, desiring only to exhibit
                    it; and that on the whole, apart from his dramatist’s necessity of finding
                    interesting matter, he cast his eye about rather with a liking for the discovery
                    of good under unpromising appearances than with any determination to detect and
                    expose vice. The observation must also be made that Dekker’s personages have
                    much more individual character, more of that mixture of good and evil which we
                    find in real human beings. Hack-writer though Dekker was, and writing often
                    under sore pressure there is no dramatist whose personages have more of the
                    breath of life in them; drawing with easy, unconstrained hand, he was a master
                    of those touches by which an imaginary figure is brought home to us as a
                    creature with human interests. A very large part of the motive power in his
                    plays consists in the temporary yielding to an evil passion. The kindly
                    philosophy that the best of natures may be for a time perverted by passionate
                    desires is the chief animating principle of his comedy. He delights in showing
                    women listening to temptation, and apparently yielding, but still retaining
                    sufficient control over themselves to be capable of drawing back when on the
                    verge of the precipice. The wives of the citizens were his heroines, pursued by
                    the unlawful addresses of the gay young courtiers; and on the whole Dekker, from
                    inclination apparently as well as policy, though himself, if Ben Jonson’s satire
                    had any point, a bit of a dandy in his youth, took the part of morality and the
                    city, and either struck the rakes with remorse or made the objects of their
                    machinations clever enough to outwit them. From Dekker’s plays we get a very
                    lively impression of all that was picturesque and theatrically interesting in
                    the city life of the time, the interiors of the shops and the houses, the tastes
                    of the citizens and their wives, the tavern and tobacco shop manners of the
                    youthful aristocracy and their satellites. The social student cannot afford to
                    overlook Dekker; there is no other dramatist of that age from whom we can get
                    such a vivid picture of contemporary manners in London. He drew direct from
                    life; in so far as he idealized, he did so not in obedience to scholarly
                    precepts or dogmatic theories, but in the immediate interests of good-natured
                    farce and tender-hearted sentiment.</p>
                <p>In all the serious parts of Dekker’s plays there is a charming delicacy of touch,
                    and his smallest scraps of song are bewitching; but his plays, as plays, owe
                    much more to the interest of the characters and the incidents than to any
                    excellence of construction. We see what use could be made of his materials by a
                    stronger intellect in <hi rend="italic">Westward Ho ∕</hi> which he wrote in
                    conjunction with John Webster. The play, somehow, though the parts are more
                    firmly knit together, and it has more unity of purpose, is not so interesting as
                    Dekker’s unaided work. Middleton formed a more successful combination with
                    Dekker than Webster; the <hi rend="italic">Honest Whore,</hi> or the <hi
                    rend="italic">Converted Courtesan,</hi> is generally regarded as the best that
                    bears Dekker’s name, and in it he had the assistance of Middleton, although the
                    assistance was so immaterial as not to be worth acknowledging in the title-page.
                    Still that Middleton, a man of little genius· but of much practical talent and
                    robust humour, was serviceable to Dekker in determining the form of the play may
                    well be believed. The two wrote another play in concert, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Roaring Girl,</hi> for which Middleton probably contributed a good deal of the
                    matter, as well as a more symmetrical form than Dekker seems to have been
                    capable of devising. In the <hi rend="italic">Witch of Edmonton,</hi> except in
                    a few scenes, it is difficult to trace the hand, of Dekker with any certainty;
                    his collaborateurs were John Ford and William Rowley; to Ford probably belongs
                    the intense brooding and murderous wrath of the old hag, which are too direct
                    and hard in their energy for Dekker, while Rowley may be supposed to be
                    responsible for the delineation of country life.</p>
                <p>When Langbaine wrote his <hi rend="italic">Account of the English Dramatic
                    Poets</hi> in 1691, he spoke of Dekker as being “more famous for the contention
                    he had with Ben Jonson for the bays, than for any great reputation he had gained
                    by his own writings.” This is an opinion that could not be professed now, when
                    Dekker’s work is read. In the contention with Ben Jonson, one of the most
                    celebrated quarrels of authors, the origin of which is matter of dispute, Dekker
                    seems to have had very much the best of it. We can imagine that Jonson’s attack
                    was stinging at the time, because it seems to be full of sarcastic
                    personalities, but it is dull enough now when nobody knows what Dekker was like,
                    nor what was the character of his mother. There is nothing in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Poetaster</hi> that has any point as applied to Dekker’s powers as
                    a dramatist, while on the contrary the <hi rend="italic">üntrussing of the
                    Humorous Poet</hi> is full of pungent ridiculo of Jonson’s style, and of retorts
                    and insults conceived in the happiest spirit of good-natured mockery. Dekker has
                    been accused of poverty of invention in adopting the characters of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Poetaster,</hi> but it is of the very pith of the jest that Dekker
                    should have set on Jonson’s own foul-mouthed Captain Tucca to abuse Horace
                    himself.</p>
                <p>Dekker’s plays were published in the following order:— <hi rend="italic">Ths
                    Shoemaker’s Holiday,</hi> 1600; <hi rend="italic">The Pleasant Comedy of
                    old</hi><hi rend="italic">Fortunatus,</hi> 1600; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Satiromastrix,</hi> 1602; <hi rend="italic">Patient Grissel</hi> (in
                    conjunction with Chettle and Haughton) 1603; <hi rend="italic">The Honest
                    Whore</hi> (Part i.) 1604; <hi rend="italic">The Whore of Babylon,</hi> 1607;
                    <hi rend="italic">Westward Hol Northward Hol</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sir
                    Thomas Wyatt</hi> (in conjunction with Webster), 1607; <hi rend="italic">The
                    Roaring Girl</hi> (in conjunction with Middleton), 1611; <hi rend="italic">If it
                    be not good, the Devil is in it,</hi> 1612; <hi rend="italic">The Virgin
                    Martyr</hi> (in conjunction with Massinger), 1622; <hi rend="italic">Match Me in
                    London,</hi> 1631; <hi rend="italic">The Wonder of a Kingdom,</hi> 1636; <hi
                    rend="italic">The Sun's Darling</hi> (not published till 1656); and <hi
                    rend="italic">The Witch of Edmonton</hi> (written in conjunction with Rowley and
                    Ford), 1658. An edition of the collected dramatic works of Dekker is published
                    by John Pearson. Some of his prose tracts, of which he wτote many, are reprinted
                    by the <hi rend="italic">Shakespeare Society,</hi> notably <hi rend="italic">The
                    Seven Deadly</hi><hi rend="italic">Sins^of</hi><hi rend="italic">London</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">The Gull's Hornbook.</hi> (W. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
