<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0571-0552-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DURANDUS (9th edition, volume 7, page 552)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n571/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DURANDUS</label>, WiLHELMUs (1237-1296), otherwise <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Durantis</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Duranti,</hi> was born at
                    Puimisson, sometimes written Puimoisson, a small town in the diocese of Beziers,
                    in Languedoc, whence he is sometimes described as a native of Provence. He
                    studied law under Bernardus of Parma, in the university of Bologna, where he was
                    promoted to the degree of doctor. He shortly afterwards migrated to the
                    university of Modena, where he became so famous by his lectures on the canon law
                    that he attracted the notice of Pope Clement I V., who appointed him auditor of
                    the palace, and subsequently subdeacon and chaplain. In 1274 he accompanied Pope
                    Gregory X. as his secretary to the Council of Lyons, which is reckoned as the
                    fourteenth general council, and under the pontificates of several subsequent
                    popes filled many highly responsible offices. He was appointed in 1277 spiritual
                    and temporal legate of the patrimony of St Peter under Pope Nicholas III., and
                    in 1278 took possession, in the name of the same Pope, of the provinces of
                    Bologna and Romagna. In 1281 Pope Martin IV. named him vicar spiritual, and in
                    1283 governor of the temporalities of the two provinces, in which office he had
                    the direction of the war against the rebellious province of Romagna. The town of
                    Castrum Riparum Urbanatium having been burnt down during the war, he rebuilt it,
                    and renamed it Castrum Durantis. Pope Urban VIII. subsequently gave to this town
                    the name of Urbania, which it bears in the present day. Pope Honorius IV.
                    retained Durandus in the same offices until the end of 1286, when his election
                    to the bishopric of Meude, in Languedoc, was the occasion of his retiring for a
                    short time from the conduct of civil affairs. Duraudus, however, appears to have
                    remained in Italy, and to have revised at this time several of his works. He
                    refused in 1295 the archbishopric of Ravenna, which was offered to him by Pope
                    Boniface VIII., and accepted in preference the more arduous office of governor
                    of the province of Romagna and of the march of Ancona. The party of the
                    Ghibellines, however, carried on hostilities against the Holy See with so much
                    vigour that he found his strength unequal to the exigencies of government; and,
                    having resigned his office, he retired to Rome, where he died on 1st November
                    1296.</p>
                <p>Durandus was the author of several very learned rvorks. The most famous of them
                    is his <hi rend="italic">Speαdum</hi><hi rend="italic">Judiciale.</hi> This work
                    is entitled in the juin ted copies, the earliest of which was published at home
                    in folio in 1474, as <hi rend="italic">Speculum Juris</hi>; but all the MSS.
                    have the title of <hi rend="italic">Speadum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Judiciale</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and Durandus himself, in his epistle
                    dedicatory to Cardinal Ottobonus Fiesco, afterwards Pope Adrian V., describes it
                    under this latter title. It is a practical treatise on civil and canon law, and
                    it earned for its author, when young, the surname of the Father of Practice.
                    Durandus is said to have completed it in 1271, at the age of thirty-four, and he
                    revised it some time between 1287 and 1291. It has since his death acquired much
                    celebrity as one of the best sources of the dogmatic history of law, and the
                    canonists are accustomed to cite Durandus under the bye-name of “the
                    Speculator.” The original work has been enriched by additions from the pen of
                    John Andreae in 1346, and by further additions from the pen of Baldus. An
                    alphabetic table of its contents (Inventorium) was drawn up by Cardinal Beranger
                    in 1306, and the <hi rend="italic">Speculum</hi> passed through thirty-eight
                    editions between 1474 and 1678. The next important work of Durandus is his <hi
                    rend="italic">Repertorium</hi><hi rend="italic">Aureum</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Breviarium,</hi> which is dedicated to Cardinal Matthaeus; Durandus himself in
                    his preface designates this work by the name of Breviarium, but it is described
                    by him in the Preface to the <hi rend="italic">Specιdum</hi> by the title of <hi
                    rend="italic">Repertorium</hi><hi rend="italic">Aureum,</hi> under which title
                    it is more generally known. It is supposed to have been composed by Durandus in
                    the interval between the first completion and the revision of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Speculum.</hi> His <hi rend="italic">Commentarius</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">in Concilium</hi><hi rend="italic">Lugdunense</hi> is a work of
                    much interest, as Durandus himself drew up the Decretals, which after his death
                    were inserted in the <hi rend="italic">Sextus.</hi> Durandus also wrote a
                    commentary on the decretals of Pope Nicholas 111., which is only known to us
                    from the epitaph on his tomb, as preserved by Sarti, and which enumerates all
                    his chief writings, amongst which may be mentioned his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Speculum Legatorum,</hi> inserted in the <hi rend="italic">Specιdum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Judiciale,</hi> his <hi rend="italic">Rationale</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Divinorum Officiorum,</hi> which has passed through many editions,
                    the earliest of which was printed at Mayence in 1459, and a copy of which is
                    stated by the Abbé Pascal to ha·ve been sold for 2700 francs. A manuscript of
                    his <hi rend="italic">Pontificale</hi><hi rend="italic">Patrum,</hi> being a
                    treatise on the duties of bishops, is preserved in the National Library of
                    Paris. Durandus the Speculator is sometimes confounded with Durandus of Santo
                    Porciano, bishop of Meaux, who died in 1332, and was the author of two
                    treatises, De <hi rend="italic">Jurisdictioni</hi> and De <hi rend="italic"
                    >Legebus,</hi> and·withWilhelmus Durandus, his own nephew, who was the author of
                    a work entitled <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">modo celebrandi
                    Consilii,</hi> and who died in Cyprus in 1328.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
