<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0551-0532-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DUNBAR, William (9th edition, volume 7, page
                    532)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z5k">Pensions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1043068">Occasionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1057086">Pensions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1068092">Poi</term>
                    <term ref="fast:828732">Baths</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n551/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DUNBAR, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>, one of the
                    most distinguished of .the early poets of Scotland, is supposed to have been
                    born about 1460. Comparatively little is known about his personal history, but,
                    from an allusion in one of his poems, he seems to have been a native of
                    Lothian.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Flyting with
                    Kennedy, line 110.</p></note> In his fifteenth or sixteenth year he was sent to
                    the university of St Andrews, where he received the degree of B.A. in 1477, and
                    that of M.A. in 1479.</p>
                <p>Of the events of his life for nearly twenty years after this we possess little
                    information. He mentions, however, in his poems that he had been employed as a
                    preaching friar of the order of St Francis, and as such had made good cheer in
                    every nourishing town in England had ascended the pulpit at Dernton and
                    Canterbury, and had crossed th sea at Dover, and instructed the inhabitants of
                    Picardy. He also mentions that this mode of life compelled him to have recourse
                    to many a pious fraud, from whose guilt no holy water could clear him. After
                    this he appears to have entered the service of James IV., by whom he was sent on
                    numerous embassies to foreign princes.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>In a poem to the king he reminds him that he had boen
                    employed nυt only in France, England, and Ireland, but also in Germany, Italy,
                    and Spain. (Notes by Laing, vol. i. app. 263).</p></note> In 1491 he was
                    residing at Paris, most likely in connection with the Scottish embassy there.
                    The knowledge of the Continent he thus obtained must have had considerable
                    influence in imparting greater strength and energy to his poetical
                    conceptions.</p>
                <p>In the year 1500 Dunbar obtained from the king a yearly pension of £10, until he
                    should be promoted to one of greater value. In 1501 he went to England with the
                    ambassadors sent to conclude the negotiations for the marriage of the young King
                    James with the Princess Margaret, daughter of Henry VII. During the festivities
                    on this occasion Dunbar was styled “the Rhymer of Scotland,” and received from
                    Henry a present of £6, 13s. 4d. in December, and a similar sum in January of the
                    subsequent year. On his return to Edinburgh a sum of £5 was paid to him in
                    addition to his salary. In honour of this marriage Dunbar composed his well
                    known poem, <hi rend="italic">The Thrissil and the</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Pois,</hi> another in honour of the city of London, and several others in which
                    he described the personal attractions of the young queen. After this he lived
                    much at court writing poems, although at the same time he hoped to obtain
                    preferment in the church.</p>
                <p>In 1504 he first performed mass before the king, whose offering on that occasion
                    was £4, 18s., a larger sum than that usually paid on the occasion of a priest’s
                    first mass. In 1507 his pension was augmented to £20, and three years afterwards
                    it was raised to £80, to be paid during his life, or until he should be promoted
                    to a benefice of £100 or more. In 1511 he seems to have been in the train of
                    Queen Margaret when she visited the northern part of Scotland, as one of his
                    poems, descriptive of her reception at Aberdeen, is evidently written by an
                    eye-witness.</p>
                <p>After the disaster of Flodden, in 1513, Dunbar’s fortunes seem to have changed,
                    and no further mention of him occurs as receiving pension. That he may have
                    obtained church preferment is quite possible, but the probability is that the
                    early death of the king, and the unpopularity of the queen and the little
                    influence she had after her marriage with the earl of Angus, may have led to
                    neglect of Dunbar in his old age. His poems contain many allusions to the
                    unequal division of the world’s goods. He was alive in 1517, as in that year he
                    wrote a poem on the occasion of the Regent Albany passing into France, in which
                    he laments the distracted state of public affaire in Scotland.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>There is considerable doubt
                    about the period of Dunbar’s death, as the poem relative to the Regent Albany
                    may have been attributed to him by mistake. Mr Laing has conjectured that he may
                    have accompanied King James, and been killed along with him in the battle of
                    Flodden, where so many ecclesiastics perished. The volume of the accounts of the
                    Treasurer from 1513 to 1515, which might have settled this and other important
                    points, has been lost.</p></note> He is supposed to have died about the year
                    1520, when he had attained his sixtieth year.</p>
                <p>The poems of Dunbar, “the darling of the Scottish muse,” are about a hundred in
                    number, for the most part of no great length. <hi rend="italic">The Thrissil and
                    the</hi><hi rend="italic">Pois,</hi> written, as before remarked, on the
                    occasion of the marriage of James IV., is an allegory in which he describes the
                    amity between England and Scotland in consequence of that event. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Golden Targe</hi> is a moral poem of great power of imagery,
                    in which the ascendency of love over reason is shown to be general—the golden
                    shield of reason being insufficient to ward off the shafts of Cupid. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Twa Maryit Wemen and the Wedo,</hi> a tale in which the poet
                    overhears three females relating their experiences of married life, is an
                    imitation of Chaucer’s <hi rend="italic">Wife of Bath. The Freiris of
                    Berwik,</hi> a tale, is also in the Chaucerian style. <hi rend="italic">The
                    Flyting of Dunbar and Kennedy</hi> is perhaps the most obscure of his poems,
                    though it seems to have been very popular, and frequently imitated in the 16th
                    century. Several of his smaller poems show a quick appreciation of peculiarities
                    of character, but some of them—such as the tournament, or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Justis</hi><hi rend="italic">betuix the Tailyeour and Sowtar—</hi> though
                    ludicrous, are very coarse. In one called <hi rend="italic">Of a Dance in the
                    Qτιeenis Chalmer,</hi> he describes himself as one of the performers</p>
                <p>Thain cam in Dunbar the makkar, On all the flure thair was nane frakkar, And
                    thair he dansit the dirrye dantoun, He hoppet like a pillie wantoun For luiff of
                    Musgraiffe, men tellis me, He trippet quhile he tint his pantoun; A mirrear
                    dance mycht na man see.</p>
                <p>Another <hi rend="italic">Dance,</hi> that <hi rend="italic">of the Sevin DeidUe
                    Synnis—in</hi> which Mahoun, prince of devils, is described as holding a
                    carnival with Pride, Ire, Envy, Covetousness, Idleness, Treachery, Gluttony,
                    each with a train of followers, while a company of fiends stand by enjoying the
                    sport, encouraging <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n552/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0552-0533"/> the performers with various hot applications—is
                    as extravagant a piece as can well be conceived. In contrast, however, he wrote
                    several poems of a religious character, <hi rend="italic">e.g., Off the
                    Nativitie of Christ; Off the Passioun of Christ; Off the licsurreciioη of
                    Christ;</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic">Maner</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">of Passyng to Confessioun</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    i</hi><hi rend="italic">&lt;L'c.</hi></p>
                <p>More fortunate than Douglas and some of the earlier Scottish poets, Dunbar had
                    the satisfaction of seeing his principal works in print. <hi rend="italic">The
                    Thrissil and the</hi><hi rend="italic">Rois,</hi><hi rend="italic">The Golden
                    Targe, The Flyting with Kennedy,</hi> and the ballad of <hi rend="italic">Lord
                    Barnard Stewart</hi> were printed by Chepman and Myllar in 1508, and are the
                    first specimens of typography that issued from the Scottish press.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Of these the only copy known
                    to exist is preserved in the Advocates’ Library, Edinburgh. This unique volume
                    was reprinted in 1827 under the title <hi rend="italic">The Knightly Tale of
                    Golagrus and Gawane, and other ancient poems printed at Edinburgh by</hi> 1Γ.
                    <hi rend="italic">Chepman. and</hi><hi rend="italic">Androw</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Myllar in the year</hi> 1508, 4to.</p></note> Several of his poems
                    were preservedin the Asloane MS., written in 1575, the Bannatyne MS. 1568 <hi
                    rend="subscript"> i</hi> preserved in the Advocates’ Libraιy, the Maitland MS.
                    in the Pepysιan Library, and the Reidpeth MS. in the University Library,
                    Cambridge. Of these detached poems some appeared in collections edited by Allan
                    Ramsay, John Pinkerton, ana Lord Hailes, in the course of the last century, but
                    at length the works of Dunbar were collected and published in 1834 by Dr Dâvid
                    Laing (2 vols. 8vo, with a supplement, 1875), having a biography and valuable
                    illustrative notes. In 1873 a minute analysis of the language of Dunbar was
                    published at Bonn by Dr Johannes Kaufmann of Elberfeld.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
