<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0374-0357-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DONALDSON, John William (9th edition, volume 7, page
                    357)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xf77">Criticism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pj93">Keys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353199">Grammar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n374/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DONALDSON, <hi rend="smallcaps">John William</hi></label>, a
                    philologist and biblical critic, born 1812, died February 10, 1861. He was
                    educated at the London university and at Trinity College, Cambridge, of which
                    college he was afterwards elected a fellow. He graduated in the year 1834, being
                    placed in the second class of the mathematical tripos, and second in the
                    classical tripos, when G. J. Kennedy was senior, and W. Forsyth, the author of
                    <hi rend="italic">Hortensius,</hi> third classic. After his degree he devoted
                    himself with unremitting energy to classical philology, and the <hi
                    rend="italic">New Cratylus,</hi> which appeared five years later, is not only a
                    work of wonderful erudition for so young a man, but forms a landmark in the
                    history of philology in England. In 1841 he was elected to the head-mastership
                    of King Edward’s school at Bury St Edmunds, a position which he held for over
                    ten years. On resigning this post he returned to Cambridge, where his time was
                    divided between literary work and private tuition. At the time of his death,
                    which was accelerated by over-study, he was engaged in the preparation of a
                    Greek lexicon.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">New Gratylus,</hi> the work on which Dr Donaldson’s fame
                    mainly rests, is an attempt to apply the general principles of comparative
                    philology to the Greek language. The book consists of two parts—a general
                    introduction, in which the philosophy of language and the ethnographical
                    affinities of the ancient Greeks are discussed, and a treatise on the
                    grammatical structure and etymology of Greek. It is mainly founded on the
                    comparative grammar of Bopp, but a large part of it is original, and it is but
                    just to the English philologist to observe that the great German’s grammar was
                    not completed till ten years after the first edition of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cratylus.</hi> In the <hi rend="italic">Varronianus,</hi> which followed in
                    1844, the same method is applied to the classification and analysis of Latin and
                    the other Italian dialects. It includes a critical commentary on the remains of
                    old Latin, Umbrian, and Oscan. If we consider the recent birth and rapid strides
                    of philology it is not wonderful that these early essays should have been
                    superseded by the riper labours of such men as Curtius, Schleicher, and Mommsen.
                    Distinguished as Donaldson’s works are by wide and varied learning, much
                    ingenuity, and independence of thought, they are deficient in soberness of
                    judgment, and, most of all, in the ability to distinguish between certain
                    inference and uncertain conjecture. More especially are these defects apparent
                    in the ethnographical theories of the <hi rend="italic">Varronianus.</hi> To
                    take a single instance, the origin and affinities of the Etruscan language,
                    problems which have yet to be solved, are stated no less confidently than those
                    of modern French.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n375/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0375-0358"/>
                <p>Before discussing his other works it is necessary to mention an unfortunate
                    controversy which this book provoked. A charge of plagiarism was brought against
                    the author by the late Professor Key, and a war of pamphlets followed as violent
                    as those which were common in the days of Bentley and Porson. Without attempting
                    to decide on the merits of this dispute, it is enough to state that though the
                    obligations of Donaldson to Key ought in the first instance to have been more
                    explicitly acknowledged, yet the strictures of the latter were needlessly
                    sweeping and aggressive.</p>
                <p>We pass on to Donaldson s work as a biblical critic. In 1854 he published his <hi
                    rend="italic">Jashar, or Fragments of original Hebrew songs inserted in the
                    Masoretic text of the Old Testament.</hi> The book was written in Latin, as an
                    appeal <hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic">clerum,</hi> to the learned
                    world in general, and especially to German theologians. It is an attempt to
                    reconstitute the lost book of Jashar from the remains of old songs and
                    historical records, which, according to the author, are incorporated in the
                    existing text of the Old Testament. Here, too, we notice the same merits and
                    defects as in the <hi rend="italic">Cratylus,</hi> the same ingenuity and
                    learning, the same rash and overconfident speculation. The bold views of the
                    author on the nature of inspiration, and the free handling of the sacred text,
                    provoked a storm of theological odium, but the only one of his numerous
                    assailants who deserves mention is Dr Perowne. A full analysis of the book will
                    be found in Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Biblical Dictionary, s. v.</hi>
                    “Jashar.”</p>
                <p>Of his numerous other works the most important are <hi rend="italic">The Theatre
                    of the Greeks, The History of the Literature of Ancient Greece</hi> (a
                    completion of K. O. Müller’s work), an edition of <hi rend="italic">Pindar,</hi>
                    and a Hebrew, a Greek, and a Latin Grammar. Among his occasional writings the
                    article “Philology” in the 8th edition of this <hi rend="italic"
                    >Encyclopaedia</hi> is the most important. Though much of what he wrote has
                    already become obsolete, Donaldson will long be remembered as one of the
                    pioneers of philology in England.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
