<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0041-0032-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DEHRA DÚN (9th edition, volume 7, page 32)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77z92">Brahmanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qf8jn74">Eurasians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837525">Brahmanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837522">Brahman</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837534">Brahmans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n41/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DEHRA DÚN</label>, a district of British India in the Meerut
                    (Mirat) division of the lieutenant-governorship of the NorthWestern Provinces,
                    lies between 29° 57' and 30° 59' N. lat., and 77° 37' 15" and 78° 22' 45" E.
                    long. It comprises the valley <hi rend="italic">(dun)</hi> of Dehra, together
                    with the hills division <hi rend="italic">(parganá)</hi> of Jaunsár Báwar, which
                    runs from S.E. to NW. of it, on the north. The district is bounded on the N. by
                    the native state of Tehri or Garhwál, on the E. by British Garhwál, on the S. by
                    the Siwálik hills, which separate it from Saháranpur district, and on the W. by
                    the hill states of Si’rmur, Jubol, and Taránch. The valley <hi rend="italic"
                    >(the Dún)</hi> has an area of about 673 square miles, and forms a parallelogram
                    45 miles from N.W. to S.E. and 15 miles broad. It is well wooded, undulating,
                    and intersected by streams. On the N.E. the horizon is bounded by the Mussooree
                    (Mansúri) or lower range of the Himálayas, and on the S. by the Siwálik hills.
                    The Himálayas in the north <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n42/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0042-0033"/> of the district attain a height of between 7000
                    and 8000 feet, one peak reaching an elevation of 8565 feet; the highest point of
                    the Siwálik range is 3041 above sea-level. The principal passes through the
                    Siwálik hills are the Timli pass, leading to the military station of Chakráta,
                    and the Mohand pass leading to the sanatoriums of Mussooree and Landaur. The
                    Ganges bounds the Dehra valley on the E.; the Jumna bounds it on the W. From a
                    point about midway between the two rivers, and near the town of Dehra, runs a
                    ridge which forms the water-shed of the valley. To the west of this ridge, the
                    water collects to form the Asan, a tributary of the Jumna; whilst to the east
                    the Suswa receives the drainage and flows into the Ganges. To the east the
                    valley is characterized by swamps and forests, but to the west the natural
                    depressions freely carry off the surface drainage. Along the central ridge, the
                    waterlevel lies at a great depth from the surface (228 feet), but it rises
                    gradually as the country declines towards the great rivers. To meet the demand
                    for water five canals have been constructed, and are fed by the hill streams.
                    These canalshave a total length of 67 miles, irrigate about 10,734 acres, and
                    yield a net annual revenue of about £2300. Jaunsár Báwar, north of the valley,
                    comprises a triangular hilly tract, situated between the Tons and Jumna rivers
                    near their point of confluence, and has an area of about 343 square miles. It is
                    covered with forests of deodars, firs, cypresses, and oaks.</p>
                <p>The agricultural products consist of rice, <hi rend="italic">mandua
                    (Eleusine</hi><hi rend="italic">corocand),</hi> oil seeds, millets, vegetables,
                    and garden crops, such as potatoes, turmeric, red pepper, &amp;c. The method of
                    cultivation in the valley does not differ from that adopted in the plains; but
                    in Jaunsár, the <hi rend="italic">khil</hi> or <hi rend="italic">jum</hi> system
                    of cultivation is largely practised. This consists in clearing and burning the
                    undergrowth on the steep banks of ravines and hills, and in sprinkling the seed,
                    chiefly millets, over the ashes. The process yields a good crop for about two
                    years, when the site is abandoned. The principal industries are tea planting and
                    cultivation, rhea cultivation, and recently silk cultivation. The area under tea
                    in 1872 was 2024 acres, yielding an out-turn of 297,828 δ&gt;, valued at
                    £17,486.</p>
                <p>The total revenue derived from Dehra district (exclusive of forests) in 1872-73
                    amounted to £19,169. Since 1872 the Dehra valley has been subject to the
                    ordinary laws of other settled districts; but in the hilly division of Jaunsár a
                    less formal code is better suited to the people, and this tract is still
                    “non-regulation.” The fiscal arrangements of Jaunsár are also peculiar. The
                    tract is divided into <hi rend="italic">khats,</hi> each presided over by a <hi
                    rend="italic">say ana,</hi> or head-man. The <hi rend="italic">say anas</hi>
                    engage with the Government for the payment of the land revenue, and exercise
                    police and civil jurisdiction in their respective <hi rend="italic">khats;</hi>
                    whilst a committee of <hi rend="italic">say anas,</hi> subject to the control of
                    the British Superintendent of Dehra Dún, decide graver disputes affecting one or
                    more <hi rend="italic">khats.</hi> Education is progressing rapidly in the Dehra
                    valley. Schools have also been established in Jaunsár. Mussooree has Protestant
                    diocesan schools for European boys and girls; and similar institutions are
                    managed by Roman Catholic priests for members of that faith. It likewise forms
                    the head-quarters of an active American mission. There is little crime in the
                    district, and in Jaunsár no regular police are found necessary.</p>
                <p>The principal places in the district are Dehra, Mussooree, with the military
                    sanatarium of Landaur, and the military station of Chakráta. Dehra town is the
                    civil head-quarters of the district, and is constituted a municipality. It
                    contained (1872) a total population of about 7000 souls, (5000 Hindus, and 2000
                    Mahometans). The municipal income is mainly derived from a house tax. Dehra is
                    the headquarters of the 2d Gurkha regiment, and of the Great Trigonometrical
                    Survey. The hill station of Mussooree is a favourite summer resort. Its
                    population varies according to the season of the year. During the winter months
                    it is almost entirely deserted. Landaur, the military depot for European
                    convalescents, is really a portion of Mussooree. Chakráta is a hill station for
                    a British regiment of infantry.</p>
                <p>The census of 1872 returned the population of the entire district at 116,953
                    souls, of λvhoιn 102,814 were Hindus, 12,427 Mussulmans, 1061 Europeans, 191
                    Eurasians, and 460 native Christians. The Brahmans numbered 10,279, Rajputs or
                    military caste 33,125, Baniyás or traders 2664. The Brahmans and Rajputs chiefly
                    belong to the spurious hill clans bearing these names. The Mahometan population
                    consists principally of Patháns and Shaikhs.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
