<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0368-0351-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DOMICILE (9th edition, volume 7, page 351)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h708385">Will</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49g84h">Wills</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc3p">Appeal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:975961">Intentionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058667">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058664">Personalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058861">Persons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205550">Paraguay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n368/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DOMICILE</label>, in law, may be defined generally as the
                    place of a man’s permanent abode; but a precise definition of the word is a
                    matter of acknowledged difficulty. Its use in jurisprudence is to fix the legal
                    rights of a person in certain cases where it is felt that the application of the
                    law of the country to which he owes allegiance on the one hand, or of the
                    country in which for the moment he happens to be, would be attended with
                    inconvenience. Thus an English citizen who, for purposes of business, health,
                    &amp;c., has for many years permanently resided in France, has, let us suppose,
                    died during a casual visit to Denmark. The question would arise under which of
                    the three systems of law—English, French, or German—the validity of his will,
                    the succession to his estate, &amp;c., would be determined. Or, again, a French
                    subject habitually resident in England, but not naturalized, might sue for a
                    dissolution of his marriage in the matrimonial courts of this country, and it
                    would be generally admitted that our courts in such a case were entitled to
                    exercise jurisdiction, and that their decision ought to be received as
                    determining the status of the persons concerned, just as fully as if they had
                    been natural-born subjects of the Crown. In such cases there is a general
                    agreement that a man’s legal character, so to speak, should be determined by his
                    domicile, rather than by his political nationality or his residence for the time
                    being. We shall notice briefly the conditions of residence under which domicile
                    may generally be established.</p>
                <p>The Roman jurists defined domicile to be the place “ubi quis larem rerumque ac
                    fortunarum summam constituit: unde rursus non sit discessurus si nihil avocet:
                    unde cum profectus est, peregrinari videtuτ: quo si rediit peregrinari jam
                    destitit.” The general result of the definitions to be found in writers on the
                    civil law is to make that place the domicile which may be described as the head
                    quarters of the person concerned, or, as it is expressed in the Code Civile, “le
                    lieu ou il a son principal établissement.” But here characteristic difficulties
                    embarrassed the civil lawyers. A man’s habits of life might point equally to two
                    places as his head-quarters. It might be impossible to say which of them was the
                    principal seat of his business. Which of the two in such a case is the legal
                    domicile. Or can the same person at the same time have two domiciles î The two
                    essential things are residence and the intention of remaining. Story’s
                    definition is, “That place is properly the domicile of a person in which his
                    habitation is fixed without any present intention of removing therefrom.” Change
                    of residence not intended to be permanent would not create a new domicile. Cases
                    will readily suggest themselves in which the question of intention may be
                    surrounded with difficulties.</p>
                <p>The following summary follows the general rules laid down by Story for
                    determining the domicile of a person <hi rend="italic">(Conflict of Laws,</hi>
                    Sec. 46). The child takes the domicile of the father, except in the case of an
                    illegitimate child, which takes the domicile of the mother. Minors follow the
                    changes of the father’s domicile; and a married woman follows the domicile of
                    her husband. The place of residence is <hi rend="italic">prima</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">facie</hi> the domicile; and when a person removes to another
                    place with the intention of making it his'permanent residence, that place
                    becomes his domicile. When a person has removed to another place with the
                    intention of remaining there for an indefinite time, that is his domicile,
                    though he may have a general intention of returning at some future time. In
                    general the domicile of a married man is the place where his family permanently
                    resides, even though he habitually transacts his business elsewhere. When a
                    married man has two places of residence, that will be his domicile “which he
                    himself selects or describes or deems to be his home, or which appears to be the
                    centre of his affairs, or where he votes or exercises the rights and duties of a
                    citizen.” An unmarried man’s domicile is where he transacts his business or
                    exercises municipal duties or privileges. Compulsory detention will not create a
                    domicile. A domicile once established remains until a new one has been
                    acquired;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Some Roman
                    jurists, however, maintained that a man might be without any domicile at all, as
                    for example when he has definitely abandoned his old domicile, and is travelling
                    in search of a new abode. It is said that, when a domicile different from that
                    of birth has been acquired and is abandoned, the domicile of birth reverts the
                    moment the other is given up. “The native domicile easily reverts.”</p></note>
                    but ambassadors resident in a foreign country retain their domicile of
                    nationality.</p>
                <p>To these general rules may be added some of the principles laid down in recent
                    cases by the English courts. The distinction between the question of domicile
                    and that of naturalization or allegiance is clearly pointed out in Haldane <hi
                    rend="italic">υ.</hi> Eckford <hi rend="italic">(Law Reports,</hi> 8 Equity,
                    631) where it is said that to effect a change of domicile it is not necessary
                    that a man should do all in his power to divest himself of his original
                    nationality <hi rend="italic">(exuere patriam),</hi> it being sufficient that
                    there should be a change of residence of a permanent character voluntarily
                    assumed. And in Udny <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> Udny <hi rend="italic">(Law
                    Reports,</hi> 1 House of Lords, Scotch Appeals) Lord Westbury said: “To suppose
                    that for a change of domicile there must be a change of natural allegiance is to
                    confound the political and civil status, to destroy the distinction between <hi
                    rend="italic">patria</hi> and <hi rend="italic">domicilium.”</hi> So the lord
                    chancellor: “A man may change his domicile as often as he pleases, but not his
                    allegiance.” In the British empire, composed as it is of communities having each
                    its own system of law, there may be numberless domiciles under one allegiance.
                    In the first of the cases above mentioned the question was as to the domicile of
                    a testator, whose domicile of origin was Scotch, who was a servant of the East
                    India Company for thirty-three years, and who on leaving India went to Jersey,
                    where he lived continuously for twenty-five years till his death. The Scotch
                    domicile reverted on his leaving India, but was held to have been lost by the
                    residence in Jersey, where a new domicile was acquired. This is a fair sample of
                    the cases which frequently arise in British courts on the question of domicile.
                    In the second of the cases mentioned above it was held to be “a settled
                    principle that no man shall be without a domicile, and to secure this end the
                    law attributes to every individual as soon as he is born the domicile of his
                    father, if the child be legitimate, and the domicile of his mother, if the child
                    be illegitimate. This is called the domicile of origin, and is involuntary. It
                    is the creation of the law, not of the party. It may be extinguished by act of
                    law, as for example by sentence of death or exile for life, which destroys the
                    <hi rend="italic">status</hi><hi rend="italic">civilis</hi> of the criminal; but
                    it cannot be destroyed by the will and act of the party. Domicile of <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n369/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0369-0352"/> choice is the creation of the party. When a
                    domicile of choice is acquired, the domicile of origin is in abeyance, but is
                    not absolutely extinguished or obliterated. When a domicile of choice is
                    abandoned, the domicile of origin revives, a special intention to revert to it
                    not being necessary. A natural-born Englishman may domicile himself in Holland,
                    but if he breaks up his establishment there and quits Holland, declaring that he
                    will never return, it is absurd to suppose that his Dutch domicile clings to him
                    until he has set up his tabernacle elsewhere.”— <hi rend="italic">Per</hi> Lord
                    Westbury. These extracts, it will be seen, state even more strongly than the
                    corresponding rule adopted by Story the position that the original domicile
                    differs from an acquired domicile, in being suspended rather than destroyed by
                    the acquisition of a new domicile. One of the law lords in Udny <hi
                    rend="italic">V.</hi> Udny even finds fault with Story’s use of the phrase “to
                    reacquire a native domicile.” The native domicile is not reacquired but restored
                    <hi rend="italic">ipso facto</hi> by the abandonment of the acquired
                    domicile.</p>
                <p>The intention necessary to effect a change of domicile may be illustrated by the
                    following cases. In the case of Douglas <hi rend="italic">V.</hi> Douglas (12
                    Equity, 617), R , son of a domiciled</p>
                <p>Scotchman, entered the Home Office, London, in 1792, remained till 1802,
                    thereafter having married an English lady, lived in England in hired houses, and
                    finally settled in Scotland and died there. It was held that he had not lost his
                    domicile of origin. The testator in the case, the son of R , was born in London
                    in 1803 during a visit of his parents to London, lived from the age of thirteen
                    with his parents in Scotland, paying occasional visits to England till his
                    mother’s death in 1857, after which he let his family estate in Scotland, and
                    lived chiefly in England in hired houses. It was held that his domicile was
                    Scotch. The intention required to create a new domicile is an intention to
                    settle in a new country as a permanent home, and this is sufficient without any
                    intention to change civil status. In another case (Brunel <hi rend="italic"
                    >v.</hi> Brunel, 12 <hi rend="italic">Equity,</hi> 298), where a French subject
                    had established himself in business in England, and resided there continuously
                    for thirty years, making only occasional visits to France, but had refused to
                    take out letters of naturalization on the ground that he might return to France,
                    and would not give up his status as a French citizen, it was held,
                    notwithstanding, that he had lost his domicile of origin, and had acquired an
                    English domicile.</p>
                <p>The effect of domicile on the rights and duties of parties is even more difficult
                    to state. Continental jurists draw a distinction between personal and real
                    laws,—the former being supposed to fix the legal character of the person and
                    accompany him wherever he may be, the latter dealing with things only. In
                    matters covered by the former, therefore, the domicile prevails; while things
                    are governed by the law of the place in which they are. If the distinction were
                    maintainable it would still be of little use in fixing the extent of the
                    operations of the law of domicile, because one large class of real laws, that
                    dealing with movables, is universally admitted to be governed by domicile; while
                    a large but undefined class of personal laws would certainly not be acted on by
                    foreign states, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> where the law of domicile fixes
                    with incapacity persons professing a religion contrary to that established by
                    the state. There is no uniformity of practice or opinion on this point in modern
                    jurisprudence. Story considers the following to be the best established
                    principles in England and America on the point of personal capacity or status
                    :—</p>
                <p>1. The capacity, state, and condition of persons according to the law of their
                    domicile, will generally be regarded as to acts done, rights acquired, and
                    contracts made in the place of their domicile touching property situate therein.
                    If valid or invalid there, they will be valid or invalid everywhere. 2. As to
                    acts done, &amp;c., in other countries touching the property therein, the law of
                    such countries, as to capacity, Ac., and not the law of domicile, will generally
                    prevail. Thus ‘ * in questions of minority or majority’ com - petency to marry,
                    incapacities incident to coverture, guardianship, emancipation, and other
                    personal qualities and disabilities,” the <hi rend="italic">lex loci contractus
                    aut actus,</hi> and not the <hi rend="italic">lex domicilii</hi> ought to
                    prevail, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> if a person over 21 but under 25 years of
                    age has his domicile in a country which fixes majority at 25, he may make
                    generally a valid contract, even of marriage, in a country which fixes majority
                    at 21. 3. Personal disqualifications not arising from the law of nature,
                    especially such as are penal, as disqualifications for heresy, popish recusancy,
                    &amp;c., are not enforced in any other country. The refusal of non-slaveholding
                    States to recognise the status of slavery is an example.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>When the foreign law which would otherwise
                    operate as <hi rend="italic">ka domicilii</hi> is repugnant to the moral
                    principles of the country in which it is sought to be enforced, the <hi
                    rend="italic">lex domicilii</hi> would not be allowed to prevail.</p></note> 4.
                    Questions of legitimacy are generally to be decided by the law of the place
                    where the marriage was celebrated. When issue bom before marriage may by the law
                    of the country of their birth be legitimated by the subsequent marriage of the
                    parents, such legitimacy would be recognized in other countries. (But see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Bastard</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Marriage).</hi></p>
                <p>The operation of the law of domicile is most free from doubt in questions
                    touching personal or movable property. Real property is governed by the <hi
                    rend="italic">lex loci;</hi> but personal property has in law no locality. On
                    this point English law is now substantially in harmony with Continental
                    jurisprudence. The principle that personal property is subject to the law of the
                    owner’s domicile is fully recognized in the distribution of the estate of a
                    person deceased, whether with or without a will. The capacity of a person to
                    make a will, the validity of the will, and its effect, are to be determined by
                    the law of his actual domicile in the case of movable property. In the case of
                    real property, on the other hand, these questions must be decided by the law of
                    the country in which it is situated. It was doubted by Story whether a will
                    valid according to testator’s domicile at the time of its execution would be
                    affected by a subsequent change of domicile. A recent case (Lynch <hi
                    rend="italic">v.</hi> Government of Paraguay) decided that personal property in
                    England is governed by the law of testator’s domicile at the time of his death.
                    In this case the testator, a domiciled Paraguayan, died leaving personal
                    property in England; and between his death and the application for probate a
                    decree of the Government of Paraguay declared that all the property of the
                    deceased, wherever situated, was the property of the state of Paraguay. The
                    court, nevertheless, held that the property in England must be governed by the
                    law of Paraguay as at the time of the death (2 Probate and Matrimonial Cases,
                    268). So in cases of intestate succession, the law of the actual domicile of the
                    intestate at the time of his death governs his personal property every where.
                    The persons entitled, the proportions in which they are to take, &amp;c., must
                    be settled by the law of the domicile, however different that may be from the
                    law of the country in which the goods are.</p>
                <p>The following statutes relating to the effect of domicile on wills were passed in
                    1861 :—</p>
                <p>24 and 25 Vict. c. 114. Wills made out of the United Kingdom by British subjects
                    (whatever may be the domicile of such person at the time of making the same or
                    at the time of death) shall, as regards personal estate be held to be well
                    executed, if the same be made according to (1), the forms required by the law of
                    the place where the same were made, or (2), the place where such person was
                    domiciled when the same were made, or (3), by the laws in force in that part of
                    her Majesty’s dominion where he had his domicileof origin. Willsmade byany
                    British subject (whatevermay be his domicile) shall, as regards personal estate,
                    be well executed if they are according to the forms then required in that part
                    of the United Kingdom in which they are made. No will or other testamentary
                    disposition shall be held to be revoked or become valid, nor shall the
                    construction thereof be altered by reason of any subsequent change of
                    domicile.</p>
                <p>24 and 25 Vict. c. 121 recites that by the operation of the law of domicile the
                    expectation and belief of British subjects dying abroad with regard to the
                    distribution of their property are often defeated, and enacts that when a
                    convention has been made between <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n370/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0370-0353"/> Her Majesty and any foreign country, it may be
                    declared and shall be enacted that no British subject dying in such, country
                    shall be deemed to have acquired a domicile therein, unless he has been resident
                    in such country for one year previous to death, and has made a declaration in
                    writing of his intention to become domiciled; and British subjects so dying
                    without having so resided and made such declaration shall be deemed for all
                    purposes of testate or intestate succession as to movables to retain the
                    domicile he possessed at the time of going to reside in such foreign country.
                    Similar exemptions are conferred on the subjects of the foreign state dying in
                    Great Britain or Ireland. But the Act does not apply to foreigners who have
                    obtained letters of naturalization in any part of Her Majesty’s dominions. (E.
                    K. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
