<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0499-0480-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DRUMMOND, William (9th edition, volume 7, page
                    480)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126608">Sonnet</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126610">Sonnets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55t8q">Sonnets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m902637">Barns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n499/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DRUMMOND, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>
                    (1585-1649), of Hawthornden, a Scottish poet of the Spenserian school, and
                    descendant of an old family of noble blood, was born at Hawthornden, near
                    Edinburgh, on the 13th December 1585. His father, John Drummond, was the first
                    laird of Hawthornden; and his mother, Susannah Fowler, was well-connected, her
                    brother William being private secretary to Queen Anne, and a man of literary
                    tastes. Drummond received his early education at the Edinburgh High School, and
                    graduated as M.A. of the recently founded (1582) metropolitan university in July
                    1605. The years 1607 and 1608 were spent at Bourges and Paris in the study of
                    law; and, in 1609, Drummond was again in Scotland, where, by the death of his
                    father in the following year, he became laird of Hawthornden at the early age of
                    twenty-four. The list of books he read up to this time indicates a strong
                    preference for the finer and more imaginative, as distinguished from the
                    argumentative kinds of literature. Accordingly, on finding himself his own
                    master, Drummond naturally abandoned law for the muses; “for,” says his
                    biographer in 1711, “the delicacy of his wit always run on the pleasantness and
                    usefulness of history, and on the fame and softness of poetry.” He was a good
                    linguist, and read Latin, Greek, Italian, Spanish, French, and Hebrew. He had
                    already written several poems, chiefly sonnets; and some early letters, which
                    have been preserved, show a fine command of pure English, as well as Drummond’s
                    critical sagacity in abandoning the Scottish dialect for the language raised to
                    literary supremacy by the illustrious Elizabethans. Drummond’s first publication
                    appeared in 1613, and was an elegy on the death of Henry, prince of Wales,
                    called <hi rend="italic">Teares on the Death of Mοeliades.</hi> As might have
                    been expected from Spenser’s influence, it is pastoral throughout. Milton, in
                    his Lycidas, has at once imitated and surpassed this early poem of Drummond’s.
                    In 1614 Drummond for the first time met Sir William Alexander, known later as
                    earl of Stirling, the author of a ponderous poem on <hi rend="italic"
                    >Doom's-day.</hi> In the following year Drummond sustained a dreadful blow in
                    the death of Miss Cunningham of Barns, to whom he was engaged to be married. In
                    1616, the year of Shakespeare’s death, appeared <hi rend="italic">Poems:
                    Amorous,</hi><hi rend="italic">Funerali,</hi><hi rend="italic">Divine,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Pastorali</hi><hi rend="italic">: in Sonnets, Songs, Sextains,
                    Madrigals,</hi> being substantially the story of his love and loss. Drummond’s
                    next poem is entitled <hi rend="italic">Forth Feasting: A Panegyric to the
                    King's Most Excellent Majesty,</hi> and celebrates James’s visit to Scotland in
                    1617. In 1618 there was an interesting correspondence between Drummond and
                    Drayton; and, about the close of the same year, or about the beginning of 1619,
                    Drummond was honoured with a visit of a fortnight or more from the great
                    literary dictator of the time—Ben Jonson. Drummond, as tradition relates, sat
                    awaiting Jonson’s arrival under the shade of a fine sycamore, and exclaimed when
                    Jonson came iu sight, “Welcome, welcome, royal Ben !” Upon which the dramatist
                    rejoined, “Thank ye, thank ye, Hawthornden.” The famous account of their
                    conversations, long supposed to be lost, was discovered in the Advocate’s
                    Library, Edinburgh, by Mr David Laing, and, after being read to the Society of
                    Scottish Antiquaries in 1832, appeared, ten years later, as a publication of the
                    Shakespeare Society. The conversations are full of interesting literary gossip,
                    and embody Ben’s opinion of himself and of his host, whom he frankly told that
                    he “was too good and simple, and that oft a man’s modesty made a fool of his
                    wit.” <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n500/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0500-0481"/> The next few years in Drummond’s life are
                    comparatively uneventful, being marked only by correspondence with Sir William
                    Alexander and Drayton. In 1623, the year of a great famine and consequent
                    mortality in Scotland, appeared the poet’s fourth publication, entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Flowers of Zion: By William Drummond of Hawthornedenne: to which
                    is adjoyned his C</hi><hi rend="italic">ypresse</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Grove.</hi> From 1625 till 1630 Drummond was probably for the most part engaged
                    in travelling on the Continent. In 1627, however, he seems to have been home for
                    a short time, as, in that year, he appears in the entirely new character of the
                    holder of a patent for the construction of military machines, entitled “Litera
                    Magistri Gulielmi Drummond de Fabrica Machinarum Militarium, Anno 1627.” ’ Γhe
                    same year, 1627, is the date of Drummond’s munificent gift of about 500 volumes
                    to the library of Edinburgh University. This collection, to which Drummond
                    afterwards made additions, is kept in a separate cabinet, and is particularly
                    rich in the English poets. In 1630 Drummond again began to reside permanently at
                    Hawthornden; and, in 1631, he received his last letter from Drayton, who died in
                    London on the 23d of December. In 1632 Drummond married Elizabeth Logan, by whom
                    he had five sons and four daughters. In 1633 Charles made his coronationvisit to
                    Scotland; and Drummond’s pen was employed in writing congratulatory speeches and
                    poetry. As Drummond naturally preferred Episcopacy to Presbytery, we are not
                    surprised to learn that he approved of the main object Charles had in view in
                    this visit, although his peace-loving nature was averse to the means employed in
                    establishing Episcopacy. Drummond was a true Scottish gentleman in his pride of
                    blood. Partly to please the earl of Perth, and partly to satisfy his own
                    curiosity, the poet had studied the genealogy of the family very carefully, and
                    had given due prominence to the fact that Annabella Drummond, daughter of Sir
                    John Drummond of Stobhall, was the queen of Robert III. This investigation was
                    the real secret of Drummond’s interest in Scottish history; and so we find that
                    he now began his <hi rend="italic">History of the Lives and Reigns of the Five
                    Jameses, Kings of Scotland—</hi> a work which did not appear till 1655, and is
                    remarkable only for its good, literary style. His next work was called forth by
                    the king’s enforced submission to the opposition of his Scottish subjects. It is
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Irene: or a Remonstrancefor Concord, Amity, and Love
                    amongst His Majesty's Subjects,</hi> and embodies Drummond’s political creed of
                    submission to authority as the only logical refuge from democracy, which he
                    hated. In 1639 Drummond had to sign the Covenant in self-protection, but was
                    uneasy under the burden, as existing squibs by him testify. Drummond’s next work
                    <hi rend="italic">⅜κLα.pαχι.α.: or a Defence of a Petition tendered to the Lords
                    of the Council of Scotland by certain Noblemen and Gentlemen,</hi> January,
                    1643, is a political pamphlet in support of those royalists in Scotland who
                    wished to espouse the king’s cause against the English Parliament. Its burden is
                    a passionate invective on the intolerance of the then dominant Presbyterian
                    clergy; but <hi rend="italic">Irene</hi> fails to do justice to the substantial
                    work they had done. Drummond’s subsequent works may be described briefly as
                    royalist pamphlets, written with more or less caution, as the times
                    required.</p>
                <p>After being an invalid for several months., the poet died on the 4th December
                    1649, and was buried in the churchyard of Lasswade, a neighbouring village.</p>
                <p>The only works of Drummond which call for special notice are the <hi
                    rend="italic">Cypresse Grove</hi> and the poems. The <hi rend="italic">Cypresse
                    Grove,</hi> one of the noblest prose poems in literature, exhibits great wealth
                    of illustration, much fine thinking, and an extraordinary command of musical
                    English. It is an essay on the folly of the fear of death, and shows how much
                    the author was impressed with the comparative insignificance of this world.
                    “This globe of the earth,” says he, “which seemeth huge to us, in respect of the
                    universe, and compared with that wide pavilion of heaven, is less than little,
                    of no sensible quantity, and but as a point” (1711 edition, p. 123). Death, he
                    argues, from many of its accidental associations, appears to be much more
                    dreadful than it really is. Its universality, and a correct estimate of human
                    life, ought to nerve us against the fear of death. Further, we should remember
                    that death is not annihilation, but the vestibule to immortality and a higher
                    life. The essay, which is composed throughout in a strain of lofty idealism, is
                    concluded in the form of a vision.</p>
                <p>A noteworthy feature in Drummond’s poetry is that it manifests no characteristic
                    Scottish element, but owes its birth and inspiration rather to the English and
                    Italian masters. This was owing partly to his anti-Presbyterian bias and his
                    long residence abroad; but it was also natural, on other grounds, for a quiet,
                    cultured, and meditative poet to imitate the Elizabethans and the great Italian
                    writers. Drummond was essentially a follower of Spenser, delighting in the
                    description of outer nature; but, amid all his sensuousness, and even in those
                    lines most conspicuously laden with lustrous beauty, there is a dash of
                    melancholy thoughtfulness—a tendency deepened by the death of his first
                    love.</p>
                <p>Drummond λvas so successful as a writer of sonnets that he was called “the
                    Scottish Petrarch ;” and his sonnets are still ranked immediately after
                    Shakespeare’s, Milton’s, and Wordsworth’s. Most of his poems are steeped in the
                    pre-Copemican ideas of astronomy, and are marked by a sense of the smallness of
                    the visible in comparison with the infinite lying beyond. This is one of
                    Drummond’s favourite moods; and he is constantly harping upon such phrases aβ
                    “the All,” “this great All.” Even in such of his poems as may be called more
                    distinctively Christian, thiβ philosophic conception is at work. Drummond’s
                    poems are distinguished by pensive beauty, sweetness of versification, and
                    richly worded descriptions, but lack vigour and originality. Altogether this
                    poet is to be remembered as the best representative of “sweetness and light”
                    amid much that was dull and ephemeral in contemporary Scottish literature.</p>
                <p>There are several editions of his works :—(1) Hall’s edition of the prose works,
                    published in 1655; (2) Phillips’s (a nephew of Milton) edition of the poems,
                    which appeared in the same year; (3) Bishop Sage’s, published in 1711, the only
                    complete edition of Drummond’s writings; (4) an edition of his poems by Lord
                    Dundrennan and David Irving, issued in 1832; (5) Cunningham’s edition of the
                    poems of 1833; and (6) Turnbull’s in 1857. The only collected edition of the
                    prose writings was published in 1711. Drummond's life has been ably written by
                    Professor Masson (1873). (T. GI.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
