<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0830-0807-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PROMETHEUS (9th edition, volume 19, page 807)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd23">Heroes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hz60">Maoris</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925173">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:955558">Heroes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821510">Australians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821509">Australianisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1938968">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:818281">Aryanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205049">Victoria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n830/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PROMETHEUS</label>, son of the Titan Iapetus by the sea nymph
                    Clymene, is the chief “culture hero,” and, in some accounts, the Demiurge of
                    Greek mythical legend. As a culture-hero or inventor and teacher of the arts of
                    life, he belongs to a wide and well-known category of imaginary beings. Thus
                    Qat, Quahteaht, Pundjel, Maui, Ioskeha, Cagn, Wainamoinen, and an endless array
                    of others represent the ideal and heroic first teachers of Melanesians, Ahts,
                    Australians, Maoris, Algonquins, Bushmen, and Finns. Among the lowest races the
                    culture-hero commonly wears a bestial guise, is a spider (Melanesia), an eagle
                    hawk (Australia), a coyote (north-west America), a dog or raven (Thlinkeet), a
                    mantis insect (Bushman), and so forth, yet is endowed with human or even
                    superhuman qualities, and often shades off into a permanent and practically
                    deathless god. Prometheus, on the other hand, is purely anthropomorphic. He is
                    the friend and benefactor of mankind. He defends them against Zeus, who, in
                    accordance with a widely diffused mythical theory, desires to destroy the human
                    race and supplant them with a new and better species, or who simply revenges a
                    trick in which men get the better of him. The pedigree and early exploits of
                    Prometheus are given by Hesiod <hi rend="italic">(Theog.,</hi> 510-616). On a
                    certain occasion gods and men met at Mecone. The business of the assembly was to
                    decide what portions of slain animals the gods should receive in sacrifice. On
                    one side Prometheus arranged the best parts of the ox covered with offal, on the
                    other the bones covered with fat. Zeus was invited to make his choice, chose the
                    fat, and found only bones beneath. A similar fable of an original choice, in
                    which the chooser is beguiled by appearances, recurs in Africa and North
                    America. The native tribes adapt it to explain the different modes of life among
                    themselves and white men. In wrath at this trick, according to Hesiod, or in
                    other versions for the purpose of exterminating the remnants of people who
                    escaped the deluge of Deucalion, Zeus never bestowed, or later withdrew, the
                    gift of fire. In his “philanthropic fashion,” Prometheus stole fire, concealed
                    in a hollow fennel stalk (Hesiod, <hi rend="italic">Op.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >et</hi><hi rend="italic">Di.),</hi> and a fennel stalk is still used in the
                    Greek islands as a means of carrying a light <hi rend="italic">(cf.</hi> Pliny,
                    xiii. 22). According to some legends he gained the fire by holding a rod close
                    to the sun. Probably the hollow fennel stalk in which fire was carried got its
                    place in myth from the very fact of its common use.</p>
                <p>We thus find Prometheus in the position of the fire-bringer, or fire-stealer, and
                    so connected with a very wide cycle of similar mythical benefactors. Among the
                    Murri of Gippsland, to begin with a backward people, the fire-stealer was a man,
                    but he became a bird. <hi rend="italic">Tow-e-ra,</hi> or fire, was in the
                    possession of two women who hated the blacks. A man who loved men cajoled the
                    women, stole fire when their backs were turned, and was metamorphosed into “a
                    little bird with a red mark on its tail, which is the mark of fire.” The
                    fire-bringer in Brittany is the golden or fire-crested wren. Myths like this
                    kill two birds with one stone, and at once account for the possession of fire by
                    men and for the marking of certain animals regarded as fire-bringers.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For these see Brough Smith,
                    <hi rend="italic">Aborigines of Victoria</hi>; Kuhn, on bird fire-bringer in
                    Isle of Man, <hi rend="italic">Die Herabkunft des Feuers,</hi> p.
                    109.</p></note> In another Australian legend fire was stolen by the hawk from
                    the bandicoot, and given to men. In yet another a man held his spear to the sun,
                    and so got a light. A bird is fire-bringer in an Andaman island tale, and a
                    ghost in another myth of the same island.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Joum. Anthrop. Inst.,</hi> Nov.
                    1884.</p></note> In New Zealand, Maui stole fire from Mauika, the lord of fire.
                    He used a bird’s intervention. Among the Ahts, in North America,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Sproat, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Savage Life.</hi></p></note> fire was stolen by animals from the cuttle-fish.
                    Among the Thlinkeets, Yehl, the raven-god, was the fire-stealer. Among the
                    Cahrocs, the coyote steals fire from “two old women.” Among the Aryans of India,
                    Soma is stolen by birds, as water is among the Thlinkeets, and mead in the
                    Edda.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Bancroft, iii. 100
                    <hi rend="italic">; Aitareya Brahmana,</hi> ii. 93, 203; Kuhn, <hi rend="italic"
                    >op. cit.,</hi> 144. <hi rend="subscript"> j</hi></p></note> Fire concealed
                    himself, in the Veda, was dragged from his hiding place by Matariçvan, and was
                    given to the priestly clan of Bhrigu. We also hear that Matariçvan “brought fire
                    from afar” <hi rend="italic">(R.</hi><hi rend="italic">V.</hi>, iii. 9, 5), and
                    that Bhrigu found fire lurking in the water (A. U., x. 46, 2).<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Compare Bergaighe, <hi
                    rend="italic">La Religion</hi><hi rend="italic">Védique,</hi> i. 52-56, and
                    Kuhn’s <hi rend="italic">Herabkunft</hi>; and see the essays by Steinthal in
                    appendix to English version of Goldziher’s <hi rend="italic">Mythology among the
                    Hebrews.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>In considering the whole question, one must beware of the hasty analogical method
                    of reasoning too common among mythologista. For example, when a bird is spoken
                    of as the fire-bringer we need not necessarily conclude that, in each case, the
                    bird means lightning. On the other hand, the myth often exists to explain the
                    cause of the markings of certain actual species of birds. Again, because a hero
                    is said to have stolen or brought fire, we need not regard that hero as the
                    personification of fire, and explain all his myth as a fire-myth. The legend of
                    Prometheus has too often been treated in this fashion, though he is really a
                    culture hero, of whose exploits, such as making <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n831/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0831-0808"/> men of clay, fire-stealing is no more than a
                    single example. This tendency to evolve the whole myth of Prometheus from a
                    belief that he is personified fire, or the fire-god, has been intensified by
                    Kuhn’s ingenious and plausible etymology of the name <hi rend="italic"
                    >∏poμηθev&lt;&gt;.</hi> The Greeks derived it from <hi rend="italic"
                    >ιrpoμ∙ηθη&lt;i,</hi> “provident,” and connected it with such other words as <hi
                    rend="italic">τrpoμηθioμaL,</hi><hi rend="italic">προμηθέα.</hi> They had also
                    the proper name <hi rend="italic                     superscript"> ,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">EπLμηθeυ&lt;s</hi> for the slow-witted brother of Prometheus who
                    turned all the hero’s wisdom to foolishness. Against these very natural
                    etymologies the philologists support a theory that Prometheus is really a Greek
                    form of <hi rend="italic">pramantha</hi> (Skt.), the fire-stick of the Hindus.
                    The process of etymological change, as given by Steinthal, was this. The boring
                    of the perpendicular in the horizontal fire-stick, whereby fire was kindled, was
                    called <hi rend="italic">manthana,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">math,</hi> “I
                    shake.” The preposition <hi rend="italic">pra</hi> was prefixed, and you get <hi
                    rend="italic">pramantha.</hi> But Matariçvan was feigned to have brought Agni,
                    fire, and “the fetching of the god was designated by the same verb <hi
                    rend="italic">mathnâmi</hi> as the proper earthly boring” of the firestick. “Now
                    this verb, especially when compounded with the preposition <hi rend="italic"
                    >pra,</hi> gained the signification to tear off, snatch to oneself, rob.”<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Cf.</hi>
                    Kuhn, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> pp. 16, 17.</p></note> Steinthal goes
                    on—“Thus the fetching of Agni became a robbery of the fire, and the <hi
                    rend="italic">pramâtha</hi> (fire-stick) a robber. The gods had intended, for
                    some reason or other, to withhold fire from men; a benefactor of mankind stole
                    it from the gods. This robbery was called <hi rend="italic">pramâtha</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">; pramathyu-s</hi> is ‘ he who loves boring or robbery, a borer or
                    robber.’ From the latter words, according to the peculiarities of Greek
                    phonology, is formed <hi rend="italic">Hpoμηθev-&lt;s,</hi> Prometheus. He is
                    therefore a firegod,” &lt;fcc. Few things more ingenious than this have ever
                    been done by philologists. It will be observed that “forgetfulness of the
                    meaning of words” is made to account for the Greek belief that fire was <hi
                    rend="italic">stolen</hi> from the gods. To recapitulate the doctrine more
                    succinctly, men originally said, in Sanskrit (or some Aryan speech more ancient
                    still), “fire is got by rubbing or boring nothing could have been more
                    scientific and straightforward. They also said, “fire is brought by Matariçvan
                    nothing can be more in accordance with the mythopoeic mode of thought. Then the
                    word which means <hi rend="superscript"> u</hi> fetched” is confused with the
                    word which means “bored,” and gains the sense of “robbed.” Lastly, fire is said
                    (owing to this confusion) to have been stolen, and the term which meant the
                    common savage fire-stick is by a process of delusion conceived to represent, not
                    a stick, but a person, Prometheus, who stole fire. Thus then, according to the
                    philologists, arose the myth that fire was stolen, a myth which, we presume,
                    would not otherwise have occurred to Greeks. Now we have not to decide whether
                    the Greeks were right in thinking that Prometheus only meant “the fore-sighted
                    wise man,” or whether the Germans know better, and are correct when they say the
                    name merely meant “fire-stick.” But we may, at least, point out that the myth of
                    the stealing of fire and of the fire-stealer is current among races who are not
                    Aryan, and never heard the word <hi rend="italic">pramantha.</hi> We have shown
                    that Thlinkeets, Ahts, Andaman Islanders, Australians, Maoris, South Sea
                    Islanders, Cahrocs, and others all believe fire was originally stolen. Is it
                    credible that, in all their languages, the name of the fire-stick should have
                    caused a confusion of thought which ultimately led to the belief that fire was
                    obtained originally by larceny? If such a coincidence appears incredible, we may
                    doubt whether the belief that is common to Greeks and Cahrocs and Ahts was
                    produced, in Greek minds by an etymological confusion, in Australia, America,
                    and so forth by some other cause. What, then, is the origin of the
                    widely-diffused myth that fire was stolen? We offer a purely conjectural
                    suggestion. No race is found without fire, but certain races<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Tγlor, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Early History of Man.</hi></p></note> are said to have no means of artificially
                    reproducing fire; whether this be true or not, certainly even some civilized
                    races have found the artificial reproduction of fire very tedious. Thus we read
                    <hi rend="italic">(Od.,</hi> v. 488-493), “As when a man hath hidden away a
                    brand in the black embers at an upland farm, one that hath no neighbour nigh,
                    and so saveth the seed of fire that he may not have to seek a light otherwhere,
                    even so did Odysseus cover him with the leaves.” If, in the Homeric age, men
                    found it so hard to get the seed of fire, what must the difficulty have been in
                    the earliest dawn of the art of fire-making? Suppose, then, that the human
                    groups of early savages are hostile. One group lets its fire go out, the next
                    thing to do would be to borrow a light from the neighbour, perhaps several miles
                    off. But, if the neighbours are hostile, the unlucky group is cut off from fire,
                    <hi rend="italic">igni interdicitur.</hi> The only way to get fire in such a
                    case is to steal it. Men accustomed to such a precarious condition might readily
                    believe that the first possessors of fire, wherever they were, set a high value
                    on it, and refused to communicate it to others. Hence the belief that fire was
                    originally stolen. This hypothesis at least explains all myths of fire-stealing
                    by the natural needs, passions, and characters of men, “a jealous race,” whereas
                    the philological theory explains the Greek myth by an exceptional accident of
                    changing language, and leaves the other widely diffused myths of fire-stealing
                    in the dark. It would occupy too much space to discuss, in the ethnological
                    method, the rest of the legend of Prometheus. Like the Australian Pundjel, and
                    the Maori Tiki, he made men of clay. He it was who, when Zeus had changed his
                    wife into a fly, and swallowed her, broke open the god’s head and let out his
                    daughter Athene. He aided Zeus in the struggle with the Titans. He was punished
                    by him on some desolate hill (usually styled Caucasus) for fire-stealing, and
                    was finally released by Heracles.</p>
                <p>His career may be studied in Hesiod, in the splendid <hi rend="italic"
                    >Prometheus</hi><hi rend="italic">Vinctus</hi> of Aeschylus, with the <hi
                    rend="italic">scholia,</hi> in Heyne’s <hi rend="italic">Apollodorus,</hi> in
                    the excursus (1) of Schiizius to the Aeschylean drama, and in the frequently
                    quoted work of Kuhn. The essay of Steinthal may also be examined (Goldziher, <hi
                    rend="italic">Myth. Hebr.,</hi> Engl, transi., p. 363-392), where the amused
                    student will discover that “Moses is a Pra-manthas,” with much else that is
                    learned and convincing. See also Mr Tylor’s <hi rend="italic">Early History of
                    Man</hi>; Mr Nesfield in <hi rend="italic">Calcutta Review,</hi> January, April,
                    1884; and above, art. <hi rend="smallcaps">Fire,</hi> vol. ix. p. 227 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.</hi> (A. L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
