<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0472-0453-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PONIATOWSKI (9th edition, volume 19, page 453)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1010769">Marshals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1006241">Majorities</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1069177">Polishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1227863">Lithuania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xp4n">Polishes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n472/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PONIATOWSKI</label>, a family of Poland, the earliest member
                    of which to acquire high distinction was <hi rend="smallcaps">Stanislaus
                    Ciolek</hi> (1677-1762), regarding whose descent there are conflicting
                    accounts,—some tracing it to the Lombard Counts Torelli, one of whom in the
                    seventeenth century married a daughter of Albert of Poniatow, and added the name
                    of Poniatowski to his own, which he changed to its equivalent in Polish, Ciolek,
                    while others affirm that the name Poniatowski was adopted by one of two brothers
                    from an estate which fell to his share, while it is also asserted that
                    Stanislaus Ciolek was the natural son of Prince Sapieha, and was adopted by a
                    Polish nobleman named Poniatowski (see Szymanowski, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Poniatowski,</hi> Geneva, 1880). In any case he had
                    sufficient influence and ability to insure his rapid promotion in the army of
                    Charles XII., and as major-general at the battle of Poltava in 1709 was able by
                    his self-command in facilitating the passage of the Dnieper to save the
                    retreating army. In 1711 he was sent on a special embassy to Constantinople,
                    when he succeeded in obtaining from the sultan a promise to send an army to aid
                    Charles in the war with Russia; but on account of a change in the office of
                    grand vizier the promise was never carried out. All possibility of undertaking a
                    Russian invasion being therefore at an end, he was appointed by Charles governor
                    of the duchy of Zweibrücken. After the death of Charles, he gave his adhesion to
                    Augustus II., by whom he was in 1724 made grand treasurer of Lithuania, and in
                    1731 palatine of Mazovia. On the death of Augustus II. he sought to effect the
                    promotion of Stanislaus Leszczynski to the throne, but ultimately he gave in his
                    submission to Augustus III., and after holding under him several high offices
                    was in 1752 appointed castellan of Cracow. He was the author of <hi
                    rend="italic">Remarques</hi><hi rend="italic">dun Seigneur</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Polonais sur</hi><hi rend="italic">l</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Histoire de
                    Charles XII. par Voltaire,</hi> 1741, which was translated into English in the
                    same year. He died in 1762, leaving by his marriage with Constance Princess
                    Czartoryski four sons, the best known of whom was the second, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Stanislaus Augustus</hi> (1732-1798), king of Poland, born 17th
                    January 1732. Sent by Augustus III. to the court of Russia, he won the favour of
                    the grandduchess Catherine, who succeeded to the throne by the assassination of
                    her husband, 9th July 1762. Through her influence he was, 7th September 1764,
                    chosen king of Poland. For an account of his despicable and disastrous rule see
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Poland</hi> (pp. 297-8). After signing his abdication, 25th
                    November 1795, he took up his residence at St Petersburg, where he enjoyed a
                    pension of 200,000 ducats paid jointly by Austria, Russia, and Prussia. He died
                    unmarried, 12th February 1798 (see <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Secrets</hi><hi rend="italic">inédits</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Stanislas II. Auguste,</hi> Leipsic, 1867, and De Mouy, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Correspondance inédite de Roi Stanislas-Auguste et de Madame</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Geoff</hi><hi rend="italic">rin,</hi> Paris, 1875). Of the other
                    sons of Stanislaus Poniatowski, Casimir (1721-1800), the eldest, was grand
                    chamberlain of Poland and commander of the royal guard; Andrew (1735-1773)
                    became an Austrian field marshal; and Michael (1736-1794) was ultimately
                    promoted primate of Poland. <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph Anton</hi> (1762-1813),
                    prince and marshal of France, son of Andrew Poniatowski was born at Warsaw, 7th
                    May 1762. At the age of sixteen he entered the service of Austria. After the
                    resolution of the diet to reorganize the Polish army he was recalled and
                    obtained the rank of major-general. On the outbreak of hostilities with Russia
                    in 1792 he was made commander of the army defending central Poland. When the
                    king his uncle acceded to the confederation of Targovitza he resigned his
                    commission, but on the outbreak of the insurrection in 1794 he enrolled himself
                    as a volunteer under Kosciuszko, although Kosciuszko had previously held
                    inferior military rank to his own. In command of a division he had charge of the
                    defence of the northern side of Warsaw, and after its capitulation he went to
                    Vienna. In 1798 he returned to Warsaw, having obtained from the Prussians a
                    portion of his confiscated estates. On the arrival of Napoleon at Warsaw, 19th
                    December 1806, Poniatowski accepted his invitation to become general of a
                    national Polish army, which, fired by the hope of national independence,
                    gathered to the number of 27,000, to assist Napoleon in his Russian campaign.
                    After the peace of Tilsit, 7th July 1807, the duchy of Warsaw was created, and
                    Poniatowski became minister of war. On the invasion of the duchy in 1809 he
                    fought a desperate battle near the village of Raszyn, and, being permitted
                    afterwards to retreat across the Vistula, invaded Galicia and compelled the
                    Russians to evacuate Cracow. In Napoleon’s campaigns he held the command of the
                    Polish army corps, distinguishing himself at Smolensk, Borodino, and Leipsic,
                    where he took 1000 prisoners, and in token of his brilliant exploit was created
                    by Napoleon a marshal of France the same evening. He was employed in covering
                    the retreat from Leipsic, and while charging a column of Prussian infantry was
                    wounded by a ball in the shoulder. When the enemy obtained possession of the
                    suburbs he endeavoured to join the main army by plunging into the’ Elster, but
                    was fired upon and, enfeebled by wounds, was drowned, 19th October 1813. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi> (1816-1873), grandson of Casimir mentioned above,
                    was born 4th February 1816, at Rome. Entering the Tuscan service, he went in
                    1849 as minister of Tuscany to London. In 1850 he took up his residence in
                    Paris, and becoming a naturalized citizen was in 1854 chosen a member of the
                    French· senate. In 1870 he removed to London, where he supported himself by
                    teaching music. He was the composer of several operas. He died 3rd July
                    1873.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
