<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0537-0518-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PORCUPINE (9th edition, volume 19, page 518)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845200">Canadians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845196">Canadianisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1006948">Mammals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1129919">Spine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950358">Hair</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950030">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099527">Rodents</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj6q">Canadians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wn8t">Mammals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx3570p">Spines</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xd3v">Spine</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tq07">Hair</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn85">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1243192">Borneo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206102">Nepal</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n537/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PORCUPINE</label>. This word, derived from the French <hi
                    rend="italic">porc-épic,</hi> or “spiny pig,” is applied to the members of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Hystric(dae,</hi> a family of rodents whose most prominent
                    peculiarity is their covering of long stout spines, which form a highly
                    efficient protection against enemies, and which are better developed in this
                    family than in any other mammal. Zoologically the porcupines are allied to the
                    cavies, chinchillas, agoutis, &lt;kc., and with them form the great section <hi
                    rend="italic">Hystricomorpha</hi> or porcupine-like rodents (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Mammalia,</hi> vol. xv. p. 420).</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">IIystricidix</hi> are readily divisible into two
                    subfamilies according to their geographical distribution, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hystricina</hi> or True Porcupines being confined to the Old World, and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Synetherina</hi> to the New. The <hi rend="italic">Hystricina</hi>
                    are distinguished by their semi-rooted molars, imperfect collar-bones, cleft
                    upper lips, rudimentary pollices, smooth soles, six mammae, and by many
                    important cranial characters. They range over the south of Europe, the whole of
                    Africa, India, and the Malay Archipelago as far eastwards as Borneo. They are
                    all stout heavily-built animals, with blunt rounded heads, fleshy mobile snouts,
                    and coats of thick cylindrical or flattened spines, which form the whole
                    covering of their body, and are not intermingled with ordinary hairs. Their
                    habits are strictly terrestrial. Of the three genera in this section, the first
                    and best-known is <hi rend="italic">Hystrix,</hi> characterized by its curiously
                    inflated skull, in which the nasal chamber is often considerably larger than the
                    brain-case, and by its short tail, tipped with numerous slender stalked open
                    quills, which make a loud rattling noise whenever the animal moves. Its
                    longest-known member is the Common Porcupine (ZZ. <hi rend="italic"
                    >cristata),</hi> which occurs throughout the south of Europe and North and West
                    Africa, but is replaced in South Africa by <hi rend="italic">H. africae-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">australis,</hi> and in India by the Hairy-nosed Porcupine <hi
                    rend="italic">(H. leucura),</hi> whose habits are described in the following
                    notice extracted from Jerdon’s <hi rend="italic">Mammals of India.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">“</hi><hi rend="italic">Hystrix</hi><hi rend="italic">leucura</hi>
                    is found over a great part of India, from the lower ranges of the Himalayas to
                    the extreme south, but does not occur in lower Bengal, where it is replaced by
                    <hi rend="italic">H. bengalensis.</hi> It forms extensive burrows, often in
                    societies, in the sides of hills, banks of rivers and nullahs, and very often in
                    the bunds of tanks, and in old mud walls, &amp;c. &amp;c. In some parts of the
                    country they are very destructive to various crops, potatoes, carrots, and other
                    vegetables. They never issue forth till after dark, but now and then one will be
                    found returning to his lair in daylight Dogs take up the scent of the porcupine
                    very keenly, and on the Nilghiris I have killed many by the aid of dogs,
                    tracking them to their dens. They charge backwards at their foes, erecting their
                    spines at the same time, and dogs generally get seriously injured by their
                    strong spines, which are sometimes driven deeply into the assailant. The
                    porcupine is not bad eating,—the meat, which is white, tasting something between
                    pork and veal.”</p>
                <p>Besides the three large crested species of <hi rend="italic">Hystrix</hi>
                    above-mentioned, there are some four or five smaller species without nuchal
                    crests occurring in north-east India and in the Malay region, from Nepal to
                    Borneo. The second genus of Old-World porcupines is <hi rend="italic"
                    >Atherura,</hi> the Brushtailed Porcupines, much smaller animals than the last,
                    with long tails tipped with bundles of peculiar flattened spines. Of the three
                    species two are found in the Malay region and one in West Africa. <hi
                    rend="italic">Trichys,</hi> the last genus, contains but one Bornean species,
                    <hi rend="italic">T. lipura,</hi> externally very like an <hi rend="italic"
                    >Atherura,</hi> but differing from the members of that genus in many important
                    cranial characteristics.</p>
                <p>The New-World porcupines, the <hi rend="italic">Synetherina,</hi> have rooted
                    molars, complete collar-bones, uncleft upper lips, tuberculated soles, no trace
                    of a pollex, and four mammae only. Their spines are to a great extent mixed with
                    long soft hairs; they are less strictly nocturnal in their habits; and, with one
                    exception, they live entirely in trees, having in correspondence with this long
                    and powerful prehensile tails. They consist of three genera, of which the first
                    is formed by the common Canadian Porcupine <hi rend="italic">(Erethizon
                    dorsatus),</hi> a stout heavily-built animal, with long hairs almost or quite
                    hiding its spines, four anterior and five posterior toes, and a short stumpy
                    tail. It is a native of the greater part of Canada and the United States,
                    where-ever there is any remnant of the original forest left. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Synetheres,</hi> the second genus, contains some eight or ten species, known as
                    Tree Porcupines, and found throughout the tropical parts of South America, one
                    of them extending northwards into Mexico. They are of a lighter build than the
                    ground porcupines, are covered with short, close, many-coloured spines often
                    mixed with hairs, and their tails are always prehensile. Their hind feet have
                    only four toes, owing to the suppression of the hallux, but instead they have a
                    peculiar fleshy pad on the inner side of the foot, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n538/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0538-0519"/></p>
                <p>between which and the toes boughs and other objects can be firmly grasped as with
                    a hand. The last genus is <hi rend="italic">Chaetomys,</hi> distinguished by the
                    shape of its skull and the greater complexity of its teeth. It contains only one
                    species, <hi rend="italic">C. subspinosus,</hi> a native of the hottest parts of
                    Brazil.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
