<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0760-0737-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PRIMROSE (9th edition, volume 19, page 737)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j3q">Darwinism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z99h">Age</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kw6x">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46m33b2g">Pollen</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1131414">Stamen</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927866">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1070009">Pollen</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800130">Age</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800293">Aging</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984032">Journalism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n760/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PRIMROSE</label>.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Lat. <hi rend="italic">primula</hi>; I tai. and Span, <hi
                    rend="italic">primavera</hi>; Fr. <hi rend="italic">primevère,</hi> or in some
                    provinces <hi rend="italic">primerole.</hi> Strangely enough, the word was
                    applied, according to Dr Prior, in the Middle Ages to the daisy <hi
                    rend="italic">{Bellis</hi><hi rend="italic">perennis),</hi> the present usage
                    being of comparatively recent origin.</p></note> The genus <hi rend="italic"
                    >Primula</hi> contains numerous species distributed throughout the cooler parts
                    of Europe and Asia, and found also on the mountains of Abyssinia and Java. They
                    are all herbaceous perennials, possessing a permanent stock, from which are
                    emitted tufts of leaves and flower-stems -which die down in winter; the new
                    growths formed in autumn remain in a bud-like condition ready to develop
                    themselves in spring. They form the typical genus of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Primulaceae,</hi> the floral conformation of which is very interesting on
                    several accounts independently of the beauty of the flowers. Thus the five
                    stamens springing from the tube of the corolla, instead of being placed
                    alternately with or between its lobes, are opposite or “super posed” to them, an
                    arrangement accounted for by some on the supposition that an outer row of
                    stamens (which, if present, would render the flower symmetrical) is suppressed.
                    In support of this view the case of <hi rend="italic">Samolus,</hi> an allied
                    genus in which there are five petaloid stamens as well as five fertile ones, may
                    be cited. By others the anomaly is explained on the hypothesis that the corolla
                    is suppressed, what appears to be such being merely an outgrowth from the
                    stamens. But this view is not borne out by observation of the development of the
                    flower. Within the base of the corolla tube is the one-celled superior ovary,
                    rising up into the centre of which is a dome-shaped placenta, quite detached
                    from the walls of the ovary and studded with ovules. The origin and explanation
                    of this free central placenta have formed the subject of a copious literature,
                    the point at issue being whether the placenta is a direct prolongation from the
                    axis of the plant or an outgrowth from the walls of the carpels.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For a full discussion of this
                    and other points in the morphology of the flower, the reader may refer to Dr
                    Masters’s paper in the <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Linnean
                    Society,</hi> 2d ser,, vol, i, (1877) p. 285, or to Eichler’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Blüthen-Diagramme.</hi></p></note> The variation in the length of the stamens
                    and of the style in the flowers of this genus has attracted much attention since
                    Darwin pointed out the true significance of these varied arrangements. Briefly
                    it may be said that some of the flowers have short stamens and a long style,
                    while others have long stamens, or stamens inserted so high up that the anthers
                    protrude beyond the corolla tube, and a short style. Gardeners and florists had
                    for centuries been familiar with these variations, calling the flowers from
                    which the anthers protruded “thrumeyed” and those in which the stigma appeared
                    in the mouth of the tube “pin-eyed.” Darwin showed by experiment and research
                    that the most perfect degree of fertility, as shown by the greatest number of
                    seeds and the healthiest seedlings, was attained when the pollen from a
                    short-stamened flower was transferred to the stigma of a short-styled flower, or
                    when the pollen from the long stamens was applied to the long style. As in any
                    given flower the stamens are short (or low down in the flowertube) and the style
                    long, or conversely, it follows that to ensure a high degree of fertility cross
                    fertilization must occur, and this is effected by the transfer of the pollen
                    from one flower to another by insects. Incomplete fertility arises when the
                    stigma is impregnated by the pollen from the same flower. The size of the
                    pollen-grains and the texture of the stigma are different in the two forms of
                    flower. The discovery of the physiological significance of these variations in
                    structure, which had long been noticed, was made by Darwin, and formed the first
                    of a series of similar observations and experiments recorded from time to time
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Linnean Society</hi> and elsewhere by
                    himself and subsequent observers. Among British species may be mentioned the
                    Common Primrose (Z <hi rend="superscript"> j</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                    >vulgaris');</hi> the Cowslip <hi rend="italic">(P. veris),</hi> which is the
                    original source of the <hi rend="italic">Polyanthus</hi> of the gardens; the
                    true Oxlip (P. <hi rend="italic">elatior),</hi> a rare plant only found in the
                    eastern counties; and the Common Oxlip, by some considered to be a form of the
                    Common Primrose but provided with a stem supporting the flowers. Darwin’s
                    experiments go to prove that the first-named three are species, while the
                    last-named is a hybrid between the cowslip and the primrose. In addition to
                    these species two others occur in Britain, namely, <hi rend="italic">P.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">farinosa,</hi> found in Wales, the north of England, and southern
                    Scotland, and <hi rend="italic">P. scotica,</hi> which occurs in Orkney and
                    Caithness. These two species are found also in high Arctic latitudes, and <hi
                    rend="italic">P farinosa,</hi> or a very closely allied form, exists in
                    Fuego.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Auricula</hi> of the gardens was formerly considered to be
                    a form of <hi rend="italic">P. Auricula,</hi> a yellow-flowered species, a
                    native of the Swiss mountains, but it has been recently shown by Kerner that in
                    all probability the origin of the <hi rend="italic">Auricula</hi> was <hi
                    rend="italic">P.</hi><hi rend="italic">pubescens,</hi> supposed to be a natural
                    hybrid between <hi rend="italic">P, Auricula</hi> and <hi rend="italic">P.
                    hirsuta.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Polyanthus</hi> has already been mentioned
                    as a variety of the cowslip, but it may further be added that some very
                    remarkable forms which have been cultivated for centuries owe their
                    peculiarities to <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n761/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0761-0738"/> the assumption by the ordinarily green calyx of a
                    petaloid condition; when this is complete we have the Condition called “hose in
                    hose” by the gardeners. This may, however, arise from actual duplication of the
                    corolla λvithin the calyx. The Chinese Primrose, now so much cultivated in
                    gardens, is derived from <hi rend="italic">P.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >preenitens.</hi> The Japanese Primrose is nearly or quite hardy, and is the
                    stateliest of the genus; its flowers of varied colours are placed tier above
                    tier, like the branches of a fir tree. <hi rend="italic">P. corl·usoides</hi> is
                    another Japanese species of which many forms are now cultivated. <hi
                    rend="italic">P. simensis,</hi> with mealy leaves and yellow flowers, is the
                    Abyssinian Primrose of gardens. The Himalayas are rich in species of primrose,
                    often very difficult of determination or limitation, certain forms being
                    peculiar to particular valleys. Of these <hi rend="italic">P.
                    denticulata,</hi><hi rend="italic">Stuartii, sikkim-mensis, nivalis,</hi> may be
                    mentioned as frequently cultivated, as well as the lovely rose-coloured species
                    <hi rend="italic">P. rosea.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
