<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0907-0884-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PROVINCE (9th edition, volume 19, page 884)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:876196">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb7v">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0652b">Consulates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n907/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PROVINCE</label><hi rend="italic">(provincia,</hi> etymology
                    uncertain), in the Roman sense, may be defined as the department or sphere of
                    duty assigned to one of the higher magistrates (the consuls and praetors).<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Only those magistrates who
                    had <hi rend="italic">imperium</hi> (military power) had a province. When the
                    province of a quaestor is mentioned it refers to the province of the consul or
                    praetor to whom the quaestor is subordinate. In familiar language any business
                    was called a province.</p></note> But when, with the spread of the Roman arms,
                    the government of conquered countries grew to be one of the most important
                    duties of the higher magistrates, the term province, from designating the
                    government of a conquered country as one particular duty of a Roman magistrate,
                    came to be used generally as a designation of the country itself. It is to
                    province in the sense of a subject territory lying outside of Italy and governed
                    by Roman magistrates that the following remarks will apply. As distinguished
                    from Italy, the provinces paid tribute to Rome, for, at least from the time of
                    the Gracchi, it was a recognized constitutional principle that the provinces
                    were the estates of the Roman people and were to be managed for its benefit.
                    Under the republic the constitution of a province was drawn up by the victorious
                    Roman general assisted by ten commissioners appointed by the senate from its own
                    body, and the province was henceforth governed on the lines laid down in this
                    constitution or charter <hi rend="italic">(lex provincial).</hi> For
                    administrative purposes the province was divided into districts, each with its
                    capital, the magistrates and council of which were responsible for the
                    collection of the district taxes. For judicial purposes the province was divided
                    into circuits <hi rend="italic">(conventus),</hi> and in the chief town of each
                    circuit the governor of the province regularly held assizes.</p>
                <p>Cities taken by the sword were destroyed, and their lands were turned into Roman
                    domains and were let out by the censors at Rome to private persons, who
                    undertook to pay a certain proportion of the produce. Royal domains, such as
                    those of Syracuse, Macedonia, Pergamum, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n908/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0908-0885"/></p>
                <p>Bithynia, and Cyrene, were also confiscated. On the other hand communities which
                    surrendered without offering an obstinate resistance were usually allowed to
                    retain their personal freedom and private property, and their chief town was
                    left in the enjoyment of its territory and civil rights, but all the lands were
                    subjected to a tax, consisting either of a payment in kind <hi rend="italic"
                    >(vectigal)</hi> or of a fixed sum of money <hi rend="italic">(tributum,
                    stipendium),</hi> and in some cases a custom-duty <hi rend="italic"
                    >(portorium)</hi> was levied. It is to this latter class of communities (the <hi
                    rend="italic">civitates vectigales</hi> or <hi rend="italic">stipendiariae)</hi>
                    that the large majority of the provincial states belonged. In a better position
                    were those states whose freedom was guaranteed by Rome on the ground of old
                    alliances or special loyalty. Their freedom was recognized either by a treaty or
                    by a decree of the Roman people or senate. As a decree of the people or senate
                    could at any time be recalled, the position of the free states without a treaty
                    was more precarious than that of the treaty states <hi rend="italic"
                    >(civitates</hi><hi rend="italic">foederatae).</hi> The latter, though not
                    allowed to meddle in foreign politics, enjoyed a certain amount of internal
                    freedom, retained their lands, paid no taxes, and were bound to render those
                    services only which were expressly stipulated for in the original treaty, such
                    as furnishing ships and troops, supplying corn at a certain price, and receiving
                    Roman officials and soldiers <hi rend="italic">en</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >route.</hi> Amongst these treaty states were Massilia (Marseilles), Athens,
                    Rhodes, and Tyre. The privileges of the free but not treaty states were somewhat
                    similar, but, as stated, more precarious. All political distinctions, save that
                    between slave and freeman, disappeared when Caracalla bestowed the Roman
                    franchise on the whole empire.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Provincial Diets.—</hi> Apart from the government by Roman
                    officials, every province appears to have had, at least under the empire, a
                    provincial assembly or diet of its own <hi rend="italic">(concilium</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">commune),</hi> and these diets are interesting as the first
                    attempts at representative assemblies. The diet met annually, and was composed
                    of deputies <hi rend="italic">(legati)</hi> from the provincial districts. It
                    arranged for the celebration of religious rites and games, especially (under the
                    empire) for the worship of the emperor, the neglect of which was severely
                    punished. The actual celebration was under the conduct of the high priest of the
                    province, a person of much dignity and importance, perhaps the forerunner of the
                    Christian bishop. The diet also decreed the erection of statues and monuments;
                    it passed votes of thanks to the outgoing governor, or forwarded complaints
                    against him to Rome; and it had the right of sending embassies direct to the
                    senate or the emperor.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Provincial Governor.—</hi> The provinces were administered
                    by governors sent direct from Rome, who held office for a year. From the
                    formation of the first provinces in 227 B.c. down to the time of Sulla (82 B.c.)
                    the governors were praetors (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Praetor)</hi>; from the
                    time of Sulla to that of Augustus the praetors remained in Rome during their
                    year of office, and at the end of it assumed the government of a province with
                    the title of propraetor. This applies, however, only to provinces which were in
                    a settled state and could consequently be administered without a large military
                    force. A province which was the seat of war, or was at least in a disturbed
                    state, was committed to the care either of one of the consuls for the year or of
                    a commander specially appointed for the purpose with the title of proconsul, who
                    might be one of the consuls of the preceding or of a previous year, or else a
                    former praetor, or even, in rare cases, a private individual who had held
                    neither consulship nor praetorship. Thus the distinction between consular (or
                    proconsular) and praetorial (or propraetorial) provinces varied from year to
                    year with the military exigencies of different parts of the empire. At the close
                    of the republic, however, we find even such a peaceful province as Asia
                    administered by a proconsul. In the earlier period of the republic the senate
                    either before or after the elections determined which provinces were to be
                    governed by consuls and which by praetors, and after their election the consuls
                    arranged between themselves by lot or otherwise which of the provinces nominated
                    by the senate each should have, and similarly with the praetors. But in order to
                    guard against partiality the Sempronian law of 123 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi> provided that the senate should yearly nominate the two consular
                    provinces before the election of the consuls, and that the consuls should after
                    their election but before their entry on office arrange between themselves which
                    of the two provinces each should have. The Pompeian law of 53 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> enacted that no one should hold the governorship of a
                    province till at least five years after his consulship or praetorship. This law
                    was repealed by Caesar after the battle of Pharsalia, but was re-enacted under
                    Augustus; it severed the connexion which had previously existed between an urban
                    magistracy and the governorship of a province, and turned the latter, from the
                    mere prolongation of a Roman magistracy, into an independent office. Like
                    magistracies at Rome a provincial governorship was regularly held for one year;
                    but, unlike them, it could be prolonged, formerly by a vote of the people, later
                    by a decree of the senate. The Julian law of Caesar (46 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.)</hi> enacted that the governorship of a consular province should be held
                    for two, that of a praetorian province for one year. The necessary supplies of
                    men and money were voted to the governor by the senate. His staff consisted of
                    one or more lieutenants <hi rend="italic">(legati),</hi> a quaestor, and <hi
                    rend="subscript"> v</hi> numerous subordinates. The lieutenants were nominated
                    by the senate from men of senatorial rank; if they proved incompetent, the
                    governor dismissed them; if they showed ability, he entrusted them with military
                    or judicial functions. As to the quaestor, see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Quaestor.</hi> Besides these the governor took with him from Rome a number of
                    young men of the upper classes to assist him in the government. These were known
                    as the companions <hi rend="italic">(comites')</hi> or suite of the governor,
                    sometimes, but incorrectly, as the praetorian cohort (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Praetorians).</hi> These members of his suite were chosen by the governor
                    himself, who was responsible for them, but they were maintained at the expense
                    of the state, and under the empire received regular pay. In addition there was a
                    crowd of beadles, clerks, couriers, criers, doctors, dragomans, &amp;c., not to
                    speak of freedmen and slaves for the personal service of the governor. Under the
                    republic the governor was not allowed to take his wife with him to his province;
                    under the empire he might do so, but he was answerable for her conduct. Before
                    setting out for his province the governor, clad in the purple military robe of
                    his office, offered sacrifice on the Capitol; then immediately after receiving
                    the <hi rend="italic">imperium</hi> or military command he marched out of the
                    city (for the <hi rend="italic">imperium</hi> could only be exercised outside of
                    Rome and was forfeited by staying in the city), preceded by his sergeants <hi
                    rend="italic">(lictores),</hi> and accompanied by his suite. He was bound to
                    travel direct to his province; the means of transport were supplied partly by
                    the state, partly by the provinces through which he travelled. His year of
                    office began from the day he set foot in his province, but the time of arrival
                    varied with the length and difficulty of the route. In the hands of the governor
                    all powers military and civil were united. He commanded all the troops in the
                    province, and had power to raise levies of Roman citizens as well as of
                    provincials, and to make requisitions of war material. He possessed both
                    criminal and civil jurisdiction; as criminal judge he had the power of life and
                    death, and from his sentence none but Roman citizens could appeal; as civil
                    judge he was guided partly by the charter of the province <hi rend="italic"
                    >(lex</hi><hi rend="italic">provinciae),</hi> partly by the edict which it was
                    customary for him to issue before his entrance on office (compare <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Praetor),</hi> partly by the original laws of the country so
                    far as their validity was acknowledged by the charter or by the governor’s own
                    edict. Under the empire Gaius wrote a commentary on the provincial edict, and it
                    is usually supposed that this was a general edict drawn up for use in all the
                    provinces and superseding all separate edicts for the different provinces.
                    Mommsen, however, is of opinion that Gaius only commented on the edict of a
                    particular province.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Condition</hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic">the
                    Provinces under the Republic.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> Under the republic
                    the Roman people regarded the provinces as so many estates from which they were
                    to derive revenue. The weal or woe of the provincials was of no moment, but the
                    development of the material resources of the provinces was of great moment.
                    Hence agriculture and commerce were encouraged, settlements were made, roads and
                    aqueducts were constructed; in short, the Roman aimed at exploiting his empire
                    by a system of prudent economy as far as possible removed from the blind
                    rapacity which has turned the empire of the Turk from a garden into a
                    wilderness. But the Roman governors were too apt to look on their provinces as
                    their own peculiar prey; they had usually bought their way to office at vast
                    expense, and they now sought in the provinces the means of reimbursing
                    themselves for the expenditure they had incuιτed at Rome. The annual change of
                    governor was thus a frightful calamity to the provincials, for every year
                    brought a repetition of the same extravagant demands to be met by the same or,
                    as the province became exhausted, still heavier sacrifices. Redress was to be
                    had originally by a complaint to the senate; after 149 B.c. there was a regular
                    court established at Rome for the trial of cases of oppression <hi rend="italic"
                    >(repetundae)</hi> by provincial governors. But, even when after much trouble
                    and expense the provincials had arraigned their oppressor, it was difficult to
                    secure his condemnation at the hands of juries composed (as they usually were)
                    of men who had a fellow-feeling for the offender because they had themselves
                    committed<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n909/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0909-0886"/> or hoped for means of committing similar
                    offences. Besides the governor, two classes of harpies joined in wringing the
                    uttermost farthing from the unhappy provincials. These were the publicans or
                    farmers of the taxes, and the money-lenders <hi rend="italic"
                    >(negotiatores'),</hi> who supplied a temporary accommodation at ruinous rates
                    of interest. Both these classes were recruited from the ranks of the Roman
                    knights, and, since from the legislation of Caius Gracchus (122 B.c.) the juries
                    were drawn at first exclusively and after Sulla’s time (81 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.)</hi> partially from the knightly order, the provincial governor could not
                    check the excesses of those bloodsuckers without risking a condemnation at the
                    hands of their brethren. Accordingly he generally made common cause with them,
                    backing their exactions when needful by military force.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Provinces under the Empire.—</hi> Under the empire the
                    provinces fared much better. The monarchy tended to obliterate the distinction
                    between Romans and provincials by reducing both to a common level of subjection
                    to the emperor, who meted out equal justice to all his subjects. The first
                    centuries of our era were probably for some of the countries included in the
                    Roman empire the happiest in their history; Gibbon indeed fixed on the period
                    from the death of Domitian to the accession of Commodus (96-180 A.D.) as the
                    happiest age of the world.</p>
                <p>Augustus, in 27 B.c., divided the provinces into imperial and senatorial. Those
                    which, from their proximity to the frontier or the turbulance of their
                    population, required the presence of an army were placed under the direct
                    control of the emperor; those which needed no troops were left to be
                    administered by the senate. (1) The senatorial provinces were ruled by an annual
                    governor as under the republic. Of these provinces Augustus ordained that Africa
                    and Asia should be consular, the rest praetorian; but all the governors of the
                    senatorial provinces were now called proconsuls. Their powers and dignities were
                    much the same as they had been under the republic, except that they had now no
                    troops, or only a handful to maintain order. (2) The imperial provinces were
                    governed by imperial lieutenants <hi rend="italic">(legati</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Caesaris),</hi> who were nominated by the emperor and held office at his
                    pleasure; all of them had the power of the sword <hi rend="italic">(jus
                    gladii).</hi> For the administration of the finances these lieutenants had
                    procurators under them, while the governors of the senatorial provinces
                    continued to have quaestors as under the republic. Another class of imperial
                    provinces consisted of those which from the physical nature of the country (as
                    the Alpine districts) or the backward state of civilization (as Mauretania and
                    Thrace) or· the stubborn character of the people (as Judaea and Egypt) were not
                    adapted to receive a regular provincial constitution. These were regarded as
                    domains of the emperor, and were managed by a procurator (in the case of Egypt
                    by a praefect, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Praefect)</hi> nominated by and
                    responsible to the emperor.</p>
                <p>Under the empire all provincial governors received a fixed salary. Complaints
                    against them were brought before the senate, and the accusers were allowed a
                    senator to act as their advocate. The lengthened periods during which the
                    governors, at least in the imperial provinces, held office, together with the
                    oversight exercised by the emperor, alleviated materially the position of the
                    provincials under the empire. In order to keep himself well informed of what was
                    passing in the empire, Augustus established <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> post
                    whereby official despatches were forwarded by couriers and official persons were
                    conveyed by coaches. The post, however, was only for the use of the Government;
                    no private person was allowed, unless by an exceptional concession, to avail
                    himself of it (J. G. FR.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
