<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0462-0443-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">POMPADOUR, Jeanne Antoinette Poisson (9th edition,
                    volume 19, page 443)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:955141">Hems</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n462/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">POMPADOUR, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jeanne Antoinette
                    Poisson</hi></label><hi rend="smallcaps">le</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Normant</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">d’Étioles, Marquise de</hi> (1721-1764), the
                    most famous of all the mistresses of Louis XV., was born in Paris on 29th
                    December 1721, and was baptized as the legitimate daughter of François Poisson,
                    an officer in the household of the duke of Orleans, and his wife Madeleine de la
                    Motte, in the church of St Eustache, but she was suspected, as well as her
                    brother, afterwards marquis of Marigny, to be the child of a very wealthy
                    financier, and farmer-general of the revenues, Le Normant de Tourne-hem. He at
                    any rate took upon himself the charge of her education; and, as from the beauty
                    and wit she showe I from childhood she seemed to be born for some uncommon·
                    destiny, he declared her “un morceau de roi,” and specially educated her to be a
                    king’s mistress. This idea was confirmed in her childish mind by the prophecy of
                    an old woman, whom in after days she pensioned for the correctness, of her
                    prediction. In 1741 she was married to a nephew of her protector and guardian,
                    Le Normant d’Étioles, who was passionately in love with her, and soon became a
                    queen of fashion. Y’et the world of the financiers at Paris was far apart from
                    the court world, where she wished to reign; she could get no introduction at
                    court, and could only try to catch the king’s eye when he went out hunting. But
                    Louis XV. was then under the influence of Madame de· Mailly, who carefully
                    prevented any further intimacy with “la petite L·tioles,” and it was not until
                    after her death that the king met the fair qιieen of the financial world of
                    Paris at a ball given by the city to the dauphin in 1744, and he was immediately
                    subjugated. She at once gave up· her husband, and in 1745 was established at
                    Versailles as. “maîtresse en titre.” Louis XV. bought her the estate of
                    Pompadour, from which she took her title of marquise. She was hardly established
                    firmly in power before she showed that ambition rather than love had guided her,
                    and began to mix in politics. Knowing that the French people of that time were
                    ruled by the literary kings of the time, she paid court to them, and tried to
                    play the part of a Maecenas. Voltaire was her poet in chief, and the founder of
                    the physiocrats, Quesnay, was her physician. In the arts she was even more
                    successful; she was herself no mean etcher and engraver, and she encouraged and
                    protected Vanloo, Boucher, Vien, Greuze, and the engraver Jacques Guay. Yet this
                    policy did not prevent her from being lampooned, and the famous Poissardes
                    against her contributed to the ruin of many wits suspected of being among the
                    authors, and notably of the Comte de Maurepas. The command of the political
                    situation passed entirely into her hands; she it was who brought Belle-Isle into
                    office with his vigorous policy; she corresponded regularly with the generals of
                    the armies in the field, as her recently published letters to the Comte de
                    Clermont prove; and she introduced the Abbé de Bernis into the ministry in order
                    to-effect a very great alteration of French politics in 1756. The continuous
                    policy of France since the days of Richelieu had been to weaken the house of
                    Austria by alliances in Germany; but Madame de Pompadour changed this hereditary
                    policy because Frederick the Great wrote scandalous verses on her; and because
                    Maria Theresa wrote her a friendly letter she entered into an alliance with
                    Austria. This alliance brought on the Seven Years’ War with all its disasters,
                    the battle of Rosbach and the loss of Canada; but Madame de Pompadour persisted
                    in her policy, and when Bernis failed her, brought Choiseul into office, and
                    supported him in all his great plans, the Pacte de Famille, the suppression of
                    the Jesuits, and the peace of Versailles. But it was to internal politics that
                    this remarkable woman paid most attention; no one obtained office except through
                    her; in imitation of Madame de Maintenon she prepared all business for the
                    king’s eye with the ministers, and contrived that they should meet in her room;
                    and she daily examined the letters sent through the post office with Janelie,
                    the director of the post office. By this continuous labour she made herself
                    indispensable to Louis. Y <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi> et, when she had lost
                    the heart of her lover after a year or two, she had a difficult task before her;
                    to maintain her influence she had not only to save the king as much trouble as
                    possible, but to find him fresh pleasures. When he first <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n463/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0463-0444"/> began to weary of her, she remembered her talent
                    for acting and her private theatricals at Etioles, and established the “théâtre
                    des petits cabinets,” in which she acted with the greatest lords about the court
                    for the king’s pleasure in tragedies and comedies, operas and ballets. By this
                    means and the “concerts spirituels” she kept in favour for a time; but at last
                    she found a surer way, by encouraging the king in his debaucheries, and Louis
                    wept over her kindness to his various mistresses. Only once, when the king was
                    wounded by Damiens in 1757, did she receive a serious shock, and momentarily
                    left the court; but on his recovery she returned more powerful than ever. She
                    even ingratiated herself with the queen, after the example of Madame de
                    Maintenon, and was made a lady-in-waiting; but the end was soon to come. “Ma vie
                    est un combat,” she said, and so it was, with business and pleasure; she
                    gradually grew weaker and weaker, and when told that death was at hand she
                    dressed herself in full court costume, and met it bravely on 15th April 1764 at
                    the age of forty-two.</p>
                <p>See Capefitrue, <hi rend="italic">Madame la Marquise de Pompadour,</hi> 1858; E.
                    and J. de Gon- &lt;ourt, ∕-&lt;s <hi rend="italic">Maîtresses</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de Louis</hi> Λ'l <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi>., vol. ii., 1860;
                    and Campardon, <hi rend="italic">Madame de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Pompadour</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">la Cour de
                    Louis</hi><hi rend="italic">XV.</hi><hi rend="italic">an milieu</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">du dix-huitième siècle,</hi> 1867. Far more valuable are Malassis
                    <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> s two recently published volumes of
                    correspondence, <hi rend="italic">Correspondance</hi><hi rend="italic">de Madame
                    de Pompadour</hi><hi rend="italic">avec</hi><hi rend="italic">son</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">père</hi><hi rend="italic">Μ.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Poisson,</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">son</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">frère</hi><hi rend="italic">Μ.</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Vandières,</hi> Ac., 1878, and Bonhomme, <hi rend="italic">Madame de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Pompadour,</hi><hi rend="italic">général d'armée.</hi> 1880,
                    containing lier letters to the Comte de Clermont. For her artistic and
                    theatrical tastes see particularly J. F. Leturcq, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Notice</hi><hi rend="italic">sur</hi><hi rend="italic">Jacques Guay,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Graveur sur pierres</hi><hi rend="italic">fines du Rd</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Louis</hi><hi rend="italic">X V.:</hi><hi rend="italic">Documents
                    inédits</hi><hi rend="italic">emanant</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Guay</hi><hi rend="italic">et notes sur les oeuvres de gravure en
                    taille douce et en pierres durs de</hi><hi rend="italic">la Marquise</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Pompadour,</hi> 1873; and Adolphe
                    Jullien, <hi rend="italic">Histoire du Théâtre</hi><hi rend="italic">de Madame
                    de</hi><hi rend="italic">Pompadour,</hi><hi rend="italic">dit Théâtre des Petits
                    Cabinets,</hi> 1874.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
