<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0753-0730-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PRIESTLEY, Joseph (9th edition, volume 19, page
                    730)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1123835">Socinianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tp6p">Socinianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204598">Pennsylvania</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n753/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PRIESTLEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi></label>
                    (1733-1804), was born on 13th March 1733 at Fieldhead near Birstal, in the West
                    Riding of Yorkshire. His father, Jonas Priestley, was a woollencloth dresser and
                    apparently of very moderate means. His mother was the only child of Joseph
                    Swift, a farmer at Shafton near Wakefield. The paternal grandfather, also named
                    Joseph, was a churchman whose high moral character became a sacred tradition in
                    his family. The young Joseph’s parents were Nonconformists. They had six
                    children in eight years, and on the birth of the last, in the hard winter of
                    1739, the mother died. During those years Joseph lived a good deal with his
                    maternal grandfather at Shafton. But he relates that his mother “was careful to
                    teach him the Assembly’s Catechism,” and that, with a view of impressing on his
                    mind “a clear idea of the distinction of property,” she on one occasion made him
                    carry back a <hi rend="italic">pin</hi> which he had picked up at the house of
                    an uncle. Three years after the loss of his mother, his father’s sister, Mrs
                    Keighley, a lady in good circumstances, having no children of her own, took the
                    boy to live with her.</p>
                <p>At the age of twelve he was sent to a neighbouring endowed school, where, under
                    the tuition of a clergyman, Mr Hague, he made rapid progress in classics, while
                    on holidays, by way of recreation, he learned Hebrew from</p>
                <p>Mr Kirkley, a Dissenting minister. On the removal of the clergyman Mr Kirkley
                    opened a school of his own, and Priestley became entirely his pupil. From the
                    age of sixteen to nearly twenty his health was unsatisfactory, and he attended
                    neither school nor college, but still continued his studies in private with
                    occasional assistance. It was thought that his constitution would be better
                    adapted to an active than to a sedentary life, and with a view to commerce he
                    learned French, Italian, and German without assistance. But the aunt, Mrs
                    Keighley, had sei her heart on making a minister of him, and young Priestley’s
                    own aspirations took the same form. When, therefore, his health improved, the
                    offer of a mercantile situation in Lisbon was surrendered, and Priestley in his
                    twentieth year (1752) was sent to Daventry, where there existed a Nonconformist
                    academy, originally founded by Dr Doddridge at Northampton, and removed after
                    his incapacitation by illness or on his death in 1751.</p>
                <p>There is no mention of any hesitation on the part of Priestley or his friends as
                    to whether he should enter the established church or not. But there was
                    certainly nothing in his theological creed at this period to have prevented his
                    taking orders. The hindrance, therefore, must have been his adherence to the
                    Nonconformist tradition on questions of ecclesiastical polity and ritual. There
                    were, however, in his early associations some elements which not only help to
                    explain his after career but throw a curious light on the fluid condition of
                    Nonconformist denominations in those days as compared with their sectarian
                    fixedness now. He was brought up in the principles of Calvinism. But he tells us
                    his aunt’s house “was the resort of all the Dissenting ministers in the
                    neighbourhood without distinction; and those who were most obnoxious on account
                    of their heresy were almost as welcome to her, if she thought them honest and
                    good men—which she was not unwilling to do—as any others.” Notwithstanding the
                    comparative freedom of the conversations to which he listened, young Priestley
                    at seventeen was strictly orthodox, and anxiously endeavoured to realize the
                    experiences he supposed to be necessary to conversion. His chief trouble was
                    that he could not repent of Adam’s transgression, a difficulty he never
                    surmounted. The pressure of this impossibility forced his candid mind to the
                    conclusion that there must be a mistake somewhere, and he began to doubt whether
                    he was really so much entangled in Adam’s guilt as he had been taught.
                    Accordingly he was refused admission into the communion of the Independent
                    church which his aunt attended. His adhesion to Calvinism was now considerably
                    relaxed. But this did not interfere with his entrance at Daventry. Dr Doddridge
                    had not confined his educational aims to students for the ministry, and he not
                    only refused to impose theological tests but he incurred reproach by resolutely
                    refusing to press his own orthodox creed on the heterodox pupils occasionally
                    received. Priestley’s intellectual preparation previous to his entrance is
                    noteworthy. Besides being a fair classic, he had improved his Hebrew by giving
                    lessons in that language. He had acquired three modern languages. He had
                    “learned Chaldee and Syriac, and just begun to read Arabic”; nor was he
                    disproportionately backward in mathematics. He had also mastered ’s Gravesande’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Elements of Natural Philosophy,</hi> and various text-books of
                    the time in logic and metaphysics. It cannot surprise us that he “was excused
                    all the studies of the first year and a great part of those of the second. ’ At
                    Daventry he stayed three years, taking a prominent part in the singularly free
                    discussions that seem to have formed a considerable part of the academical
                    exercises. “In this situation,” he says, “I saw reason to embrace what is
                    generally called the heterodox side of almost every question.” His chief tutors
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n754/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0754-0731"/></p>
                <p>were Dr Ashworth of conservative and the Rev. Samuel Clark of decidedly liberal
                    tendencies. Priestley’s speculations at this time were philosophical rather than
                    scientific. Under the influence of Hartley’s <hi rend="italic">Observations on
                    Man</hi> and Collins’s <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Enquiry</hi> he exchanged
                    his early Calvinism for a system of “necessarianism,”—that is, he learned to
                    hold that the invariable connexion of cause and effect is as inviolable in the
                    moral as in the material world. During these early years he began his enormous
                    industry as a writer, and in particular laid down the lines of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Institutes of Natural and Revealed Religion.</hi></p>
                <p>From Daventry he went in 1755, at twenty-two years of age, to take charge of a
                    small congregation at Needham Market in Suffolk. This church was halting between
                    Presbyterianism and Independency, being subsidized by both. Priestley insisted
                    on dropping the Independent connexion. As a consequence he had to content
                    himself with a salary of &lt;£30, and succeeded in living on less. His studies
                    had not in the least chilled his devotion to the sacred work, which indeed to
                    the end of his life he counted his highest honour. He was diligent in preaching
                    and teaching, but his intellectual freedom, together with a physical difficulty
                    in speech, prevented his attaining popularity. To cure the defect in speech he
                    paid twenty guineas, given by his aunt, to a London specialist or quack. But
                    this difficulty turned out to be as irremediable as his intellectual
                    unconformability; and the only permanent advantage derived from his visit to the
                    metropolis was an introduction to various scholars of the day, such as Dr Price,
                    also Dr Benson and Dr Kippis, friends of Lardner. Later on he made the
                    acquaintance of the last also through some manuscript notes on the doctrine of
                    atonement, which attracted the great scholar’s attention.</p>
                <p>In 1758 Priestley removed to Nantwich, obtaining a more congenial congregation;
                    and there he established a school, which increased his income but lessened his
                    literary activity. Always bringing his best intelligence to bear on everything
                    he undertook, he varied his elementary lessons with instruction in natural
                    philosophy, illustrated by experiments, for which he could now afford the
                    needful instruments. “These,” he says, “I taught my scholars in the highest
                    class to keep in order, and to make use of; and by entertaining their parents
                    and friends with experiments, in which the scholars were generally the
                    operators, and sometimes the lecturers too, I considerably extended the
                    reputation of my school.” Up to this time his studies had been entirely literary
                    and theologico-philosophical. It is noteworthy that his efforts to liberalize
                    education turned his attention to science. He was probably one of the very first
                    teachers to appreciate the importance of physical science to early culture.</p>
                <p>In 1761 he was appointed classical tutor in a Nonconformist academy, then
                    recently established at Warrington on the same liberal principles as the
                    institution at Daventry. In this position he passed six of his happiest years,
                    pursuing his scientific studies, especially in chemistry and electricity,
                    enjoying congenial intercourse with Dr Turner of Liverpool, also with Wedgwood’s
                    partner Mr Bentley, Dr Enfield, and various Manchester men whose sons or
                    grandsons helped to form the “Manchester school.” In 1762 he married the
                    daughter of Mr Isaac Wilkinson, an ironmaster of Wrexham. At Warrington
                    Priestley received the complimentary degree of LL.D, from Edinburgh, apparently
                    in recognition of his <hi rend="italic">Chart of History.</hi> On a visit to
                    London he made the acquaintance of Dr Franklin, and his researches in
                    electricity procured his election to the Royal Society in 1766.</p>
                <p>In the following year (1767) Dr Priestley removed to Leeds to take charge of Mill
                    Hill chapel; and in the same year was published his <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Electricity,</hi> a work suggested by Dr Franklin, and contributing greatly to
                    the author’s fame. Now, however, he turned once more to speculative theology,
                    and surrendered the Arianism he had hitherto loosely held, adopting instead
                    definite Socinian views. In addition to preaching and teaching diligently in his
                    congregation he carried on his chemical researches with results considered at
                    the time startling. Chemistry was hardly in its infancy; it was unborn. “The
                    vast science,” says Mr Huxley, “which now passes under that name had no
                    existence.” Living next door to a brewery Dr Priestley amused himself with
                    experiments on the “fixed air” (carbonic acid) produced there, and succeeded in
                    forcing it into water. Thus commenced his researches on “different kinds of
                    air,” remarkable rather for the impulse they gave to controversy and experiment
                    than for any mature scientific results. He had a keen instinct for surmise, but
                    no adequate method of research and verification. On this point Roscoe and
                    Schorlemmer observe in their treatise on <hi rend="italic">Chemistry</hi> (vol.
                    i. p. 18) that “Priestley’s notion of original research, which seems quite
                    foreign to our present ideas, may be excused, perhaps justified by the state of
                    science in his day. He believed that all discoveries are made by chance, and he
                    compares the investigation of nature to a hound, wildly running after, and here
                    and there chancing on game (or, as James Watt called it, ‘his random
                    haphazarding’), whilst we would rather be disposed to compare the man of science
                    to the sportsman, who having, after persistent effort, laid out a distinct plan
                    of operations, makes reasonably sure of his quarry.” At this time also he wrote
                    various political tracts and papers, always in favour of popular rights, and in
                    particular hostile to the attitude of the Government towards the American
                    colonies.</p>
                <p>In 1771 he was nearly appointed to accompany Captain Cook to the South Seas. But
                    the Government of the day was shocked at the idea of giving official position to
                    a Socinian minister, and Priestley was disappointed. Shortly afterwards he
                    accepted the somewhat anomalous situation of “literary companion” and librarian
                    to Lord Shelburne. With this nobleman he travelled in Holland and Germany,
                    returning by Paris, where he spent a month in 1774. The position gave him ample
                    leisure for his scientific and literary pursuits. But on the completion of his
                    most noteworthy philosophical treatise, <hi rend="italic">Disquisitions on
                    Matter and Spirit,</hi> the connexion was dissolved. It has been surmised that
                    the patron feared to share the unpopularity of his client’s views. Those views
                    Priestley himself considered to be “materialistic.” It is a question of words.
                    Seeing that he denied impenetrability to matter, it is difficult to say why the
                    substance he left might not as well be called spirit as anything else.</p>
                <p>In 1780 he removed to Birmingham, where he enjoyed the friendship of James Watt
                    and his partner Boulton, also of Dr Darwin, grandfather of the illustrious man
                    in whom the honours of the name culminated. Here Dr Priestley again took charge
                    of a congregation, and resumed his theological efforts in a controversy with the
                    bishop of Waterford, and in a laborious <hi rend="italic">History of the
                    Corruptions of Christianity.</hi> But bad times were at hand. The French
                    Revolution excited passionate controversy, and Priestley was naturally on the
                    side of the revolutionists. In 1791 the anniversary of the capture of the
                    Bastille was observed in Birmingham by a dinner at which he was not present, and
                    with which he had nothing to do. But the mob wished to testify by some signal
                    deed their abhorrence of the un-English notions propounded at the dinner, and
                    therefore burned down Priestley’s chapel and house. Before the deed was done
                    they waded knee deep in torn manuscripts, and amused themselves with futile
                    efforts to make an electric machine avenge its owner’s impiety by firing <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n755/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0755-0732"/> the papers with a spark. The blow was a terrible
                    one. Priestley and his family had escaped violence by timely flight, but every
                    material possession he valued was destroyed and the labours of years
                    annihilated. But neither despair nor bitterness possessed him. He left
                    Birmingham, and for three years preached in Hackney, then a suburban village,
                    and in 1794 he went out to the young States whose cause he had advocated, to
                    spend the last ten years of his life in the land of the future. He resided at
                    Northumberland in Pennsylvania, eager as ever for controversy and research. His
                    materialism, so-called, never dimmed his hope of immortality. His religion to
                    the end was characterized by a childlike simplicity of spirit. On his deathbed
                    he would have his grandchildren to kneel by his side for their daily prayers,
                    and listened with pleasure to the hymns they lisped. On the 6th of February 1804
                    he clearly and audibly dictated a few alterations he wished to make in some of
                    his publications. “That is right,” he said, “I have now done”; and within an
                    hour he quietly expired.</p>
                <p>The interest of Dr Priestley’s life lies not so much in any splendid
                    achievements, either literary or scientific, but rather in the character of the
                    man. His career also affords a typical illustration of the mutual relation and
                    interaction of several great factors of human progress at a very critical
                    period. As a Nonconformist minister, born into a Calvinistic circle, educated in
                    an Independent academy, developing into a Socinian divine, yet maintaining
                    always the most friendly relations with clergymen, priests, and orthodox
                    ministers, he gives us a curious insight into the condition of English religion
                    just before its sectarian divisions had hardened into their modern form. As a
                    pioneer in the investigation of gases and the discoverer of oxygen he
                    helped—but, it must be admitted, as often by his mistakes as by his successes—to
                    erect chemistry into a science. As a professed materialist whose doctrines
                    seemed at the same time to merge matter in force he, amongst others, prepared
                    the way for the modern agnosticism, which declines to look behind phenomena. As
                    a politician he anticipated nineteenth-century radicalism. In general, as an
                    exceptionally single-eyed and fearless searcher after truth he bore the brunt of
                    persecution by vulgar ignorance, and in his disappointments illustrated how
                    little can be practically accomplished by isolated enlightenment apart from
                    popular education.</p>
                <p>The works of Dr Priestley, as collected and edited by John Towill Rutt, fill
                    twenty-five octavo volumes, one of which, however, consists of memoirs and
                    correspondence. The date of this collected edition is 1832. It contains upwards
                    of 130 separate works, varying in size from brief pamphlets to treatises in four
                    volumes, and his labours range over almost all possible subjects of human
                    knowledge or speculation. Mathematics, chemistry, physiology, grammar, logic,
                    mental and moral philosophy, history, theology, interpretation of prophecy,
                    politics, and sociology, all alike furnished themes for Priestley’s untiring
                    pen, and if he did not write on any of them with striking originality he treated
                    all with freedom and intelligence. In 1761 he issued his first published works,
                    a treatise on the <hi rend="italic">Scripture Doctrine of Remission</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">The Rudiments of English Grammar.</hi> From that date till 1767 he
                    was content with publishing something every alternate year. But from 1767 to
                    1804 he allowed only two years to go by unmarked by one or more publications,
                    many of them remarkable as monuments of conscientious and laborious industry.
                    His first scientific work, <hi rend="italic">The History and Present State of
                    Electricity, with Original Experiments,</hi> was published in 1767. The rapid
                    advance of science has left to this and similar works of his little more than an
                    antiquarian interest. But the treatise illustrates his prophetic spirit,
                    inasmuch as it shows how far he was in advance of his contemporaries in
                    appreciation of the prospects of physical research. In 1774 he issued his first
                    volume of <hi rend="italic">Experiments and Observations on Different Branches
                    of Air, Ac.</hi> In this volume he announced his discovery of “dephlogisticated
                    air,” now known as oxygen. The then prevalent theory of <hi rend="italic"
                    >phlogiston,</hi> or the combustible principle in matter, betrayed him into
                    great confusion, evident enough in the very name he gave to his new “branch of
                    air.” Nevertheless it is said of him in Roscoe and Schorlemmer’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Chemistry</hi> (vol. i. p. 16) that “no one obtained more
                    important results or threw more light upon the chemical existence of a number of
                    different gases than Joseph Priestley.” These <hi rend="italic">Experiments and
                    Observations</hi> were continued through five volumes, of which the last
                    appeared in 1780. Perhaps the limit of Priestley’s power of growth is
                    illustrated by the persistency with which he clung to <hi rend="italic"
                    >phlogiston</hi> notwithstanding the discoveries of Black, Lavoisier, and
                    Cavendish. In 1800 he issued a treatise called <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of
                    Phlogiston established, and that of the Composition of Water ref uted.</hi> In a
                    letter of that year to the Rev. T. Lindsay he says, “I have well considered all
                    that my opponents have advanced, and feel perfectly confident of the ground I
                    stand upon. In this definitive treatise I insert all that is contained in my
                    former publications on the subject, with many new experiments. Though nearly
                    alone, I am under no apprehension of defeat.” Dr Priestley clearly failed to
                    appreciate the progress of the science he had done so much to promote. But the
                    attempt made by Lavoisier to claim for himself a concurrent discovery oι oxygen
                    at the same time as Priestley’s was certainly unjustifiable. This achievement,
                    together with the first preparation of nitric oxide, nitrous oxide, hydrochloric
                    acid, and other important gases, constitutes the true ground of his fame as a
                    scientific pioneer (see Roscoe and Schorlemmer, <hi rend="italic"
                    >l.c.).</hi></p>
                <p>Priestley’s chief theological works were the <hi rend="italic">Institutes of
                    Natural and Revealed Religion, A History of the Corruptions of
                    Christianity,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A General History of the Christian
                    Church to the Fall of the Western Empire.</hi> Bishop Horsley’s criticisms on
                    the second of these works produced letters in reply, “with additional evidence
                    that the primitive church was Unitarian.” His principal metaphysical writings
                    were <hi rend="italic">Disquisitions relating to Matter and Spirit</hi> and
                    various essays and letters on necessarianism. A complete list of his works will
                    be found in vol. i. part ii. of Rutt’s collected edition. (J. A. P., jr.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
