<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0264-0255-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PODOPHYLLIN (9th edition, volume 19, page 255)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s24m">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04032">Alcohol</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41s37">Alcoholates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z70w4g">Alcohols</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43t9d59r">Alcoholism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795828">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804631">Alcohols</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804414">Alcoholics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804361">Alcoholates</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804461">Alcoholism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n264/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PODOPHYLLIN</label>, a popular remedy which is much used by
                    those who are averse to the employment of calomel and other mercurial
                    preparations, and hence has been called vegetable mercury. The drug, as used in
                    medicine, is obtained from the rhizome of the American mandrake or May apple,
                    <hi rend="italic">Podophyllum</hi><hi rend="italic">peltatum,</hi> L., an
                    herbaceous perennial belonging to the natural order <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ber-</hi><hi rend="italic">beridaceae,</hi> indigenous in woods in Canada and
                    the United States. The plant is about a foot high, bearing two peltate,
                    deeply-divided leaves, which are about 5 inches in diameter, and bear in the
                    axil a solitary, stalked, white flower about the size and shape of the garden
                    anemone, with six or more petals and twice as many hypogynous stamens. The fruit
                    is ripe in May, and is an oval, yellowish, fleshy berry containing twelve or
                    more arillate seeds. The rhizome, as met with in commerce, occurs in cylindrical
                    pieces two or three inches long and about ⅛ inch in diameter, of a chocolate or
                    purplish brown colour, smooth and slightly enlarged where the juncture of the
                    leafy stem is indicated by a circular scar on the upper and a few broken
                    rootlets on the under side. The odour is heavy and disagreeable, and the taste
                    acrid and bitter.</p>
                <p>Podophyllin is a resinous powder obtained by precipitating an alcoholic tincture
                    of the rhizome by means of water acidulated with hydrochloric acid. It varies in
                    colour from greyish to bright yellow or greenish brown, the first-named being
                    the purest. The drug has been the subject of numerous chemical investigations,
                    the most recent of which (Podwyssotzki, in <hi rend="italic">Ztschr. f.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Russland,</hi> xx. 777) indicates that its activity is due to a
                    definite resinous compound which has been named by its discoverer <hi
                    rend="italic">podophyllotoxin</hi>; another constituent named <hi rend="italic"
                    >podophylloquercetin</hi> has neither emetic nor purgative properties, but
                    appears to be the cause of the griping pains which sometimes accompany the
                    action of podophyllin; a third substance, <hi rend="italic">podophyllic
                    acid,</hi> has no medicinal action. <hi rend="italic">Podophyllotoxin</hi> is a
                    bitter amorphous principle soluble in weak alcohol and in hot water, ether, and
                    chloroform, but insoluble in petroleum spirit. It is split up by the action of
                    alkalies into a resin-acid named picropodophyllic acid, which is inert, and a
                    very active substance, picropodophyllin, which crystallizes in delicate silky
                    needles. _ Picropodophyllin is insoluble in water, and almost insoluble in
                    spirit of less than 80 per cent., but is rendered soluble when united to the
                    picropodophyllic acid. <hi rend="italic">Podophylloquercetin</hi> crystallizes
                    in short needles of a yellow colour and metallic lustre. It is soluble in etheι∙
                    and alcohol, and forms a compound with acetate of lead which is soluble in
                    acetic acid and can be sublimed in shining yellow crystals, and which on
                    exposure to the air gradually becomes green. <hi rend="italic">Podophyllic
                    acid</hi> is insoluble in water and in ether, but soluble in alcohol. In
                    medicine podophyllin is employed for torpor of the liver and obstinate
                    constipation, arising from sedentary employment, imprudence in diet, and
                    irregularity of habits. In small doses it acts as a slow and gentle laxative,
                    especially if combined with henbane and belladonna, but in large doses it is an
                    irritant hydragogue cathartic, the action of which persists for some time. The
                    usual dose as a laxative and mild hepatic stimulant is about ⅜ of a grain, but
                    the samples met with in commerce vary considerably in strength, and act with
                    varying effect upon different individuals. Specimens having a greenish tint
                    should be avoided, since they probably contain podophylloquercetin and tend to
                    cause severe griping. In large doses it appears to lose its stimulant action on
                    the liver. Podophyllin is official in the pharmacopoeias of Great Britain,
                    India, France, Russia, and the United States.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
