<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0697-0674-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PRESBYTER (9th edition, volume 19, page 674)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892p9k">Spiritism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v395">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698j66">Prophets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kz4v">Teachers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888378">Deacons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:875210">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079211">Prophets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1181450">Worship</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n697/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PRESBYTER</label>. Towards the end of the 2d century the
                    organization of the Christian congregations throughout the Roman empire, at
                    least of all the greater ones, was identical. At the head of each was the
                    bishop, whose function it was to conduct public worship, control the church
                    funds, and keep watch over the manners of his flock. The free prophets and
                    teachers having almost everywhere died out, the duty of religious instruction
                    and edification also fell on him. In conducting the worship and in ministering
                    to the wants of the poor he was assisted by the deacons as his subordinates. The
                    presbyters formed a college, whose business was that of advising the bishop. Of
                    this college he was the president, and as such he was himself a presbyter, and
                    conversely the presbytery, inclusive of the bishop, formed the governing body of
                    the community.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Tertull.,
                    <hi rend="italic">Apol.,</hi> 39: “Praesident probati quique seniores, honorem
                    istum non pretio sed testimonio adepti.”</p></note> Outside of »the presbytery
                    the individual presbyter as such had no definite official duties. If he
                    baptized, celebrated the eucharist, preached, or the like, this was only as
                    commissioned and deputed by the bishop.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Tertull., <hi rend="italic">De Bapt.,</hi> 17: “Baptismi
                    dandi habet jus summus sacerdos, qui est episcopus; dehinc presbyteri . . . non
                    tamen sine episcopi auctoritate.” In the oldest constitution of the Catholic
                    Church which has come down to us relating to presbyters a regular service of
                    some presbyters in public worship is indeed presupposed <hi rend="italic"
                    >{</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">iavbves iκκ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">η∙ σιaστ. τ.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ày.</hi><hi rend="italic">άττοστόΧοιν,</hi> c. 18), but this fact is unique of
                    its kind.</p></note> Such deputation was frequently necessary, and therefore the
                    presbyter behoved as far as possible to be qualified to teach. As member of the
                    college, which before everything had to do with jurisdiction and discipline, it
                    was required of him that he should be of blameless life, that he should
                    administer just judgment without respect of persons, and that in private life
                    also he should as occasion offered exhort and admonish the faithful and set
                    before them the law of God. The presbyters, who as a rule were expected to be
                    men of advanced years, were, like the bishop and the deacons, chosen by the
                    congregation. Their number was unrestricted, but there were small communities in
                    which they did not exceed three or even two. In rank they were above the
                    deacons, but below the bishop, yet in such a way that the bishop could call them
                    his “co-presbyters.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Compare the regulations laid down in the Arabic text of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Canones</hi><hi rend="italic">Hippolyti</hi> (c. 4): “At the
                    ordination of a presbyter everything is to be done as in the case of a bishop,
                    save that he does not seat himself upon the throne. The same prayer also shall
                    be said as for a bishop, the name of bishop only being left out. The presbj·ter
                    shall in all things be equal with the bishop save in the matters,of presiding
                    and ordaining, for the power to ordain is not given him.”</p></note> As the
                    bishop was not unfrequently chosen from among the deacons, even although in many
                    congregations it may have been the case that the office was invariably bestowed
                    on presbyters, and as the deacons stood in closer personal relation with the
                    bishop than the presbyters, cases of invasion of the rights of the latter by the
                    former began to occur from an early period. There can be no doubt that at the
                    end of the 2d century all presbyters were elected office-bearers, but the way in
                    which Irenaeus speaks makes it quite clear that at an earlier date “presbyter”
                    was also a title of honour borne by worthy and prominent persons in the
                    congregations, who, in virtue of their advanced years, were witnesses for the
                    purity of tradition. Irenaeus, frequently speaking (as he does) of bishops
                    simply as “presbyters/’ also proves that there must have been a time in which
                    the bishop as member of the “synedrium” of the church cannot have held a higher
                    position than the other members of this college.</p>
                <p>Tracing the history upwards from Irenaeus, we find in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Epistles</hi> of Ignatius, which may be assigned perhaps to about 140, the
                    presbyters holding essentially the same <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n698/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0698-0675"/> position as they have at the end of the century.
                    With Ignatius also the presbyters come into account only as a college; according
                    to him they constitute a senate, as it were; he compares them to the college of
                    the apostles, but gives great prominence to their subordination under the
                    bishop, whom he likens to our Lord Himself. Except in the Ignatian <hi
                    rend="italic">Epistles,</hi> however, one finds the presbyters holding a
                    different position within the Christian communities of the period from 90 to
                    140. This is not at all surprising, for there was not at that time any rigid and
                    uniform organization of the congregations at all; as yet no <hi rend="italic"
                    >one</hi> bishop stood at the head of each congregation, and as yet the church
                    constitution was not determined by the idea of <hi rend="italic">office</hi>
                    alone, that of <hi rend="italic">charismata</hi> (spiritual gifts) still having
                    wide scope alongside of the other. Church organization was still influenced by a
                    variety of ways of looking at the question—ways which sometimes crossed each
                    other, and from the combination of which it cannot be doubted that a variety of
                    constitutions resulted. We are not in a position to give a complete view of
                    these, the historical material being insufficient, but points of leading
                    importance can be established. Before all it is of consequence to recognize that
                    in the congregations a threefold organization had place. (1) The duty of
                    edifying and of preaching the gospel was not yet attached to an office but to a
                    charisma. “Service in the word” was the business of apostles, prophets, and
                    teachers who had been awakened by the Spirit and by the Spirit endowed. These
                    were the <hi rend="italic">iγγovμevoι</hi> in the congregations; they alone in
                    the first instance form the class of persons entitled to honour in Christendom;
                    they never belonged to any one congregation exclusively, but were held to be
                    “organs of the Spirit,” given by God to the whole church. (2) In so far as each
                    local church embraced a system of higher and lower functions—each was indeed a
                    little world to itself—it possessed a governing body (οικονόμοι). For the care
                    of the poor, for worship, for correspondence,—in a word, for its “economy,” in
                    the widest sense of that word, the congregation needed controlling officials.
                    These were the bishop and the deacons,—the former for higher, the latter for
                    inferior services; they owed their official position to the congregation, and in
                    the nature of their offices there was, strictly speaking, nothing which could
                    have laid the foundation of any special rank or exaltation. Many of the
                    functions discharged by them nevertheless had the result of making the post of a
                    bishop a very influential one (charge of the worship, control of the funds), and
                    in so far as their service rested upon a charisma <hi rend="italic"
                    >(χάρισμα</hi> ττ}ς αpτιλιj∕zι∕'∈ωs) a certain inner relation between them and
                    the teachers endowed with the gift of the Spirit was established. (3) In so far
                    as the individual congregation was an actual organism in which the varieties of
                    age, of sex, of experience, of manner of life, and of ethical culture continued
                    to exist and which had to be admonished, disciplined, and heeded, it from the
                    nature of the case divided itself into leaders and led, a distinction which
                    would assert itself in every sphere of the congregation’s activities. The
                    leaders were, as might be expected, the “elders” (oi <hi rend="italic"
                    >πpeσ-βυτepoι),</hi> or, so to speak, the patrons; the led were the “younger”
                    members (oi <hi rend="italic">veωτερoι).</hi> Out of this distinction arose
                    equally naturally—for it was impossible for all the ‘‘elders” to take part in
                    the conduct of affairs—the separation of an elected ruling college (oi
                    7rpe&lt;ry0υr∈poι oi <hi rend="italic">πpoισ-τaμevoι)</hi> from the <hi
                    rend="italic">πλήθος</hi><hi rend="italic">(plebs,</hi> λαό?). Thus an “order”
                    <hi rend="italic">(ordo)</hi> arose, placed over the congregation by the
                    congregation itself.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Tertull., <hi rend="italic">De exhort, cast.,</hi> 7: “Differentiam inter
                    ordinem et plebem constituit ecclesiae auctoritas et honor per ordinis consessum
                    εanctificatus.”</p></note> To the presbyters belonged a τιμτ) <hi rend="italic"
                    >καθήκουσα,</hi> —that is to say, the honour which naturallv came from their
                    position in life. In some congregations it may have been long before the elders
                    were <hi rend="italic">chosen,</hi> in others this may have come very soon; in
                    some the sphere of the competency of the presbyters and patrons may have been
                    quite indefinite and in others more precise. In some congregations, lastly, as
                    in those of Asia Minor, the presbyters may have enjoyed particular honour for
                    the special reason that they had known apostles or disciples of apostles
                    personally;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Compare what
                    is said by Papias, Irenaeus, and also by Clement of Alexandria.</p></note> in
                    the majority of congregations this was not the case. With the congregational
                    administration, properly so called, in any case, they had nothing to do.</p>
                <p>We may call the first-named organization the <hi rend="italic">spiritual,</hi>
                    the second the <hi rend="italic">administrative,</hi> the third the <hi
                    rend="italic">patriarchal.</hi> It is obvious that from the first it was
                    impossible they should coexist side by side without coming into contact. Here
                    two facts are of the highest importance. (1) If in any congregation prophets and
                    teachers were wanting, then the administrative officials charged themselves with
                    their function.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See
                    ∆ιδαχ⅛ <hi rend="italic">των αποστόλων,</hi> 15. According to 1 Tim. v. 17 those
                    presbyters are to be counted worthy of special honour <hi rend="italic">ol
                    κoπιωvτes iv</hi> λoγ⅛&gt; <hi rend="italic">καί διδασκαλία.</hi> But this makes
                    it plain that the presbyters were under no obligation to teach.</p></note> (2)
                    The bishops had as such a seat and a voice in the presbyters’ college; every
                    bishop was at the same time a presbyter, whether old or young, but every
                    presbyter was not necessarily also a bishop. In many communities, indeed—as, for
                    example, at Philippi,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Polyc., <hi rend="italic">Ad Philipp., 5, 6,</hi> 11.</p></note> at
                    Ephesus,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Tim. and Acts
                    xx. 17, 28.</p></note> and in Crete<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Ep. to Titus.</p></note> —all the presbyters may possibly
                    also have been bishops, although this is by no means certain; but in other
                    cases—as, for example, in that of Rome, as we learn from the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pastor of</hi><hi rend="italic">Hermas—</hi> all presbyters were not also
                    bishops. Thus it is not the case that originally the bishops were simply
                    identical with the presbyters, and that the one bishop was a gradual development
                    out of the presbyters’ college; on the contrary, the attributes of presbyters
                    and bishops were originally distinct. But, since the bishops had a seat and a
                    voice in the college and exercised special functions of importance besides, they
                    ultimately acquired a higher place.</p>
                <p>The office of presbyter was not during the oldest period (90-140) a <hi
                    rend="italic">spiritual</hi> one. The apostle,, the prophet, the teacher, in a
                    certain sense also even the old bishop and deacon, had a spiritual character,
                    for they possessed a charisma. It was not so with the presbyters; they had no
                    charisma, and the respect in which they were held arose out of the <hi
                    rend="italic">natural</hi> position which they took within the congregations.
                    Hence the newly-discovered Διδαχή των <hi rend="italic">αποστόλων</hi> has
                    nothing to say at all about presbyters, but only about apostles, prophets,
                    teachers, bishops, and deacons. The design of that writing was to give those
                    institutions of the apostles which are peculiar to the Christian community. The
                    system of leaders and led is, however, a matter of order; it does not depend
                    upon the special Christian charismata, and therefore does not impart to the
                    Christian community its peculiar character. But, on the other hand, that the
                    community is God’s building is shown by such marks as these, that the apostles
                    spread the gospel by their inspired preaching, that prophets and teachers edify
                    the churches, that everywhere bishops and deacons are found at work in the
                    churches, endowed with the gift of government and of loving service. Other
                    communities also—towns, temples, synagogues, and the like—have presbyters, but
                    they have no persons endowed with the gift of the Spirit. A sure proof of the
                    correctness of the view just given is found in the circumstance that before the
                    time of Domitian we do not <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n699/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0699-0676"/> possess in Christian literature a single sure
                    testimony to the existence of presbyters. In the genuine epistles of St Paul and
                    in the Epistle to the Hebrews they are not mentioned. In 1 Cor. xii. 28 Paul
                    says that God has given to the church apostles, prophets, teachers, miracles,
                    gifts of healing, help, government; but of presbyters he has not a word to say.
                    Even from passages where he is speaking of the jurisdiction of the
                    congregation—as, for example, in 1 Cor. v., vi.—the presbyters are absent, while
                    in Phil. i. 1 it is the bishops and deacons that he mentions. In the Epistle of
                    James, in the First Epistle of Peter, in the Acts of the Apostles, and in the
                    pastoral epistles the presbyters certainly occur, but no one is able to show
                    that any of these writings are earlier than the age of Domitian. Even Clement of
                    Rome <hi rend="italic">(Ad Cor.,</hi> 42, 4) does not say that the apostles had
                    appointed presbyters in the congregation; he speaks only of bishops and deacons.
                    For this very reason is the statement in Acts xiv. 23 to be looked upon with
                    suspicion. It would be much too precipitate to assert that before the time of
                    Domitian there were no presbyters in the Christian churches; on the contrary, it
                    may be assumed that the distinction between “elder” and “younger” would not fail
                    from the very first to assert itself in these communities, organized as they
                    were so largely on the model of the family. But in this there is no reason for
                    assigning any special importance to the distinction. Out of it there grew very
                    gradually a special rank and gradually the presbyters had assigned to them
                    definite functions; or, in other words, the functions which they had exercised
                    from the first, of exhorting, rebuking, superintending, became recognized
                    ecclesiastical duties and privileges. There is accordingly no need for answering
                    the question whether the Christian “elder” is akin to the Jewish or to any kind
                    of heathen “elder.” This, however, can well be affirmed, that the pattern of the
                    civic senates was not without its influence upon the later development of the
                    presbyterate. As for the communities of Jewish Christians, we know nothing
                    certain about their constitution, and are therefore unable to say anything
                    definite about their presbyters.</p>
                <p>See Hatch, <hi rend="italic">Organization of the Early Christian Churches</hi>
                    (2d ed., 1882), and Harnack’s excursus in the German translation of this work
                    (1883); also Harnack, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Lehre der
                    zwölf Apostel</hi> (1884). (A. HA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
