<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0222-0213-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PLATYPUS (9th edition, volume 19, page 213)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:899294">Ducks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903849">Eggs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1131021">Spurs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950030">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1034543">Naturalists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n87327d">Ducks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3d540">Eggs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63bd91">Spurs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn85">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4416t18p">Coleoptera</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vs35">Naturalists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m61bw1w">Magazines</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206536">Tasmania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n222/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PLATYPUS</label>. The Duck-billed Platypus <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Platypus</hi><hi rend="italic">anatinus)</hi> was the name assigned to one of
                    the most remarkable of known animals by Shaw, who had the good fortune to
                    introduce it to the notice of the scientific world in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Naturalist's Miscellany</hi> (vol. x., 1799). In the following year it was
                    independently described by Blumenbach <hi rend="italic">( Voigts</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Magazin,</hi> ii. p. 205) under the name of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ornithorhynchus paradoxus.</hi> Shaw’s generic name, although having priority
                    to that of Blumenbach, could not be retained, as it had been used at a still
                    earlier time (1793) by Herbst for a genus of <hi rend="italic">Coleoptera.
                    Ornithorhynchus</hi> is therefore now universally adopted as the scientific
                    designation, although Duck-billed Platypus may be conveniently retained as a
                    vernacular appellation. By the colonists it is called “Water-Mole,” but its
                    affinities with the true moles are of the slightest and most superficial
                    description.</p>
                <p>The anatomical differences by which the platypus, and its only ally the echidna,
                    are separated from all other mammals, so as to form a distinct subclass with
                    relationship to the inferior vertebrated classes, have been described in the
                    article <hi rend="smallcaps">Mammalia</hi> (vol. xv. pp. 371 and 377), where <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n223/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0223-0214"/> also will be found the main distinctive
                    characters of the two existing representatives of the group. It is there stated
                    that the early stages of the development of the young are not yet fully known;
                    in fact this was till very recently one of the most interesting problems in
                    zoology to be solved. It has been repeatedly affirmed, in some cases by persons
                    who have had actual opportunities of observation, that the platypus lays eggs;
                    but these statements have been generally received with scepticism and even
                    denial. This much-vexed question has, however, been settled by the researches of
                    Mr W. H. Caldwell (1884), who has found that these animals, although undoubtedly
                    mammals throughout the greater part of their structure, are oviparous, laying
                    eggs, which in the manner of their development bear a close resemblance to the
                    development of those of the <hi rend="italic">Reptilia.</hi> Two eggs are
                    produced at a time, each measuring about three-fourths of an inch in its long
                    and half an inch in its short axis, and enclosed in a strong, flexible, white
                    shell.</p>
                <p>The platypus is pretty generally distributed in situations suitable to its
                    aquatic habits throughout the island of Tasmania and the southern and eastern
                    portions of Australia. Slight variations in the colouring and size of different
                    individuals have given rise to the idea that more than onè species may exist;
                    but all naturalists who have had the opportunity of investigating this question
                    by the aid of a good series of specimens have come to the conclusion that there
                    is but one; and no traces of any extinct allied forms have yet been
                    discovered.</p>
                <p>The length of the animal when full grown is from 18 to 20 inches from the
                    extremity of the beak to the end of the tail, the male being slightly larger
                    than the female. The fur is short, dense, and rather soft to the touch, and
                    composed of an extremely fine and close under-fur, and of longer hairs which
                    project beyond this, each of which is very slender at the base, and expanded,
                    flattened, and glossy towards the free end. The general colour is deep brown,
                    but paler on the under parts. The tail is short, broad, and depressed, and
                    covered with coarse hairs, which in old animals generally become worn off from
                    the under surface. The eyes are small and brown. There is no projecting pinna or
                    ear-conch. The mouth, as is well known, bears a striking resemblance to the bill
                    of a duck. It is covered with a naked skin, a strong fold of which projects
                    outwards around its base. The nostrils are situated near the extremity of the
                    upper surface. There are no true teeth, but their purposes are served by horny
                    prominences, two on each side of each jaw,—those in the front narrow,
                    longitudinal, sharp-edged ridges, and those behind broad, flattened, and
                    molariform. The upper surface of the lateral edges of the mandible has also a
                    number of parallel fine transverse ridges, like those on the bill of a duck. In
                    the cheeks are tolerably capacious pouches, which appear to be used as
                    receptacles for food.</p>
                <p>The limbs are strong and very short, each with five well-developed toes provided
                    with strong claws. In the fore feet the web not only fills the interspaces
                    between the toes, but extends considerably beyond the ends of the long, broad,
                    and somewhat flattened nails, giving great expanse to the foot when used for
                    swimming, though capable of being folded back on the palm when the animal is
                    burrowing or walking on the land. On the hind foot the nails are long, curved,
                    and pointed, and the web extends only to their base. On the heel of the male is
                    a strong, curved, sharply pointed, movable horny spur, directed upwards and
                    backwards, attached by its expanded base to the accessory bone of the tarsus.
                    This spur, which attains the length of nearly an inch, is traversed by a minute
                    canal, terminating in a fine longitudinal slit near the point, and connected at
                    its base with the duct of a large gland situated at the back part of the thigh.
                    The whole apparatus is so exactly analogous in structure to the poison gland and
                    tooth of a venomous snake as to suggest a similar function, but evidence that
                    the platypus ever employs its spur as an offensive weapon has, at all events
                    until lately, been wanting. A case is, however, related by Mr Spicer in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Proceedings</hi> of the Royal Society of Tasmania for 1876 (p.
                    162) of a captured platypus inflicting a severe wound by a powerful lateral and
                    inward movement of the hind legs, which wound was followed by symptoms of active
                    local poisoning. It is not improbable that both the inclination to use the
                    weapon and the activity of the secretion of the gland may be limited to the
                    breeding season, and that their purpose may be, like that of the antlers of deer
                    and many similar organs, for combat among the males. In the young of both sexes
                    the spur is present in a rudimentary condition, but it disappears in the adult
                    females.</p>
                <p>The platypus is aquatic in its habits, passing most of its time in the water or
                    close to the margin of lakes and streams, swimming and diving with the greatest
                    ease, and forming for the purpose of sleeping and breeding deep burrows in the
                    banks, which generally have two orifices, one just above the water level,
                    concealed among long grasses and leaves, and the other below the surface. The
                    passage at first runs obliquely upwards in the bank, sometimes to a distance of
                    as much as 50 feet, and expands at its termination into a cavity, the floor of
                    which is lined with dried grass and leaves, and in which the eggs are laid and
                    the young brought up. Their food consists of aquatic insects, small crustaceans,
                    and worms, which are caught under water, the sand and small stones at the bottom
                    being turned over with their bills to find them. They appear at first to deposit
                    what they have thus collected in their cheek pouches, and when these are filled
                    they rise to the surface and quietly triturate their meal with the horny teeth
                    before swallowing it. Swimming is effected chiefly by the action of the broad
                    forepaws, the hind feet and tail taking little share in locomotion in the water.
                    When asleep they roll themselves into a ball, as shown in the figure. In their
                    native haunts they are extremely timid and wary, and very difficult to approach,
                    being rarely seen out of their burrows in the daytime. Mr A. B. Crowther, who
                    has supplemented the often quoted observations of Dr George Bennett upon the
                    habits of these animals in confinement, says, “They soon become very tame in
                    captivity; in a few days the young <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n224/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0224-0215"/> ones appeared to recognize a call, swimming
                    rapidly to the hand, paddling the water; and it is curious to see their attempts
                    to procure a worm enclosed in the hand, which they greedily take when offered to
                    them. I have noticed that they appear to be able to smell whether or not a worm
                    is contained in the closed hand to which they swim, for they desisted from their
                    efforts if an empty fist was offered.” When irritated they utter a soft low
                    growl, resembling that of a puppy. (w. <hi rend="smallcaps">h. f.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
