<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0098-0089-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PILATE (9th edition, volume 19, page 89)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104504">Samaritans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878645">Copts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1125233">Soldiers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65f63">Soldiers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hd7p16n">Samaritans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n98/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PILATE</label>,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">I.e.,</hi><hi rend="italic">Pilatus,</hi>
                    either derived from <hi rend="italic">pilum,</hi> and thus analogous with the
                    surname <hi rend="italic">Torquatus,</hi> or a contraction of <hi rend="italic"
                    >pileatus.</hi> The pileus was the badge of manumitted slaves, and if this
                    etymology be accepted, the name probably indicates that Pilate was a <hi
                    rend="italic">libertus,</hi> or the descendant of a libertus, of a member of the
                    Samnite gens of the Pontii.</p></note><hi rend="smallcaps">Pontius,</hi> the
                    fifth Roman procurator or “governor” <hi rend="italic">(eττlτpoπo&lt;s,
                    ηγeμ,ωv)</hi> of Judaea, Samaria, and Idumaea, succeeded Valerius Gratus in 26
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> By rank he was a Roman eques, possibly of Samnite
                    extraction; his official appointment he owed to the influence of Sejanus. His
                    ordinary residence as procurator was* at Caesarea, the capital, but from time to
                    time he visited Jerusalem, especially at the greater feasts, and on these
                    occasions he had his <hi rend="italic">bema</hi> in the magnificent palace of
                    Herod the Great, hence called the <hi rend="italic">praetorium.</hi> Apart from
                    the supreme (to him, likely enough, most trivial) incident in his life
                    (“suffered under Pontius Pilate ”) the few facts that are known of him indicate
                    a somewhat exceptional recklessness about awakening Jewish fanaticism, and
                    unscrupulousness as to the means used in quelling its manifestations. Not long
                    after his appointment he allowed his soldiers to carry their eagles and other
                    insignia to Jerusalem, and did not give way until an excited mob had stormed for
                    five whole days and nights around his palace at Caesarea. At a later date, in
                    order to provide for the completion of his aqueduct for bringing water to the
                    city from the “Pools of Solomon,” he appropriated funds from the Corban or
                    sacred treasury; but, profiting by his former experience, when this conduct was
                    resented by the populace he caused some of his. soldiers, disguised as Jewish
                    citizens but armed with staves and daggers, to mingle in the crowd, when many
                    casual spectators as well as rioters were trampled to death. For having hung up
                    in Herod’s palace certain gilt shields dedicated to Tiberius he was in vain
                    remonstrated with by the Jews, but Tiberius, on being appealed to, ordered their
                    transference to the temple of Augustus at Caesarea. Of the circumstançes under
                    which he “mingled the blood” of certain Galilaeans “with their sacrifices”
                    nothing is known; but his cruelty in causing a number of Samaritans to be
                    attacked and massacred when assembled on Mount Gerizim led to a complaint being
                    lodged with Vitellius the legate of Syria, and ultimately to his being deprived
                    of his office early in 36 A.D. According to Eusebius <hi rend="italic">(H.
                    E.,</hi> ii. 7) he was banished to Vienne in Gaul, where various misfortunes
                    caused him at last to commit suicide; the <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi> of
                    Malalas alleges, with less probability, that he was beheaded under Nero. Later
                    legend (see, for example, the apocryphal <hi rend="italic">Mors</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Pilati</hi> mentioned below) has a good deal more to say: his
                    suicide was anticipatory of Caligula’s sentence; the body was thrown into the
                    Tiber and there caused disastrous tempests and floods; it afterwards produced
                    similar effects in the Rhine at Vienne, and finally had to be consigned to a
                    deep pool among the Alps. Local tradition points to a little tarn on Mount
                    Pilatus near Lucerne; if anything is thrown into it the water is forthwith
                    strangely agitated. The devil takes the body from the water on Good Fridays and
                    sets it on a throne where it goes through the gesture of washing its hands. The
                    fact that Pilate allowed Jesus to be crucified is by no means out of keeping
                    with what we know of his indifference to the claims alike of justice and of
                    mercy; that he obviously wished to spare him if this could be done without too
                    much inconvenience to himself has, however, gained him in some quarters very
                    generous recognition; thus Tertullian speaks of him as “jam pro sua conscientia
                    Christianum,” the Copts regard him as a martyr, and the Abyssinian Church has
                    given him a place in its calendar (June 25). This view is reflected in the
                    spurious <hi rend="italic">Paradosis</hi><hi rend="italic">Pilati.</hi> Pilate’s
                    wife, known to tradition as Procla or Claudia Procula, is represented as having
                    been a proselyte of the gate and a secret disciple of Jesus. She is commemorated
                    as a saint in the Greek Church (Oct. 27).</p>
                <p>There is a considerable body of apocryphal literature connected with the name of
                    Pilate. The <hi rend="italic">Acta</hi><hi rend="italic">Pilati,</hi> which
                    forms part of the <hi rend="italic">Evangelium</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Nicodemi,</hi> gives a copious account of the trial of Jesus, intermingled with
                    legendary details of uncertain and very unequal value. It exists in a variety of
                    texts, but in substance is supposed with most probability to date from about the
                    middle of the 2nd century, and to be the work of a Jewish Christian, written for
                    Jews. The <hi rend="italic">Epistola Pilati,</hi> of which there are two
                    differing forms, contains what purports to be Pilate’s account to Tiberius of
                    the resurrection of Jesus. The <hi rend="italic">Paradosis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Pilati</hi> relates his trial, condemnation, and execution at the emperor’s
                    command; Pilate appeals in prayer to Jesus, and, along with Procla his wife, is
                    received as a true penitent into the number of the faithful.. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Mors</hi><hi rend="italic">Pilati</hi> relates the circumstances
                    of his suicide, the casting of his body into the Tiber, its removal to Vienne
                    (explained as “Via Gehennae”), and the final disposal of it at “Losania.” For
                    all <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n99/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0099-0090"/> these apocryphal writings see Tischendorfs <hi
                    rend="italic">Evangelia</hi><hi rend="italic">Apocrypha</hi> (1863).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
