<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0901-0178-0163-05" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ADOPTION (9th edition, volume 1, page 163)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z60x">Hindoos</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0341g">Customs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fc3b">Adoption</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093581">Relationism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n178/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ADOPTION</label>, the act by which the relations of paternity
                    and filiation are recognised as legally existing between persons not so related
                    by nature. Cases of adoption were very frequent among the Greeks and Romans, and
                    the custom was accordingly very strictly regulated in their laws. In Athens the
                    power of adoption was allowed to all citizens who were of sound mind, and who
                    possessed no male offspring of their own, and it could be exercised either
                    during lifetime or by testament. The person adopted, who required to be himself
                    a citizen, was enrolled in the family and <hi rend="italic">demus</hi> of the
                    adoptive father, whose name, however, he did not necessarily assume. In the
                    interest of the next of kin, whose rights were affected by a case of adoption,
                    it was provided that the registration should be attended with certain
                    formalities, and that it should take place at a fixed time—the festival of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Thargelia.</hi> The rights and duties of adopted children
                    were almost identical with those of natural offspring, and could not be
                    renounced except in the case of one who had begotten children to take his place
                    in the family of his adoptive father. Adopted into another family, children
                    ceased to have any claim of kindred or inheritance through their natural father,
                    though any rights they might have through their mother were not similarly
                    affected. Among the Romans the existence of the <hi rend="italic">patria
                        potestas</hi><hi rend="italic">gave</hi> a peculiar significance to the
                    custom of adoption. The motive to the act was not so generally childlessness, or
                    the gratification of affection, as the desire to acquire those civil and agnate
                    rights which were founded on the <hi rend="italic">patria potestas.</hi> It was
                    necessary, however, that the adopter should have no children of his own, and
                    that he should be of such an age as to preclude reasonable expectation of any
                    being born to him. Another limitation as to age was imposed by the maxim <hi
                        rend="italic">adoptio imitatur naturam,</hi> which required the adoptive
                    father to be at least eighteen years older than the adopted children. According
                    to the same maxim eunuchs were not permitted to adopt, as being impotent to
                    beget children for themselves. Adoption was of two kinds according to the state
                    of the person adopted, who might be either still under the <hi rend="italic"
                        >patria potestas (alieni</hi><hi rend="italic">juris),</hi> or his own
                    master <hi rend="italic">(sui juris).</hi> In the former case the act was one of
                        <hi rend="italic">adoption proper,</hi> in the latter case it was styled <hi
                        rend="italic">adrogation,</hi> though the term adoption was also used in a
                    general sense to describe both species. In adoption proper the natural father
                    publicly sold his child to tho adoptive father, and the sale being thrice
                    repeated, the maxim of the Twelve Tables took effect, <hi rend="italic">Si
                        pater</hi><hi rend="italic">filium</hi><hi rend="italic">ter
                        venunduit,</hi><hi rend="italic">filius</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">patre</hi><hi rend="italic">liber esto.</hi> The process was
                    ratified and completed by a fictitious action of recovery brought by the
                    adoptive father against the natural parent, which the latter did not defend, and
                    which was therefore known as the <hi rend="italic">cessio</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >in jure. Adrogation</hi> could be accomplished originally only by the
                    authority of the people assembled in the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n179/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0901-0179-0164"/><hi rend="italic">Comitia,</hi> but from the
                    time of Diocletian it was effected by an imperial rescript. Females could not be
                    adrogated, and, as they did not possess the <hi rend="italic">patria
                        potestas,</hi> they could not exercise the right of adoption in either kind.
                    The whole Roman law on the subject of adoption will be found in Justinian’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Institutes,</hi> lib. i. tit. 11. In Hindoo law, as in nearly
                    every ancient system, wills are almost unknown, and adoptions take their place.
                    The strict law of adoption in India has been relaxed to the extent that a Hindoo
                    widow may adopt when her deceased husband has not done so. Adoption is not
                    recognised in the laws of England and Scotland, though there are legal means by
                    which one may be enabled to assume the name and arms and to inherit the property
                    of a stranger. In France and Germany, which may be said to have embodied the
                    Roman law in their jurisprudence, adoption is regulated according to the
                    principles of Justinian, though with several more or less important
                    modifications, rendered necessary by the usages of these countries respectively.
                    The part played by the legal fiction of adoption in the constitution of
                    primitive society and the civilisation of the race is so important, that Sir
                    Henry S. Maine, in his valuable work on <hi rend="italic">Ancient Law,</hi>
                    expresses the opinion that, had it never existed, the primitive groups of
                    mankind could not have coalesced except on terms of absolute superiority on the
                    one side, and absolute subjection on the other. With the institution of
                    adoption, however, one people might <hi rend="italic">feign itself</hi> as
                    descended from the same stock as the people to whose <hi rend="italic"
                        >sacra</hi><hi rend="italic">gentilicia</hi> it was admitted; and amicable
                    relations were thus established between stocks which, but for this expedient,
                    must have submitted to the arbitrament of the sword with all its
                    consequences.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Adoption,</hi> as a Biblical term, occurs only in the <hi
                        rend="italic">New Testament.</hi> In Old Testament history the practice was
                    unknown, though cases approximating to it have been pointed out. In the New
                    Testament <hi rend="italic">υ</hi><hi rend="italic">ἱ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >o</hi><hi rend="italic">θ</hi><hi rend="italic">∈</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >σ</hi><hi rend="italic">ί</hi><hi rend="italic">α</hi> occurs in several
                    passages, on which is founded one of the leading doctrines of theology.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
