<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0620-0583-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALLEYN, Edward</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 583</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1172973">Wealth</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942628">Gifts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:825145">Bacon</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:914131">Epigrams</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207170">Malta</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nx59">Gifts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49z90b98">Epigrams</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fk98">Devil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7712k">Wealth</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n620/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALLEYN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward</hi></label>, eminent as
                    a stage-player in the reigns of Elizabeth and James I., but better remembered in
                    after-times as the founder of Dulwich college, was born in London, in the parish
                    of St Botolph, Bishopsgate, on the 1st of September 1566. When he was only four
                    years old, his father, an innkeeper, died, and his mother soon afterwards
                    married an actor named Browne. This change in his domestic surroundings brought
                    young Alleyn into early and close association with the stage, for which he
                    possessed great natural aptitude. Thus it chanced that “he was bred a
                    stage-player,” as stated by Fuller (<hi rend="italic">Worthies).</hi> A
                    tenacious memory, a polished elocution, a stateliness of figure and countenance,
                    and a genial temperament, were among the natural and acquired accomplishments
                    that he brought to bear on his chosen pursuit. He gained distine tion in his
                    calling while yet quite a young man, and by common consent was eventually rated
                    as the foremost actor of his time. Several prominent dramatists and other
                    writers of the period have left forcible testimony to his <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n621/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0621-0584"/> rare excellence in the histrionic art. Ben
                    Jonson, a critic nowise prone to exalt the merits of men of mark among his
                    contemporaries, but addicted rather to disparagement, and even, as Drummond of
                    Hawthornden tells, to bitterest detraction, bestowed, nevertheless, unstinted
                    praise on Alleyn’s acting (see Jonson’s <hi rend="italic">Epigrams,</hi> No.
                    89). Nash, in <hi rend="italic">Pierce Pennyless, his Supplication to the
                    Devil,</hi> expresses in prose the same eulogy that Jonson renders in verse.
                    Heywood calls Alleyn “inimitable,” “the best of actors,” and</p>
                <p>“Proteus for shapes and Roscius for a tongue.”</p>
                <p>—(Prologue to Marlowe’s <hi rend="italic">Jew of Malta.)</hi> Peele’s letter to
                    Marlowe, quoted by several of Alleyn’s biographers, telling of a merry meeting
                    at which Shakespeare, Ben Jonson, and Alleyn figure in the front rank of a group
                    of choice spirits, has long been numbered among literary forgeries. (See the
                    Life prefixed to Dyce’s <hi rend="italic">Peele's</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Works,</hi> 1829.)</p>
                <p>But ample and clear evidence remains to show his great celebrity as an actor. His
                    professional earnings as a player formed, however, one only, and not the chief,
                    among several sources from which he drew the wealth that afterwards sustained
                    his great foundation; and his fame as an actor must long since have faded into a
                    dim tradition, of little or no concern to present times, but for the association
                    of his name with an institution around which cluster interesting historic
                    reminiscences, and whose future is fraught with high promise. He inherited house
                    property in Bishops-gate from his father. His marriage, in 1592, with Joan
                    Woodward, stepdaughter to Henslowe, a successful speculator in theatrical and
                    kindred enterprises, brought him eventually much wealth. He became successively
                    part owner in Henslowe’s ventures, and in the end sole proprietor of sundry
                    play-houses and other resorts for the diversion of pleasure-seekers. Among these
                    were the Rose Theatre at Bankside, in close contiguity to Shakespeare’s Globe
                    Theatre; the Paris Garden, in the same vicinage, where were enacted such
                    pastimes as bear-baiting, bullbaiting, and other sports of the period; and the
                    Fortune Theatre in St Luke’s. He filled, too, in conjunction with Henslowe, the
                    post of “master of the king’s games of bears, bulls, and dogs.” He continued to
                    discharge the duties of this office long after he had relinquished his other
                    professional work.</p>
                <p>Alleyn’s ownership in Dulwich lands began in 1606, and further acquisitions, made
                    in the course of the next five years, during which he was gradually breaking
                    away from the actual practice of the histrionic art, though not from theatrical
                    speculations or kindred enterprises, increased his holding to more than 1300
                    acres. His residential connection with Dulwich began in 1607. He occupied the
                    manor-house, a mansion even then very ancient, but which is still tenanted,
                    after many additions and alterations. The priors and abbots of Bermondsey owned
                    and occupied it through the four centuries preceding their expulsion in 1537,
                    when Henry VIII. assigned their house and adjacent church lands to Thomas
                    Calton, grandfather to the Calton who sold his heritage to Alleyn. Some details
                    respecting this and other purchases of neighbouring estates are set forth in
                    Alleyn’s own writing, in a small thick memorandum-book which, with other Alleyn
                    papers preserved at Dulwich, has been carefully scrutinised by the writer of
                    this notice.</p>
                <p>The landed property stretches from the crest of that range of Surrey hills on
                    whose summit rests the Crystal Palace, to the crest of the parallel ridge, three
                    miles nearer London, known in its several portions as Herne Hill, Denmark Hill,
                    and Champion Hill. Alleyn acquired this large suburban property for little more
                    than £10,000, which may be estimated as equivalent to £50,000 in the present
                    day. But the present value of the lands which he bought for such a price is
                    hardly under a million and a-half sterling, so enormous has been the rise in the
                    value of land in and near London. Alleyn had barely got full possession of this
                    property before the question how to dispose of it began to press upon him. He
                    was still childless, after twenty years of wedded life. Then it was that the
                    prosperous player—the man “so acting to the life that he made any part to become
                    him” (Fuller, <hi rend="italic">Worthies)</hi> —began “playing the last act of
                    his life so well” (Bacon’s Letter to the Marquis of Buckingham, dated 18th
                    August 1618), as to gain the general applause of his own age, and a large
                    measure of admiration in after times. He built and endowed in his own lifetime
                    the College of God’s Gift at Dulwich. All was completed in 1617, except the
                    charter or deed of incorporation for setting his lands in mortmain. Tedious
                    delays occurred in the Star Chamber, where Lord Chancellor Bacon was scheming to
                    bring the pressure of kingly authority to bear on Alleyn with the aim of
                    securing a large portion of the proposed endowment for the maintenance of
                    lectureships at Oxford and Cambridge. Alleyn finally carried his point, and the
                    College of God’s Gift at Dulwich was founded, and endowed under letters patent
                    of James I. dated 21st of June 1619. The college, as thus incorporated,
                    consisted of twelve “poor scholars” and as many pensioners, the latter
                    comprising equal numbers of men and women— “poor brethren” and “poor
                    sisters,”—together with a teaching and governing staff of six higher officials.
                    These latter included a master and a warden, who were always to be of the
                    founder’s surname, and four fellows, all “graduates and divines,” among whom
                    were apportioned the ministerial work of the chapel, the instruction of the
                    boys, and the supervision of the almspeople or pensioners. The scholars and
                    pensioners were to be drawn in equal numbers from the four London parishes out
                    of which the founder drew his wealth. A curious legend, dating from the time of
                    the founder, and always current afterwards among the pensioners on his bounty,
                    tells that he was scared into hiε generous and charitable scheme by an
                    apparition of the devil, <hi rend="italic">in propria persona,</hi> among some
                    theatrical demons in a drama in which he was acting. In the fright thus
                    occasioned he was said to have made a vow, which he redeemed in the founding of
                    Dulwich College.</p>
                <p>Alleyn was never a member of his own foundation, as stated by Heywood, and copied
                    by succeeding writers. The college records clearly set this point at rest. But
                    he continued to the close of his life to guide and control the affairs of his
                    foundation, under powers reserved to himself in the letters patent. His diary
                    shows that he mixed much and intimately in the daily life of the college. Many
                    of the jottings in that curious record of daily doings and incidents favour the
                    inference that he was genial, kind, amiable, and withal a religious man. His
                    fondness for his old professional work is indicated by the fact that he engaged
                    the boys in occasional theatrical performances. At a festive gathering on the
                    6th of January 1622 “the boyes play’d a playe.”</p>
                <p>Shakespeare’s name is interwoven with local traditions bearing on Alleyn’s life
                    at Dulwich, and the links of association between these famous contemporaries
                    afford strong antecedent probability that the tradition sprang from something
                    more solid than “such stuff as dreams are made of.” Each began and closed his
                    professional career as a stage-player in nearly the self-same period and in
                    neighbouring theatres. During several years they were near neighbours in their
                    homes at Bankside, then the headquarters of players and play-houses. Leading
                    actors then, as afterwards, came much in contact with the living authors whose
                    creations they personated. Alleyn performed in “Leir,” the “Moore of Venis,”
                    “Romeo,” <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n622/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0622-0585"/> "Pericles,” and “Henry VIII.,” as appears from
                    his inventory of his own theatrical wardrobe. Among the intimate friends of both
                    were Ben Jonson, Michael Drayton, and other members of the goodly company of
                    poets and dramatists whose genius shed a lustre on their day. Shakespeare had
                    not finally betaken himself to the retirement of Stratford-on-Avon until seven
                    years after Alleyn took up his abode at Dulwich. In the face of all these facts,
                    it can hardly be said the local tradition is groundless, though no direct proof
                    has yet been brought to bear on the point.</p>
                <p>Alleyn’s first wife died in the summer of 1623. In December of the same year he
                    married Constance Donne, who survived him. This lady was a daughter of Dr Donne,
                    dean of St Paul’s. Her maiden name was misquoted by an early biographer. This
                    mistake gave rise to the further error which attributes to Alleyn a third wife.
                    He died in November 1626, in the sixty-first year of his age. His gravestone at
                    Dulwich fixes the date of his death on 21st November, but there are grounds for
                    the belief that the true date is the 25th of the same month.</p>
                <p>Besides dispensing bounties within the bounds of his college, Alleyn provided, by
                    an after-thought, some years later than his deed of foundation, for certain
                    extensions of the benefits of his endowment. But successive actions at law,
                    carried on at various periods, resulted in the ruling that it was not within the
                    competence of the founder to divert any portion of the revenues of his
                    foundation to the use of others than the members thereof, as specified in the
                    letters patent. Chief among the good intents on the part of the founder that
                    were thus frustrated was his scheme for embracing in the school work within the
                    college as many outsiders as would bring the total number to eighty boys,
                    inclusive of the twelve foundationers. But as this was not within the bond, his
                    successors in the administration of the trust, for more than two centuries after
                    his death, declined the work. In the latter part of that period, decay, and not
                    development, fixed on the time-honoured memorial of Alleyn’s high but thwarted
                    purposes the stigma of a public scandal. Then came, in 1842, a grudging and
                    partial, rather than a full and loyal, concession towards the realisation of the
                    founder’s aims. Finally, however, an Act of Parliament, in 1857, extinguished
                    the stagnant and unprogressive corporation. Alleyn’s College of God’s Gift at
                    Dulwich entered thenceforward on that prosperous career which already links its
                    name with the front rank of institutions doing good service in the educational
                    work of the day. (J. <hi rend="smallcaps">go.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
