<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0901-0020-0005-06" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ABATTOIR (9th edition, volume 1, page 5)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1010167">Marketing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010316">Markets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1013210">Meat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881894">Cousins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gs41">Marketing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r22w">Markets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jm0p">Abattoirs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n20/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ABATTOIR</label>, from <hi rend="italic">abattre,</hi>
                    primarily signifies a slaughterhouse proper, or place where animals are killed
                    as distinguished from <hi rend="italic">boucheries</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >étaux</hi><hi rend="italic">publics,</hi> places where the dead meat is
                    offered for sale. But the term is also employed to designate a complete meat
                    market, of which the abattoir proper is merely part.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the first indication of the existence of abattoirs may be found in the
                    system which prevailed under the Emperors in ancient Rome. A corporation or
                    guild of butchers undoubtedly existed there, which delegated to its officers the
                    duty of slaughtering the beasts required to supply the city with meat. The
                    establishments requisite <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n21/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0901-0021-0006"/> for this purpose were at first scattered
                    about the various streets, but were eventually confined to one quarter, and
                    formed the public meat market. This market, in the time of Nero, was one of the
                    most imposing structures in the city, and some idea of its magnificence has been
                    transmitted to us by a delineation of it preserved on an ancient coin. As the
                    policy and customs of the Romans made themselves felt in Gaul, the Roman system
                    of abattoirs, if it may be so called, was introduced there in an imperfect form.
                    A clique of families in Paris long exercised the special function of catering
                    for the public wants in respect of meat. But as the city increased in magnitude
                    and popidation, the necessity of keeping slaughter-houses as much as possible
                    apart from dwelling-houses became apparent. As early as the time of Charles IX.,
                    the attention of the French authorities was directed to the subject, as is
                    testified by a decree passed on the 25th of February 1567. But although the
                    importance of the question was frequently recognised, no definite or decided
                    step seems to have been taken to effect the contemplated reform until the time
                    of Napoleon I. The evil had then reached a terribly aggravated form.
                    Slaughter-houses abutted on many of the principal thoroughfares; the traffic was
                    impeded by the constant arrival of foot-sore beasts, whose piteous cries pained
                    the ear; and rivulets of blood were to be seen in the gutters of the public
                    streets. The constant accumulation of putrid offal tainted the atmosphere, and
                    the Seine was polluted by being used as a common receptacle for slaughter-house
                    refuse. This condition of things could not be allowed to continue, and on the
                    9th of February 1810, a decree was passed authorising the construction of
                    abattoirs in the outskirts of Paris, and appointing a Commission, to which was
                    committed the consideration of the entire question.</p>
                <p>The resιdt of the appointment of this Commission was the construction of the five
                    existing abattoirs, which were formally opened for business on the 15th of
                    September 1818. The Montmartre abattoir occupies 8¾ English acres;</p>
                <p>Ménilmontant, 10¼ acres; Grenelle, 7¾; Du Roule, 5¾; and Villejuif, 5½. The first
                    two contain each 64 slaughterhouses and the same number of cattle-sheds; the
                    third, 48; and each of the others 32. The dimensions of each of the
                    slaughter-houses is about 29 ½ feet by 13. The general arrangement of the
                    abattoirs will be understood from the preceding plan of that of
                    Ménilmontant.</p>
                <p>The component parts of a French abattoir are—1. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Echaudoirs,</hi> which is the name given by the Paris butcher to the
                    particular division allotted to him for the purpose of knocking down his beasts;
                    2. <hi rend="italic">Bouveries et</hi><hi rend="italic">Bergeries,</hi> the
                    places set apart for the animals waiting to be slaughtered, where the animals,
                    instead of being killed at once, after a long and distressing journey, when
                    their blood is heated and their flesh inflamed, are allowed to cool and rest
                    till the body is restored to its normal healthy condition; 3. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fondeurs,</hi> or boiling-down establishments; and, 4. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Triperies,</hi> which are buildings set apart for the cleaning of the tripe
                    of bullocks, and the fat, heads, and tripe of sheep and calves. Besides these, a
                    Paris abattoir contains <hi rend="italic">Logements des</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >agens,</hi><hi rend="italic">Magasins, Réservoirs, Voiries, Lieux
                        d'aisance, Voûtes, Remises et écuries, Parcs aux Boeufs,</hi> &amp;c., and
                    is provided with an abundant supply of water. All the abattoirs are under the
                    control of the municipal authorities, and frequent inspections are made by
                    persons regularly appointed for that purpose.</p>
                <p>The abattoirs are situated within the barriers, each at a distance of about a
                    mile aud three-quarters from the heart of the city, in districts where human
                    habitations are still comparatively few. There are two principal markets from
                    which the abattoirs at Paris are supplied,—the one at Poissy, about 13 miles to
                    the north-west, and the other at Sceaux, about 5 miles and a quarter to the
                    south of the city. There are also two markets for cows and calves, namely, La
                    Chapelle and Les Bernadins.</p>
                <p>The Paris abattoirs were until recently the most perfect specimens of their
                    class; and even now, although in some of their details they have been surpassed
                    by the new Islington meat market, for their complete and compact arrangement
                    they remain unrivalled.</p>
                <p>The example set by Paris in this matter has been followed in a more or less
                    modified form by most of the principal Continental towns, and the system of
                    abattoirs has become almost universal in France.</p>
                <p>The condition of London in this important sanitary respect was for a long period
                    little more endurable than that of Paris before the adoption of its reformed
                    system. Smithfield market, situated in a very populous neighbourhood, continued
                    till 1852 to be an abomination to the town and a standing reproach to its
                    authorities. No fewer than 243,537 cattle and 1,455,249 sheep were sold there in
                    1852, to be afterwards slaughtered in the crowded courts and thoroughfares of
                    the metropolis. But public opinion at length forced the Legislature to
                    interfere, and the corporation was compelled to abandon Smithfield market and to
                    provide a substitute for it elsewhere.</p>
                <p>The site selected was in the suburb of Islington, and the designs for the work
                    were prepared by Mr Bunning. The first stone was laid March 24, 1854, and the
                    market was opened by Prince Albert, June 15, 1855. The Islington market is
                    undoubtedly the most perfect of its kind. It occupies a space of some 20 acres
                    on the high land near the Pen-tonville prison, and is open to both native and
                    foreign cattle, excepting beasts from foreign countries under quarantine.</p>
                <p>In connection with the Islington cattle market are a few slaughter-houses, half
                    of which were originally public, and half rented to private individuals; but at
                    present they are all practically private, and the majority of the cattle sold
                    are driven away and killed at private slaughter-houses. In this respect the
                    London system differs from that of Paris; and it may be said for the former that
                    the meat is less liable to be spoiled by being carted to a distance, and is
                    therefore probably delivered in better condition; but the latter secures that
                    great desideratum, the practical extinction of isolated slaughter-houses.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n22/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0022-0007"/>
                <p>The Edinburgh abattoir, erected in 1851 by the corporation, from designs prepared
                    by Mr David Cousin, the city architect, is the best as regards both construction
                    and management in the United Kingdom. It occupies an area of four acres and a
                    quarter, surrounded by a screen-wall, from which, along the greater part of its
                    length, the buildings are separated by a considerable open space. Opposite the
                    principal gateway is a double row of buildings, extending in a straight line to
                    about 376 feet in length, with a central roadway (marked AA in the annexed
                    plan), 25 feet wide. There are three separate blocks of building on each side of
                    the roadway, the central one being 140 feet in length, and the others 100 feet
                    each—cross-roads 18 feet wide separating the blocks. These ranges of building,
                    as well as two smaller blocks that are placed transversely behind the eastern
                    central block, are divided into compartments, numbering 42 in all, and all
                    arranged on the same plan. Next the roadway is the slaughtering-booth (BB), 18
                    feet by 24, and 20 feet in height, and behind this is a shed (CC) 18 feet by 22,
                    where the cattle are kept before being slaughtered. All the cattle are driven
                    into these sheds by a back-entrance, through the small enclosed yards (DD). The
                    large doors of the booths are hung by balance weights, and slide up and down, so
                    as to present no obstruction either within the booth or outside. By a series of
                    large ventilators along the roof, and by other contrivances, the
                    slaughtering-booths are thoroughly ventilated. Great precautions have been used
                    to keep rats out of the buildings. To effect this, the booths are laid with
                    thick well-dressed pavement, resting on a stratum of concrete 12 inches thick,
                    and the walls, to the height of 7 feet, are formed of solid ashlar; the
                    roadways, too, are laid with concrete, and causewayed with dressed whinstone
                    pavement; and the drainage consists entirely of glazed earthenware tubes.</p>
                <p>The ground on which the abattoir is built was previously connected with a
                    distillery, and contains a well 100 feet deep (E), which, with the extensive
                    system of tunnels attached to it, provides the establishment with an abundant
                    supply of pure water. By means of a steam-engine (F), introduced in 1872, the
                    water is pumped up into a raised tank (G), whence it is distributed to the
                    different booths and sheds, as well as for scouring the roadways and drains. The
                    steam from the engine is utilised in heating water for the numerous cast-iron
                    tanks required in the operations of cleansing and dressing the tripery (H) and
                    pig slaughtering-house (I). By an ingenious arrangement of rotary brushes driven
                    by the steam-engine,—the invention of Mr Rutherford, the superintendent,—the
                    tripe is dressed in a superior manner, and at greatly less cost than by the
                    tedious and troublesome method of handcleaning.</p>
                <p>By the Edinburgh Slaughter-Houses Act of 1850, the management is vested in the
                    city authorities. Booths are let at a statutory rent of £8 each per annum, and,
                    in addition to this, gate-dues are payable for every beast entering the
                    establishment. The present rates for tenants of booths are 1½d. for an ox or
                    cow, fd. for a calf or pig, and ¼d. for a sheep. Common booths are provided for
                    butchers who are not tenants, on payment of double gate-dues. The city claims
                    the blood, gut, and manure. The tripe and feet are dressed for the trade without
                    extra charge.</p>
                <p>The blood was formerly collected in large casks, and disposed of for
                    manufacturing purposes. This necessitated the storage of it for several days,
                    causing in warm weather a very offensive effluvium. It even happened at times,
                    when there was little demand for the commodity, that the blood had to be sent
                    down the drains. All nuisance is now avoided, and the amount received annually
                    for the blood has risen from between £200 and £450 to from £800 to £1200, by a
                    contract into which Messrs Smith and Forrest of Manchester have entered w'ith
                    the city authorities, to take over the whole blood at a fixed price per beast.
                    They have erected extensive premises and apparatus at their own cost, for
                    extracting from the blood the albumen, for which there is great demand in
                    calico-printing, and for converting the clot into manure.</p>
                <p>In connection with the establishment is a boiling-house, where all meat unfit for
                    human food is boiled down and destroyed. The number of carcases seized by the
                    inspector, and sent to the boiling-house, during the 5½ years ending with the
                    close of 1872, amounted to 1449, giving a weight of upwards of 400,000
                    pounds.</p>
                <p>Before the erection of these buildings, private slaughterhouses were scattered
                    all over the city, often in the most populous districts, where, through want of
                    drainage and imperfect ventilation, they contaminated the whole neighbourhood.
                    Since the opening of the public abattoir, all private slaughtering, in the city
                    or within a mile of it, is strictly prohibited.</p>
                <p>Few of the provincial towns in Great Britain have as yet followed the example of
                    London and Edinburgh. In some instances improvements on the old system have been
                    adopted, but Great Britain is still not only far behind her foreign neighbours
                    in respect of abattoirs, but has even been excelled by some of her own
                    dependencies. In America abattoirs are numerous, and at Calcutta and other towns
                    in British India, the meat markets present a very creditable appearance from
                    their cleanliness and systematic arrangement. (c. N. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
