<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0095-0080-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ACCENT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 80</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4k93192h">Rhythm</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f4j">Ear</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4fn1111w">Scholars</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42z12q4d">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1010775">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198642">Conquest</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1169292">Vowels</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1097273">Rhythm</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n95/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ACCENT</label>, in reading or speaking, is the stress or
                    pressure of the voice upon a <hi rend="italic">syllable</hi> of a word. The
                    derivation of the term (Lat. <hi rend="italic">accentus,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >quasi adcantus)</hi> clearly shows that it was employed by the classical
                    grammarians to express the production of a musical effect. Its origin is
                    therefore to be sought in the natural desire of man to gratify the ear by
                    modulated sound, and probably no language exists in which it does not play a
                    more or less important part. “Only a machine,” says Professor Blackie <hi
                    rend="italic">(Place and Power of Accent in Language,</hi> in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Transactions of the Loyal Society of Edinburgh,</hi> 1871), “could
                    produce a continuous series of sounds in undistinguished monotonous repetitions
                    like the <hi rend="italic">turn, turn, turn,</hi> of a drum; a rational being
                    using words for a rational purpose to manifest his thoughts and feelings,
                    necessarily accents both words and sentences in some way or other.” That tho
                    accentuation of some languages is more distinct, various, aud effective than
                    that of others is beyond question, but there are none, so far as we know, in
                    which its power is not felt. The statement sometimes made, that the French have
                    no accent in their words, can only mean that their accent is less emphatic or
                    less variously so than that of certain other nations. If it means more, it is
                    not merely an error, but an absurdity. From this conception of the subject, it
                    is obvious that accent must be fundamentally the same thing in all languages,
                    and must aim more or less successfully at the same results, however diverse the
                    rules by which it is governed. But there are, nevertheless, important
                    differences between the conditions under which accent operated in the classical,
                    and those in which it operates in modern tongues. It did not wholly determine
                    the rhythm, nor in the least affect the metre of classical verse; it did not fix
                    the quantity or length of classical syllables. It was a musical element
                    superadded to the measured structure of prose and verse.</p>
                <p>Passing over the consideration of the accentual system of the Hebrews with the
                    single remark, that it exhibits, though with more elaborate and complicated
                    expression, most of the characteristics both of Greek and English accent, we
                    find that the Greeks employed three grammatical accents, viz., the <hi
                    rend="italic">acute accent</hi> ('), which shows when the tone of the voice is
                    to be raised; the <hi rend="italic">grave accent</hi> ('), when it is to be
                    depressed; and the <hi rend="italic">circumflex accent (^),</hi> composed of
                    both the acute and the grave, and pointing out a kind of undulation of the
                    voice. The Latins have made the same use as the Greeks of these three accents,
                    and various modern nations, French, English, &amp;c., have also adopted them. As
                    to the Greek accents, now seen both in manuscripts and printed books, there has
                    been great dispute about their antiquity and use. But the following things seem
                    to be undoubtedly taught by the ancient grammarians and rhetoricians:—(1.) That
                    by <hi rend="italic">accent</hi><hi rend="italic">(προσωδία, τόνος)</hi> the
                    Greeks understood the elevation or falling of the voice on a particular syllable
                    of a word, either absolutely, or in relation to its position in a sentence,
                    accompanied with an <hi rend="italic">intension</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >remission</hi> of the vocal utterance on that syllable (<hi rend="italic"
                    >∈</hi><hi rend="italic">πί</hi><hi rend="italic">τασιs</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                    >ἃ</hi><hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic">ε</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >σις),</hi> occasioning a marked predominance of that syllable over the other
                    syllables of the word. The predominance thus given, however, had no effect
                    whatever on the quantity —long or short—of the accented syllable. The accented
                    syllable in Greek as in English, might be long or it might be short; elevation
                    and emphasis of utterance being one thing, and prolongation of the vocal sound
                    quite another thing, as any one acquainted with the first elements of music will
                    at once perceive. The difficulty which many modern scholars have experienced in
                    conceiving how a syllable could be accented and not lengthened, has arisen
                    partly from a complete want of distinct ideas on the nature of the elements of
                    which human speech is composed, and partly also from a vicious practice which
                    has long prevailed in the English schools, of reading Greek, not according to
                    the laws of its own accentuation, but according to the accent of Latin handed
                    down to us through the Roman Catholic Church. For the rules of Latin
                    accentuation are, as Quintilian and Cicero and the grammarians expressly
                    mention, very different from the Greek; and the long syllable of a word has the
                    accent in Latin in a hundred cases, where the musical habit of the Greek ear
                    placed it upon the short. There is, besides, a vast number of words in Greek
                    accented on the last syllable (like <hi rend="italic">voluntee'r, ambusca'de
                    ,</hi> in English), of which not a single instance occurs in the Latin
                    language<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n96/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0096-0081"/>. Partly, however, from ignorance, partly from
                    carelessness, and partly perhaps from stupidity, our scholars transferred the
                    pronunciation of the more popular learned language to that which was less known;
                    and with the help of time and constant usage, so habituated themselves to
                    identify the accented with the long syllable, according to the analogy of the
                    Latin, that they began seriously to doubt the possibility of pronouncing
                    otherwise. English scholars have long ceased to recognise its existence, and
                    persist in reading Greek as if the accentual marks meant nothing at all. Even
                    those who allow (like Mr W. G. Clark and Professor Munro) that ancient Greek
                    accent denoted an elevation of voice or tone, are still of opinion that it is
                    impossible to reproduce it in modern times. “Here and there,” says the former
                    <hi rend="italic">(Cambridge Journal of Philology,</hi> vol. i. 1868), “a person
                    may be found with such an exquisite ear, and such plastic organs of speech, as
                    to be able to reproduce the ancient distinction between the length and tone of
                    syllables accented and unaccented, and many not so gifted may fancy that they
                    reproduce it when they do nothing of the kind. For the mass of boys and men,
                    pupils as well as teachers, the distinction is practically impossible.” But, in
                    spite of such pessimist views, it may, on the whole, be safely asserted that
                    since the appearance of a more philosophical spirit in philology, under the
                    guidance of Hermann, Boeckh, and other master-minds among the Germans, the best
                    grammarians have come to recognise the importance of this element of ancient
                    Hellenic enunciation, while not a few carry out their principles into a
                    consistent practice. The only circumstance, indeed, that prevents our English
                    scholars from practically recognising the element of accent in classical
                    teaching, is the apprehension that this would interfere seriously with the
                    practical inculcation of quantity; an apprehension in which they are certainly
                    justified by the practice of the modern Greeks, who have given such a
                    predominance to accent, as altogether to subordinate, and in many cases
                    completely overwhelm quantity; and who also, in public token of this departure
                    from the classical habit of pronunciation, regularly compose their verses with a
                    reference to the spoken accent only, leaving the quantity —as in modern language
                    generally— altogether to the discretion of the poet. But, as experiment will
                    teach any one that there is no necessity whatever in the nature of the human
                    voice for this confusion of two essentially different elements, it is not
                    unlikely that English scholars will soon follow the example of the Germans, and
                    read Greek prose at least systematically according to the laws of classical
                    speech, as handed down to us by the grammarians of Alexandria and Byzantium. In
                    the recitation of classical verse, of course, as it was not constructed on
                    accentual principles, the skilful reader will naturally allow the musical
                    accent, or the emphasis of the rhythm to overbear, to a great extent, or
                    altogether to overwhelm, the accent of the individual word; though with regard
                    to the recitation of verse, it will always remain a problem how far the ancients
                    themselves did not achieve an <hi rend="italic">“</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >accentuum</hi><hi rend="italic">cum quantitate</hi><hi rend="italic">apta
                    conciliatio,”</hi> such as that which Hermann <hi rend="italic">(De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">emendanda ratione, &amp;</hi><hi rend="italic">c.)</hi> describes
                    as the perfection of a polished classical enunciation. A. historic survey of the
                    course of learned opinion on the subject of accent, from the age of Erasmus down
                    to the present day, forms an interesting and important part of Professor
                    Blackie’s essay quoted above. See Pennington’s work on Greek Pronunciation,
                    Cambridge, 1844; the German work on Greek Accent by Göttling (English), London,
                    1831; and Blackie’s essay on the <hi rend="italic">Place and Power of
                    Accent,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Royal Society of
                    Edinburgh,</hi> 1870-71.</p>
                <p>If there is any perplexity regarding the nature or influence of classical accent,
                    there is none about English. <hi rend="italic">It</hi> does not conflict or
                    combine with the modulations of quantity. It is the sole determining element in
                    our metrical system. Almost the very earliest of our authors, the Venerable
                    Bede, notices this. In defining rhythm he says—“It is a modulated composition of
                    words, not according to the laws of metre, but adapted in the number of its
                    syllables to the judgment of the ear, <hi rend="italic">as are the verses of our
                    vulgar poets” (Bede, Op.</hi> vol. i. p. 57, ed. 1553). We have, of course, long
                    vowels and short, like the Greeks and the Romans, but we do not regulate our
                    verse by them; and our mode of accentuation is sufficiently despotic to
                    occasionally almost change their character, so that a long vowel shall seem
                    short, and <hi rend="italic">vice versa.</hi> In reality this is not so. The
                    long vowel remains long, but then its length gives it no privilege of place in a
                    verse. It may modify the enunciation, it may increase the roll of sound, but a
                    short vowel could take its place without a violation of metre. Take the word <hi
                    rend="italic">far,</hi> for example; there the vowel <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is
                    long, yet in the line</p>
                <l part="N"> “O Moon, far-spooming Ocean bows to thee,” </l>
                <p>it is not necessary that the <hi rend="italic">a</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
                    >far</hi> should be long; a short vowel would do as well for metrical purposes,
                    and would even bring out more distinctly the accentuation of the syllable <hi
                    rend="italic">spoom.</hi></p>
                <p>Originally English accent was upon the root, and not upon inflectional syllables.
                    Göttling finds the same principle operating in Greek, but in that language it
                    certainly never exercised the universal sway it does in the earlier forms of
                    English. In the following passage from <hi rend="italic">Beowulf,</hi> the
                    oldest monument of English literature, belonging, in its first form, to a period
                    even anterior to the invasion of Britain by the Angles and Saxons, we shall put
                    the accented or emphatic syllables in italics:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">Stráet</hi> waes
                            <hi rend="italic">stán-fah . .</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The street was of variegated
                            stone,</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">stíg</hi>
                            wísode</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>the path directed</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">gum</hi> um aet-
                            <hi rend="italic">gaed</hi> ere . .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>the men together;</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">gúd</hi>-byrne scán
                            ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>the war-corselet shone</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">heard, hond-</hi>
                            locen <hi rend="italic">. . . .</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>hard, hand-locked;</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">hring-íren</hi>
                            scír ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>the ring-iron bright</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">song</hi> in
                            searwum . . .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>sang in their trappings,</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>pá híe tó <hi rend="italic">sele</hi>
                            furdum</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>when they to the hall
                            forward</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>in hyra <hi rend="italic"
                            >grýre-geat</hi> wum <hi rend="italic">.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>in their terrible armour</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">gang</hi> an cwomon
                            . . .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>came to go.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>It will be observed that in these verses the accent (not to be confounded with
                    the mark which is used in Anglo-Saxon to show that the vowel over which it is
                    placed is long) is invariably on a monosyllable, or on the root part of a word
                    of more than one syllable. The passage is also a good illustration of what has
                    previously been stated, that the metre or rhythm in English is determined not by
                    the vowel-quantity of a syllable, but by the stress of the voice on particular
                    syllables, whether the vowels are long or short. In the older forms of English
                    verse the accent is somewhat irregular; or, to put it more accurately, the
                    number of syllables intervening between the recurrent accents is not definitely
                    fixed. Sometimes two or more intervene, sometimes none at all. Take, for
                    example, the opening lines of Langland’s poem, entitled the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vision of Piers the Plowman:—</hi></p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> “In a <hi rend="italic">so</hi> mer <hi rend="italic">se</hi> son </l>
                    <l part="N"> Whan soft was the sonne, </l>
                    <l part="N"> I <hi rend="italic">shope</hi> me in <hi rend="italic"
                        >shroudes,</hi></l>
                    <l part="N"> As I a <hi rend="italic">shepe</hi> were, </l>
                    <l part="N"> In <hi rend="italic">ha</hi> bit as an <hi rend="italic">he</hi>
                        remite </l>
                    <l part="N"> Un <hi rend="italic">ho</hi> ly of workes, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Went <hi rend="italic">wide</hi> in this <hi rend="italic"
                        >world</hi></l>
                    <l part="N"><hi rend="italic">Wonders</hi> to here. </l>
                    <l part="N"> Ac on a <hi rend="italic">May</hi><hi rend="italic">morn</hi> ynge </l>
                    <l part="N"> On <hi rend="italic">Ma</hi> luerne hulles, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Me by <hi rend="italic">fel</hi> a <hi rend="italic">fer</hi> ly
                        <hi rend="italic">,</hi></l>
                    <l part="N"> Of <hi rend="italic">fairy,</hi> me thoughte; </l>
                    <l part="N"> I was <hi rend="italic">wery</hi> for <hi rend="italic">wand</hi>
                        red <hi rend="italic">,</hi></l>
                    <l part="N"> And <hi rend="italic">went</hi> me to reste </l>
                    <l part="N"> Under a <hi rend="italic">brode</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >banke</hi></l>
                    <l part="N"> By a <hi rend="italic">bornes</hi> side. </l>
                    <l part="N"> And as I <hi rend="italic">lay</hi> and Zoned, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And <hi rend="italic">lok</hi> ed in the waters, </l>
                    <l part="N"> I <hi rend="italic">slom</hi> bred in a <hi rend="italic">slep</hi>
                        yng <hi rend="italic">,</hi></l>
                    <l part="N"> It <hi rend="italic">sweyu</hi> ed so merye,” </l>
                </lg>
                <p>But no matter how irregular the time elapsing between the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n97/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0097-0082"/> recurrence of the accents, they are always on the
                    rootsyllables.</p>
                <p>The Norman Conquest, however, introduced a different system, which gradually
                    modified the rigid uniformity of the native English accentuation. The change is
                    visible as early as the end of the 12th century. By the middle of the 14th, that
                    is to say, in the age of Chaucer, it is in full operation. Its origin is thus
                    explained by Mr Marsh, in his <hi rend="italic">Origin and History of the
                    English Language</hi> (Lond., 1862) :—“The vocabulary of the French language is
                    derived, to a great extent, from Latin words deprived of their terminal
                    inflections. The French adjectives <hi rend="italic">mortal</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">fatal</hi> are formed from the Latin <hi rend="italic"
                    >mortalis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">fatalis,</hi> by dropping the inflected
                    syllable; the French nouns <hi rend="italic">nation</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >condition</hi> from the Latin accusatives <hi rend="italic">nationem,
                    conditionem,</hi> by rejecting the <hi rend="italic">em</hi> final. In most
                    cases, the last syllable retained in the French derivatives was prosodically
                    long in the Latin original; and either because it was also accented, or because
                    the slight accent which is perceivable in the French articulation represents
                    temporal length, the stress of the voice was laid on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >final</hi> syllable of all these words. When we borrowed such words from the
                    French we took them with their native accentuation; and as accent is much
                    stronger in English than in French, the <hi rend="italic">final</hi> syllable
                    was doubtless more forcibly enunciated in the former than in the latter
                    language.” The new mode of accentuation soon began to affect even words of pure
                    English origin— <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Robert of
                    Gloucester</hi> we find fals <hi rend="italic">hede</hi> instead of <hi
                    rend="italic">fals</hi> hede, tid <hi rend="italic">inge</hi> instead of <hi
                    rend="italic">tid</hi> inge, trewe <hi rend="italic">hede</hi> instead of <hi
                    rend="italic">trewe</hi> hede, glad <hi rend="italic">dore</hi> instead of <hi
                    rend="italic">glad</hi> dore <hi rend="italic">,</hi> wis <hi rend="italic"
                    >liche</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">wis</hi> liche, begynn <hi
                    rend="italic">yny</hi> instead of beg <hi rend="italic">ynn</hi> yng, end <hi
                    rend="italic">yng</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">end</hi> yng. In the <hi
                    rend="italic">Proverbs of Hendyng</hi> we haveh no- <hi rend="italic">thyng</hi>
                    for <hi rend="italic">noth</hi> ing, hab <hi rend="italic">ben</hi> for <hi
                    rend="italic">hab</hi> ben, f <hi rend="italic">omon</hi> for <hi rend="italic"
                    >fo</hi> mon; in <hi rend="italic">Robert of</hi><hi rend="italic">Brunne,</hi>
                    haly <hi rend="italic">dom</hi> for <hi rend="italic">hal</hi> ydom, cloth <hi
                    rend="italic">yng</hi> for <hi rend="italic">cloth-</hi> ing, gret <hi
                    rend="italic">and</hi> for <hi rend="italic">gret</hi> and. Chaucer furnishes
                    numerous instances of the same foreign influence revolutionising the native
                    accent; fre <hi rend="italic">dom</hi> for <hi rend="italic">fre</hi> dom,
                    hethen <hi rend="italic">esse</hi> for <hi rend="italic">heth</hi> enesse,
                    worthin <hi rend="italic">esse</hi> for <hi rend="italic">worth</hi> inesse, low
                    <hi rend="italic">ly</hi> for <hi rend="italic">low</hi> ly <hi rend="italic"
                    >,</hi> wynn <hi rend="italic">ynge</hi> for <hi rend="italic">wynn</hi> ynge,
                    wedd <hi rend="italic">ynge</hi> for <hi rend="italic">wedd</hi> ynge, com <hi
                    rend="italic">ynge</hi> for <hi rend="italic">com</hi> ynge <hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> and it is traceable even in Spenser. On the other hand, a contrary
                    tendency must not be overlooked. We see an effort, probably unconscious, to
                    compel words of French origin to submit to the rule of English accentuation. It
                    is noticeable in the century before Chaucer: in Chaucer himself it begins to
                    work strongly; mort <hi rend="italic">al</hi> becomes <hi rend="italic"
                    >mortal;</hi> tem <hi rend="italic">pest</hi>, <hi rend="italic">tem</hi> pest;
                    sub <hi rend="italic">stance</hi>, sub <hi rend="italic">stance</hi>; amy <hi
                    rend="italic">able,</hi><hi rend="italic">am</hi> yable; mor <hi rend="italic"
                    >sel</hi>, <hi rend="italic">mor</hi> sel; ser <hi rend="italic">vise,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ser</hi> vise; duch <hi rend="italic">esse</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                    >duchesse</hi>; co <hi rend="italic">syn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">cos</hi> yn,
                    &amp;c.; while a multitude of words oscillate between the rival modes of
                    accentuation, now following the French and now the English. Before and during
                    the Elizabethan period, the latter began to prove the stronger, and for the last
                    300 years it may be said to have, for the most part, Anglicised the accent and
                    the nature of the foreign additions to our vocabulary. Nevertheless, many French
                    words still retain their own accent. Morris (<hi rend="italic">Historical
                    Outlines of English Accidence,</hi> p. 75) thus classifies these :—</p>
                <quote> “(1.) Nouns in <hi rend="italic">-ade, -ier(-eer), -e', -ee,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">-oon, -ine, (-in),</hi> as <hi rend="italic">cascade',
                    crusade',</hi> &amp;c.; <hi rend="italic">cavalier', chandelier'</hi>, &amp;c.;
                    <hi rend="italic">gazetteer', pioneer', &amp;</hi> c. (in conformity with these
                    we say <hi rend="italic">harpooneer', mountaineer',); legatee', payee',</hi>
                    &amp;c.; <hi rend="italic">balloon', cartoon',</hi> &amp;c.; <hi rend="italic"
                    >chagrin', violin',</hi> &amp;c.; <hi rend="italic">routine', marine'</hi>,
                    &amp;c. </quote>
                <p>“Also the following words:— <hi rend="italic">cadet', brunette', gazette',
                    cravat’, canal', control', gazelle', amateur', fatigue', antique', police',</hi>
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p>“(2.) Adjectives (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) from Lat. adj. in <hi rend="italic"
                    >us,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">august', benign', robust,</hi> &amp;c.; (<hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi>) in <hi rend="italic">-ose,</hi> as <hi rend="italic"
                    >morose', verbose',</hi> &amp;c.; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) <hi rend="italic"
                    >-esque,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">burlesque, grotesque’,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p>“ (3.) Some verbs, as <hi rend="italic">baptize', cajole’, caress', carouse’,
                    chastise’, escape’, esteem’,</hi> &amp;c.”</p>
                <p>To these may be added the Greek and Latin words which have been introduced into
                    English for scientific and other learned purposes, and which, not having been
                    altered in form, retain their original accentuation—as <hi rend="italic"
                    >auro'ra,</hi><hi rend="italic">corona, colossus, ide'a, hypothesis,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">caesu'ra,</hi><hi rend="italic">diaeresis, diagno'sis, diluvium,
                    diploma, efflu'vium, elys'ium,</hi> &amp;c.; besides the still larger number
                    that have suffered a slight modification of form, but no change of accent, as
                    <hi rend="italic">dialec'tic, diagnostic,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >efflores'</hi><hi rend="italic">cent, elliptic, emer'sion, emol'lient,</hi> Ac.
                    The Italian contributions to our tongue retain their original accent when the
                    form is untouched, as <hi rend="italic">mulat'to, sona'ta, vol-ca'no,</hi> but
                    lose it when the form is shortened, as <hi rend="italic">bandit</hi> (It. <hi
                    rend="italic">bandi'to).</hi></p>
                <p>A change in the position of the accent serves a variety of purposes in English.
                    It distinguishes (1.) a <hi rend="italic">noun</hi> from a <hi rend="italic"
                    >verb,</hi> as accent, accent'; augment, augment'; tor'ment, torment'; com'ment,
                    comment'; con'sort, consort'; con'test, contest'; con'trast, contrast'; digest,
                    digest'; discount, discount'; in'sult, insult', &amp;c.; (2.) an <hi
                    rend="italic">adjective</hi> from a <hi rend="italic">verb,</hi> as ab'sent,
                    absent'; fre'quent, frequent'; pre'sent, present'; com'pound, compound',
                    &amp;c.; (3.) an <hi rend="italic">adjective</hi> from a <hi rend="italic"
                    >noun,</hi> as ex'pert, expert'; com'pact, compact'. It also denotes a
                    difference of meaning, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> conjure, conjure'; in'cense,
                    incense'; au'gust, august'; su'pine, supine'.</p>
                <p>Accent has exercised a powerful influence in changing the <hi rend="italic"
                    >forms</hi> of words. The unaccented syllables in the course of time frequently
                    dropped off. This process was necessarily more rapid and thorough in English
                    than in many other languages which were not subjected to equal strain. The
                    Norman Conquest made havoc of the English tongue for a time. It was expelled
                    from the court, the schools, the church, and the tribunals of justice; it ceased
                    to be spoken by priests, lawyers, and nobles; its only guardians were churls,
                    ignorant, illiterate, indifferent to grammar, and careless of diction. Who can
                    wonder if, in circumstances like these, it suffered disastrous eclipse? The
                    latter part of the Anglo-Saxon <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi> furnishes
                    melancholy evidence of the chaos into which it had fallen, yet out of this chaos
                    it rose again into newness of life, reforming and re-accenting its half-ruined
                    vocabulary, and drawing from the very agent of its destruction the elements of a
                    richer and more plastic expression. For it cannot be doubted that the
                    irregularities now existing in English accent, though perplexing to a foreigner,
                    copiously vary the modulation, and so increase the flexibility and power of the
                    language. The older forms of English, those in use before the Conquest, and down
                    to the period of Chaucer, are stiff, monotonous, and unmusical. A hard strength
                    is in the verse, but no liquid sweetness or nimble grace. Now, it is possible,
                    in spite of our deficiency in vowel endings, to produce the noblest melody in
                    accent words known to the modern world. Almost every kind of metre, swift or
                    slow, airy or majestic, has been successfully attempted since the age of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Canterbury Tales.</hi> When we compare the drone of Caedmon with
                    the aerial melody of the <hi rend="italic">Skylark,</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cloud,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Arethusa</hi> of Shelley, we see what an
                    infinite progress has been made by the development of accent in the rhythm of
                    our native tongue.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Lectures on the English Language,</hi> by G. P. Marsh
                    (Lond. 1861); the <hi rend="italic">Origin and History of the English
                    Language,</hi> Ac., by G. P. Marsh (Lond. 1862); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historische</hi><hi rend="italic">Grammatik</hi><hi rend="italic">der Englische
                    Sprache,</hi> von. C. Friedrich Koch (1863-69); <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">English Language,</hi> by R. G. Latham (1855); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Philological Essays,</hi> by the Rev. Richard Garnett (Lond. 1859); <hi
                    rend="italic">On Early English Pronunciation, with especial reference to
                    Shakspere and Chaucer,</hi> by A. J. Ellis (Lond. 1867-71); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historical Outlines of English Accidence,</hi> by Dr R. Morris (Lond. 1872).
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(j. μ. r.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
