<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0901-0469-0434-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AKBAR, Akhbar, or Akber, Jellaladin Mohammed (9th
                    edition, volume 1, page 434)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150446">Thrones</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198938">Rebellion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z60x">Hindoos</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669j0w">Turkomans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gh9bg6t">Mussulmans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hs61">Moslems</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s33k">Creeds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n469/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AKBAR, <hi rend="smallcaps">Akhbar</hi>, or <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">Akber, Jellaladin Mohammed</hi></label>, one of the
                    greatest and wisest of the Moghul emperors, was born at Amerkote in Sindh on the
                    14th October 1542, his father, Humayun, having been driven from the throne a
                    short time before by the usurper Sher Khan. After more than twelve years’ exile,
                    Humayun regained his sovereignty, which, however, he had held only for a few
                    months when he died. Akbar succeeded his father in 1556 under the regency of
                    Bahram Khan, a Turkoman noble, whose energy in repelling pretenders to the
                    throne, and severity in maintaining the discipline of the army, tended greatly
                    to the consolidation of the newly-recovered empire. Bahram, however, was
                    naturally despotic and cruel; and when order was somewhat restored, Akbar found
                    it necessary to take the reins of government into his own hands, which he did by
                    a proclamation issued in March 1560. The discarded regent lived for some time in
                    rebellion, endeavouring to establish an independent principality in Malwah, but
                    at last he was forced to cast himself on Akbar’s mercy. The emperor not only
                    freely pardoned him, but magnanimously offered him the choice of a high place in
                    the army or a suitable escort for a pilgrimage to Mecca, and Bahram preferred
                    the latter alternative. When Akbar ascended the throne, only a small portion of
                    what had formerly been comprised within the Moghul empire owned his authority,
                    and he devoted himself with great determination and marvellous success to the
                    recovery of the revolted provinces. Over each of these, as it was restored, he
                    placed a governor, whom he superintended with great vigilance and wisdom. He
                    tried by every means to develop and encourage commerce; he had the land
                    accurately measured for the purpose of rightly adjusting taxation; he gave the
                    strictest instructions to prevent extortion on the part of the tax-gatherers,
                    and in many other respects displayed an enlightened and equitable policy. Thus
                    it happened that, in the fortieth year of Akbar’s reign the empire had more than
                    regained all that it had lost, the recovered provinces being reduced, not to
                    subjection only as before, but to a great degree of peace, order, and
                    contentment. Akbar’s method of dealing with what must always be the chief
                    difficulty of one who has to rule widely diverse races, affords perhaps the
                    crowning evidence of his wisdom and moderation. In religion he was at first a
                    Mussulman, but the intolerant exclusiveness of that creed was quite foreign to
                    his character. Scepticism as to the divine origin of the Koran led him to seek
                    the true religion in an eclectic system. He accordingly set himself to obtain
                    information about other religions, sent to Goa, requesting that the Portuguese
                    missionaries there would visit him, and listened to them with intelligent
                    attention when they came. As the result of these inquiries, he adopted the creed
                    of pure deism and a ritual based upon the system of Zoroaster. The religion thus
                    founded, <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n470/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0901-0470-0435"/> however, having no vital force, never spread
                    beyond the limits of the court, and died with Akbar himself. But though his
                    eclectic system failed, the spirit of toleration which originated it produced in
                    other ways many important results; and, indeed, may be said to have done more to
                    establish Akbar’s power on a secure basis than all his economic and social
                    reforms. He conciliated the Hindoos by giving them freedom of worship; while at
                    the same time he strictly prohibited certain barbarous Brahminical practices,
                    such as trial by ordeal and the burning of widows against their will. He also
                    abolished all taxes upon pilgrims as an interference with the liberty of
                    worship, and the capitation tax upon Hindoos, probably upon similar grounds.
                    Measures like these gained for him during his lifetime the title of “Guardian of
                    Mankind,” and caused him to be held up as a model to Indian princes of later
                    times, who in the matter of religious toleration have only too seldom followed
                    his example. Akbar was a munificent patron of literature. He established schools
                    throughout his empire for the education of Hindoos as well as Moslems, and he
                    gathered round him many men of literary talent, among whom may be mentioned the
                    brothers Feizi and Abulfazl. The former was commissioned by Akbar to translate a
                    number of Sanscrit scientific works into Persian; and the latter (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Abulfazl)</hi> has left, in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Akbar-Nameh,</hi> an enduring record of the emperor’s reign. It is also
                    said that Akbar employed Jerome Xavier, a Jesuit missionary, to translate the
                    four Gospels into Persian. The closing years of Akbar’s reign were rendered very
                    unhappy by the misconduct of his sons. Two of them died in youth, the victims of
                    intemperance; and the third, Selim, afterwards the emperor Jehanghir, was
                    frequently in rebellion against his father. These calamities were keenly felt by
                    Akbar, and may even have tended to hasten his death, which occurred at Agra on
                    the 13th October 1605. His body was deposited in a magnificent mausoleum at
                    Sicandra, near Agra.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
