<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0840-0797-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANALYTIC JUDGMENTS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 797</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49z90c0c">Logic</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f45m">Judgments</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zc7rw8b">Priories</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48w38446">Contentment</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1002014">Logic</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:872956">Conception</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:872969">Concepts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:984609">Judgments</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n840/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ANALYTIC JUDGMENTS</label> have been distinguished under that
                    name, in opposition to Synthetic, since the time of Kant. It was necessary, for
                    the purposes of his critical inquiry into the principles of human knowledge,
                    that he should carefully determine the character of those assertions which
                    metaphysicians had so freely made respecting the supernatural, and he found them
                    to be such that, while the predicate was added on to the subject, not involved
                    in it, the connection was affirmed as necessary and universal. He therefore
                    called them, as well as other assertions of like character in mathematics and
                    pure physics, synthetic judgments <hi rend="italic">ά</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >priori,</hi> and the aim of his critical inquiry came to be the determining of
                    the conditions under which such judgments were possible. Now, as differing from
                    these, he noted two classes of judgments: (1), such as in the predicate added
                    indeed to the content of the subject, but only <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n841/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0841-0798"/> empirically, as, for example, Bodies have weight,
                    and these he called synthetic <hi rend="italic">à</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >posteriori;</hi> (2), such as were indeed necessary and universal, but added
                    nothing to the content of the subject, as, for example, Bodies are extended, and
                    these he called analytic.</p>
                <p>The general distinction of analytic and synthetic judgments has a value apart
                    from the specific character of those (synthetic) judgments in which Kant was
                    most interested, and for the sake of which mainly it was fixed by him. Trained
                    in the metaphysics of the Leibnitzo-Wolffian school, which marked off necessary
                    judgments from those of simple fact without considering the kinds of necessity,
                    Kant, when he came, by the route that can be traced in his earlier works, to
                    apprehend the différence between merely logical analysis and real synthesis in
                    thought, applied it almost exclusively to those judgments for which a character
                    of necessity was claimed. He therefore noticed traces of the distinction in
                    other thinkers, as Locke, only in so far as there was a suggestion also of this
                    special reference. In truth, the general distinction, under a variety of
                    expressions, was familiar to both Hume and Locke, and it had already been drawn
                    by the ancients. The old doctrine of the Predicables, in distinguishing the
                    essential predication of genus, species, and difference from the non-essential
                    predication of property and accident, plainly involves it; making besides, as
                    between the last two predicables, a distinction which is very closely related to
                    that drawn by Kant between the <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">a posteriori</hi> synthetic. From the nominalistic point of view
                    it is expressed by the difference of Verbal and Real propositions, as in Mill’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Logic,</hi> and also often in Locke.</p>
                <p>While the synthetic judgment, as the name implies, brings together in thought two
                    distinct concepts, each of which may be thought apart, the analytic judgment is
                    merely the explication of a single concept in the form of a proposition. It is
                    disputed what may be the ground of synthesis in different cases, but on all
                    hands it is agreed that the logical Law of Contradiction is the controlling
                    principle for the explication of concepts already in the mind, however they may
                    have come there. Now the explication may be made either completely or partially,
                    according as the whole or part only of the intension of the concept is set
                    forth: in other words, the aim may be to give the definition (where, in the full
                    sense, that is possible), or simply to express any one or more of the contained
                    attributes. Propositions giving such partial explication are spoken of by Locke
                    as “trifling;” and it is true that, if the concept is supposed already in the
                    mind, no increase of knowledge is thereby obtained. This word, however, is
                    unfortunate. Not to say that it is equally applicable to definitions, where the
                    explication is only more complete, it tends to keep out of view the fact that
                    analytic judgments, when not arbitrarily formed, are themselves—or rather the
                    concepts, of which they are the explications, are—the permanent result or
                    deposit of foregone real synthesis. So much, indeed, is this the case with
                    concepts of things in nature—what Mill calls natural kinds—that in them a
                    constant process of accretion is going on; new attributes, as they are
                    discovered, being taken up into the essence, if they are at the same time
                    characteristic and underived. Much also that is mere explication to one mind is
                    real information to another.</p>
                <p>The terms Analytic and Synthetic, thus applied to judgments, are so expressive in
                    themselves that they have now come into general use. It is, however, a serious
                    drawback to such an association of the terms, that it traverses what is
                    otherwise the consistent use of the words analysis and synthesis in relation to
                    each other. As the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Analysis</hi> has shown, there
                    is a synthesis which, as much as any analysis, is purely logical, and there is
                    an analysis which, as much as any synthesis, is a means of real advance in
                    knowledge. The terms Explicative <hi rend="italic">(Erläuterungsurtheile)</hi>
                    and Ampliative <hi rend="italic">(Erweiterungsurtheile),</hi> also employed by
                    Kant, while not less expressive, are open to no such objection. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(g. c. r.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
