<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0491-0454-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALBIGENSES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 454</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1739809">Manichaeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:841374">Bulgarians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:943906">Gnosticism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp1x">Gnosticism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1212489">Bulgaria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n491/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALBIGENSES</label>, a sect opposed to the Church of Rome,
                    which derives its name from Albiga (the modern <hi rend="italic">Albi,</hi>
                    noticed above), either because its doctrines were expressly condemned at a
                    council held there, or, more probably, because its adherents were to be found in
                    great numbers in that town and its neighbourhood. The Albigenses were kindred in
                    origin and more or less similar in doctrine to the sects known in Italy as
                    Paterins, in Germany as Catharists, and in France as Bulgarians, but they are
                    not to be entirely identified with any of these. Still less ought they to be
                    confounded, as has frequently been the case, with the Waldenses, who first
                    appear at a later period in history, and are materially different in their
                    doctrinal views. The descent of the Albigenses may be traced with tolerable
                    distinctness from the Paulicians, a sect that sprang into existence in the
                    Eastern Church during the 6th century. (See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Paulicians.)</hi> The Paulicians were Gnostics, and were accused by their
                    enemies and persecutors of holding Manichaean doctrines, which, it is said, they
                    vehemently disowned. Their creed, whatever it was precisely, spread gradually
                    westward through Europe. In the 9th century it found many adherents in Bulgaria,
                    and 300 years later it was maintained and defended, though not without important
                    modifications, by the Albigenses in the south of France. The attempt to discover
                    the precise doctrinal opinions held by the Albigenses is attended with a double
                    difficulty. No formal creed or definite doctrinal statement framed by themselves
                    exists, and in default of this it is impossible to depend on the representations
                    of their views given by their opponents in the Church of Rome, who did not
                    scruple to exaggerate and distort the opinions held by those whom they had
                    branded as heretics. It is probably impossible now to determine accurately what
                    is true and what is false in these representations. It seems almost certain,
                    however, that the bond which united the Albigenses was not so much a positive
                    fully-developed religious faith as a determined opposition to the Church of
                    Rome. They inherited indeed, as has been already said, certain doctrines of
                    eastern origin, such as the Manichaean dualism, docetism in relation to the
                    person of Christ, and a theory of metempsychosis. They seem, like the Manichees,
                    to have disowned the authority of the Old Testament; and the division of their
                    adherents into <hi rend="italic">perfecti</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >credentes</hi> is similar to the Manichaean distinction between <hi
                    rend="italic">electi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">auditores.</hi> The statement
                    that they rejected marriage, often made by Roman Catholics, has probably no
                    other foundation in fact than that they denied that marriage was a sacrament;
                    and many other statements as to their doctrine and practice must be received at
                    least with suspicion as coming from prejudiced and implacable opponents. The
                    history of the Albigenses may be said to be written in blood. At first the
                    church was content to condemn their errors at various councils (1165, 1176,1178,
                    1179), but as their practical opposition to Rome became stronger, more decided
                    measures were taken. Innocent III. had scarcely ascended the papal throne when
                    he sent legates to Toulouse (1198) to endeavour to suppress the sect. Two
                    Cistercians, Guy and Regnier, were first commissioned, and in 1199 they were
                    joined by Peter of Castelnau and others, who were known throughout the district
                    as inquisitors. Raymond VI., count of Toulouse, took the part of his Albigensian
                    subjects, though not himself belonging to the sect, and for this he was
                    excommunicated in 1207. A year later the pope found a pretext for resorting to
                    the most extreme measures in the assassination of his legate Peter of Castelnau,
                    Jan. 15, 1208. A crusade against the Albigenses was at once ordered, and
                    Raymond, who had meanwhile submitted and done penance, was forced to take the
                    field against his own subjects. The bloody war of extermination which followed
                    has scarcely a parallel in history. Aa <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n492/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0492-0455"/> town after town was taken, the inhabitants were
                    put to the sword without distinction of age or sex, and the numerous
                    ecclesiastics who were in the army especially distinguished themselves by a
                    bloodthirsty ferocity. At the taking of Beziers (July 22, 1209), the Abbot
                    Arnold, being asked how the heretics were to be distinguished from the faithful,
                    made the infamous reply, “Slay all; God will know his own.” The war was carried
                    on under the command of Simon de Montfort with undiminished cruelty for a number
                    of years. Raymond’s nephew, Viscount Raymond Roger, who had espoused the cause
                    of the Albigenses, was taken prisoner at Carcassone, and the sect became fewer
                    in numbers year by year. The establishment of an Inquisition at Languedoc in
                    1229 accelerated the exterminating process, and a few years later the sect was
                    all but extinct.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
