<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0702-0665-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">AMBULANCE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 665</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29m34">Canteen</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jj2j">Transportation</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j75q">Sick</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1118032">Sick</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1155007">Transportation</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n702/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AMBULANCE</label>, the French <hi rend="italic"
                    >ambulance,</hi><hi rend="italic">hôpital</hi><hi rend="italic">ambulant,</hi>
                    derived from the Latin <hi rend="italic">ambulare,</hi> to move from place to
                    place.</p>
                <p>Ambulances, in military phraseology, are hospital establishments moving with
                    armies in the field, and organised for providing early surgical assistance to
                    the wounded after battles. They are only prepared for affording help of a more
                    or less temporary kind, and they are thus distinguished from the <hi
                    rend="italic">stationary</hi> or <hi rend="italic">fixed hospitals,</hi> in
                    which sick and wounded soldiers receive care and treatment of a permanent
                    character. The term is not un-frequently misapplied in common speech in England
                    to the ambulance waggons, or other conveyances by which the wounded are carried
                    from the field to the ambulances and fixed hospitals. Such vehicles form part of
                    the ambulance equipment, and will be noticed presently.</p>
                <p>The constitution of an ambulance includes (1) a certain staff of officers and
                    subordinates, and (2) a certain equipment. The equipment naturally divides
                    itself into (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the medical and surgical equipment, and
                    (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the equipment forming the means of transport for the
                    wounded. But the constitution would hardly be understood without a general
                    comprehension of the system on which the functions of ambulances are discharged,
                    or, in other words, the plan of administering surgical assistance in the field
                    to the wounded of armies. <hi rend="italic">Ambulance administration</hi> will
                    therefore be first noticed, keeping in view the circumstances of armies
                    operating in Europe, and the <hi rend="italic">ambulance staff</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">equipment</hi> subsequently.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ambulance Administration.</hi> —The origin of the ambulance
                    system which now prevails in all civilised armies, though variously modified
                    among them in particular details, only dates from the last decade of the last
                    century. Before that time no ambulance establishments had been organised for
                    effecting the removal of the wounded, or for giving the requisite surgical
                    attention to them, while battles were in progress. Soldiers wounded in the ranks
                    were either carried to the rear by comrades, or were left to lie exposed to all
                    risks, and unheeded, until after the fighting had ceased. The means of surgical
                    assistance did not reach the battle-field till the day after the engagement, or
                    often later, and to a large proportion of the wounded it was then of no avail.
                    In 1792 Larrey introduced his system of <hi rend="italic">ambulances</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">volantes,</hi> or flying field hospitals, establishments capable
                    of moving from place to place with speed, like the flying artillery of the time.
                    They were adapted both for giving the necessary primary surgical help, and also
                    for removing the wounded quickly out of the sphere of fighting. The first
                    Napoleon warmly supported Larrey in his endeavours to introduce And perfect the
                    new system of surgical aid to the wounded in battle; and, being received with
                    much favour by the troops, the plan obtained a firm footing, and was
                    subsequently brought to a high state of perfection. About the same time another
                    distinguished surgeon of high position in the French army, Baron Percy,
                    introduced and developed a corps of <hi rend="italic">brancardiers,</hi> or
                    stretcher-bearers. These consisted of soldiers trained and regularly equipped
                    for the duty of collecting the wounded while a battle was in progress, and
                    carrying them on stretchers to places where means of surgical aid were
                    provided.</p>
                <p>From the period when these improvements were introduced most civilised armies
                    have had ambulance establishments formed for giving surgical help near to the
                    combatants. It is only, however, during the last twenty years that ambulances
                    have acquired the completeness of organisation which they have now attained in
                    some armies, especially in those of Germany. In the armies of the United States
                    of America, during the late great civil war, the ambulance system attained a
                    very complete organisation, particularly from March 1864, when an Act was passed
                    by Congress, entitled “An Act to establish a uniform system of Ambulances in the
                    United States.” This law fixed a definite and single system of ambulance
                    arrangements for all the armies of the United States at that time in the
                    field.</p>
                <p>The ambulance arrangements of the British army have never reached the degree of
                    completeness which they have reached in Continental armies. During the
                    Peninsular war the want of a trained ambulance corps, and of
                    properly-constructed sick-transport carriages, formed a theme of constant
                    complaint. For the former, soldiers from the ranks were substituted—a double
                    evil, as they were unsuited for the work, while their employment lessened the
                    fighting strength; for the latter, commissariat waggons, or the agricultural
                    carts of the country in which the troops were operating. It was not from want of
                    attention being called to the subject, as the writings of Sir J. M'Grigor,
                    Hennen, Millingen, and other Peninsular surgeons sufficiently testify. The
                    last-named military surgeon published a very complete scheme of an ambulance
                    establishment shortly after the war was concluded, approaching closely in its
                    principles to those put into practice of late years in the armies of Germany.
                    There is reason for believing that had the operations of the British troops on
                    the Continent not been discontinued, some plan of the kind would have been
                    introduced. As it was, subsequently to 1815, so far as army hospitals were
                    concerned, administrative attention was chiefly given to improving those for the
                    accommodation of the sick in peace time. The wars that British troops were
                    engaged in in India, China, the south of Africa, and elsewhere, did not lead to
                    improvements like those which have been made in Continental armies; for either
                    the habits of the natives of the respective countries, or the nature of the
                    climate, or the state of the country, necessitated special arrangements for the
                    care of the sick and wounded unsuited for meeting the circumstances of European
                    warfare. Thus, when the Crimean war broke out the English army was still without
                    an ambulance corps, or an ambulance establishment of <hi rend="italic"
                    >matériel.</hi> An ambulance corps of military pensioners was hastily raised,
                    but failed from the habits and enfeebled constitutions of the men. They were
                    succeeded by a corps formed of civilians, unused to the discipline and habits of
                    military life, which likewise failed. Several forms of sick-transport vehicles
                    were tried, but only indifferently answered their intended purposes.
                    Fortunately, as the troops were for the most part stationary during the war, the
                    want of thoroughly organised ambulances was not felt to the same extent as it
                    would have been had the operations been extended far into the interior of the
                    country. The experience of the Crimean war led to efforts to repair the <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n703/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0703-0666"/> defects which were then made manifest. Since that
                    time a trained army hospital corps has been constituted, and much of the
                    ambulance equipment has been revised.</p>
                <p>One serious impediment to perfecting an ambulance system is the costliness of
                    maintaining, in time of peace, establishments which will only be required for
                    use in time of war. All that can be done is to form a nucleus which can be
                    expanded according to need when war breaks out. But even in Continental armies,
                    with frequent wars pressing upon them, the urgency of giving close attention to
                    the subject, and in, countries where the existence of conscription furnishes a
                    greater supply of men at less cost than in England, the deficiencies of the
                    ambulance establishments have hitherto been so great in respect to the numbers
                    and necessities of the wounded on occasions of great battles, that an extensive
                    volunteer organisation, with national societies in every country of Europe, has
                    sprung up for giving additional assistance. This is not the place to discuss the
                    advantages of such volunteer aid; but, if accepted, all who have considered the
                    subject well have admitted the necessity for its being placed under military
                    authority, and under distinct regulations, in order to secure maintenance of
                    order and discipline. It is also generally admitted that volunteer aid to
                    wounded soldiers is out of place in the ambulances, and can best be employed in
                    the fixed hospitals, by which means some of the regular military <hi
                    rend="italic">personnel</hi> may be set free for work in the field.</p>
                <p>One important step, taken a few years since, towards the amelioration of the
                    condition of the wounded of armies in the field must be just mentioned. This was
                    the European Convention signed at Geneva in 1864, by the terms of which, subject
                    to certain regulations, not only the wounded themselves, but the official staff
                    of ambulances and their equipment have been rendered neutral; the former,
                    therefore, not being liable to be retained as prisoners of war, nor the latter
                    to be taken as prize of war. This convention has greatly favoured the
                    development of ambulance establishments.</p>
                <p>The conditions of modern warfare have led to the need of army ambulances being
                    arranged on principles different from what were applicable only a few years ago.
                    The immensely increased range of rifles and artillery in the present day, the
                    consequent extension of the area over which fire is maintained, the suddenness
                    with which armies can be brought into the field from increased facilities of
                    locomotion, the rapidity of their movements, the shortened duration of
                    campaigns, the large numbers of wounded which have to be dealt with, not merely
                    from the destructive qualities of the fire-arms, but from the vast forces
                    collected on occasions of important battles, the increased proportion of severe
                    wounds,—are all circumstances which have entailed need for revision of
                    ambulances and their administration. The ambulances must be so organised as to
                    be able to keep up with the troops, and so disposed as in no way to interfere
                    with their movements. They must be capable of meeting the wants of a partial or
                    general engagement at any moment, and if the troops advance, must be prepared to
                    accompany them, so as to be ready to meet future wants.</p>
                <p>Whatever the details of organisation may be when an important battle is fought,
                    the ambulance system must admit of three help stations at least being
                    established in rear of the combatants. There must be a station of limited
                    character immediately in rear of the troops for attention to such wounds as
                    entail speedy loss of life if no assistance be rendered; a second station, more
                    remote, where temporary assistance of a more general nature can be afforded; a
                    third, where more thorough attention can be given, and where the wounded can
                    receive food and protection until there are means of sending them away.
                    Recently, in some armies, the ambulance arrangements have been calculated for
                    furnishing aid at four stations; and, indeed, owing to the increased range of
                    fire, and the consequent distance between the help stations when only three are
                    formed, the fatigue thrown on the bearers is so great, and the time the wounded
                    are left without help so long, that the division of the ambulances into four
                    stations has become almost essential. If this arrangement be followed, there
                    will be —1st, the <hi rend="italic">field station,</hi> for help of prime
                    urgency; 2d, the <hi rend="italic">transfer station,</hi> where the wounded will
                    be transferred from the hand conveyances to wheeled vehicles; 3d, the <hi
                    rend="italic">dressing station,</hi> where the provisional dressings will be
                    applied; and 4th, the <hi rend="italic">field hospital station,</hi> where
                    definitive treatment will be adopted.</p>
                <p>The disposition and distances of these four ambulance sections must vary
                    according to the nature of the battle, the configuration of the terrain, and
                    other circumstances, but in a general way will be as follows :—1st, the field
                    station, in the immediate rear of the troops, moving with them, and therefore
                    under fire; 2d, the transfer station, clear of the enemy’s rifle fire, but not
                    too far for the bearers, and at a place practicable for waggons, from 800 to 900
                    yards behind the troops engaged; 3d, the dressing station, beyond range of
                    artillery fire, at a spot easily reached by the ambulance waggons, and on the
                    way to the fourth station, with a running stream or well at hand if possible,
                    from 800 to 1000 yards in rear of No. 2; and 4th, the field hospital station, at
                    a place free from risk of being brought within the sphere of fighting, from 2 to
                    4 miles in rear of the combatants. This last station may be at a farm or country
                    house, or in a village, but should not be in a place of strategical importance,
                    or in one likely to be blocked by the general transport of the army. When the
                    four stations are in working order, as men fall badly wounded, those within
                    reach will be placed on stretchers by the men told off for duty as bearers, and,
                    after hasty inspection by the field surgeon, and, as far as practicable,
                    receiving such help as is of vital importance, they will be borne to the second
                    or transfer station, and placed in ambulance waggons, or on wheeled stretchers
                    if they are in use. The bearers, then taking vacant stretchers, will return to
                    the field station for more wounded. The wounded who have been transferred to the
                    wheeled conveyances will be driven by the men of the ambulance train to the
                    third or dressing station, and there receive whatever provisional dressing may
                    be necessary before being sent on to the fourth or field hospital station, where
                    definitive treatment will be adopted, and any surgical operations performed that
                    may be required.</p>
                <p>It is obvious that such a system of help can only be carried out, with any
                    approach to regularity and requisite speed, with ambulance establishments
                    proportionate to the number of troops in the field, each ambulance being well
                    organised, provided with a sufficient staff and complete equipment, and acting
                    under the general supervision of an experienced director, whose duty it is to
                    watch the varying events of the contest while it is in progress, and to order
                    changes in the ambulance arrangements according as the troops advance, retire,
                    or otherwise change position. Even with these advantages, the difficulties of
                    adequately meeting the wants of the wounded must always be very great, owing to
                    the rapid manoeuvres of the troops, the varying features of the ground over
                    which battles are extended, and the rapidity with which the wounded fall; but
                    without a proper organisation arranged beforehand, the difficulties are
                    insuperable, and no help of much value can be afforded until all fighting has
                    ceased.</p>
                <p>Ambulance arrangements have to be modified to suit particular military
                    operations, such as when troops disembark on a hostile shore, on occasion of
                    sieges, &amp;c.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n704/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0704-0667"/>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ambulance Staff.</hi> —The scheme of ambulance
                    administration and action just described involves the necessity of a staff
                    comprising the following <hi rend="italic">personnel,</hi> viz.: — 1. Bearers of
                    wounded; 2. Surgeons and attendants; 3. Ambulance train <hi rend="italic"
                    >personnel;</hi> 4. Ambulance police; 5. Servants to officers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bearers of Wounded. —</hi> These are soldiers specially trained
                    and told off for the duty of picking up and carrying the badly wounded on
                    stretchers. In Continental armies special provision is made to meet this
                    particular want, but under different systems in different armies. In the
                    Prussian army companies of bearers, distinguished by a particular uniform, and
                    denominated “sanitäts-detache-ments,” have the duty assigned to them of
                    gathering the wounded during battles, and carrying them to the dressing and
                    field hospital stations. Each of these bearer columns consists of a military
                    staff of officers for discipline and direction, non-commissioned officers,
                    buglers, and a large number of bearers; a special medical staff, with assistants
                    and dressers; a transport staff of non-commissioned officers and drivers, with a
                    certain number of stretchers, wheeled stretcher supports, sick transport
                    waggons, and store waggons for the carriage of instruments, dressings, and other
                    necessary materials. Separate establishments exist for the field hospitals. In
                    addition to these sanitary detachments, auxiliary sick-bearers (<hi
                    rend="italic">Hilfs-krankenträger)</hi> are provided for service on occasions of
                    great battles. To form these auxiliaries, four men in each company of every
                    battalion of the army are practised at regular periods with the sanitary
                    detachments in time of peace in the modes of picking up, temporarily attending
                    to, and carrying wounded. These auxiliary bearers wear the uniform of their
                    regiments, of which they perform the ordinary duties, but have a distinguishing
                    badge on the left arm when serving as bearers. When a battle is imminent, the
                    auxiliary bearers fall out, are provided with stretchers and other needful
                    appliances from the ambulance waggons, and act under the orders of the officers
                    of the divisional sanitary detachments. The system in the Austrian army is very
                    like that in the Prussian. In the British army no corresponding establishment
                    exists. The hospital attendants belonging to the Army Hospital Corps are trained
                    in all that refers to the care of wounded men, but in time of war they will be
                    too urgently needed for their duties in the field and fixed hospitals to be
                    spared for duty as bearers of the wounded from the field to the dressing
                    stations. The regimental bandsmen are generally regarded as available for these
                    duties in the British service; but though the army regulations order that
                    bandsmen are liable to serve in the ranks on an emergency, they nowhere
                    constitute them bearers of wounded, nor do bandsmen receive the necessary
                    training to fit them for the duties. As it is understood that the ambulance
                    arrangements of the British army are at present under consideration, this, with
                    other details, will probably be shortly placed on a settled basis.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Surgical Staff. —</hi> This section embraces the medical
                    officers (administrative and executive), the dispensers of medicine, and the
                    officers, non-commissioned officers, and men of the Army Hospital Corps. The
                    last-named corps includes the dressers, nurses, cooks, and all the hospital
                    subordinates who are required for the care, dieting, watching, and protection of
                    the patients, for the hospital correspondence, &amp;c. The men act
                    professionally under the directions of the surgeons; in respect of other
                    matters, under their own officers. The constitution and duties of the several
                    divisions and grades of the army medical department are shown in a special code
                    of instructions known as the “Army Medical Regulations.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ambulance Train.—</hi> On the officers and men of the ambulance
                    train devolve the duties of conducting the wheeled transport, and the mule
                    litters and cacolets when such conveyances are used. In the British service
                    these duties are entrusted to the ordinary transport branch of the Control
                    department. It has been recommended that the officers and men to whom these
                    duties are entrusted should be specially selected and trained, as well as
                    familiarised, to co-operate with the bearers and ambulance corps. They would
                    thus form an ambulance train somewhat like that which exists in the sanitary
                    detachments of the Prussian army.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Military Servants.—</hi> Orderlies are required as servants to
                    the ambulance surgeons and other officers, in order that they may give their
                    time fully to the concerns of the sick and wounded. When special orderlies are
                    not provided, men of the Army Hospital Corps usually act as servants to
                    officers,—a bad system, for the whole time and services of these trained men
                    should be devoted to their legitimate functions.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ambulance Police.—</hi> Many irregularities are liable to occur
                    in the rear of troops engaged in a general action; not so much from acts of the
                    troops themselves as from camp followers, hired drivers, and others. The
                    officers charged with the military discipline of the bearer, train, and hospital
                    corps have other pressing duties to engage them on such occasions. In the
                    British army it devolves on the provost-marshal to arrange for this service.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ambulance Equipment.</hi> —As before mentioned, ambulance
                    equipment divides itself into two categories:—1. The medical and surgical
                    equipment; 2. The equipment for the transport of wounded. These divisions will
                    therefore be noticed separately, and the description will be confined to the
                    equipment supplied in the British army for service in Europe. In India and in
                    tropical countries special ambulance equipments are rendered necessary.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Medical and Surgical Equipment.—</hi> This portion of ambulance
                    equipment consists of the articles necessary for the service of the wounded in
                    the field itself, at the dressing stations, and in the field hospitals. It has
                    to be distributed in forms such that it may be readily conveyed to the places
                    where it is required, and such also as will admit of its being hastily packed up
                    and removed should the circumstances of the field operations require it. At the
                    same time, these forms must be adapted for use at all seasons of the year, for
                    passage over all descriptions of ground that troops can march over, and must be
                    protected against the effects of exposure to all varieties of weather.</p>
                <p>It would occupy too much space to name the articles comprising this equipment.
                    The special forms under which it is issued will be mentioned, and a brief
                    explanation of them and the nature of their contents be added.</p>
                <p>The equipment is distributed as follows:—Supplies of instruments, dressings,
                    medicines, and restoratives, of first necessity, in small cases named “medical
                    field companions,” and in large cases named “field panniers;” of cooking
                    utensils and other articles for field hospital service in “canteens;” of
                    articles of light nourishment, stimulants, &amp;c., in “medical comfort boxes;”
                    of hospital tents, bedding, and the bulkier articles of surgical equipment, in
                    ambulance equipment carts or store waggons. In addition, every soldier on taking
                    the field is supplied with a “field dressing;” each surgeon carries a
                    pouch-belt, arranged both for distinguishing his functions and at the same time
                    carrying his “pocket case” of instruments; and each Army Hospital Corps man has
                    his “orderly’s dressing-case.” Every wounded man has therefore on his person the
                    means of a first dressing for his wound, every surgeon has at hand instruments
                    for affording surgical aid, and every ambulance and field hospital attendant the
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n705/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0705-0668"/> means of assisting the surgeon in his duties.
                    Moreover, wherever the soldier can go, there the first two forms of the surgical
                    equipment—the medical field companion and the field panniers—can also be taken.
                    The articles for use in the field hospitals, being carried in wheeled vehicles,
                    can only move where the other transport of the army can be taken.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Medical Field Companions.</hi> —These are small cases carried
                    by men of the Army Hospital Corps selected to accompany surgeons. They consist
                    of two pouches and a wallet, worn nearly in the same way as the pouches and
                    belt-bag in which ammunition is carried by combatant troops. The two pouches,
                    carried on the waist-belt, contain small supplies of essential medicines and
                    styptics; the surgical wallet, also carried on the waist-belt, and supported by
                    valise straps, contains materials for surgical dressings and other articles. As
                    these attendants are not armed with rifles, they can carry their valises and the
                    medical field companions at the same time without inconvenience. With each
                    medical field companion is carried, by a shoulder-strap, a water-bottle and a
                    drinking-cup.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Field Panniers.—</hi> These are tough wicker baskets covered
                    with hide, each being 2 feet 2 inches in length, by 1 foot 2½ inches in breadth,
                    and 1 foot 4½ inches in depth. They are supplied in pairs, and are arranged for
                    being attached to a pack-saddle and carried on a bât-pony or mule. They are
                    capable of being opened while on the animal in such a way that all the contents
                    can be readily got at. The field panniers contain instruments for important
                    surgical operations, chloroform, surgical materials (such as splints, bandages,
                    plaisters, &amp;c.), a lamp, supplies of wax candles, restoratives, and medical
                    comforts in concentrated forms, and other articles necessary for urgent cases at
                    the dressing stations and field hospitals. Each pannier has a double lid, and
                    the four lids of the two panniers, when they are laid on the ground, can be
                    connected so as to form a substitute for an operating table.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Field. Hospital Canteens.—</hi> These are also supplied in
                    pairs, and are distinguished as A and B canteens. They are wooden boxes nearly
                    similar in size to the field panniers, so that, although usually carried in the
                    equipment vehicles, they can, in case of need, be carried on the backs of
                    bât-animals. Their contents consist of camp-kettles and other utensils for
                    cooking purposes; tin plates, drinking-cups, and other such requisites; sets of
                    measures and weights; a lantern of coloured glass for indicating the field
                    hospital at night; together with various articles required for the service of
                    patients in a tent or other field hospital.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Medical Comfort Boxes.—</hi> These also are supplied in pairs,
                    and resemble the canteens in shape and dimensions. The contents of the two are
                    different, and they are therefore marked No. 1 and No. 2 respectively. Each box
                    is partitioned and fitted with cases or bottles with labels indicating their
                    contents. These principally consist of essence of beef, groceries, arrowroot,
                    preserved vegetables, brandy, wine, and sundry accessory articles. The wounded
                    are supplied with the same rations as the healthy troops, and they are turned to
                    the best account available for their nutriment, supplemented by such medical
                    comforts as are named above.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ambulance Equipment Waggons.—</hi> In these vehicles are
                    carried the tents for forming the field hospital in case of no building being
                    available, with a supply of blankets, waterproof covers, and other articles of
                    bedding for the patients. The canteens and medical comfort boxes are also
                    carried in these vehicles. Certain implements, as reaping-hooks, spades,
                    pickaxes, saws, which are constantly required when men are thrown so much on
                    their own resources as they must be in campaigning, are also carried in the
                    equipment waggons.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ambulance Equipment for the Transport of Wounded Troops.</hi>
                    —The ambulance conveyances authorised for use in the British army are of four
                    kinds. They are the following:—1. Conveyances carried by the hands of bearers,
                    called <hi rend="italic">stretchers;</hi> 2. Conveyances wheeled by men, <hi
                    rend="italic">wheeled stretchers;</hi> 3. Conveyances borne by mules, <hi
                    rend="italic">mule litters</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mule cacolets;</hi> and 4.
                    Wheeled conveyances drawn by horses, <hi rend="italic">ambulance waggons.</hi>
                    The forms of all these conveyances have been lately revised by a committee which
                    was appointed in 1868 by Sir J. Pakington, then Secretary of State for War, to
                    inquire into the general question of ambulance and hospital conveyances for the
                    army, and the new pattern vehicles have now been authorised for use. (T. L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
