<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0901-0137-0122-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ACT OF PARLIAMENT (9th edition, volume 1, page
                    122)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sf3s">Charters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058667">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058664">Personalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058861">Persons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n137/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ACT OF PARLIAMENT</label>. An Act of Parliament may be
                    regarded as a declaration of the Legislature, enforcing certain rules of
                    conduct, or defining rights and conferring them upon or withholding them from
                    certain persons or classes of persons. The collective body of such declarations
                    constitutes the statutes of the realm or written law of the nation, in the
                    widest sense, from Anglo-Saxon times to the present day. It is not, however,
                    till Magna Charta that, in a more limited constitutional sense, the statute-book
                    is generally held to open, and the Parliamentary records only begin to assume
                    distinct outlines late in the reign of Edward I. The maladministration of the
                    common law by the royal judges had gradually taught the people the necessity of
                    obtaining written declarations of their rights—often acknowledged, still oftener
                    violated. Insensibly almost, the Commons, whose chief function it originally was
                    to vote supplies to the crown, began to couple their grants with petitions for
                    the redress of grievances. The substance of these petitions and of the royal
                    responses was in time made the groundwork of Acts which, as framed by court
                    redactors, and appearing annexed to proclamationwrits after the dissolution of
                    Parliament, were frequently found seriously to misrepresent its will. To check
                    this evil an Act was passed (8 Henry IV.), authorising the Commons to be
                    represented at the engrossing of the Parliament roll; but even this surveillance
                    was not enough, for in the beginning of the reign of Henry V. it was enacted, at
                    the instance of the Commons, that in regard to their petitions the royal
                    prerogative should in future be limited to granting or refusing them <hi
                        rend="italic">simpliciter.</hi> In this way it became a fixed constitutional
                    principle that an Act of Parliament, to be valid, must express concurrently the
                    will of the entire Legislature. It was not, however, till the reign of Henry VI.
                    that it became customary, as now, to introduce bills into Parliament in the form
                    of finished Acts; and the enacting clause, regarded by constitutionalists as the
                    first perfect assertion, in words, of popular right, came into general use as
                    late as the reign of Charles II. It is thus expressed:—“Be it enacted by the
                    King’s most excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords
                    Spiritual and Temporal and Commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by
                    the authority of the same.” The use of the preamble with which Acts are usually
                    prefaced, is thus quaintly set forth by Lord Coke,—“The rehearsal or preamble of
                    the statute is a good meane to find out the meaning of the statute, aud, as it
                    were, a key to open the understanding thereof.” Originally, the collective Acts
                    of each session formed but one statute, to which a general title was attached,
                    and for this reason an Act of Parliament is always cited as the chapter of a
                    particular statute— <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> 24 and 25 Vict. c. 101. Titles
                    were, however, prefixed to individual Acts as early as 1488. Since 33 Geo. III.
                    c. 13, an Act of Parliament is complete whenever it receives the royal assent,
                    and takes effect from that date, unless the Act itself fix some other. British
                    Acts require no formal promulgation, for it is presumed that every subject of
                    the realm is cognisant of the resolutions of Parliament, either by himself or
                    his representative therein.</p>
                <p>&gt;Modern Acts of Parliament are—1. <hi rend="italic">Public.</hi> These are
                    binding on all citizens, and are <hi rend="italic">ex officio</hi> cognisable by
                    the judges. Since 1850 every Act is held to be public unless the contrary be
                    expressly declared. 2. <hi rend="italic">Private Acts.</hi> These relate to
                    particular classes, persons, or places. Private Acts are (1.) Personal, viz.,
                    those which relate to name, naturalisation, estate, &amp;c., of particular
                    persons. (2.) Local, affecting bridges, canals, docks, turnpikes, railways,
                    &amp;c. To prevent such Acts from being unduly passed, the promoters of private
                    bills are required to comply with the standing orders of the two Houses, by
                    whieh private bill procedure is regulated. Acts of Parliament, for convenience
                    of reference, are classified as Public General Acts, Local and Personal Acts
                    declared Public, Private Acts printed, and Private Acts not printed. Public
                    General Acts (if no exception be expressed), extend to Great Britain and
                    Ireland, exclusively only of the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man.</p>
                <p>The first complete edition of English Acts of Parliament published by state
                    authority appeared between the years 1810 and 1824. It includes the early
                    charters, and ends with the reign of Queen Anne. Many private editions of the
                    statutes had appeared previous to that of the Record Commissioners. The practice
                    of printing Acts of Parliament commenced in the reign of Richard III. The
                    charters and Acts were written in Latin till the <hi rend="italic">Statutum de
                        Scaccario, 51</hi> Henry III. (1266), which is in French. The Acts of Edward
                    I. are indiscriminately in Latin or French; but from the fourth year of Henry
                    VII. Acts are exclusively in English.</p>
                <p>Scotch Acts.—The earliest attempts at a written record of the proceedings of the
                    Parliament of Scotland consisted of detached instruments or indentures, and the
                    next step was the entering of these detached instruments on a roll for more
                    permanent preservation. No such record, however, is preserved before the
                    disputed succession, which commenced in 1289. The earliest roll of <hi
                        rend="italic">placita in parliamento</hi> is dated 1292; but the <hi
                        rend="italic">Blak Buik,</hi> containing a series of proceedings in
                    Parliament from 1357 to 1402, is the most important of the earliest records of
                    Parliament. The original books of Parliament of the reigns of James I. and James
                    II. are not preserved, but from the year 1466 down to the Union a voluminous,
                    but not unbroken, series has been preserved. Down to the reign of James V.,
                    scarcely any Act in the original registers is distinguished by a title or
                    rubric; and even after that period the practice has not in this respect been
                    uniform. In like manner there is no numeration of the Acts of Parliament during
                    this period. The language of the earliest Scotch records is in Latin; but as
                    early as 1398 some of the proceedings of Parliament 'or the Council-General were
                    written in Scots, and subsequently to 1424 always in that language. Unlike the
                    English Acts, French was never used in Scotch legislation. In 1541 a selection
                    of the Acts of James V. was printed. The first edition of the Acts was published
                    in 1566, the second in 1597, the third in 1681; and the great national work, the
                    complete record of Parliament, has just been completed, with a general index to
                    the whole Acts from 1124 to 1707, which forms the great repertory of the legal,
                    constitutional, and political history of Scotland. In 1540 an Act was passed
                    requiring all the Acts of Parliament to be pronounced in presence of the king
                    and the estates,—the assent of the king being indicated by his touching them
                    with the sceptre; and in 1641 it was ordained that the Acts passed in 1640 be
                    published in the king’s name, and with the consent of the estates. But during
                    the civil war the Acts of Parliament were passed in name of the estates alone.
                    These Acts, however, were rescinded after the restoration of Charles II. by Act
                    1661, c. 126, because “the power of making laws is an essential privilege of the
                    royal prerogative.” In 1457 an Act was passed for proclaiming the Acts of
                    Parliament in the shires and burghs, that none be ignorant; and in 1581 it was
                    ordained that Arts need not be proclaimed at the market-cross of the head burgh
                    of each shire, but at the market-cross of Edinburgh only, the lieges obeying
                    them forty days thereafter. The clerk of register was always bound to give
                    extracts of Acts to the lieges in their particular affairs. In 1425 a committee,
                    consisting of an equal number of each estate, was appointed to amend the books
                    of law; and in 1567 a commission was issued to codify the laws, civil and
                    municipal, dividing them into heads like the Roman law,—the heads as they are
                    ready to be brought to Parliament to be confirmed. Lord Bacon recommended the
                    Scotch Acts for their “excellent brevity.” His lordship’s praise applies very
                    properly to the Acts down to the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n138/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0901-0138-0123"/> reign of Queen Mary and the early part of the
                    reign of James VI.; but the logomachy of subsequent legislation is intolerable
                    to the consulter.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Irish Acts</hi> may be said to commence <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >a.d.</hi> 1310, in the reign of Edward II., and to close with the union
                    with the British Parliament in 1801. From the former date, however, there is a
                    break till 1429. In 1495 <hi rend="italic">Poyning's Law</hi> provided that no
                    bill should be introduced into the Irish Parliament which has not previously
                    received the royal assent in England; and till 1/82 the Parliament of Ireland
                    remained in tutelage to that of England. Since 1801 it has been incorporated
                    with the Parliament of Great Britain.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
