<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0901-0789-0746-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AMONTONS, Guillaume (9th edition, volume 1, page
                    746)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941253">Telegraphers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w24w">Telegraph</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz5d">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j6867c">Deafness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1146190">Telegraphers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1146129">Telegraph</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n789/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AMONTONS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Guillaume</hi></label>, a
                    celebrated French experimental philosopher, was the son of an advocate who had
                    left his native province of Normandy and established himself at Paris, where the
                    subject of this notice was bom on the 31st August 1663. The exertions of genius
                    frequently take a particular direction from accidental circumstances. A severe
                    illness with which Amontons was afflicted in his early youth had the effect of
                    rendering him almost entirely deaf, and consequently of secluding him in a great
                    measure from the ordinary intercourse of society. Being compelled by this
                    accident to depend for his enjoyments on the resources of his own mind, he began
                    to take great pleasure in the construction of machines of various kinds, and in
                    the study of the laws of mechanics, a path of inquiry which he pursued through
                    life with unremitting ardour and distinguished success. One of the first objects
                    which engaged his attention was the discovery of the perpetual motion,—an
                    attempt which, though necessarily unsuccessful, was productive of greater
                    advantage to him than it has usually been to those who have pursued that vain
                    chimera. Amontons devoted himself particularly to the improvement of instruments
                    employed in physical experiments, a subject which requires the finest
                    applications of mechanical principles, and which till that time had not met with
                    a due share of attention. In 1687, before he had attained his 24th year, he
                    presented to the Academy of Sciences an hygrometer of his own invention, which
                    was received with approbation by that learned body. In 1695 he published the
                    only work which he has given to the world. It was dedicated to the Academy, and
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Remarques et Expériences Physiques sur la
                        Construction</hi><hi rend="italic">(Tun</hi><hi rend="italic">Nouvel
                        Clepsydre, sur les Baromètres, les Thermomètres, et les Hygromètres.</hi>
                    After Huyghens’s beautiful application of the pendulum to the regulation of the
                    motion of clocks, any attempt to revive the clepsydra, an incommodious
                    instrument, and not susceptible of much accuracy, might seem to subject its
                    author to the imputation of not sufficiently appreciating the great importance
                    of a discovery which has so completely changed the face of astronomical science;
                    but the object of Amontons was to produce an instrument capable of measuring
                    time on board ship, in circumstances where the motion of the vessel rendered
                    such timekeepers as were then known useless. The machine which he constructed is
                    said to have been extremely ingenious, and probably differed entirely from those
                    of the ancients, among whom the clepsydra was in common use. In 1689 Amontons
                    was admitted into the Academy of Sciences, the Memoirs of which he enriched with
                    many important contributions. The first paper which he presented after his
                    admission was one on the theory of <hi rend="italic">friction,</hi> a subject
                    then involved in great obscurity, and on which his inquiries tended to throw
                    considerable light. After that appeared in succession descriptions of a new
                    thermometer, and of numerous experiments made with the barometer relative to the
                    nature and properties of air,—a detailed account of all which is given in the
                    history of the Academy. In the course of these investigations he found that the
                    boiling point of water varies with the pressure of the atmosphere, a discovery
                    made almost contemporaneously in England by Dr Halley. By his countrymen he is
                    generally regarded as the inventor of the telegraph; and he had the honour of
                    exhibiting the methods by which he proposed to accomplish the object in view
                    before some members of the royal family. It appears, however, from a paper read
                    by Dr Hooke to the Royal Society in 1684, that that ingenious philosopher had
                    brought the telegraph, in theory at least, to a state of far greater maturity
                    than Amontons, and nearly 20 years earlier. The experiments of the latter were
                    made about the year 1702. It may be regarded as a curious fact in the history of
                    inventions, that although the great importance of telegraphic communication is
                    obvious, and the method of accomplishing it was clearly explained by Hooke, and
                    its practicability demonstrated by Amontons, it continued to be regarded as of
                    no practical value, and was not regularly applied to useful purposes till nearly
                    a century afterwards, at the time of the French Revolution. Amontons died in
                    1705, aged 42.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
