<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0528-0491-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALEXANDER, Paulovich</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 491</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kn9d">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1227863">Lithuania</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n528/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALEXANDER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Paulovich</hi></label>,
                    Emperor of Russia—born on 28th December 1777, died 1825—was the son of Paul,
                    afterwards emperor, by Maria, daughter of Prince Eugene of Würtemberg. His early
                    education was conducted under his excellent mother, and afterwards was carefully
                    directed by his grandmother, the Empress Catherine II., who con-tided<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n529/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0529-0492"/> its general superintendence to Frederick Caesar
                    de La Harpe. On the assassination of his father Paul in 1801, Alexander
                    succeeded to the Russian throne. He had been married in 1793 to the Princess
                    Louisa Maria of Baden, but the union proved an unhappy one, and had no
                    issue.</p>
                <p>The policy of the young emperor was indicated by his concluding a peace with
                    Britain, against which his father had declared war. In 1805 he joined Austria
                    and Sweden in a coalition with Great Britain against the pretensions of France.
                    The war that followed was disastrous to the allies. The armies of Austria were
                    totally defeated in a succession of battles between the 6th and 13th October of
                    that year; and the combined Austrian and Russian armies, under the two emperors,
                    were defeated by Napoleon in the great battle of Austerlitz on the 2d December.
                    Austria concluded a separate treaty of peace, and Alexander led the remains of
                    his army into his own dominions. Prussia, which had injudiciously stood neutral
                    while France was humbling Austria and Russia, rashly engaged in hostilities with
                    Napoleon in 1806, while her allies, the Russians, were still beyond the Vistula;
                    but the defeats at Auerstadt and Jena laid Prussia prostrate; and in the
                    succeeding year the battles of Eylau and Friedland, in which the Russians were
                    fairly beaten, led to the dismemberment of Prussia, and the treaty of Tilsit
                    with Russia. A few days after the last battle, Alexander and Napoleon met on a
                    raft anchored in the river Niemen, and agreed to the treaty, which was signed at
                    Tilsit on July 7. By a secret article of this treaty Alexander was not only to
                    withdraw from his connection with Britain, but to become her enemy; and he
                    declared war against her on the 26th October.</p>
                <p>For nearly five years Alexander appeared attached to the alliance of France; but
                    the privations of his subjects by the interruption of the commerce with England,
                    and the intolerable load of Napoleon’s “Continental System,” at length induced
                    him to return to his old alliance, and to declare war against France on March
                    19, 1812. On the 24th April he left St Petersburg to join his armies on the west
                    frontier of Lithuania. Napoleon assembled the most numerous and magnificent army
                    that had ever been brought together in modern times, augmented by the unwilling
                    levies of Prussia and Austria, and entered Russia on the 25th June 1812. The
                    first encounter was at Borodino, where there was a well-contested action, in
                    which each army suffered the loss of 25,000 men. The burning of Moscow, and the
                    subsequent retreat of Napoleon, during which his army was all but annihilated,
                    are among the best known events of modern history.</p>
                <p>In 1813 the advancing Russians were successively joined by the forces of Prussia,
                    Austria, and Sweden. Alexander continued with the allied armies, and in
                    particular was present at the battles of Dresden and Leipsic. Napoleon had made
                    wonderful exertions to repair his losses in the early part of 1814; but the
                    victories of Wellington in Spain, and his advance into the heart of France,
                    favoured the progress of the allies; and on March 30, 181-4, 150,000 men of the
                    allied armies took possession of Paris, which was entered next day by Alexander
                    and the king of Prussia.</p>
                <p>After the deposition of Napoleon the allied sovereigns visited England. By the
                    treaty of Vienna, Alexander was acknowledged king of Poland; but before the
                    congress of Vienna broke up, Napoleon had escaped from Elba, and was
                    enthusiastically received at Paris. The two eastern emperors and the king of
                    Prussia remained together until the battle of Waterloo gave peace to Europe. On
                    the advance of the British and Prussians to Paris, the three allied sovereigns
                    again made their entry into that capital, where they concluded, on September 26,
                    the treaty which has been designated <hi rend="italic">the Holy
                    Alliance.</hi></p>
                <p>Alexander was henceforward chiefly occupied in the internal administration of his
                    vast dominions, which certainly improved more during the twenty-five years of
                    his reign than under any of his predecessors from the time of Peter I. The
                    gradual abolition of the feudal servitude of the peasantry, begun by the most
                    enlightened of his predecessors, was continued under Alexander. Education,
                    agriculture, manufactures, commerce, were also greatly extended; while
                    literature and the fine arts were liberally encouraged. His disposition has been
                    represented by his subjects as mild and merciful; yet his influence in the
                    affairs of Europe was not exerted in the cause of public liberty. But this could
                    hardly be expected from the autocrat of an unmitigated despotism in his own
                    territories. He will, however, bear very favourable comparison with any Russian
                    sovereign, or even with any contemporary monarch.</p>
                <p>Early in the winter of 1825 he left St Petersburg for the last time on a tour of
                    inspection of his southern provinces. About the middle of November he was
                    attacked by a violent intermittent fever, which proved fatal at Taganrog on
                    December 1, 1825. In foreign countries his death has been attributed to poison;
                    but this is refuted by the history of his disease, and is very improbable, from
                    his great popularity with his countrymen. He was succeeded, in accordance with a
                    family compact, by his second brother Nicholas.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
