<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0901-0488-0451-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALBERT (9th edition, volume 1, page 451)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830115">Belgians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:847566">Caring</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm13w80">Patents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09w92">Addresses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n488/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALBERT</label> (PRINCE), <hi rend="smallcaps">Francis Charles
                        Augustus Albert Emmanuel,</hi> Prince Consort of England, born at Rosenau on
                    the 26th Aug. 1819, was the second son of the hereditary Duke of
                    Saxe-Coburg-Gotha, by his first wife the Princess Louise of
                    Saxe-Gotha-Altenburg. He thus belonged to the Ernestine or elder branch of the
                    royal family of Saxony, which, on account of its adherence to the doctrines of
                    the Reformation, had to surrender the kingdom to the Albertine or younger
                    branch, which is still in possession of it. The marriage of his parents proving
                    an unhappy one, they separated in 1824, and the young prince never again saw his
                    mother, who died in 1831. He was educated, along with his elder brother Ernest,
                    under the care of <hi rend="italic">Consistorial-Rath</hi> Florschütz, who, in a
                    memorandum drawn up after the prince’s death, speaks in the highest terms of his
                    pupil’s benevolent disposition and studious habits. At the proper age the
                    brothers proceeded to the university of Bonn, where Herr Florschütz still
                    continued to exercise a general superintendence of their studies. Prince Albert
                    devoted himself especially to the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n489/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0901-0489-0452"/> natural sciences, political economy, and
                    philosophy, having for teachers men of such world-wide fame as Fichte, Schlegel,
                    and Perthes. He also diligently cultivated at this period the sister arts of
                    music and painting, and thus qualified himself for some of the most valuable
                    services he was afterwards to render to the land of his adoption. His feeling
                    for art in all its forms was very sensitive, and his executive skill, both as a
                    musician and painter, very considerable. In gymnastic exercises he greatly
                    excelled, carrying off the first prize for fencing in a competition with a large
                    number of students.</p>
                <p>In 1836 the prince visited England in company with his father, and met his future
                    consort for the first time. The idea of a matrimonial alliance between the
                    cousins had occurred to various members of the family, and had been cherished
                    especially by their grandmother the dowagerduchess of Coburg, and their uncle
                    Leopold, the king of the Belgians. From the time of the queen’s accession there
                    seems to have been a family understanding on the subject, though, owing to the
                    youth of the prince and his cousin, no formal engagement was entered into till
                    two years later. In the winter of 1838-9 the prince travelled in Italy,
                    accompanied by Mr Seymour, a young English gentleman, who was selected doubtless
                    out of regard to the probable future of his charge. A year later the hopes of
                    many were realised when, on the 23d Nov. 1839, the queen announced to the Privy
                    Council her intended marriage with her cousin. The circumstances of the
                    engagement have been fully made known since the prince’s death, and they show
                    that the union was founded upon mutual choice, springing from mutual affection.
                    On the 10th February 1840 the marriage was celebrated at the chapelroyal, St
                    James’s, amid universal rejoicings. A few days before the event two bills had
                    been passed in parliament, one naturalising the prince as a British subject, and
                    the other providing an annuity of £30,000 a year for the maintenance of his
                    establishment. The ministry had proposed that the sum should be £50,000,
                    following the precedent established in the case of Prince Leopold; but the
                    reduction was made on the motion of Colonel Sibthorpe, who received the support
                    of the radicals and the entire opposition. The result of the vote caused the
                    prince considerable vexation and disappointment, which were enhanced when
                    difficulties were raised in parliament as to the precedence to be accorded to
                    him. The latter question was only settled by an exercise of the queen’s
                    prerogative. Letters patent were issued on the 5th March, giving the prince
                    precedence next to the queen.</p>
                <p>The position in which the prince was placed by his marriage, while it was one of
                    distinguished honour, was also one of peculiar difficulty, and it was only the
                    possession of a rare discretion that enabled him to fill it so irreproachably as
                    he did. Published letters and memoranda show how thoroughly he appreciated the
                    delicate nature of his duties, and how clearly he perceived the limits within
                    which his influence must be confined if it was to be legitimately and usefully
                    exerted. A letter to the Duke of Wellington, declining, after mature
                    consideration, to be designated to the office of commander-in-chief of the army,
                    is especially noteworthy as containing an admirable description of the proper
                    functions of a princeconsort. Generally, his idea was that it was his duty to
                    merge his personality as completely as possible in that of the sovereign, while
                    giving her in all things real but unobtrusive advice and support; and that he
                    acted during his whole life in conformity with this idea those who had the best
                    means of knowing were the readiest to testify. Once, indeed, at the commencement
                    of the Crimean war, it was generally believed that he had overstepped the limits
                    of his position by interfering unwarrantably with the foreign policy of the
                    country and the patronage of the army. The charges were so definite and so
                    widely circulated that it was deemed necessary to take notice of them in
                    parliament. They were met by a complete and emphatic denial on the part of the
                    ministry, and no one now believes that they had any real foundation. It was, of
                    course, both natural and proper that the prince should interest himself deeply
                    in the affairs of the country over which, by an Act passed on the 4th Aug. 1840,
                    he had been named regent in the event of the death of the queen before the heir
                    to the crown had attained the age of eighteen years. He had also a right to
                    interest himself in the administration of the army, as being himself a
                    field-marshal and a colonel of hussars.</p>
                <p>It was fortunate for the prince, shut out as he was by the circumstances of his
                    station from any share in party politics, that he found other and more congenial
                    work sufficient to engage all his energies. He was qualified, as few of his rank
                    are, to deal with those social and scientific problems in the solution of which
                    men of all parties are equally interested. He engaged himself especially in
                    endeavours to secure the more perfect application of science and art to
                    manufacturing industry. The Great Exhibition of 1851 originated in a suggestion
                    he threw out at a meeting of the Society of Arts, and owed the greater part of
                    its success to his intelligent and unwearied efforts. Similar institutions, on a
                    smaller scale but with a kindred aim, always found in him warm advocacy and
                    substantial sup port. It was chiefly at meetings in connection with these that
                    he found occasion for the delivery of addresses characterised by profound
                    thought and comprehensiveness of view, a collection of which was published in
                    1857. One of the most favourable specimens of his powers as a speaker is the
                    inaugural address which he delivered as President of the British Association for
                    the Advancement of Science when it met at Aberdeen in 1859, printed in an
                    edition of his speeches which appeared in 1862. The education of his family and
                    the management of his domestic affairs furnished the prince with another very
                    important sphere of action, in which he employed himself with conscientious
                    devotedness. The training of the Prince of Wales was carried on under his own
                    superintendence, in accordance with a plan he himself had drawn up; and it may
                    be questioned whether so much wisdom and care was ever bestowed on the
                    upbringing bf an heir to the British throne. The estates of the Duchy of
                    Cornwall, the hereditary appanage of the Prince of Wales, were so greatly
                    improved under his father’s management that the rent-roll rose from £11,000 to
                    £50,000 a year. Prince Albert, indeed, had a peculiar talent for the management
                    of landed estates. His model farm at Windsor was in every way worthy of the
                    name; and the grounds at Balmoral and Osborne, so universally admired, were laid
                    out entirely in conformity with his designs.</p>
                <p>A character so pure, and a life so useful and well-directed in all its aims,
                    could scarcely fail to secure universal respect. As the prince became better
                    known, the mistrust, of which the adverse votes in parliament were undoubtedly
                    to some extent an expression, gave way, and the people vied with their queen in
                    showering deserved honours upon him. After a keen contest with Earl Powis, he
                    was elected chancellor of the university of Cambridge in 1847; and he was
                    afterwards appointed master of the Trinity House. In 1857 the formal title of
                    “Prince-Consort” was conferred upon him by letters patent, in order to settle
                    certain difficulties as to precedence that had been raised at foreign courts. As
                    he had previously possessed no distinctive title, the precedence he had received
                    was only by courtesy.</p>
                <p>It was in the prime of manhood and the full career of his usefulness that the
                    prince-consort was removed by death. He had been greatly occupied during the
                    autumn <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n490/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0901-0490-0453"/> of 1861 with the arrangements for the
                    projected international exhibition, and it was just after returning from one of
                    the meetings in connection with it that he was seized with his last illness. He
                    died of typhoid fever on the 14th of Dec. 1861. Few have ever been more
                    sincerely or more universally mourned. The grief of the queen was deep and
                    lasting, and the whole nation sympathised in the truest sense with her in her
                    sorrow. Perhaps never before, except on the occasion of the death of the
                    Princess Charlotte, had all classes of the people been so closely knit together
                    in the feeling of a common bereavement and a common sorrow. A national memorial,
                    to be erected partly by parliamentary vote and partly by public subscription,
                    was at once resolved upon, and nearly every town of importance throughout the
                    kingdom embodied in a statue or some other form its tribute to the memory of
                    “The Good Prince.” The magnificent mausoleum at Frogmore, in which his remains
                    were finally deposited, was erected at the expense of the Queen and the royal
                    family. (See <hi rend="italic">Early Years of H.R.H. the Prince Consort,</hi>
                    1867; <hi rend="italic">Principal Speeches and Addresses of Prince Albert,</hi>
                    with an Introduction, 1862).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
