<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0052-0037-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ABERCROMBY, Patrick</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 37</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dn7s">Witnesses</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4wp9tb5s">Historians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44x4f">Doctors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:957686">Historians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1062841">Physicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1176383">Witnesses</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n52/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ABERCROMBY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Patrick</hi></label>, M.D.,
                    was the third son of Alexander Abercromby of Fetterneir in Aberdeenshire, and
                    brother of Francis Abercromby, who was created by James II. Lord Glasford. He
                    was born at Forfar in 1656. As throughout Scotland, he could have had there the
                    benefits of a good parish school; but it would seem from after events that his
                    family was Roman Catholic, and hence, in all probability, his education was
                    private. This, and not the unproved charge of perversion from Protestantism in
                    subserviency to James II., explains his Roman Catholicism and adhesion to the
                    fortunes of that king. But, intending to become a doctor of medicine, he entered
                    the University of St Andrews, where he took his degree of M.D. in 1685, From a
                    statement in one of his preface-epistles to his <hi rend="italic">magnum
                    opus,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Martial Achievements of the Scots Nation,</hi>
                    he must have spent most of his youthful years abroad. It has been stated that he
                    attended the University of Paris. The <hi rend="italic">Discourse of Wit</hi>
                    (1685), assigned to him, belongs to Dr David Abercromby, a contemporary. On his
                    return to Scotland, he is found practising as a physician in Edinburgh, where,
                    besides his professional duties, he gave himself with characteristic zeal to the
                    study of antiquities, a study to which he owes it that his name still lives, for
                    he finds no place in either Haller or Hutchison’s <hi rend="italic">Medical
                    Biographies.</hi> He was out-and-out a Scot of the old patriotic type, and,
                    living as he did during the agitations for the union of England and Scotland, he
                    took part in the war of pamphlets inaugurated and sustained by prominent men on
                    both sides of the Border. He crossed swords with no less redoubtable a foe than
                    Daniel Defoe in his <hi rend="italic">Advantages of the Act of Security,
                    compared with those of the intended Union</hi> (Edinburgh, 1707), and <hi
                    rend="italic">A Vindication of the Same against Mr De Foe (ibid.)</hi> The logic
                    and reason were with Defoe, but there was a <hi rend="italic">sentiment</hi> in
                    tho advocates of independence which was not sufficiently allowed for in the
                    clamour of debate; and, besides, the disadvantages of union were near, hard, and
                    actual, the advantages remote, and contingent on many things and persons. Union
                    wore the look to men like Abercromby and Lord Belhaven of absorption, if not
                    extinction. Abercromby was appointed physician to James II., but the Revolution
                    deprived him of the post. Crawford (in his <hi rend="italic">Peerage,</hi> 1716)
                    ascribes the title of Lord Glasford to an intended recognition of ancestral
                    loyalty; its bestowment in 1685 corresponding with the younger brother’s
                    graduation as M.D., may perhaps explain his appointment. A minor literary work
                    of Abercromby’s was a translation of Μ. Beague’s partizan History (so called) of
                    the War carried on by the Popish Government of Cardinal Beaton, aided by the
                    French, against the English under the Protector Somerset, which appeared in
                    1707. The work with which Abercromby’s name is permanently associated is his
                    already noticed <hi rend="italic">Martial Achievements of the Scots Nation,</hi>
                    issued in two noble folios, vol. i. 1711, vol. ii. 1716. In the titlepage and
                    preface to vol. i. he disclaims the ambition of being an historian, but in vol.
                    ii., in title-page and preface alike, he is no longer a simple biographer, but
                    an historian. That Dr Abercromby did not use the word <hi rend="italic"
                    >“genuine</hi> history” in his title-page without warrant is clear on every page
                    of his large work. Granted that, read in the light of after researches, much of
                    the first volume must necessarily be relegated to the region of the mythical,
                    none the less was the historian a laborious and accomplished reader and
                    investigator of all available authorities, as well manuscript as <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n53/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0053-0038"/> printed; while the roll of names of those who
                    aided him includes every man of note in Scotland at the time, from Sir Thomas
                    Craig and Sir George Mackenzie to Mr Alexander Nisbet and Mr Thomas Ruddiman.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Martial Achievements</hi> has not been reprinted, though
                    practically the first example of Scottish typography in any way noticeable, vol.
                    ii. having been printed under the scholarly supervision of Thomas Ruddiman. The
                    date of his death is uncertain. It has been variously assigned to 1715, 1716,
                    1720, and 1726, and it is usually added that he left a widow in great poverty.
                    That he was living in 1716 is certain, as Crawford speaks of him (in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Peerage,</hi> 1716) as “my worthy friend.” Probably he died about
                    1716. <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Abercrombys,</hi> commonly given to him,
                    does not appear to have been published. (Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Eminent
                    Scotsmen, s. v.;</hi> Anderson’s <hi rend="italic">Scottish Nation, s. υ.;</hi>
                    Chalmers’s <hi rend="italic">Biog. Dict., s. v.;</hi> Chalmers’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of Ruddiman;</hi> Haller’s <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca
                    Medicin</hi><hi rend="italic">ae</hi><hi rend="italic">Pract.,</hi> 4 vols. 4to,
                    1779; Hutchinson’s <hi rend="italic">Biog. Medical,</hi> 2 vols. 8vo, 1799;
                    Lee’s <hi rend="italic">Defoe,</hi> 3 vols. 8vo.) <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. b.
                    g.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
