<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0901-0817-0774-05" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AMPHITHEATRE (9th edition, volume 1, page 774)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:814226">Arenas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q814s63">Beasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n817/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AMPHITHEATRE</label> (from <hi rend="italic">άρ,φί</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">θeaτpov)</hi> denotes a theatre in which the spectators
                    were placed “all round’’ the stage. Though the word is of Greek formation, the
                    thing itself is distinctively Roman, being designed for those cruel shows of
                    gladiators and wild beasts in which that people took great pleasure, and which
                    in modem times are only represented by the barbarous bull-fights still popular
                    in Spain.</p>
                <p>In the present article we do not enter on the consideration of the spectacles
                    themselves, but shall confine ourselves to the buildings, which were devised to
                    allow as large a number of spectators as possible to enjoy the sight of the
                    show. In a -dramatic representation it is necessary, that the actors should be
                    heard, and also that their faces should be seen, and the audience has therefore
                    to be arranged in a semicircle in front of them; but when men fought with other
                    men or with beasts, they could be seen equally well from all sides.</p>
                <p>In Italy, combats of gladiators at first took place in the forums, where
                    temporary wooden scaffoldings were erected for the spectators; and Vitruvius
                    gives this as the reason why in that country the forums were in the shape of a
                    parallelogram instead of being squares as in Greece. Wild beasts were also
                    hunted in the circus. But towards the end of the Roman republic, when the shows
                    increased both in frequency and in costliness as the city grew in power, special
                    buildings began to be provided for them; and when the consolidation of peace
                    under the empire had secured great material prosperity for the provinces, such
                    as they had never enjoyed when separated into small states and often at war with
                    each other, the example of the capital was followed by many other towns in the
                    West; so that nearly a hundred amphitheatres have been identified, either by the
                    existence of their ruins or by being mentioned by old writers. There were even a
                    few in the East, although such cruel games were quite alien to the elegance and
                    refinement of the Hellenic mind.</p>
                <p>From their being so admirably adapted for enabling the greatest possible number
                    of people to behold a spectacle, it is natural to suppose that they would be
                    occasionally used for purposes different from those usually intended by them;
                    and accordingly Suetonius relates how Caligula had an impertinent poet burnt
                    alive in the amphitheatre, and how Titus ordered the informers, after having
                    been whipped in the forum, to be led through the arena, apparently that they
                    might be exposed to the execrations of the people. Criminals were also sometimes
                    exposed in them to be devoured by wild beasts, and many of the Christian martyrs
                    died in this way.</p>
                <p>The first amphitheatre was that constructed, 59 B.c., by C. Scribonius Curio. The
                    only author by whom it is described is Pliny, whose account of it rather taxes
                    our credulity. He tells that Scribonius built two wooden theatres, which were
                    placed back to back, and that after the dramatic representations were finished,
                    they were turned round, with all the spectators in them, so as to make one
                    circular theatre, in [the centre of which gladiators fought And this was
                    repeated more than once. Thirteen years later, Caesar built (also of wood) the
                    first regular amphitheatre, and exhibited wild beasts in it; and sixteen years
                    after, C. Statilius Taurus built the first one of stone, which was burnt in the
                    great fire of Rome during the reign oi Nero. Probably the outside walls only
                    were of stone.</p>
                <p>Several others were constructed under the early em perors, but they were entirely
                    superseded and eclipsed bj that of. Vespasian and Titus, the vast ruins of which
                    strike the traveller with awe. Set on fire by lightning undeι the emperor
                    Macrinus, it was restored by Alexandeι Severus, the shows during the interval
                    being held (as oi old) in the circus. The latest record of its being used if in
                    the 6th century, when Cassiodorus was present; bul Bede in the 8th century
                    speaks of the edifice as still entire. During the Middle Ages many of the stones
                    of this, as of many other ancient buildings, were carried' away foi building
                    purposes; and among the plunderers we regret tc have to reckon the great Michel
                    Angelo, who worked up a large number of its stones into a palace for one oi the
                    Roman noble families. As, however, the Colosseun had been the scene of many of
                    the Christian martyrdoms Benedict XIV., whose name ought never tp be mentioned
                    without an expression of admiration and gratitude for his enlightened patronage
                    of learning and antiquities, tool advantage of this to consecrate the interior
                    by the erec tion of crosses and oratories, thereby preserving it fron further
                    depredations. Of late years considerable excava tions have been made to examine
                    its substructures. Its name is variously written, but on the whole it wouk seem
                    that the most correct orthography is Colosseum (no Coliseum), and that it is.
                    derived from its colossal size which far surpassed any former edifice of the
                    sort. Mam of its minor arrangements are uncertain, but the mail features and
                    general plan are sufficiently intelligible.</p>
                <p>The external elevation of the Colosseum consisted o four stages, each adorned
                    with engaged columns of th three orders of Greek architecture. The lowest three
                    wer arcaded, having each eighty columns and as many arches Those of the basement
                    story served as entrances; seventy <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n818/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0901-0818-0775"/> eîx being numbered and allotted to the
                    general body of spectators, while four, at the extremities of the axes of the
                    ellipse, were the principal éntrances. The higher arcades had a low parapet with
                    (apparently) a statue in each arch, and gave light and air to the passages which
                    surrounded the building. The openings of the arcades above the principal
                    entrances were larger than the rest, and were adorned with figures of chariots.
                    The highest stage was much more solid, being composed of a continuous wall of
                    masonry, only pierced by forty small square windows. The object of this may have
                    been to obtain the necessary solidity and weight for steadying the poles which
                    supported the awning, and must have had to carry a severe inward strain. The
                    alternate arcades were ornamented with metal shields. There was also a series of
                    brackets to support the poles on which the awning was stretched.</p>
                <p>The interior may be naturally divided into the <hi rend="italic">arena</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">cavea,</hi> with their respective appendages.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">arena</hi> was the portion assigned to the combatants, and
                    derived its name from the sand with which it was strewn, to absorb the blood and
                    prevent it from becoming slippery. Some of the emperors showed their prodigality
                    by substituting precious powders, and even gold dust, for sand. The <hi
                        rend="italic">arena</hi> was generally of the same shape as the amphitheatre
                    itself, and was separated from the spectators by a wall built perfectly smooth,
                    that the wild beasts might not by any possibility climb it. At Rome it was faced
                    inside with polished marble, but at Pompeii it was simply painted. For further
                    security, it was surrounded by a metal railing or network, and the arena was
                    sometimes surrounded also by a ditch <hi rend="italic">(euripus),</hi>
                    especially on account of the elephants. Connected with the arena were the dens
                    from which the beasts came, and the rooms where the gladiators met before the
                    show began. In spite of the excavations which have been made, it is not very
                    easy to understand how all the effects described by ancient authors were
                    produced; for after the regular shows were over, the arena was sometimes filled
                    with water, and sea-fights were exhibited with ships.</p>
                <p>The part assigned to the spectators was called <hi rend="italic">cavea.</hi> In
                    the different amphitheatres whose ruins have been examined, there are some
                    differences in the arrangements, but the general features are nearly the same in
                    all. The <hi rend="italic">cavea</hi> was divided into several galleries,
                    concentric with the outer walls, and therefore, like them, of an elliptic form.
                    The place of honour was the lowest of these, nearest to the arena, and called
                    the <hi rend="italic">podium.</hi> The divisions in it were larger, so as to be
                    able to contain movable seats. At Rome it was here that the emperor sat, his
                    seat bearing the name of <hi rend="italic">suggestum.</hi> The senators,
                    principal magistrates, vestal virgins, the provider <hi rend="italic"
                        >(editor)</hi> of the show, and other persons of note, occupied the rest of
                    the <hi rend="italic">podium.</hi> At Nismes, besides the nigh officials of the
                    town, the <hi rend="italic">podium</hi> had places assigned to the principal
                    guilds, whose names are still seen inscribed upon it, with the number of places
                    reserved for each. In the Colosseum there were three <hi rend="italic"
                        >moeniana</hi> or galleries above the <hi rend="italic">podium,</hi>
                    separated from each other by terraces <hi rend="italic">(proednctiones)</hi> and
                    walls <hi rend="italic">(baltei).</hi> The lowest was appropriated to the
                    equestrian order. Numerous passages <hi rend="italic">(vomitoria)</hi> and small
                    stairs gave access to them; while long covered corridors, behind and below them,
                    served for shelter in the event of rain. At Pompeii each place was numbered, and
                    elsewhere their extent is defined by little marks cut in the stone. The
                    spectators were admitted by tickets <hi rend="italic">(tesseroe),</hi> and order
                    preserved by a staff of officers appointed for the purpose.</p>
                <p>The height of the Colosseum is given as from 160 to 180 feet. The seats in the
                    interior do not rise higher than the level of the third order of the exterior,
                    that is, about half the entire height of the building; and this apparent excess
                    of height beyond what was made available, has led some to suppose that there
                    were upper seats and galleries, of which no trace now exists. The height,
                    however, appears to have been necessary for the ventilation of the building.
                    When such enormous crowds were packed closely together for several hours at a
                    time on an Italian summer day, with an awning drawn over them, the atmosphere
                    would have become quite pestilential if there had not been a considerable space
                    overhead, and at least one range of open arcades, unencumbered by any galleries
                    to prevent the free circulation of air. Scented liquids were at times squirted
                    over the spectators from concealed tubes; but no aroma would have compensated
                    for the want of air, which the arcade all round the building, above the highest
                    spectators, would supply. There may also have been another series of openings
                    serving the same purpose between the top of the wall and the edge of the awning,
                    which was supported upon poles. It has been calculated that the Colosseum
                    contained 87,000 places, and that besides these, 15,000 more spectators could be
                    admitted. The greatest length is about 612 feet, and the length of the shortest
                    axis of the ellipse about 515 feet. The dimensions of the arena are variously
                    stated by different writers, some making it 247 feet by 150, and others 281 by
                    176.</p>
                <p>With regard to the provincial amphitheatres, Maffei, in his account of that of
                    Verona, appears to have unduly restricted their number, with the object of
                    exalting the honour of the one he describes. Besides the Colosseum, he would
                    hardly allow any ruins to be entitled to this name except those at Verona and
                    Capua. But subsequent writers have not followed him in this rigorism; and
                    Friedländer, who is the latest and most complete authority on the subject, gives
                    the measurements and description of fifty-two. Naturally, the early ones would
                    be of wood, like that erected by Atilius at Fidenae in the time of Tiberius,
                    which gave way while shows were being exhibited, on which occason 50,000 persons
                    were killed or injured. One at Placentia is also mentioned, which is said to
                    have been the most spacious then in Italy, and to have been burned in the wars
                    between Otho and Vitellius by the inhabitants of a neighbouring town whose envy
                    it had excited. Such disasters, coupled with the growing scarcity of wood and
                    the greater facilities for quarrying stone, would naturally lead to the
                    construction of more solid buildings. At the same time, the progress of this
                    improvement must have been slow, and the building of at least the great majority
                    of the provincial amphitheatres of stone may be ascribed to the period between
                    the reign of Vespasian and that of Constantine, when the establishment of
                    Christianity threw a discredit on the cruel and bloody shows for which these
                    vast structures were designed. Hadrian is especially commemorated for the
                    numerous <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n819/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0901-0819-0776"/> buildings he caused to be erected almost
                    everywhere, and this is mentioned in connection with games being held.</p>
                <p>In constructing many of the amphitheatres in the provincial towns, advantage was
                    taken of the natural slope of a hill to lessen the labour of construction; and
                    in some cases a narrow ravine between two hills allowed of both sides being
                    formed on the natural slopes, and of the stream at their feet being dammed up
                    for combats on the water. The conformation of the ground and the caprices of
                    local authorities have produced slight minor differences of plan, but the
                    general description of the Colosseum will suffice for all. For details regarding
                    others the reader may consult, in addition to other authorities, the
                    descriptions given in this work of the different towns where their remains are
                    still found. Here it may be sufficient to name that at Pompeii, which is
                    probably better known to most persons by the graphic description in Lord
                    Lytton’s novel than by any of the illustrated accounts that have been published
                    of that wonderful town; that at Verona, which served as a basis to Maffei’s
                    careful investigation of the whole subject; those at Capua and PozzuoH, which
                    almost rival the Colosseum in dimensions; those at Nismes, Arles, and Frejus in
                    France; that at Italica, near Seville in Spain, remarkable for the thickness of
                    its walls and the strength of its masonry—leading Florez to remark that its ruin
                    is due not to the injuries of time and the weather, but to the hand of man; that
                    at the ancient Thysdrus, in the province of Carthage, now called <hi
                        rend="italic">ElrDjemm,</hi> which alone resembles the Colosseum in having
                    five galleries or corridors in the first storey; and that at Pola in Istria,
                    whose external shell —the internal fittings, which were probably all of wood,
                    having quite disappeared—forms a striking object as seen from the sea.</p>
                <p>A very fair summary of the whole subject will be found in Smith’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Dictionary of Classical Antiquities;</hi> and a much more
                    minute and elaborate account, by C. Thierry, with good illustrations, in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Dictionnaire des Antiquités</hi> of Daremberg and Saglio,
                    which has the further advantage of giving numerous references to larger works on
                    the subject, —its chief defect being one too common in French books, the almost
                    complete ignoring of eveιything published in this country, where Taylor and
                    Cresy’s <hi rend="italic">Architectural Antiquities of Rome,</hi> of which a
                    second edition has recently appeared, is entitled to special mention. Nor does
                    it notice that treasure of information about Spanish history and antiquities,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Espana Sagrada,</hi> where (vol. xii. p. 228) will be
                    found the most careful account of the amphitheatre at Italica, with several
                    drawings. The following table, abridged from Friedlander’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Darstellung aus der Sittengeschichte Roms</hi> (1865, 2d ed. 1867), gives
                    the dimensions, in English feet, of a few of the principal amphitheatres that
                    have been examined:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>1 Entire Building.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Arena.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>I Greeter Axis.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Shorter Axis.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Greater Axis.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Shorter Axis.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Puzzuoli,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Feet.</p><p>626⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Feet.</p><p>475</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Feet.</p><p>367</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Feet.</p><p>216</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Rome (Colosseum),</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>616</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>δlθ⅛</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>281</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>176</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Falerii,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>586⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>348</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Capua,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>557</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>458</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>250</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>150</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Julia Coesarea,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>551</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>289</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>459</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>197</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Italica (Seville),</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>513</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>439⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Verona,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>505∣</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>403</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>248</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1454</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Tarraco,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>486</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>390</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>277</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>181</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Thysdrus</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>457</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>392</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>253⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>188</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Pola</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>452</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3694</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>230;</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>147</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Arles,</p><p>Pompeii,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>448</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>352</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>228</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>129</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>445</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>341</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2184</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>115</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Tours,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>443</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>393⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>223</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>984</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Niemes,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4334</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>332⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>227</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>126⅜</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
