<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0825-0782-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">AMYRAUT, Moses</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 782</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x59s">Calvinism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hv69">Nonconformists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:959074">Home</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1353235">Homes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:844591">Calvinism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n825/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AMYRAUT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Moses</hi></label>, a
                    pre-eminent French Protestant theologian and metaphysician, was born at
                    Bourgueil, in the valley of Anjou, in 1596. His family was an ancient and
                    illustrious one from Hagenau, Alsace. They migrated to Orleans in the 13th or
                    14th century. His father was a lawyer of local note, and designing Moses for his
                    own profession, on the completion of his studies at Orleans of humanity and
                    philosophy, he sent him to the university of Poictiers. It is recorded that
                    there the youth studied fourteen hours a day, and made such swift progress that
                    he was able to maintain theses and disputations, and to take the degree of
                    licentiate (B.A.) of laws. On his way home from the university he passed through
                    Saumur, and having visited Mons. Bonchereau, pastor of the Protestant church
                    there, he introduced him to the renowned lord of Plessis-Mornay, governor of the
                    city. Both were struck with young Amyraut’s ability and culture, and both urged
                    him to change from law to theology. Plessis-Mornay, who was chary of laudations,
                    pronounced that “there was nothing above the grasp of his great parts.” Returned
                    home, his father, after considerable hesitation, gave consent to the change from
                    law to divinity, with a proviso that he should revise his philological and
                    philosophical studies, and read over Mons. Calvin’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Institutions,</hi> before finally determining. He did so, and, as might have
                    been anticipated, decided for theology. He thereupon removed to Saumur —destined
                    to be for ever associated with his name—and “sat at the feet of the great
                    Cameron,” who ultimately regarded him as his greatest scholar. He had a
                    brilliant course, and was in due time licensed as a minister of the French
                    Protestant Church. The contemporary civil wars and excitements hindered his
                    advancement. His first church was in St Aignau, in the province of Maine. There
                    he remained two years. The celebrated Daille, being then removed to Paris,
                    advised the church at Saumur to secure Amyraut as his successor, praising him
                    “as above himseif.” <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n826/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0826-0783"/> The university of Saumur at the same time had
                    fixed its eyes on him as professor of theology. The great churches of Paris and
                    Rouen also contended for him, and sent their deputies to win him, to the
                    provincial synod of Anjou. Amyraut had left the choice to the synod. He was
                    appointed to Saumur, and to the professor’s chair along with the pastorate. On
                    the occasion of his inauguration he maintained for thesis <hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Sacerdotio</hi><hi rend="italic">Christi.</hi> His
                    coprofessors were Lewis Capell and Josua de la Place, who were also Cameron’s
                    pupüs. Very beautiful was the lifelong friendship of these three remarkable men.
                    They remain associated still as the joint authors of a body of divinity entitled
                    <hi rend="italic">Theses Salmurienses.</hi> Full of energy in every atom of him,
                    Amyraut devoted himself to his labour of love with a fine enthusiasm of love of
                    labour. He very speedily gave French Protestantism a potentiality it had never
                    possessed before. In 1631 he published his <hi rend="italic">Traité</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Religions,</hi> a book that still lives; and from this year
                    onward he was a foremost man in the church, especially at the national and
                    provincial synods. One incident in his synodical services stands out, as the
                    like do in the story of Luther and of John Knox. Chosen to represent the
                    provincial synod of Anjou, Touraine, and Maine at the national synod held in
                    1631 at Charenton, that assembly appointed him their orator to address the king,
                    and to present to him “The Copy of their Complaints and Grievances for the
                    Infractions and Violations of the Edict of Nantes.” Previous deputies had
                    addressed the king on their bended knees, whereas the representatives of the
                    Roman Catholics had been permitted to stand. Amyraut consented to be orator only
                    if the assembly authorised him to stand. There was intense resistance. Richelieu
                    himself, preceded by lesser dignitaries, condescended to visit Amyraut
                    privately, to draw him over to kneel; but the stout-hearted orator held
                    resolutely to equality with the Roman Catholics, and carried his point. Standing
                    iiι the presence of king and court, he recounted the complaints and grievances
                    of his church, and charmed even his adversaries with his mingled dignity of
                    manner and suavity of address. Long afterwards Richelieu recalled the memorable
                    incident; and the “Oration,” which was immediately published in the French <hi
                    rend="italic">Mercury,</hi> remains a historic landmark in the history of French
                    Protestantism. During his absence on this matter the assembly debated “Whether
                    the Lutherans who desired it, might be admitted into communion with the'Reformed
                    Churches of France at the Lord’s Table Î” It was decided in the affirmative
                    previous to his return; but he approved with astonishing eloquence, and
                    thereafter was ever in the front rank in maintaining intercommunication between
                    all churches holding the main doctrines of the Reformation. His defence against
                    many adversaries on the question was published in 1647— <hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Secessione</hi><hi rend="italic">ab Ecclesia
                    Romana</hi><hi rend="italic">deque</hi><hi rend="italic">Ratione Pacis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">inter Evangelicos in</hi><hi rend="italic">Religionis Negotio
                    constituendae.</hi> Bayle (s.v.) recounts the title-pages of no fewer than
                    thirty-two books of which Amyraut was the author. These show that he took part
                    in all the great controversies on Predestination and Arminianism which then so
                    agitated and harassed all Europe. Substantially he held fast the Calvinism of
                    his preceptor Cameron; but, like Richard Baxter in England, by his breadth and
                    charity exposed himself to all manner of misconstruction from Peter du Moulin
                    and others ultraorthodox. His <hi rend="italic">La Defense de Calvin</hi> never
                    was answered, although superabundantly replied to. The university of Saumur
                    became the university of French Protestantism. Amyraut had as many as a hundred
                    students in attendance upon his prelections. Another historic part filled by
                    Amyraut was in the negotiations originated with Mons, le Goux, lord of Berchère,
                    first president of the parliament of Burgundy, when exiled to Saumur, for a
                    reconciliation and reunion of the Roman Catholics of France with the French
                    Protestants. Very large were the concessions made by Richelieu in his personal
                    interviews with Amyraut; but, as with the Worcester House negotiations in
                    England between the Church of England and Nonconformists, they inevitably fell
                    through. On all sides the statesmanship and eloquence of Amyraut were conceded.
                    When the king visited Saumur in 1651, Amyraut declined to close his church on
                    the Sunday, but preached a sermon that rang through Europe on the text, “Fear
                    God, honour the king.” Amyraut remained to the end one of the most prominent
                    names of French Protestantism; and his <hi rend="italic">De l’Elévation de
                    la</hi><hi rend="italic">Foy</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    l</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Abaissement</hi><hi rend="italic">de la
                    Raison</hi><hi rend="italic">en la Créance des Mystères</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    la Religion</hi> (1641) gave him early a high place as a metaphysician, which
                    was sustained by’after works. Exclusive of his controversial writings, he left
                    behind him a very voluminous series of practical evangelical books, which remain
                    the fireside favourites of the peasantry of French Protestantism still. His <hi
                    rend="italic">Estât des Fidèles après</hi><hi rend="italic">la Mort</hi> has
                    comforted many mourners; his <hi rend="italic">Sur</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ι</hi><hi rend="italic">Oraison Dominicale</hi> is striking and rich; his <hi
                    rend="italic">Du Mérite des Oeuvres</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Traité</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de la Justification,</hi> weighty and powerful; his Paraphrases on
                    Old Testament and New Testament books of Holy Scripture, judicious and
                    suggestive—sometimes penetrative. His closing years were weakened by a severe
                    fall he met with in 1657. He died on 18th January 1664. His portrait was
                    published by his son, but with no name or inscription underneath. (Bayle, <hi
                    rend="italic">s.v.; Biog. Univ., s.v.;</hi> John Quick’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Synod, in Gall. Reform.,</hi> pp. 352-7; ibid. MS. <hi rend="italic"
                    >leones</hi><hi rend="italic">Sacrae Gallicanae;</hi><hi rend="italic">Life of
                    Cameron.')</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(a. b. g.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
