<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0242-0225-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">AETOLIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 225</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1095872">Rest</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:891345">Designers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:891253">Design</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:795626">Achaeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x62g">Rest</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zz3k">Design</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n242/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AETOLIA</label>, a country of ancient Greece, bounded on the
                    N. by Epirus and Thessaly, on the E. by the provinces of Doris and Locris, on
                    the S. by the Gulf of Corinth, and separated on the W. from Acarnania by the
                    river Achelous. The part which lay westward of the river Evenus, and south of a
                    line joining Thermum and Stratus in Acarnania, was called old Aetolia, the rest
                    of the country new or acquired Aetolia. The country is in general mountainous
                    and woody, but along the coast from the Achelous to the Evenus, and northward to
                    Mount Aracynthus, is a plain of great fertility; while another extensive and
                    fertile plain stretches north from this mountain along the east bank of the
                    Achelous as far as the northern limit of old Aetolia. The Aetolians were a
                    restless and turbulent people, strangers to friendship or principles of honour,
                    and they were consequently regarded by the other states of Greece as outlaws and
                    public robbers. On the other hand, they were bold and enterprising in war,
                    undaunted in the greatest dangers, and jealous defenders of their liberties.
                    They distinguished themselves above all the other nations of Greece in opposing
                    the ambitious designs of the Macedonian princes, who, after having reduced most
                    of the other states, were forced to grant them a peace upon very honourable
                    terms. The constitution of the Aetolian league was copied from that of the
                    Achaeans, and with a view to form, as it were, a counter alliance. The Cleomenic
                    war, and that of the allies, called the Social War, were kindled by the
                    Aetolians with the express purpose of humbling the Achaeans. In the latter they
                    held out, with the assistance only of the Eleans and Lacedemonians, for the
                    space of three years, against the united forces of Achaia and Macedon, but were
                    obliged at last to purchase a peace by yielding up to Philip all Acarnania. In
                    order to regain this province they entered into an alliance with Rome against
                    Philip, and proved of great service to the Romans in their war with him; but
                    being dissatisfied with the terms of peace granted by Flaminius, they made war
                    upon the -Romans themselves. They were speedily overcome, and only obtained
                    peace on very humiliating terms. After the conquest of Macedon by Aemilius
                    Paullus the Aetolians were reduced to a much worse condition; for not only those
                    among them who had openly declared for Perseus, but those who were only
                    suspected to have secretly favoured him, were sent to Rome to clear themselves
                    before the senate. There they were detained, and never afterwards permitted to
                    return to their native country. Five hundred and fifty of the chief men were
                    barbarously assassinated by the partisans of Rome solely on the suspicion of
                    favouring the designs of Perseus. The Aetolians appeared before Aemilius Paullus
                    in mourning habits, and made loud complaints of such inhuman treatment, but
                    could obtain no redress; on the contrary, ten commissioners, who had been sent
                    by the senate to settle the affairs of Greece, enacted a decree, declaring that
                    those who were killed had suffered justly, since it appeared to them that they
                    had favoured the Macedonian party. From this time those only were raised to the
                    chief honours and employments in the Aetolian republic who were known to prefer
                    the interest of Rome to that of their country, and thus all the magistrates of
                    Aetolia became the creatures and mere tools of the Roman senate. In this state
                    of servile subjection they continued till the destruction of Corinth and the
                    dissolution of the Achaean league, when Aetolia, with the other free states of
                    Greece, was reduced to a Roman province, commonly called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >province of Achaia.</hi> In this state, with little alteration, Aetolia
                    continued under the emperors till the reign of Constantine the Great, who, in
                    his new partition of the provinces of the empire, divided the western parts of
                    Greece from the rest, calling them <hi rend="italic">New Epirus,</hi> and
                    subjecting the whole country to the <hi rend="italic">praefectus praetorio</hi>
                    for Illyricum. Under the successors of Constantine Greece was parcelled out into
                    several principalities, especially after the taking of Constantinople by the
                    western princes. About the beginning of the 13th century Theodoras Angelus, a
                    noble Grecian of the imperial family, seized on Aetolia and Epirus. The former
                    he left to Michael his son, who maintained it against Michael Palaeologus, the
                    first emperor of the Greeks, after the expulsion of the Latins. Charles, the
                    last prince of this family, dying in 1430 without lawful issue, bequeathed
                    Aetolia to his brother’s son, named also Charles; and Acarnania to his natural
                    sons Memnon, Turnus, and Hercules. But great disputes arising about this
                    division, Amurath II., after the reduction of Thessalonica, laid hold of so
                    favourable an opportunity, and expelled all the contending heirs in 1432. The
                    Mahometans were afterwards dispossessed of this country by the famous prince of
                    Epirus, George Castriot, commonly called Scanderbeg, who with a small army
                    opposed the whole power of the Ottoman empire, and was victorious in twenty-two
                    pitched battles. That hero at his death left great part of Aetolia to the
                    Venetians; but they not being able to make head against such a mighty power, the
                    whole country was soon reduced by Mahommed II. It is now included in the kingdom
                    of Greece.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
