<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0115-0100-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ACOUSTICS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 100</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term n="113" ref="fasttopic:802066">Air</term>
                    <term n="49" ref="fasttopic:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term n="41" ref="fasttopic:900541">Ear</term>
                    <term n="41" ref="fasttopic:900686">Earrings</term>
                    <term n="40" ref="fasttopic:1064885">Pitch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="113" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term n="49" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term n="41" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f4j">Ear</term>
                    <term n="40" ref="lcsh1910:b44746z94">Pitch</term>
                    <term n="39" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39307">Equality</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z08r">Doves</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n115/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ACOUSTICS</label></p>
                <p>1. ACOUSTICS (from άκούω, to hear) is that branch of Natural Philosophy which
                    treats of the nature of sound, and the laws of its production and propagation,
                    in so far as these depend on physical principles. The description of the
                    mechanism of the organ of voice and of the ear, and the difficult questions
                    connected with the processes by which, when sound reaches the drum of the ear,
                    it is transmitted to the brain, must be dealt with in separate articles of this
                    work. It is to the physical part of the science of acoustics that the present
                    article is restricted.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> I.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">General notions as to Vibrations, Waves, &amp;c.</hi></p>
                <p>2. We may easily satisfy ourselves that, in every instance in which the sensation
                    of sound is excited, the body, whence the sound proceeds, must have been thrown,
                    by a blow or other means, into a state of agitation or tremor, implying the
                    existence of a vibratory motion, or motion to and fro, of the particles of which
                    it consists.</p>
                <p>Thus, if a common glass-jar be struck so as to yield an audible sound, the
                    existence of a motion of this kind may be felt by the finger lightly applied to
                    the edge of the glass; and, on increasing the pressure so as to destroy this
                    motion, the sound forthwith ceases. Small pieces of cork put in the jar will be
                    found to dance about during the continuance of the sound; water or spirits of
                    wine poured into the glass will, under the same circumstances, exhibit a ruffled
                    surface. The experiment is usually performed, in a more striking manner, with a
                    bell-jar and a number of small light wooden balls suspended by silk strings to a
                    fixed frame above the jar, so as to be just in contact with the widest part of
                    the glass. On drawing a violin bow across the edge, the pendulums are thrown off
                    to a considerable distance, and falling back are again repelled, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>It is also in many cases possible to follow with the eye the motions of the
                    particles of the sounding body, as, for instance, in the case of a violin string
                    or any string fixed at both ends, when the string will appear, by a law of
                    optics, to occupy at once all the positions which it successively assumes during
                    its vibratory motion.</p>
                <p>3. It is, moreover, essential, in order that the ear may L be affected by a
                    sounding body, that there be interposed between it and the ear one or more
                    intermediate bodies <hi rend="italic">(media),</hi> themselves capable of
                    molecular vibration, which shall receive such motion from the source of sound,
                    and transmit it to the external parts of the ear, and especially to the <hi
                    rend="italic">membrana tympani</hi> or <hi rend="italic">drum</hi> of the ear.
                    This statement is confirmed by the well-known effect of stopping the ear with
                    soft cotton, or other substance possessing little elasticity.</p>
                <p>The air around us forms the most important medium of communication of sound to
                    our organs of hearing; in fact, were air devoid of this property, we should
                    practically be without the sense of hearing. In illustration of the part thus
                    assigned to the atmosphere in acoustics, an apparatus has been constructed,
                    consisting of a glass receiver, in which is a bell and a hammer connected with
                    clock-work, by which it can be made to strike the bell when required. The
                    receiver is closed air-tight by a metal plate, through which passes, also
                    air-tight, into the interior, a brass rod. By properly moving this rod with the
                    hand, a detent is released, which checks the motion of the wheel-work, and the
                    hammer strikes the bell continuously, till the detent is pushed into its
                    original position. As long as the air in the receiver is of the usual
                    atmospheric density, the sound is perfectly audible. But on rarefying the air by
                    means of an air-pump (the clock-work apparatus having been separated from the
                    plate of the pump by means of a padding of soft cotton), the sound grows
                    gradually fainter, and at last becomes inaudible when the rarefaction of the air
                    has reached a very low point. If, however, at this stage of the experiment, the
                    metal rod be brought into contact with the bell, the sound will again be heard
                    clearly, because now there is the necessary communication with the ear. On
                    readmitting the air, the sound recovers its original intensity. This experiment
                    was first performed by Hawksbee in 1705.</p>
                <p>4. Inasmuch, then, as sound necessarily implies the existence in the sounding
                    body, in the air, &amp;c., and (we may add) in the ear itself, of vibratory
                    motion of the particles of the various media concerned in the phenomenon, a
                    general reference to the laws of such motion is essential to a right
                    understanding of the principles of acoustics.</p>
                <p>The most familiar instance of this kind of motion is afforded by the pendulum, a
                    small heavy ball, for instance, attached to a fine string, which is fixed at its
                    other end. There is but one position in which the ball will remain at rest,
                    viz., when the string is vertical, there being then equilibrium between the two
                    forces acting on the body, the tension of the string and the earth’s attractive
                    force or gravity. Thus, in the adjoining fig., if C is the point of suspension,
                    and CA the vertical through that point of length <hi rend="italic">l,</hi> equal
                    to the string, A is the equilibrium position of the particle.</p>
                <p>Let now the ball be removed from A to P, the string being kept tight, so that P
                    describes the arc AP of a circle of radius equal to <hi rend="italic">l,</hi>
                    and let the ball be there dropped. The tension of the string not being now
                    directly opposite in direction to gravity (<hi rend="italic">g</hi>), motion
                    will ensue, and the body will retrace the arc PA. Tn doing so, it will
                    continually increase its velocity until it reaches the point A, where its
                    velocity will be a maximum, and will consequently pass to the other side of A
                    towards Q. But now gravity tends to draw it back towards A, and hence the motion
                    becomes a retarded one; the velocity continually diminishes, and is ultimately
                    destroyed at some point Q, which would be at a distance from A equal to that of
                    P, but for the existence of friction, resistance of the air, &amp;c., which make
                    that distance less. From Q it will next move down with accelerated motion
                    towards A, where it will have its greatest velocity in the direction from left
                    to right, and whence it will pass onwards towards P, and so on. Thus the body
                    will vibrate to and fro on either side of A, its <hi rend="italic"
                    >amplitude</hi> of vibration or distance between its extreme positions gradually
                    diminishing in consequence of the resistances before mentioned, and at last
                    being sensibly reduced to nothing, the body 'then resuming its
                    equilibrium-position A.</p>
                <p>If the amplitude of vibration is restricted within inconsiderable limits, it is
                    easy to prove that the motion takes place just as if the string were removed,
                    the ball deprived altogether of weight and urged by a force directed to the
                    point A, and proportional to the distance from that point. For then, if <hi
                    rend="italic">m</hi> be any position of the ball, the chord <hi rend="italic"
                    >mA</hi> may be regarded as coincident with the tangent to the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n116/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0116-0101"/> circie at <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> and therefore
                    as being perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">Cm.</hi> Hence <hi rend="italic"
                    >g,</hi> acting parallel to CA, being resolved along <hi rend="italic">Cm</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">mA.,</hi> the former component is counteracted by the
                    tension of the string, and there remains as the only effective acceleration, the
                    tangential component along <hi rend="italic">mA,</hi> which, by the triangle of
                    forces, is equal to or <hi rend="italic">g/l.</hi> and is therefore proportional
                    to <hi rend="italic">Am.</hi></p>
                <p>On this supposition of indefinitely small vibrations, the pendulum is
                    isochronous; that is, the time occupied in passing from one extreme position to
                    the other is the same, for a given length <hi rend="italic">l</hi> of the
                    pendulum, whatever the extent of vibration.</p>
                <p>We conclude from this that, whatever may be the nature of the forces by which a
                    particle is urged, if the resultant of those forces is directed towards a fixed
                    point, and is proportional to the distance from that point, the particle will
                    oscillate to and fro about that point in times which are independent of the
                    amplitudes of the vibrations, provided these are very small.</p>
                <p>5. The particle, whose vibratory motion we have been considering, is a solitary
                    particle acted on by external forces. But, in acoustics, we have to do with the
                    motion of particles forming a connected system or medium, in which the forces to
                    be considered arise from the mutual actions of the particles. These forces are
                    in equilibrium with each other when the particles occupy certain relative
                    positions. But, if any new or disturbing force act for a short time on any one
                    or more of the particles, so as to cause a mutual approach or a mutual
                    recession, on the removal of the disturbing force, the disturbed particles will,
                    if the body be <hi rend="italic">elastic,</hi> forthwith move towards their
                    respective positions of equilibrium. Hence arises a vibratory motion to and fro
                    of each about a given point, analogous to that of a pendulum, the velocity at
                    that point being always a maximum, alternately in opposite directions. Thus, for
                    example, if to one extremity of a pipe containing air were applied a piston, of
                    section equal to that of the pipe, by pushing in the piston slightly and then
                    removing it, we should cause particles of air, forming a thin section at the
                    extremity of the pipe, to vibrate in directions parallel to its axis.</p>
                <p>In order that a medium may be capable of molecular vibrations, it must, as we
                    have mentioned, possess <hi rend="italic">elasticity,</hi> that is, a tendency
                    always to return to its original condition when slightly disturbed out of
                    it.</p>
                <p>6. We now proceed to show how the disturbance whereby certain particles of an
                    elastic medium are displaced from their equilibrium-positions, is successively
                    transmitted to the remaining particles of the medium, so as to cause these also
                    to vibrate to and fro.</p>
                <p>Let us consider a line of such particles <hi rend="italic">y, x, a, b,</hi>
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">x a</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    1</hi><hi rend="italic">a a</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">b c d e f</hi><hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic">h i k l m
                    n o p</hi> equidistant from each other, as above; and suppose one of them, say
                    <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> to be displaced, by any means, to <hi rend="italic"
                    >a</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>. As we have seen, this particle will swing
                    from <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> to <hi rend="italic"
                    >a</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi> and back again, occupying a certain
                    time T, to complete its double vibration. But it is obvious that, the distance
                    between <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and the next particle <hi rend="italic">b</hi>
                    to the right being diminished by the displacement of the former to <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, a tendency is generated in <hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi> to move towards <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> the mutual forces being no longer in
                    equilibrium, but having a resultant in the direction <hi rend="italic"
                    >ba</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> The particle
                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi> will therefore also suffer displacement, and be
                    compelled to swing to and fro about the point <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> For
                    similar reasons the particles <hi rend="italic">c, d . . .</hi> will all
                    likewise be thrown into vibration. Thus it is, then, that the disturbance
                    propagates itself in the direction under consideration. There is evidently also,
                    in the case supposed, a transmission from <hi rend="italic">a</hi> to <hi
                    rend="italic">x, y,</hi> &amp;c., <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> in the opposite
                    direction.</p>
                <p>Confining our attention to propagation in the direction <hi rend="italic">abc . .
                    .,</hi> we have next to remark that each particle in that line will be affected
                    by the disturbance always later than the particle immediately preceding it, so
                    as to be found in the same stage of vibration a certain interval of time after
                    the preceding particle.</p>
                <p>7. Two particles which are in the same stage of vibration, that is, are equally
                    displaced from their equilibriumpositions, and are moving in the same direction
                    and with equal velocities, are said to be in the same <hi rend="italic"
                    >phase.</hi> Hence we may express the preceding statement more briefly thus: Two
                    particles of a disturbed medium at different distances from the centre of
                    disturbance, are in the same phase at different times, the one whose distance
                    from that centre is the greater being later than the other.</p>
                <p>8. Let us in the meantime assume that, the intervals <hi rend="italic">ab, bc, cd
                    . . .</hi>. being equal, the intervals of time which elapse between the like
                    phases of <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> of <hi
                    rend="italic">c</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b . . . .</hi> are also equal to each
                    other, and let us consider what at any given instant are the appearances
                    presented by the different particles in the row.</p>
                <p>T being the time of a <hi rend="italic">complete</hi> vibration of each particle,
                    T</p>
                <p>let — be the interval of time requisite for any phase of <hi rend="italic">a
                    to</hi> pass on to <hi rend="italic">b. If</hi> then at a certain instant <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> is displaced to its greatest extent to the right, <hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi> will be somewhat short of, but moving towards, <hi
                    rend="italic">its</hi> corresponding position, c still further short, and so on.
                    Proceeding in this way, we shall come at length to a particle <hi rend="italic"
                    >p,</hi> for which the distance <hi rend="italic">ap</hi> = <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi>. <hi rend="italic">ab,</hi> which therefore lags in its vibrations
                    behind <hi rend="italic">a</hi> T</p>
                <p>by a time = <hi rend="italic">p ×</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> T</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">/</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> p</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi>
                    T, and is consequently precisely in the same phase as <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>
                    And between these two particles <hi rend="italic">a, p, we</hi> shall evidently
                    have particles in all the possible phases of the vibratory motion. At <hi
                    rend="italic">h,</hi> which is at distance from <hi rend="italic">a =</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">½</hi><hi rend="italic">ap,</hi> the difference of phase, compared
                    with <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> will be ½T, that is, <hi rend="italic">h</hi>
                    will, at the given instant, be displaced to the greatest extent on the opposite
                    side of its equilibrium-position from that in which <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is
                    displaced; in other words, <hi rend="italic">h</hi> is in the exactly opposite
                    phase to <hi rend="italic">a.</hi></p>
                <p>9. In the case we have just been considering, the vibrations of the particles
                    have been supposed to take place in a direction coincident with that in which
                    the disturbance passes from one particle to another. The vibrations are then
                    termed <hi rend="italic">longitudinal.</hi></p>
                <p>But it need scarcely be observed that the vibrations may take place in any
                    direction whatever, and may even be curvilinear. If they take place in
                    directions at right angles to the line of progress of the disturbance, they are
                    said to be <hi rend="italic">transversal.</hi></p>
                <p>10. Now the reasoning employed in the preceding case will evidently admit of
                    general application, and will, in particular, hold for transversal vibrations.
                    Hence if we mark (as is done in fig. 2) the positions <hi rend="italic"
                    >a</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">. .</hi>., occupied by the various particles, when swinging
                    transversely, at the instant at which <hi rend="italic">a</hi> has its maximum
                    displacement <hi rend="italic">above</hi> its equilibrium-position, and trace a
                    continuous line running through the points so found, that line will by its
                    ordinates indicate to the eye the state of motion at the given instant.</p>
                <p>Thus <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">p</hi> are in the <hi
                    rend="italic">same</hi> phase, as are also <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">q, c</hi> and <hi rend="italic">r, &amp;c. a</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">h</hi> are in <hi rend="italic">opposite</hi> phases, as are also
                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i,</hi><hi rend="italic">c</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">k,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n117/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0117-0102"/>
                <p>Distances <hi rend="italic">a p, b q,</hi> &amp;c., separating particles in the
                    same phase, and each of which, as we have seen, is passed over by the
                    disturbance in the time T of a complete vibration, include within them <hi
                    rend="italic">all</hi> the possible phases of the motion.</p>
                <p>Beyond this distance, the curve repeats itself exactly, that is, the phases recur
                    in the same order as before.</p>
                <p>Now the figure so traced offers an obvious resemblance to the undulating surface
                    of a lake or other body of water, after it has been disturbed by wind,
                    exhibiting a wave with its trough A∕qB, and its crest B <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> C. Hence have been introduced into
                    Acoustics, as also into Optics, the terms <hi rend="italic">wave</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">undulation.</hi> The distance <hi rend="italic">ap,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">bq . . .</hi> or A C, which separates two particles in same phase,
                    or which includes both a wave-crest and a wave-trough, is termed the <hi
                    rend="italic">length of the wave,</hi> and is usually denoted by λ.</p>
                <p>As the curve repeats itself at intervals each =λ, it follows that particles are
                    in the same phase at any given moment, when the distances between them in the
                    direction of transmission of the disturbance = λ, 2λ, 3λ .. . and generally =
                    <hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="italic">λ</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> where
                    <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is any whole number.</p>
                <p>Particles such as <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">h,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> &amp;c., which are at
                    distances = ½λ , being in <hi rend="italic">opposite</hi> phases, so will also
                    be particles separated by distance, ½λ + λ = <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>
                    /2λ,or, in general, by ½λ + <hi rend="italic">m</hi> λ = (2 <hi rend="italic"
                    >m</hi> + 1 ) <hi rend="superscript"> λ</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>,
                    that is, by any <hi rend="italic">odd</hi> multiple of <hi rend="superscript">
                    λ</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>11. A like construction to the one just adopted for the displacements of the
                    particles at any given instant, may be also applied for exhibiting graphically
                    their velocities at the same instant. Erect at the various points <hi
                    rend="italic">a, b, c,</hi> &amp;c., perpendiculars to the line joining them, of
                    lengths proportional to and in the direction of their velocities, and draw a
                    line through the extreme points of these perpendiculars; this line will answer
                    the purpose required. It is indicated by dots in the previous figure, and
                    manifestly forms a wave of the same length as the wave of displacements, but the
                    highest and lowest point's of the one wave correspond to the points in which the
                    other wave crosses the line of equilibrium.</p>
                <p>12. In order to a graphic representation of the displacements and velocities of
                    particles vibrating <hi rend="italic">longitudinally,</hi> it is convenient to
                    draw the lines which represent those quantities, not in the actual direction in
                    which the motion takes place and which coincides with the line <hi rend="italic"
                    >a</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic">c ...</hi>, but at right angles
                    to it, ordinates drawn upwards indicating displacements or velocities to the
                    right <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> in the direction of transmission of the
                    disturbance), and ordinates drawn downwards indicating displacements or
                    velocities in the opposite direction. When this is done, waves of displacement
                    and velocity are figured identically with those for transversal vibrations, and
                    are therefore subject to the same resulting laws.</p>
                <p>13. But not only will the above waves enable us to see at a glance the
                    circumstances of the vibratory motion at the instant of time for which it has
                    been constructed, but also for any subsequent moment. Thus, if we desire to
                    consider what is going on after an interval <hi rend="superscript"> T</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> p</hi>, we have simply to conceive the whole wave (whether of
                    displacement or velocity) to be moved to the right through a distance <hi
                    rend="italic">=ab.</hi> Then the state of motion in which <hi rend="italic"
                    >a</hi> was before will have been transferred to <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> that
                    of <hi rend="italic">b</hi> will have been transferred to <hi rend="italic"
                    >c,</hi> and so on. At the end of another such interval, the state of the
                    particles will in like manner be represented by the wave, if pushed onward
                    through another equal space. In short, the whole circumstances may be pictured
                    to the eye by two waves (of displacement and of velocity) advancing continuously
                    in the line <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic">c
                    ...</hi> with a velocity V which will take it over the distance <hi
                    rend="italic">ab</hi> in the time <hi rend="superscript"> T</hi> / <hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> p</hi>,V being therefore = <hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ab</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> T</hi> = <hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> p.ab</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> T</hi> = <hi rend="superscript">
                    AC</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> T</hi> or V = <hi rend="superscript"> λ/</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> T</hi>.</p>
                <p>This is termed the velocity of propagation of the wave, and, as we see, is equal
                    to the length of the wave divided by the time of a complete vibration of each
                    particle.</p>
                <p>If, as is usually more convenient, we express T in terms of the number <hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi> of complete vibrations performed in a given time, say in
                    the unit of time, we shall have <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> T</hi> = <hi rend="italic">n ,</hi> and hence V = <hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi> λ</p>
                <p>14. There is one very important distinction between the two cases of longitudinal
                    and of transversal vibrations which now claims our attention, viz., that whereas
                    vibrations of the latter kind, when propagated from particle to particle in an
                    elastic medium, do not alter the relative distances of the particles, or, in
                    other words, cause no change of density throughout the medium; longitudinal
                    vibrations, on the other hand, by bringing the particles nearer to or further
                    from one another than they are when undisturbed, are necessarily accompanied by
                    alternate condensations and rarefactions.</p>
                <p>Thus, in fig. 2, we see that at the instant to which that fig. refers, the
                    displacements of the particles immediately adjoining <hi rend="italic">a</hi>
                    are equal and in the same direction; hence at that moment the density of the
                    medium at <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is equal to that of the undisturbed medium.
                    The same applies to the points <hi rend="italic">h, p,</hi> &amp;c., in which
                    the displacements are at their maxima and the velocities of vibration =0.</p>
                <p>At any point, such as <hi rend="italic">c,</hi> between <hi rend="italic">a</hi>
                    and A, the displacements of the two adjoining particles on either side are both
                    to the right, but that of the <hi rend="italic">preceding</hi> particle is now
                    the greater of the two, and hence the density of the medium throughout <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> A exceeds the undisturbed density. So at any point, such as
                    <hi rend="italic">f</hi>, between A and <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> the same
                    result holds good, because now the displacements are to the left, but are in
                    excess on the right side of the point <hi rend="italic">f.</hi> From <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> to <hi rend="italic">h</hi>, therefore, the medium is
                    condensed.</p>
                <p>From <hi rend="italic">h</hi> to B, as at <hi rend="italic">k,</hi> the
                    displacements of the two particles on either side are both to the <hi
                    rend="italic">left,</hi> that of the preceding particle being, however, the
                    greater. The medium, therefore, is here in a state of rarefaction. And in like
                    manner it may be shown that there is rarefaction from B to <hi rend="italic"
                    >p;</hi> so that the medium is rarefied from <hi rend="italic">h</hi> to <hi
                    rend="italic">p.</hi></p>
                <p>At A the condensation is a maximum, because the displacements on the two sides of
                    that point are equal and both directed towards A. At B, on the other hand, it is
                    the rarefaction which is a maximum, the displacements on the right and left of
                    that point being again equal, but directed outwards from B.</p>
                <p>It clearly follows from all this that, if we trace a curve of which any ordinate
                    shall be proportional to the difference between the density of the corresponding
                    point of the disturbed medium and the density of the undisturbed
                    medium—ordinates drawn upwards indicating condensation, and ordinates drawn
                    downwards rarefaction—that curve will cross the line of rest of the particles
                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic">c ...</hi> in
                    the same points as does the curve of velocities, and will therefore be of the
                    same length λ, and will also rise above that line and dip below it at the same
                    parts. But the connection between the <hi rend="italic">wave</hi> of
                    condensation and rarefaction and the wave of velocity, is still more intimate,
                    when the extent to which the particles are displaced is very small, as is always
                    the case in acoustics. For it may be shown that then the degree of condensation
                    or rarefaction at any point of the medium is proportional to the velocity of
                    vibration at that point. The same ordinates, therefore, will represent<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n118/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0118-0103"/> the degrees of condensation, which represent the
                    velocities, or, in other words, the wave of condensation and rarefaction may be
                    regarded as coincident with the velocity wave.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> II.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Velocity of propagation of waves of longitudinal disturbance
                    through any elastic medium.</hi></p>
                <p>15. Sir Isaac Newton was the first who attempted to determine, on theoretical
                    grounds, the velocity of sound in air and other fluids. The formula obtained by
                    him gives, however, a numerical value, as regards air, falling far short of the
                    result derived from actual experiment; and it was not till long afterwards, when
                    Laplace took up the question, that complete coincidence was arrived at between
                    theory and observation. We are indebted to the late Professor Rankine, of
                    Glasgow <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Trans.</hi> 1870, p. 277)<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See also Maxwell. <hi rend="italic">Theory of
                    Heat,</hi> p. 203.</p></note>, for a very simple and elegant investigation of
                    the question, which we will here reproduce in an abridged form.</p>
                <p>Let us conceive the longitudinal disturbance to be propagated through a medium
                    contained in a straight tube having a transverse section equal to unity, but of
                    indefinite length.</p>
                <p>Let two transverse planes <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    1</hi> A <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> (fig. 3) be conceived as moving along the
                    interior of the tube in the same direction and with the same velocity V as the
                    disturbance-wave itself,</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >u</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi> be the velocities of displacement of
                    the particles of the medium at A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> A <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> respectively, at any given instant, estimated in the
                    same direction as V; and ρ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ρ <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi> the corresponding densities of the medium.</p>
                <p>The disturbances under consideration, being such as preserve a permanent type
                    throughout their propagation, it follows that the quantity of matter between A
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> and A <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> remains constant
                    during the motion of these planes, or that as much must pass into the
                    intervening space through one of them as issues from it through the other. Now
                    at A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> the velocity of the particles relatively to A
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> itself is V - <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">inwards,</hi> and consequently
                    there flows into the space A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> A <hi rend="subscript"
                    > 2</hi> through A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> a mass (V - <hi rend="italic"
                    >u</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>)ρ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> in the unit
                    of time.</p>
                <p>Forming a similar expression as regards A <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, putting
                    <hi rend="italic">m</hi> for the invariable mass through which the disturbance
                    is propagated in the unit of time, and considering that if <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi> denote the density of the undisturbed medium, <hi rend="italic">m</hi>
                    is evidently equal to Vp, we have—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">V-u</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >)</hi><hi rend="italic">ρ</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi> = (V- <hi
                    rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>)ρ <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>
                    = Vρ = <hi rend="italic">m</hi>. . (1.)</p>
                <p>Now, <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi> being the pressures at A <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, A <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> respectively, and
                    therefore <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">- p</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi> the force generating
                    the acceleration <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">- u</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >,</hi> in unit of time, on the mass <hi rend="italic">m</hi> of the medium, by
                    the second law of motion, <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">-p</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">= m(u</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >-u</hi><hi rend="italic                     subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >) . .</hi>. (2.)</p>
                <p>Eliminating <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">, u</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi> from these equations,
                    and putting for — , , - the symbols s <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, <hi
                    rend="italic">s</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">,
                    s</hi> (which therefore denote the <hi rend="italic">Pl f</hi> ’ <hi
                    rend="italic">2 P</hi> volumes of the unit of mass of the disturbed medium at A
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, A <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, and of the
                    undisturbed medium), we get:</p>
                <p>= <hi rend="subscript"> and V</hi> 2 <hi rend="subscript"> = s</hi> 2 <hi
                    rend="italic">Pi∑P∑</hi><hi rend="italic">— S</hi> 2 #2</p>
                <p>Now, if (as is generally the case in sound) the changes of pressure and volume
                    occurring during the disturbance of the medium are very small, we may assume
                    that these changes are proportional one to the other. Hence, denoting the ratio
                    which any increase of pressure bears to the diminution of the unit of volume of
                    the substance, and which is termed the <hi rend="italic">elasticity</hi> of the
                    substance, by <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> we shall obtain for the velocity of a
                    wave of longitudinal displacements, supposed small, the equation: <hi
                    rend="subscript smallcaps"> ot</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">v=√j} · · · ·</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">«</hi></p>
                <p>16. In applying this formula to the determination of the velocity of sound in any
                    particular medium, it is requisite, as was shown by Laplace, to take into
                    account the thermic effects produced by the condensations and rarefactions
                    which, as we have seen, take place in the substance. The heat generated during
                    the sudden compression, not being conveyed away, raises the value of the
                    elasticity above that which otherwise it would have, and which was assigned to
                    it by Sir Isaac Newton.</p>
                <p>Thus, in a <hi rend="italic">perfect</hi> gas, it is demonstrable by the
                    principles of <hi rend="smallcaps">Thermodynamics,</hi> that the elasticity <hi
                    rend="italic">e,</hi> which, in the undisturbed state of the medium, would be
                    simply equal to the pressure <hi rend="italic">p,</hi> is to be made equal to
                    γp, where γ is a number exceeding unity and represents the ratio of the specific
                    heat of the gas under constant pressure to its specific heat at constant
                    volume.</p>
                <p>Hence, as air and most other gases may be practically regarded as perfect gases,
                    we have for them:</p>
                <p>v=√⅛=√^ . . . (II.)</p>
                <p>17. From this the following inference may be drawn:—The velocity of sound in a
                    given gas is unaffected by change of pressure if unattended by change of
                    temperature. For, by Boyle’s law, the ratio <hi rend="superscript"> p</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> ρ</hi> is constant at a given temperature. The accuracy of
                    this inference has been confirmed by recent experiments of Regnault.</p>
                <p>18. To ascertain the influence of change of temperature on the velocity of sound
                    in a gas, we remark that, by Gay Lussac’s law, the pressure of a gas at
                    different temperatures varies proportionally both to its density <hi
                    rend="italic">ρ</hi> and to 1 + <hi rend="italic">a t,</hi> where <hi
                    rend="italic">t</hi> is the number of degrees of temperature above freezing
                    point of water (32° Fahr.), and <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is the expansion of
                    unit of volume of the gas for every degree above 32°.</p>
                <p>If, therefore, <hi rend="italic">p, p</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 0</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">,</hi><hi rend="italic">ρ, p</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    0</hi> denote the pressures and densities corresponding to temperatures 32° <hi
                    rend="italic">+t</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi> and 32°, we have:</p>
                <p>∣^=r^ (<hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> + <hi rend="superscript"> α</hi> 0</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Po Po</hi> and hence, denoting the corresponding velocities of
                    sound by V, V <hi rend="subscript"> o</hi>, we get:</p>
                <p>V = √ ’ (1 +α <hi rend="italic">t</hi>)</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> v</hi> o whence, <hi rend="italic">a</hi> being always a
                    very small fraction, is obtained very nearly:</p>
                <p>1 <hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> ∣(andV-V,-p.V,</p>
                <p>The velocity increases, therefore, by <hi rend="superscript"> α</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> V <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> for every de-</p>
                <p>gree of rise of temperature above 32°.</p>
                <p>19. The general expression for V given in (II.) may be put in a different form:
                    if we introduce a height H of the gas, regarded as having the same density <hi
                    rend="italic">ρ</hi> throughout and exerting the pressure <hi rend="italic"
                    >p,</hi> then <hi rend="italic">p=g</hi><hi rend="italic">ρ</hi> H, where <hi
                    rend="italic">g</hi> is the acceleration of gravity, and there results:</p>
                <p>V= √^H · . . (HI.)</p>
                <p>Now <hi rend="italic">Jgιi</hi> or <hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >J</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">⅛∙</hi> v is the
                    velocity U which would H be acquired by a body falling <hi rend="italic">in
                    vacuo</hi> from a height — . Hence V = U√γ.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n119/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0119-0104"/>
                <p>if γ were equal to 1, V = U, which is the result obtaiued by Newton, and would
                    indicate that the velocity of sound in a gas equals the velocity of a body
                    falling from a height equal to half of that of a homogeneous atmosphere of the
                    gas.</p>
                <p>20. In common dry air at 32° Fahr., <hi rend="italic">g</hi> being 32∙2 ft., and
                    the mercurial barometer 30 ins. or 2∙5 ft., the density of air is to that of
                    mercury as 1: 10,485∙6; hence H = 10,458∙6 × 2∙5 ft. = 26,214 ft.</p>
                <p>Also <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> 1 ∙408</p>
                <p>Hence V <hi rend="subscript"> o</hi> = √1,4O8 × 32,2 × 26,214= 1090 ft.</p>
                <p>and, by § 18, the increase of velocity for each degree of rise of temperature (α
                    being is or <hi rend="superscript"> 545</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 491</hi>
                    =1∙110 ft.</p>
                <p>1 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 9</hi> ft. very
                    nearly.</p>
                <p>21. If the value of γ were the same for different gases, it is obvious from
                    formula V = - that, at a given temperature, the velocities of sound in those
                    gases would be to each other inversely as the square roots of their densities.
                    Regnault has found that this is so for common air, carbonic acid, nitrous oxide,
                    hydrogen and ammoniacal gas (though less so as regards the two last).</p>
                <p>22. The experimental determination of the velocity of sound in air has been
                    carried out by ascertaining accurately the time intervening between the flash
                    and report of a gun as observed at a given distance, and dividing the distance
                    by the time. A discussion of the many experiments conducted on this principle in
                    various countries and at various periods, by Van Der Kolk <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Lond. and Edin. Phil. Mag.,</hi> July 1865), assigns to the velocity of sound
                    in dry air at 32° Fahr., 1091 ft. 8 in. per second, with a probable error of
                    ±3∙7 ft.; and still more recently (in 1871) Mr Stone, the Astronomer Royal at
                    the Cape of Good Hope, has found 1090∙6 as the result of careful experiments by
                    himself there. The coincidence of’ these numbers with that we have already
                    obtained theoretically sufficiently establishes the general accuracy of the
                    theory.</p>
                <p>23. Still it cannot be overlooked that the formula for V is founded on
                    assumptions which, though approximately, are not strictly correct. Thus, the air
                    is not a perfect gas, nor is the variation of elastic force, caused by the
                    passage through it of a wave of disturbance always very small in comparison with
                    the elastic force of the undisturbed air. Earnshaw (1858) first drew attention
                    to these points, and came to the conclusion that the velocity of sound increases
                    with its loudness, that is, with the violence of the disturbance. In
                    confirmation of this statement, he appeals to a singular fact, viz., that,
                    during experiments made by Captain Parry, in the North Polar Regions, for
                    determining the velocity of sound, it was invariably found that the report of
                    the discharge of cannon was heard, at a distance of 2½ miles, perceptibly
                    earlier than the sound of the word <hi rend="italic">fire,</hi> which, of
                    course, preceded the discharge.</p>
                <p>As, in the course of propagation in unlimited air, there is a gradual decay in
                    the intensity of sound, it would follow that the velocity must also gradually
                    decrease as the sound proceeds onwards. This curious inference has been verified
                    experimentally by Regnault, who found the velocity of sound to have decreased by
                    2∙2 ft. per second in passing from a distance of 4000 to one of 7500 feet.</p>
                <p>24. Among other interesting results, derived by the accurate methods adopted by
                    Regnault, but which want of space forbids us to describe, may be mentioned the
                    dependence of the velocity of sound on its pitch, lower notes being, <hi
                    rend="italic">cad. par.,</hi> transmitted at a more rapid rate than higher ones.
                    Thus, the fundamental note of a trumpet travels faster than its harmonies.</p>
                <p>25. The velocity of sound in liquids and solids (the displacements being
                    longitudinal), may be obtained by formula (I.), neglecting the thermic effects
                    of the compressions and expansions as being comparatively inconsiderable, and
                    may be put in other forms:</p>
                <p>Thus, if we denote by ε the change in length of one foot of a column of the
                    substance produced by its own weight <hi rend="italic">w,</hi> then <hi
                    rend="italic">e</hi> being = w/ε or — , we have - = - and hence:</p>
                <p>e s ps</p>
                <p>.... (IV.)</p>
                <p>or, replacing i (which is the length in feet of a column that would be increased
                    1 foot by the weight of 1 cubic foot) by <hi rend="italic">I,</hi></p>
                <p>. . (V.)</p>
                <p>which shows that the velocity is that due to a fall through</p>
                <p>^2 ’</p>
                <p>Or, again, in the case of a liquid, if <hi rend="italic">η</hi> denote the change
                    of volume, which would be produced by an increase of pressure equal to one
                    atmosphere, or to that of a column H of the liquid, since ε is the change of
                    volume due to weight of a column 1 of the liquid, and .∙. <hi rend="superscript"
                    > η</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> ε</hi> = <hi rend="superscript"> H</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> and 1/ε = H/η, we get</p>
                <p>V= Ae . . . (VI.</p>
                <p>η</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ex.</hi> 1. For water, <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> η</hi> = 20,000 very nearly; H = 34 ft. and hence V = 4680
                    feet.</p>
                <p>This number coincides very closely with the value obtained, whether by direct
                    experiment, as by Colladon and Sturm on the Lake of Geneva in 1826, who found
                    4708, or by indirect means which assign to the velocity in the water of the
                    River Seine at 59° Fahr. a velocity of 4714 ft. (Wertheim).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ex.</hi> 2. For iron. Let the weight necessary to double the
                    length of an iron bar be 4260 millions of lbs. on the square foot. Then a length
                    <hi rend="italic">l</hi> will be extended to <hi rend="italic">l</hi> + 1 by . .
                    4260 millions lbs. . ,. <hi rend="subscript"> rr</hi>,.. .. , a force of - on
                    the sq. ft. lhιs, therefore, by our definition of <hi rend="italic">I,</hi> must
                    be the weight of a cubic foot of the iron. Assuming' the density of iron to be
                    7’8, and 62∙32 lbs. as the weight of a cubic foot of water, we get 7∙8 × 62∙32
                    or 486 lbs. as the weight of an equal bulk of iron. Hence <hi rend="superscript"
                    > 4260 millions</hi> / <hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi> = 486 and <hi
                    rend="italic">l =</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 4260</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >/</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 486</hi> millions, which gives V = <hi
                    rend="italic">Jgl =</hi> millions</p>
                <p>= ∕⅛≡ × 1000 = 1000 √284 V 15</p>
                <p>or V = 17,000 feet per second nearly.</p>
                <p>As in the case of water and iron, so, in general, it may be stated that sound
                    travels faster in liquids than in air, and still faster in solids, the ratio -
                    being least in gases</p>
                <p>P</p>
                <p>and greatest in solids.</p>
                <p>26. Biot, about 50 years ago, availed himself of the great difference in the
                    velocity of the propagation of sound through metals and through air, to
                    determine the ratio of the one velocity to the other. A bell placed near one
                    extremity of a train of iron pipes forming a joint length of upwards of 3000
                    feet, being struck at the same instant as the same extremity of the pipe, a
                    person placed at the other extremity heard first the sound of the blow on the
                    pipe, conveyed through the iron, and then, after an interval <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n120/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0120-0105"/> of time, which was noted as accurately as
                    possible, the sound of the bell transmitted through the air. The result was a
                    velocity for the iron of 10∙5 times that in air. Similar experiments on iron
                    telegraph wire, made more recently near Paris by Wertheim and Brequet, have led
                    to an almost identical number. Unfortunately, owing to the metal in those
                    experiments not forming a continuous whole, and to other causes, the results
                    obtained, which fall short of those otherwise found, cannot be accepted as
                    correct.</p>
                <p>Other means therefore, of an indirect character, to which we will refer
                    hereafter, have been resorted to for determining the velocity of sound in
                    solids. Thus Wertheim, from the pitch of the lowest notes produced by
                    longitudinal friction of wires or rods, has been led to assign to that velocity
                    values ranging, in different metals, from 16,822 feet for iron, to 4030 for
                    lead, at temperature 68° Fahr., and which agree most remarkably with those
                    calculated by means of the formula V = · He points out, however, that these
                    values refer only to solids whose cross dimensions are small in comparison with
                    their length, and that in order to obtain the velocity of sound in an unlimited
                    solid mass, it is requisite to multiply the value as above found by √ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> or <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> nearly. For while, in
                    a solid bar, the extensions and contractions due to any disturbance take place
                    laterally as well as longitudinally; in an extended solid, they can only occur
                    in the latter direction, thus increasing the value of <hi rend="italic"
                    >e.</hi></p>
                <p>27. To complete the discussion of the velocity of the propagation of sound, we
                    have still to consider the case of transversal vibrations, such as are executed
                    by the points of a stretched wire or cord when drawn out of its position of rest
                    by a blow, or by the friction of a violin-bow.</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">ox</hi> (fig. 4) be the position of the string when
                    undisturbed, <hi rend="italic">mnp</hi> when displaced. We will suppose the
                    amount of displacement to be very small, so that we may regard the distance
                    between any two given points of it as remaining the same, and also that the
                    tension P of the string is not changed in its amount, but only in its direction,
                    which is that of the string.</p>
                <p>Take any origin <hi rend="italic">o</hi> in <hi rend="italic">ox,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">ab = bc = δx</hi> (a very small quantity), then the perpendiculars
                    <hi rend="italic">am, bn, cp,</hi> are the displacements of <hi rend="italic"
                    >abc.</hi> Let <hi rend="italic">k, l</hi> be the middle points of <hi
                    rend="italic">mn, nρ∙,</hi> then <hi rend="italic">kl</hi> (which <hi
                    rend="italic">=mn</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ab</hi> very nearly) may be regarded
                    as a very small part of the string acted on by two forces each = P, and acting
                    at <hi rend="italic">n</hi> in the directions <hi rend="italic">np, nm.</hi>
                    These give a component parallel to <hi rend="italic">ac,</hi> which on our
                    supposition is negligible, and another F along <hi rend="italic">nb,</hi> such
                    that</p>
                <p>F = P(sin0-sin 0') = P. (^-^Vp∕±L^</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">mn nqj</hi> δz</p>
                <p>Now if <hi rend="italic">c</hi> = a length of string of weight equal to P, and
                    the string bc supposed of uniform thickness and density,</p>
                <p>PP <hi rend="superscript"> j</hi> the weight of <hi rend="italic">kl = - .kl = -.
                    8x,</hi> and the mass <hi rend="italic">m</hi> of <hi rend="italic">kl = c
                    c</hi></p>
                <p>σc</p>
                <p>Hence the acceleration /in direction <hi rend="italic">nb</hi> is— <hi
                    rend="italic">fΛ=~Ol=r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> j</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">m</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> j</hi><hi
                    rend="italic smallcaps"> ox</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript
                    smallcaps"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>If we denote <hi rend="italic">ma</hi> by <hi rend="italic">y, oa</hi> by <hi
                    rend="italic">x,</hi> and the time by <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> we shall readily
                    see that this equation becomes ultimately,</p>
                <p>&lt;⅜ =</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2 9</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dx</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> which is satisfied by putting <hi
                    rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">= φ (x +</hi><hi rend="italic">Jgï</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">t) + ψ (xJ go. ∕)</hi> where <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">ψ</hi> indicate any functions.</p>
                <p>Now we know that if for a given value of <hi rend="italic">t, x</hi> be increased
                    by the length λ of the wave, the value of <hi rend="italic">y</hi> remains
                    unchanged; hence, <hi rend="italic">Φ (x + J gc.</hi> ί) + &amp;c. = φ (z + λ +
                    <hi rend="subscript"> χ</hi> ∕ <hi rend="italic">gc. t)</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p>But this condition is equally satisfied for a given value of <hi rend="italic"
                    >x,</hi> by increasing √ <hi rend="italic">gc. t.</hi> by λ, <hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e.,</hi> increasing <hi rend="italic">t</hi> by <hi rend="italic">~j^</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> c</hi><hi rend="italic">∙</hi> This therefore must = T
                    (the time of a complete vibration of any point of the string). But V = <hi
                    rend="superscript"> λ</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> T</hi>. Hence,</p>
                <p>V = √ <hi rend="italic">gc</hi> (VII·)</p>
                <p>is the expression for the velocity of sound when due to very small transversal
                    vibrations of a thin wire or chord, which velocity is consequently the same as
                    would be acquired by a body falling through a height equal to one half of a
                    length of the chord such as to have a weight equal to he tension.</p>
                <p>The above may also be put in the form—</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> v</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">= a∕-- ’</hi></p>
                <p>V <hi rend="italic">W</hi> where P is the tension, and <hi rend="italic">w</hi>
                    the weight of the unit of length of the chord.</p>
                <p>28. It appears then that while sound is propagated by longitudinal vibrations
                    through a given substance with the same velocity under all circumstances, the
                    rate of its transmission by transversal vibrations through the same substance
                    depends on the tension and on the thickness. The former velocity bears to the
                    latter the ratio of <hi rend="italic subscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >j~l".</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">j~c,</hi> (where
                    <hi rend="italic">I</hi> is the length of the substance, which would be
                    lengthened <hi rend="italic">one</hi> foot by the weight of <hi rend="italic"
                    >one</hi> foot, if we take the foot as our unit) or of √ <hi rend="italic"
                    >l</hi> / <hi rend="italic">c</hi>: 1, that is, of the square</p>
                <p>, Λtfw root of the length which would be extended <hi rend="italic">one</hi> foot
                    by the weight of <hi rend="italic">c</hi> feet, or by the tension, to 1. This,
                    for ordinary tensions, results in the velocity for longitudinal vibrations being
                    very much in excess of that for transversal vibrations.</p>
                <p>29. It is a well known fact that, in all but very exceptional cases, the loudness
                    of any sound is less as the distance increases between the source of sound and
                    the ear. The law according to which this decay takes place is the same as
                    obtains in other natural phenomena, viz., that in an unlimited and uniform
                    medium the loudness or intensity of the sound proceeding from a very small
                    sounding body (strictly speaking, a point) varies inversely as the square of the
                    distance. This follows from considering that the ear AC receives only the
                    conical portion OAC of the whole volume of sound emanating from O, and that in
                    order that an ear BD, placed at a greater distance from O, may admit the same
                    quantity, its area must be to that of AC: as OB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>:
                    OA <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. But if A' = AC be situated at same distance
                    as BD, the amount of sound received by it and by BD (and therefore by AC) will
                    be as the area of A <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> or AC to that of BD. Hence,
                    the intensities of the sound as <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n121/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0121-0106"/> heard by the same ear at the distances OA and OB
                    are to each other as OB <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> to OA <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>30. In order to verify the above law when the atmosphere forms the intervening
                    medium, it would be necessary to test it at a considerable elevation above the
                    earth’s surface, the ear and the source of sound being separated by air of
                    constant density. As the density of the air diminishes, we should then find that
                    the loudness of the sound at a given distance would decrease, as is the case in
                    the air-pump experiment previously described. This arises from the decrease of
                    the quantity of matter impinging on the ear, and the consequent diminution of
                    its <hi rend="italic">vis-viva.</hi> The decay of sound due to this cause is
                    observable in the rarefied air of high mountainous regions. De Saussure, the
                    celebrated Alpine traveller, mentions that the report of a pistol at a great
                    elevation appeared no louder than would a small cracker at a lower level.</p>
                <p>But it is to be remarked that, according to Poisson, when air-strata of different
                    densities are interposed between the source of sound and the ear placed at a
                    given distance, the intensity depends only on the density of the air at the
                    source itself; whence it follows that sounds proceeding from the surface of the
                    earth may be heard at equal distances as distinctly by a person in a floating
                    balloon as by one situated on the surface itself; whereas any noise originating
                    in the balloon would be heard at the surface as faintly as if the ear were
                    placed in the rarefied air on a level with the balloon. This was exemplified
                    during a balloon ascent by Glaisher and Coxwell, who, when at an elevation of
                    20,000 feet, heard with great distinctness the whistle of a locomotive passing
                    beneath them.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> III.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Reflexion and Refraction of Sound.</hi></p>
                <p>31. When a wave of sound travelling through one medium meets a second medium of a
                    different kind, the vibrations of its own particles are communicated to the
                    particles of the new medium, so that a wave is excited in the latter, and is
                    propagated through it with a velocity dependent on the density and elasticity of
                    the second medium, and therefore differing in general from the previous
                    velocity. The direction, too, in which the new wave travels is different from
                    the previous one. This change of direction is termed <hi rend="italic"
                    >refraction,</hi> and takes place according to the same laws as does the
                    refraction of light, viz., (1.) The new direction or <hi rend="italic">refracted
                    ray</hi> lies always in the <hi rend="italic">plane of incidence,</hi> or plane
                    which contains the incident ray <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> the direction of
                    the wave in the first medium), and the normal to the surface separating the two
                    media, at the point in which the incident ray meets it; (2.) The <hi
                    rend="italic">sine</hi> of the angle between the normal and the incident ray
                    bears to the <hi rend="italic">sine</hi> of the angle between the normal and the
                    refracted ray, a ratio which is constant for the same pair of media.</p>
                <p>For a theoretical demonstration of these laws, we must refer to the art. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Optics,</hi> where it will be shown that the ratio involved in
                    the second law is always equal to the ratio of the velocity of the wave in the
                    first medium to the velocity in the second; in other words, the <hi
                    rend="italic">sines</hi> of the angles in question are <hi rend="italic"
                    >directly</hi> proportional to the velocities.</p>
                <p>32. Hence sonorous rays, in passing from one medium into another, are bent in
                    towards the normal, or the reverse, according as the velocity of propagation in
                    the former exceeds or falls short of that in the latter. Thus, for instance,
                    sound is refracted <hi rend="italic">towards</hi> the perpendicular when passing
                    into air from water, or into carbonic acid gas from air; the converse is the
                    case when the passage takes place the opposite way.</p>
                <p>33. It further follows, as in the analogous case of light, that there is a
                    certain angle termed the <hi rend="italic">limiting angle,</hi> whose <hi
                    rend="italic">sine</hi> is found by dividing the less by the greater velocity,
                    such that all rays of sound meeting the surface separating two different bodies
                    will not pass onward, but suffer total reflexion back into the first body, if
                    the velocity in that body is less than that in the other body, and if the angle
                    of incidence exceeds the limiting angle.</p>
                <p>The velocities in air and water being respectively 1090 and 4700 feet, the
                    limiting angle for these media may be easily shown to be slightly above 15½ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi>. Hence, rays of sound proceeding from a distant
                    source, and therefore nearly parallel to each other, and to PO (fig. 6), the
                    angle POM being greater than 15½ <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, will not pass
                    into the water at all, but suffer total reflexion. Under such circumstances, the
                    report of a gun, however powerful, would be inaudible by an ear placed in the
                    water.</p>
                <p>34. As light is concentrated into a focus by a convex glass lens (for which the
                    velocity of light is less than for the air), so sound ought to be made to
                    converge by passing through a convex lens formed of <hi rend="italic">carbonic
                    acid</hi> gas. On the other hand, to produce convergence with water or hydrogen
                    gas, in both which the velocity of sound exceeds its rate in air, the lens ought
                    to be <hi rend="italic">concave.</hi> These results have been confirmed
                    experimentally by Sondhaus and Hajech, who also succeeded in verifying the law
                    of the equality of the index of refraction to the ratio of the velocities of
                    sound.</p>
                <p>35. When a wave of sound falls on a surface separating two media, in addition to
                    the refracted wave transmitted into the new medium, which we have just been
                    considering, there is also a fresh wave formed in the new medium, and travelling
                    in it in a different direction, but, of course, with the same velocity. This <hi
                    rend="italic">reflected</hi> wave is subject to the same laws as regulate the
                    reflexion of light, viz., (1.) the coincidence of the planes of incidence and of
                    reflexion, and (2.) the equality of the angles of incidence and reflexion, that
                    is, of the angles made by the incident and reflected rays with the normal.</p>
                <p>36. As in an ellipse (fig. 7), the normal PG at any point bisects the angle SPH
                    (S, H being the foci), rays of sound diverging from S, and falling on the
                    spheroidal surface formed by the revolution of the ellipse about the longest
                    diameter AB, will be reflected to H. Also, since SP + PH is always = AB, the
                    times in which the different rays will reach H will all be equal to each other,
                    and hence a crash at S will be heard as a crash at H.</p>
                <p>37. At any point P of a parabola (fig. 8) of which S is the focus, and AX the
                    axis, the normal PG bisects the angle SPX, PX being drawn parallel to AX.</p>
                <p>Hence rays of sound diverging from S, and falling on the paraboloid formed by the
                    revolution of the parabola about its axis, will all be reflected in directions
                    parallel to the axis. And <hi rend="italic">vice versa</hi> rays of sound XP,
                    XQ, &amp;c., from a very distant source, and parallel to the axis of a
                    paraboloid, will be reflected into the focus. Consequently, if two reflecting
                    paraboloids be placed at a considerable distance from and opposite to each
                    other, with their axis coincident in direction (fig. 9), the tick of a watch
                    placed at the focus S of one will be heard distinctly by an ear at S', the focus
                    of the other.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n122/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0122-0107"/>
                <p>38. As a luminous object may give a succession of images when placed between two
                    or more reflecting surfaces, so also in like circumstances may a sound suffer
                    repetition.</p>
                <p>To these principles are easily traceable all the peculiarities of echoes. A wall
                    or steep cliff may thus send back, somewhat reduced in intensity, a shout, the
                    report of a pistol, &amp;c. The time which elapses between the sound and its
                    echo may be easily deduced from the known velocity of sound in air, if the
                    distance of the wall be given. Thus, for a distance of 37 yards, the interval
                    will be found by dividing the double of that or 74 yards by 370 yards, the
                    velocity of sound at 50° Falir., to amount to <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> /
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> of a second. Hence, if we assume that the rate at
                    which syllables can be distinctly uttered is five per second, the wall must be
                    at a distance exceeding 37 yards to allow of the echo of a word of one syllable
                    reaching the ear <hi rend="italic">after</hi> the word has been uttered, 74
                    yards for a word of <hi rend="italic">two</hi> syllables, and so on.</p>
                <p>If the reflecting surface consists of one or more walls, cliffs, &amp;c., forming
                    together a near approach in shape to that of a prolate spheroid or of a double
                    parabolic surface, then two points may be found, at one of which if a source of
                    sound be placed, there will be produced, by convergence, a distinct echo at the
                    other. As examples of this may be mentioned the whispering gallery in St Paul’s,
                    London, and the still more remarkable case of the Cathedral of Girgenti in
                    Sicily mentioned by Sir John Herschel.</p>
                <p>39. On similar principles of repeated reflexion may be explained the well-known
                    fact that sounds may be conveyed to great distances with remarkably slight loss
                    of intensity, on a level piece of ground or smooth sheet of water or ice, and
                    still more so in pipes, chimneys, tunnels, &amp;c. Thus, in one of Captain
                    Parry’s Polar expeditions, a conversation was on one occasion carried on, at a
                    distance of 1¼ mile, between two individuals separated by a frozen sheet of
                    water. Μ. Biot heard distinctly from one end of the train of pipes <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> of a mile long,
                    previously referred to, a low whisper proceeding from the opposite end.</p>
                <p>Practical illustrations are afforded by the system of communication by means of
                    tubing now so extensively adopted in public and private buildings, and by the
                    <hi rend="italic">speaking trumpet</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">ear
                    trumpet.</hi></p>
                <p>40. The prolonged roll of thunder, with its manifold varieties, is partly to be
                    ascribed to reflexion by mountains, clouds, &amp;c.; but is mainly accounted for
                    on a different acoustic principle, viz., the comparatively low rate of
                    transmission of sound through air, as was first shown by Dr Hooke at the close
                    of the 17th century. The explanation will be more easily understood by adverting
                    to the case of a volley fired by a long line of troops. A person situated at a
                    point in that line produced, will first it is evident hear the report of the
                    nearest musket, followed by that of the one following, and so down to the last
                    one in the line, which will close the prolonged roll thus reaching his ear; and
                    as each single report will appear to him less intense according as it proceeds
                    from a greater distance, the roll of musketry thus heard will be one of
                    gradually decreasing loudness. But if he were to place himself at a relatively
                    great distance right opposite to the centre of the line, the separate reports
                    from each of the two wings would reach him nearly at the same moment, and hence
                    the sound of the volley would now approach more nearly to that of a single loud
                    crash. If the line of soldiers formed an arc of a circle having its centre in
                    his position, then the distances gone over by the separate reports being equal,
                    they would reach his ear at the same absolute instant of time, and with exactly
                    equal intensities; and the effect produced would be strictly the same as that of
                    a single explosion, equal in violence to the sum of all the separate discharges,
                    occurring at the same distance. It is easy to see that, by varying the form of
                    the line of troops and the position of the observer, the sonorous effect will be
                    diversified to any extent desired. If then we keep in view the great diversity
                    of form exhibited by lightning-flashes, which may be regarded as being lines, at
                    the points of which are generated explosions at the same instant of time, and
                    the variety of distance and relative position at which the observer may be
                    placed, we shall feel no difficulty in accounting for all those acoustic
                    phenomena of thunder to which Hooke’s theory is applicable.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> IV.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Principles of Musical Harmony.</hi></p>
                <p>41. A few words on the subject of <hi rend="italic">musical harmony</hi> must be
                    introduced here for the immediate purposes of this article, further details
                    being reserved for the special article on that subject.</p>
                <p>Sounds in general exhibit three different qualities, so far as their effect on
                    the ear is concerned, viz., <hi rend="italic">loudness, pitch,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">timbre.</hi></p>
                <p>Loudness depends, <hi rend="italic">caet. par.,</hi> on the violence with which
                    the vibrating portions of the ear are excited; and therefore on the <hi
                    rend="italic">extent</hi> or <hi rend="italic">amplitude</hi> of the vibrations
                    of the body whence the sound proceeds. Hence, after a bell has been struck, its
                    effect on the ear gradually diminishes as its vibration becomes less and less
                    extensive. By the theory of vibrations, loudness or intensity is measured by the
                    <hi rend="italic">vis-viva</hi> of the vibrating particles, and is consequently
                    proportional to the square of their maximum velocity or to the square of their
                    maximum displacement. Helmholtz, however, in his remarkable work on the
                    perception of tone, observes that notes differing in pitch differ also in
                    loudness, where their <hi rend="italic">vis viva</hi> is the same, the higher
                    note always exhibiting the greater intensity.</p>
                <p>42. Difference of <hi rend="italic">pitch</hi> is that which finds expression in
                    the common terms applied to notes: <hi rend="italic">Acute, shrill, high, sharp,
                    grave, deep, low, flat.</hi> We will point out presently in what manner it is
                    established that this quality of sound depends on the rapidity of vibration of
                    the particles of air in contact with the external parts of the ear. The pitch of
                    a note is higher in proportion to the number of vibrations of the air
                    corresponding to it, in a given time, such as one</p>
                <p>V second. If <hi rend="italic">n</hi> denote this number, then, by § 13, <hi
                    rend="italic">n = V/</hi> λ and hence, V being constant, the pitch is higher the
                    less the length λ of the wave.</p>
                <p>43. <hi rend="italic">Timbre,</hi> or, as it is termed by German authors, <hi
                    rend="italic">klang-farbe,</hi> rendered by Tyndall into <hi rend="italic"
                    >clang-colour</hi> or <hi rend="italic">clang-tint,</hi> but for which we would
                    substitute the expression <hi rend="italic">acoustic colour,</hi> denotes that
                    peculiarity of impression produced on the ear by sounds otherwise, in pitch,
                    loudness, &amp;c., alike, whereby they are recognisable as different from each
                    other. Thus human voices are readily interdistinguishable; so are notes of the
                    same pitch and intensity, produced by different instruments. The question whence
                    arises this distinction must be deferred for the present.</p>
                <p>44. Besides the three qualities above mentioned, there exists another point in
                    which sounds may be distinguished among each other, and which, though perhaps
                    reducible to difference of timbre, requires some special remarks, viz., that by
                    which sounds are characterised, either as <hi rend="italic">noises</hi> or as
                    <hi rend="italic">musical notes.</hi> A musical note is the result of regular,
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n123/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0123-0108"/> periodic vibrations of the air-particles acting
                    on the ear, and therefore also of the body whence they proceed, each particle
                    passing through the same phase at stated intervals of time. On the other hand,
                    the motion to which <hi rend="italic">noise</hi> is due is irregular and
                    flitting, alternately fast and slow, and creating in the mind a bewildering and
                    confusing effect of a more or less unpleasant character. Noise may also be
                    produced by combining in an arbitrary manner several musical notes, as when one
                    leans with the fore-arm against the keys of a piano. In fact, the composition of
                    regular periodic motions, thus effected, is equivalent to an irregular
                    motion.</p>
                <p>45. We now proceed to state the laws of musical harmony, and to describe certain
                    instruments by means of which they admit of being experimentally established.
                    The chief of these laws are as follow :—</p>
                <p>(1.) The notes employed in music always correspond to certain definite and
                    invariable ratios between the numbers of vibrations performed in a given time by
                    the air when conveying these notes to the ear, and these ratios are of a very
                    simple kind, being restricted to the various permutations of the first four
                    prime numbers 1, 2, 3, 5, and their powers.</p>
                <p>(2.) Two notes are in <hi rend="italic">unison</hi> whose corresponding
                    vibrations are executed exactly at the same rate, or for which (denoting by <hi
                    rend="italic">n, n</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi> the numbers per
                    second) n <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> /n = 1. This ratio or <hi rend="italic"
                    >interval</hi> (as it is termed) is the simplest possible.</p>
                <p>(3.) The next <hi rend="italic">interval</hi> is that in which <hi rend="italic"
                    >n</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 2, and is
                    termed the <hi rend="italic">octave.</hi></p>
                <p>(4.) The interval — = 3 is termed the <hi rend="italic">twelfth,</hi> and if we
                    reduce the higher note of the pair by an 8 <hi rend="superscript"> ve</hi>, <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> divide its number of vibrations by 2, we obtain the
                    interval <hi rend="italic">n</hi> 3</p>
                <p>= -, designated as the interval of the <hi rend="italic">fifth.</hi></p>
                <p>(5.) The interval = 5 has no particular name attached to it, but if we lower the
                    higher note by two n <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> /n = 5/45</p>
                <p>8 <hi rend="superscript"> ves</hi> or divide <hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi> by 4, we get the interval — -, or the interval
                    of the <hi rend="italic">major third.</hi></p>
                <p>(6.) The interval = <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>
                    is termed the <hi rend="italic">major sixth.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">ιi</hi>
                    2x3 6</p>
                <p>(7.) The interval — = —— = - is termed the <hi rend="italic">minor</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> x ,</hi> n 5 5</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">third.</hi></p>
                <p>72 2x2 4</p>
                <p>(8.) The interval -^∙ = —— = - is termed the <hi rend="italic">fourth.</hi> g 3
                    3</p>
                <p>(9.) The interval - which, being = - × -, may be re-o <hi rend="italic">Δ
                    Δ</hi><hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 2~</p>
                <p>garded as formed by taking in the first place a note one-fifth higher than the
                    key-note or fundamental, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> higher 3</p>
                <p>than the latter by the interval -, thence ascending by</p>
                <p>3 3</p>
                <p>another fifth, which gives us - × - and lowering this by</p>
                <p>9</p>
                <p>an octave, which results in <hi rend="superscript"> 9</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"
                    > 8</hi>, which is called the <hi rend="italic">second.</hi></p>
                <p>(10.) The interval <hi rend="superscript"> 15</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>
                    or <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> × <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> may be regarded as the
                    major third (<hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>) of
                    the fifth (<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>), and
                    is called the interval of the <hi rend="italic">seventh.</hi></p>
                <p>46. If the key-note or fundamental be denoted by C, and the notes, whose
                    intervals above C are those just enumerated, by D, E, F, G, A, B, C, we form
                    what is known in music as the natural or <hi rend="italic">diatonic</hi> scale,
                    in which therefore the intervals reckoned from C are successively <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 9</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 4</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 15</hi> /, 2, and therefore the intervals between each note
                    and the one following are <hi rend="superscript"> 9</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                    8</hi>, <hi rend="superscript"> 10</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 9</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 16</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 15</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 9</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 10</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 9</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 9</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 16</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 15</hi>.</p>
                <p>Of these last intervals the <hi rend="italic">first, fourth,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">sixth</hi> are 9 . .</p>
                <p>each = -, which is termed a <hi rend="italic">major tone.</hi> The <hi
                    rend="italic">second</hi> and 8</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">fifth</hi> are each = <hi rend="superscript"> 10</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 9</hi>, which is a ratio slightly less than the former, and
                    hence is called a <hi rend="italic">minor tone.</hi> The <hi rend="italic"
                    >third</hi> and <hi rend="italic">seventh</hi> are each = <hi rend="superscript"
                    > 16</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 15</hi>,to which is given the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">semi-tone.</hi></p>
                <p>By interposing an additional note between each pair of notes whose interval is a
                    major or a minor tone, the resulting series of notes may be made to exhibit a
                    nearer approach to equality in the intervals successively separating them, which
                    will be very nearly <hi rend="italic">semi-tones.</hi> This sequence of twelve
                    notes forms the <hi rend="italic">chromatic</hi> scale. The note interposed
                    between C and D is either C sharp (C♯) or D flat (D♭), according as it is formed
                    by <hi rend="italic">raising</hi> C a semi-tone or <hi rend="italic"
                    >lowering</hi> D by the same amount.</p>
                <p>47. Various kinds of apparatus have been contrived with a view of confirming
                    experimentally the truth of the laws of musical harmony as above stated.</p>
                <p>Savart’s toothed wheel apparatus consists of a brass wheel, whose edge is divided
                    into a number of equal projecting teeth distributed uniformly over the
                    circumference, and which is capable of rapid rotation about an axis
                    perpendicular to its plane and passing through its centre, by means of a series
                    of multiplying wheels, the last of which is turned round by the hand. The
                    toothed wheel being set in motion, the edge of a card or of a funnel-shaped
                    piece of common note paper is held against the teeth, when a note will be heard
                    arising from the rapidly succeeding displacements of the air in its vicinity.
                    The pitch of this note will, agreeably to the theory, rise as the rate of
                    rotation increases, and becomes steady when that rotation is maintained uniform.
                    It may thus be brought into unison with any sound of which it may be required to
                    determine the corresponding number of vibrations per second, as for instance the
                    note A <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, three 8 <hi rend="superscript"> ves</hi>
                    higher than the A which is indicated musically by a small circle placed between
                    the second and third lines of the G clef, which A is the note of the tuning-fork
                    usually employed for regulating concert-pitch. A <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>
                    may be given by a piano. Now, suppose that the note produced with Savart’s
                    apparatus is in unison with A <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, when the
                    experimenter turns round the first wheel at the rate of 60 turns per minute or
                    one per second, and that the circumferences of the various multiplying wheels
                    are such that the rate of revolution of the toothed wheel is thereby increased
                    44 times, then the latter wheel will perform 44 revolutions in a second, and
                    lienee, if the number of its teeth be 80, the number of taps imparted to the
                    card every second will amount to 44 × 80 or 3520. This, therefore, is the number
                    of vibrations corresponding to the note A <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>. If we
                    divide this by 2 <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> or 8, we obtain 440 as the
                    number of vibrations answering to the note A. This, however, tacitly assumes
                    that the bands by which motion is transmitted from wheel to wheel do not <hi
                    rend="italic">slip</hi> during the experiment. If, as is always more or less the
                    case, slipping occurs, a different mode for determining the rate at which the
                    toothed wheel revolves, such as is employed in the syren of De la Tour <hi
                    rend="italic">(vide</hi> below), must be adopted.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n124/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0124-0109"/>
                <p>If, for the single toothed wheel, be substituted a set of four with a common
                    axis, in which the teeth are in the ratios 4: 5: 6: 8, and if the card be
                    rapidly passed along their edges, we shall hear distinctly produced the
                    fundamental chord C, E, G, C <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> and shall thus satisfy
                    ourselves that the intervals C, E; C <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> G, and C C <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> are (as they 5 3</p>
                <p>ought to be) -, -, and 2 respectively.</p>
                <p>48. The <hi rend="italic">syren</hi> of Seebeck is the simplest form of apparatus
                    thus designated, aud consists of a large circular disc of pasteboard mounted on
                    a central axis, about which it may be made to revolve with moderate rapidity.
                    This disc is perforated with small round holes arranged in circles about the
                    centre of the disc. In the first series of circles, reckoning from the centre,
                    the openings are so made as to divide the respective circumferences, on which
                    they are found, in aliquot parts bearing to each other the ratios of the numbers
                    2, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 20, 24, 32, 40, 48, 64. The second series consists of
                    circles each of which is formed of two sets of perforations, in the first circle
                    arranged as 4: 5, in the next as 3: 4, then as 2: 3, 3: 5, 4: 7. In the outer
                    series is a circle divided by perforations into four sets, the numbers of
                    aliquot parts being as 3: 4: 5: 6, followed by others which we need not further
                    refer to.</p>
                <p>The disc being started, then by means of a tube held at one end between the lips,
                    and applied near to the disc at the other, or more easily with a common bellows,
                    a blast of air is made to fall on the part of the disc which contains any one of
                    the above circles. The current being alternately transmitted and shut off, as a
                    hole passes on and off the aperture of the tube or bellows, causes a vibratory
                    motion of the air, whose rapidity depends on the number of times per second that
                    a perforation passes the mouth of the tube. Hence the note produced with any
                    given circle of holes rises in pitch as the disc revolves more rapidly; and if,
                    the revolution of the disc being kept as steady as possible, the tube be passed
                    rapidly across the circles of the first series, the notes heard are found to
                    produce on the ear, as required by theory, the exact impression corresponding to
                    the ratios 2: 4: &amp;c., <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> of a series of notes,
                    which, if the lowest be denoted by C, form the sequence C C <hi rend="subscript"
                    > 1</hi> E <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> G <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> C <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> &amp;c., Ac. In like manner, the first circle in which
                    we have two sets of holes dividing the circumference, the one into say 8 parts,
                    and the other into 10, or in ratio 4: 5, the note produced is a compound one,
                    such as would be obtained by striking on the piano two notes separated by the
                    interval of a major third Similar results, all agreeing with the theory, are
                    obtainable by means of the remaining perforations.</p>
                <p>A still simpler form of syren may be constituted with a good spinning top, a
                    perforated card disc, and a tube for blowing with.</p>
                <p>49. The syren of Cagnard de la Tour is founded on the same principle as the
                    preceding. It consists of a cylindrical chest of brass, the base of which is
                    pierced at its centre with an opening in which is fixed a brass tube projecting
                    outwards, and intended for supplying the cavity of the cylinder with compressed
                    air or other gas, or even liquid. The top of the cylinder is formed of a plate
                    perforated near its edge by holes distributed uniformly in a circle concentric
                    with the plate, and which are cut obliquely through the thickness of the plate.
                    Immediately above this fixed plate, and almost in contact with it, is another of
                    the same dimensions, and furnished with the same number, <hi rend="italic"
                    >n,</hi> of openings similarly placed, but passing obliquely through in an
                    opposite direction from those in the fixed plate, the one set being inclined to
                    the left, the other to the right.</p>
                <p>This second plate is capable of rotation about a steel axis perpendicular to its
                    plane and passing through its centre. Now, let the movable plate be at any time
                    in a position such that its holes are immediately above those in the fixed
                    plate, and let the bellows by which air is forced into the cylinder (air, for
                    simplicity, being supposed to be the fluid employed) be put in action; then the
                    air in its passage will strike the side of each opening in the movable plate in
                    an oblique direction (as shown in fig. 10), and will therefore urge the latter
                    to rotation round its centre. After -th of a revolution, the two sets of
                    perforations will again coincide, the lateral impulse of the air repeated, and
                    hence the rapidity of rotation increased. This will go on continually as long as
                    air is supplied to the cylinder, and the velocity of rotation of the upper plate
                    will be accelerated up to a certain maximum, at which it may be maintained by
                    keeping the force of the current constant.</p>
                <p>Now, it is evident that each coincidence of the perforations in the two plates is
                    followed by a non-coincidence, during which the air-current is shut off, and
                    that consequently, during each revolution of the upper plate, there occur <hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi> alternate passages and interceptions of the current. Hence
                    arises the same number of successive impulses of the external air immediately in
                    contact with the movable plate, which is thus thrown into a state of vibration
                    at the rate of <hi rend="italic">n</hi> for every revolution of the plate. The
                    result is a note whose pitch rises as the velocity of rotation increases, and
                    becomes steady when that velocity reaches its constant value. If, then, we can
                    determine the number <hi rend="italic">m</hi> of revolutions performed by the
                    plate in every second, we shall at once have the number of vibrations per second
                    corresponding to the audible note by multiplying <hi rend="italic">m</hi> by <hi
                    rend="italic">n.</hi></p>
                <p>For this purpose the steel axis is furnished at its upper part with a screw
                    working into a toothed wheel, and driving it round, during each revolution of
                    the plate, through a space equal to the interval between two teeth. An index
                    resembling the hand of a watch partakes of this motion, and points successively
                    to the divisions of a graduated dial. On the completion of each revolution of
                    this toothed wheel (which, if the number of its teeth be. 100, will comprise 100
                    revolutions of the movable plate), a projecting pin fixed to it catches a tooth
                    of another toothed wheel and turns it round, and with it a corresponding index
                    which thus records the number of turns of the first toothed wheel. As an example
                    of the application of this syren, suppose that the number of revolutions of the
                    plate, as shown by the indices, amounts to 5400 in a minute of time, that is, to
                    90 per second, then the number of vibrations per second of the note heard
                    amounts to 90 <hi rend="italic">n</hi>, or (if number of holes in each plate =
                    8) to 720.</p>
                <p>50. Dove, of Berlin, has produced a modification of the syren by which the
                    relations of different musical notes may be more readily ascertained. In it the
                    fixed and movable plates are each furnished with four concentric series of
                    perforations, dividing the circumferences into different aliquot parts, as <hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi>. <hi rend="italic">ex.,</hi> 8, 10, 12, 16. Beneath the
                    lower or fixed plate are four metallic rings furnished with holes corresponding
                    to those in the plates, and which may be pushed round by projecting pins, so as
                    to admit the air-current through any one or more of the series of perforations
                    in the fixed plate. Thus, may be obtained, either separately or in various
                    combinations, the four notes whose vibrations are in the ratios of the above
                    numbers, and which therefore form the fundamental chord (CEGC <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>). The inventor has given to this instrument the name of
                    the <hi rend="italic">many-voiced syren.</hi></p>
                <p>51. Helmholtz has further adapted the syren for more extensive use, by the
                    addition to Dove’s instrument of another chest containing its own fixed and
                    movable perforated<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n125/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0125-0110"/> plates and perforated rings, both the moveable
                    plates being driven by the same current and revolving about a common axis.
                    Annexed is a figure of this instrument (fig. 11).</p>
                <p>52. The relation between the pitch of a note and the frequency of the
                    corresponding vibrations has also been studied by <hi rend="italic">graphic</hi>
                    methods. Thus, if an elastic metal slip or a pig’s bristle be attached to one
                    prong of a tuningfork, and if the fork, while in vibration, is moved rapidly
                    over a glass plate coated with lamp black, the attached slip touching the plate
                    lightly, a wavy line will be traced on the plate answering to the vibrations to
                    and fro of the fork. The same result will be obtained with a stationary fork and
                    a movable glass plate; and, if the time occupied by the plate in moving through
                    a given distance can be ascertained, and the number of complete undulations
                    exhibited on the plate for that distance, which is evidently the number of
                    vibrations of the fork in that time, is reckoned, we shall have determined the
                    numerical vibration-value of the note yielded by the fork. Or, if the same plate
                    be moved in contact with two tuning-forks, we shall, by comparing the number of
                    sinuosities in the one trace with that in the other, be enabled to assign the
                    ratio of the corresponding numbers of vibrations per second. Thus, if the one
                    note be an octave higher than the other, it will give double the number of waves
                    in the same distance. The motion of the plate may be simply produced by dropping
                    it between two vertical grooves, the tuning-forks being properly fixed to a
                    frame above.</p>
                <p>53. Greater accuracy may be attained with the so-called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vibrograph</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Phonautograph</hi> (Duhamel’s or
                    Koenig’s), consisting of a glass cylinder coated with lamp-black, or, better
                    still, a metallic cylinder round which a blackened sheet of paper is wrapped.
                    The cylinder is mounted on a horizontal axis and turned round, while the <hi
                    rend="italic">pointer</hi> attached to the vibrating body is in light contact
                    with it, and traces therefore a wavy circle, which, on taking off the paper and
                    flattening it, becomes a wavy straight line. The superiority of this arrangement
                    arises from the comparative facility with which the number of revolutions of the
                    cylinder in a given time may be ascertained. In Koenig’s phonautograph, the axis
                    of the cylinder is fashioned as a screw, which works in fixed nuts at the ends,
                    causing a sliding as well as a rotatory motion of the cylinder. The lines traced
                    out by the vibrating pointer are thus prevented from overlapping when more than
                    one turn is given to the cylinder.</p>
                <p>Any sound whatever may be made to record its trace on the paper by means of a
                    large parabolic cavity resembling a speaking-trumpet, which is freely open at
                    the wider extremity, but is closed at the other end by a thin stretched
                    membrane. To the centre of this membrane is attached a small feather-fibre,
                    which, when the reflector is suitably placed, touches lightly the surface of the
                    revolving cylinder. Any sound (such as that of the human voice) transmitting its
                    rays into the reflector, and communicating vibratory motion to the membrane,
                    will cause, the feather to trace a sinuous line on the paper. If, at the same
                    time, a tuningfork of known number of vibrations per second be made to trace its
                    own line close to the other, a comparison of the two lines gives the number
                    corresponding to the sound under consideration.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Pakt</hi> V.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Stationary Waves.</hi></p>
                <p>54. We have hitherto, in treating of the propagation of waves of sound, assumed
                    that the medium through which it took place was unlimited in all directions, and
                    that the source of sound was single. In order, however, to understand the
                    principles of the production of sound by musical instruments, we must now direct
                    our attention to the case of two waves from different sources travelling through
                    the same medium in opposite directions. Any particle of the medium being then
                    affected by two different vibrations at the same instant will necessarily
                    exhibit a different state of motion from that due to either wave acting
                    separately from the other, and we have to inquire what is the result of this
                    mutual <hi rend="italic">interference</hi> (as it is termed) of the two given
                    waves. Supposing, as sufficient for our purpose, that the given waves are of
                    equal lengths and of equal amplitudes, in other words, that the corresponding
                    notes are of the same pitch and equally loud; and supposing, further, that they
                    are advancing in exactly opposite directions, we shall now show that the result
                    of the mutual interference of two such waves is the production of a <hi
                    rend="italic">stationary wave,</hi> that is, taking any line of particles of the
                    medium along the direction of motion of the component waves, certain of them,
                    such as <hi rend="italic">a, c, e</hi>. . . at intervals each</p>
                <p>= λ/2, will remain constantly in their usual undisturbed positions. All the
                    particles situated between <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
                    will vibrate (transversely or longitudinally, as the case may be) to and fro in
                    the same direction as they would if affected by only one of the interfering
                    waves, but with different amplitudes of vibration, ranging from zero at <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> to a maximum at <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and thence to zero
                    at <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> Those between <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">e</hi> will vibrate in like manner, but always in an opposite
                    direction to the similarly placed particles in <hi rend="italic">ac,</hi> and so
                    on alternately.</p>
                <p>The annexed figures will represent to the eye the states of motion at intervals
                    of time = ¼ of the time T of a complete vibration of the particles. In fig. 13,
                    1, the particles in <hi rend="italic">ac</hi> are at their greatest distances
                    from their undisturbed positions <hi rend="italic">(above</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">to the right,</hi> according as the motion is <hi rend="italic"
                    >transversal</hi> or <hi rend="italic">longitudinal).</hi> In fig. 13, 2, they
                    are all in their undisturbed positions. In fig. 13, 3, the displacements are all
                    reversed relatively to fig. 13, 1. In fig. 13, 4, the particles are again
                    passing through their equilibrium positions, resuming the positions indicated in
                    fig. 13, 1, after the time T.</p>
                <p>The points <hi rend="italic">ace,</hi> &amp;c., which remain stationary are
                    termed <hi rend="italic">nodes,</hi> and the vibrating parts between them <hi
                    rend="italic">ventral segments.</hi></p>
                <p>54a. <hi rend="italic">Proof.</hi> In fig. 14, 1, the full curved line represents
                    the two interfering waves at an instant of time such that, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n126/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0126-0111"/> in their progress towards each other, they are
                    then coincident. It is obvious that the particles of the medium will at the
                    moment in question be displaced to double the extent of the displacement
                    producible by either wave alone, so that the <hi rend="italic">resultant</hi>
                    wave may be represented by the <hi rend="italic">dotted</hi> curve. In fig. 14,
                    2, the two interfering waves, represented by the full and dotted curves
                    respectively, have each passed over a distance = ¼ λ, the one to the right, the
                    other to the left, and it is manifest that any disturbance of the medium,
                    producible by the one wave, is completely neutralised by the equal and opposite
                    action of the other. Hence, the particles of the medium are now in their
                    undisturbed positions. In fig. 14, 3, a further advance of the two waves, each
                    in its own direction, over a space = ¼ λ, has again brought them into
                    coincidence, and the result is the wave represented by the dotted line, which,
                    it will be remarked, has its <hi rend="italic">crests,</hi> where, in fig. 1,
                    are found <hi rend="italic">troughs.</hi> In fig. 14, 4, after a further advance
                    = ¼ λ, we have a repetition of the case of fig. 14, 2, the particles are now
                    again unaffected by the waves. A still further advance of ¼ λ, or of λ reckoned
                    from the commencement, brings us back to the same state of things as subsisted
                    in fig. 14, 1. An inspection and inter-comparison of the dotted lines in these
                    figures are now sufficient to establish the accuracy of the laws, before
                    mentioned, of <hi rend="italic">stationary waves.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Part</hi> VI.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Musical Strings.</hi></p>
                <p>55. We have in musical strings an instance of the occurrence of stationary
                    waves.</p>
                <p>Let AB (fig. 15) be a wire or string, supposed meanwhile to be fixed only at one
                    extremity B, and let the wire be, at any part, excited (whether by passing a
                    violin bow across or by friction along it), so that a wave (whether of
                    transversal or longitudinal vibrations) is propagated thence towards B. On
                    reaching this point, which is fixed, reflexion will occur, in consequence of
                    which the particles there will suffer a complete reversal of velocity, just as
                    when a perfectly elastic ball strikes against a smooth surface perpendicularly,
                    it rebounds with a velocity equal and opposite to that it previously had. Hence,
                    the displacement due to the incident wave being BM, the displacement after
                    reflexion will be BN equal and opposite to BM, and a reflected wave will result,
                    represented by the faint line in the fig., which will travel with the same
                    velocity, but in the opposite direction to the incident wave fully lined in the
                    fig. The interference of these two. oppositely progressing waves will
                    consequently give rise to a stationary wave (fig. 16), and if we take on the
                    wire distances BC, CD, DE, &amp;c. = ½ λ, the points B, C, D, E, . . . will be
                    <hi rend="italic">nodes,</hi> each of which separate portions of the wire
                    vibrating in opposite directions, <hi rend="italic">i.e., ventral
                    segments.</hi></p>
                <p>56. Now, it is obvious that, inasmuch as a node is a point which remains always
                    at rest while other parts of the medium to which it belongs are vibrating, such
                    point may be absolutely fixed without thereby interfering with the oscillatory
                    motion of the medium. If, therefore, a length AB of wire be taken equal to any
                    multiple of λ/2, A may be fixed as well as B, the motion remaining the same as
                    before, and thus we shall have the usual case of a musical string. The two
                    extremities being now both fixed, there will be repeated reflexions at both, and
                    a consequent persistence of two progressive waves advancing in opposite
                    directions and producing together the stationary wave above figured.</p>
                <p>57. We learn from this that a musical string is susceptible of an infinite
                    variety of modes of vibration corresponding to different numbers of subdivision
                    into ventral segments.</p>
                <p>Thus, it may have but <hi rend="italic">one</hi> ventral segment (fig. 17), or
                    but two nodes formed by its fixed extremities. In this case, the note emitted by
                    it is the lowest which can possibly be obtained from it, or, as it is called,
                    its <hi rend="italic">fundamental</hi> note. If <hi rend="italic">l</hi> denote
                    the length of the wire, by what has been already proved, <hi rend="italic"
                    >l=</hi> λ/2, and therefore the length of the wave λ = 2 <hi rend="italic"
                    >l</hi>. Hence, V being the velocity of propagation of the wave through the
                    wire, the number <hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi> of
                    vibrations performed in the unit of time with the fundamental note is —.</p>
                <p>The next possible sub-division of the wire is into <hi rend="italic">two</hi>
                    ventral segments, the three nodes being the two fixed ends A, B, and the middle
                    point C (fig. 18). Hence, <hi rend="italic">l =</hi><hi rend="italic">λ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">,</hi> and the number of vibrations <hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> V <hi rend="italic">/l</hi> or
                    double of those of the fundamental. The note, therefore, now is an 8 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ve</hi> higher.</p>
                <p>Reasoning in a like manner for the cases of three, four, &amp;c., ventral
                    segments, we obtain the following general law, which is applicable alike to <hi
                    rend="italic">transversely</hi> and to <hi rend="italic">longitudinally</hi>
                    vibrating wires:</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="italic">wire or string fixed at both ends is
                    capable of yielding, in addition to its fundamental note, any one of a series of
                    notes corresponding to</hi> 2, 3, 4 <hi rend="italic">times, &amp;c., the number
                    of vibrations per second of the fundamental, viz., he octave, twelfth, double
                    octave, &amp;c.</hi></p>
                <p>These higher notes are termed the <hi rend="italic">harmonics</hi> or (by the
                    Germans) the <hi rend="italic">overtones</hi> of the string.</p>
                <p>It is to be remarked that the overtones are in general fainter the higher they
                    are in the series, because, as the number of ventral segments or independently
                    vibrating parts of the string increases, the extent or amplitude of the
                    vibrations diminishes.</p>
                <p>58. Not only may the fundamental and its harmonics <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n127/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0127-0112"/> be obtained independently of each other, but they
                    are also to be heard simultaneously, particularly, for the reason just given,
                    those that are lower in the scale. A practised ear easily discerns the
                    coexistence of these various tones when a pianoforte or violin string is thrown
                    into vibration. It is evident that, in such case, the string, while vibrating as
                    a whole between its fixed extremities, is at the same time executing subsidiary
                    oscillations about its middle point, its points of trisection, &amp;c., as shown
                    in fig. 19, for the fundamental and the first harmonic.</p>
                <p>59. The easiest means for bringing out the harmonics of a string consists in
                    drawing a violin-bow across it near to one end, while the feathered end of a
                    quill or a hair-pencil is held lightly against the string at the point which it
                    is intended shall form a node, and is removed just after the bow is withdrawn.
                    Thus, if a node is made in this way, at ⅓ of AB from A, the note heard will be
                    the twelfth. If light paper rings be strung on the cord, they will be driven by
                    the vibrations to the nodes or points of rest, which will thus be clearly
                    indicated to the eye.</p>
                <p>V</p>
                <p>GO. The formula <hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">=</hi><hi rend="superscript"> V</hi><hi rend="italic">/</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi> shows that the pitch
                    of the fundamental note of a wire of given length rises with the velocity of
                    propagation of sound through it. Now we have learned (§28) that this velocity,
                    in ordinary circumstances, is enormously greater for a wire vibrating
                    longitudinally than for the same wire vibrating transversely. The fundamental
                    note, therefore, is far higher in pitch in the former than in the latter
                    case.</p>
                <p>As, however, the quantity V depends, for longitudinal vibrations, solely on the
                    nature of the medium, the pitch of the fundamental note of a wire rubbed along
                    its length depends—the material being the same, brass for instance— on its
                    length, not at all on its thickness, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>But as regards strings vibrating transversely, such as are met with in our
                    instrumental music, V, as we have seen (§ 27), depends not only on the nature of
                    the substance used, but also on its thickness and tension, and hence the pitch
                    of the fundamental, even with the same length of string, will depend on all
                    those various circumstances.</p>
                <p>61. If we put for V its equivalent expressions before given, we have for the
                    fundamental note of transversely vibrating strings:</p>
                <p>, <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ='⅛ or, <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> =L /2, whence
                    the following inferences may be easily drawn:</p>
                <p>If a string, its tension being kept invariable, have its length altered, the
                    fundamental note will rise in pitch in exact proportion with its diminished
                    length, that is, <hi rend="italic">n</hi> varies then inversely as <hi
                    rend="italic">l.</hi></p>
                <p>Hence, on the violin, by placing a finger successively on any one of the strings
                    at <hi rend="superscript"> 8</hi> /9, <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 5</hi>, <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                    4</hi>, <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 8</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 15</hi>, ½, we shall obtain
                    notes corresponding to numbers of vibrations bearing to the fundamental the
                    ratios to unity of the following, viz., <hi rend="superscript"> 9</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 8</hi>, <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                    4</hi>, <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 15</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>, 2, which notes form,
                    therefore, with the fundamental, the complete scale.</p>
                <p>G2. By <hi rend="italic">tightening</hi> a musical string, its length remaining
                    unchanged, its fundamental is rendered higher. In fact, then, <hi rend="italic"
                    >n</hi> is proportional to the square root of the tension. Thus, by quadrupling
                    the tension, the note is raised an octave. Hence, the use of keys in tuning the
                    violin, the pianoforte, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>63. Equal lengths of strings of the same density and equally stretched, but of
                    different thicknesses, give fundamentals which are higher in pitch in proportion
                    to diminution of thickness (<hi rend="italic">i.e., n</hi> varies inversely as
                    the thickness) Thus, of two strings of same kind of gut, same length and same
                    tension, if one be twice as thick as the other, its fundamental will be an
                    octave lower. Hence, three of the strings of the violin, though all of gut, have
                    different fundamentals, because unequally thick.</p>
                <p>64. Equally long and equally stretched strings or wires of different thickness
                    and different material, have fundamentals higher in pitch the less the weights
                    of the strings; <hi rend="italic">n</hi> here varies inversely as the square
                    root of the weight <hi rend="italic">w</hi> of a given length of the string.</p>
                <p>65. If, in last case, the thicknesses of the strings which are to be compared
                    together are equal, then <hi rend="italic">n</hi> varies inversely as the square
                    root of the density.</p>
                <p>Hence, in the violin and in the pianoforte, the lower notes are obtained from
                    wires formed of denser material. Thus, the fourth string of the violin is formed
                    of gut covered with silver wire.</p>
                <p>66. A highly ingenious and instructive method for illustrating the above laws of
                    musical strings, has been recently contrived by Μ. Melde, and consists simply in
                    attaching to the ventral segment of a vibrating body, such as a tuning-fork or a
                    bell-glass, a silk or cotton thread, the other extremity being either fixed or
                    passing over a pulley and supporting weights by which the thread may be
                    stretched to any degree required. The vibrations of the larger mass are
                    communicated to the thread which, by proper adjustment of its length and
                    tension, vibrates in unison and divides itself into one or more ventral segments
                    easily discernible by a spectator. If the length of the thread be kept
                    invariable, a certain tension will give but one ventral segment; the fundamental
                    note of the thread is then of same pitch as the note of the body to which it is
                    attached. By reducing the tension to ¼ of its previous amount, the number of
                    ventral segments will be seen to be increased to two, indicating that the first
                    harmonic of the thread is now in unison with the solid, and consequently that
                    its fundamental is an octave lower than it was with the former tension; thus
                    confirming the law that <hi rend="italic">n</hi> varies as √P. In like manner,
                    on further lowering the tension to <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 9</hi> three ventral segments will be formed, and so on.</p>
                <p>The law that, <hi rend="italic">coet.</hi><hi rend="italic">par., n</hi> varies
                    inversely as the thickness may be tested by forming a string of four lengths of
                    the single thread used before, and consequently of double the thickness of the
                    latter, when, for the same length and tension, the compound thread will exhibit
                    double the number of ventral segments presented by the single thread.</p>
                <p>The other laws admit of similar illustration.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> VII.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Stiff Rods, Plates,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p>67. If, instead of a string or thin wire, we make use of a rod or narrow plate,
                    sufficiently stiff to resist flexure, we may cause it to vibrate transversely
                    when fixed at one end only. In this case the number of vibrations corresponding
                    to the fundamental note varies as the thickness directly, and as the square of
                    the length inversely. The annexed figures represent the modes of vibration
                    corresponding to the fundamental aud the first two overtones, the rod passing to
                    and fro between the positions AGKC and AHLD. In all cases <hi rend="italic"
                    >A</hi><pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n128/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0128-0113"/> being fixed is necessarily a node, and B being
                    free is the middle of a ventral segment. We have thus a succession of cases in
                    which the rod contains ½, <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi>, <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, &amp;c.
                    ventral segments. The numbers of vibrations per second are as the squares of
                    these, or, as 1: 9: 25: &amp;c. The reason of this is, that (taking the case of
                    fig. 20, 3) the part FB, which may be regarded as an independent rod fixed at
                    the end F, is evidently <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                    5</hi> of the length of AB, and consequently, since <hi rend="italic">nx</hi>
                    has a proper note of 5 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> or 25 times the rapidity
                    of vibration in fig. 20, 1.</p>
                <p>By attaching, with a little bees’ wax, stiff hog’s bristles to one prong of a
                    tuning-fork, or to the edge of a bell-glass, or even a common jar, and clipping
                    them on trial to suitable lengths, we shall find that, on drawing a note in the
                    usual way from the tuning-fork or glass, the bristles will divide into one or
                    more separately vibrating segments, as in the above figs.</p>
                <p>68. The <hi rend="italic">tuning-fork</hi> itself may be regarded as belonging to
                    the class of stiff rods. When emitting its fundamental note, it vibrates, as in
                    fig. 21, with nodes at <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">d</hi> and
                    extreme positions <hi rend="italic">abcde</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >fbgdh.</hi></p>
                <p>69. The transversal vibrations of thin square, circular, and other plates of
                    metal or glass, are interesting, because, if these are kept in a horizontal
                    position, light dry sand or powder sifted over the upper surface, will be thrown
                    off the ventral segments to the nodal lines, which will thus be rendered
                    manifest to the eye, forming what are termed <hi rend="italic">Chladni’s
                    figures.</hi> As in the case of a musical string, so here we find that the pitch
                    of the note is higher for a given plate the greater the number of ventral
                    segments into which it is divided; but the converse of this does not hold good,
                    two different notes being obtainable with the same number of such segments, the
                    position of the nodal lines being, however, different.</p>
                <p>70. The upper line of annexed figures shows how the sand arranges itself in three
                    cases, when the plates are square. The lower line gives the same in a sort of
                    <hi rend="italic">idealised</hi> form, and as usually to be found in acoustical
                    works. Fig. 22, 1 corresponds to the lowest possible note of the particular
                    plate used; Fig. 22, 2 to the <hi rend="italic">fifth</hi> higher; Fig. 22, 3 to
                    the <hi rend="italic">tenth</hi> or octave of the <hi rend="italic">third,</hi>
                    the numbers of vibration in the same time being as 2 to 3 to 5.</p>
                <p>If the plate be small, it is sufficient, in order to bring out the simpler
                    sand-figures, to hold the plate firmly between two fingers of the same hand
                    placed at any point where at least two nodal lines meet, for instance the centre
                    in (1) and (2), and to draw a violin bow downwards across the edge near the
                    middle of a ventral segment. But with larger plates, which alone will furnish
                    the more complicated figures, a clamp-screw must be used for fixing the plate,
                    and, at the same time, one or more other nodal points ought to be touched with
                    the fingers while the bow is being applied. In this way, any of the possible
                    configurations may be easily produced.</p>
                <p>71. By similar methods, a circular plate may be made to exhibit nodal lines
                    dividing the surface by diametral lines into four or a greater, but always <hi
                    rend="italic">even,</hi> number of sectors, an odd number being incompatible
                    with the general law of stationary waves that the parts of a body adjoining a
                    nodal line on either side must always vibrate oppositely to each other.</p>
                <p>Another class of figures consists of circular nodal lines along with diametral
                    (fig. 23).</p>
                <p>Circular nodal lines unaccompanied by intersecting lines cannot be produced in
                    the manner described; but may be got either by drilling a small hole through the
                    centre, and drawing a horse-hair along its edge to bring out the note, or by
                    attaching a long thin elastic rod to the centre of the plate, at right angles to
                    it, holding the rod by the middle and rubbing it lengthwise with a bit of cloth
                    powdered with resin, till the rod gives a distinct note; the vibrations are
                    communicated to the plate, which consequently vibrates transversely, and causes
                    the sand to heap itself into one or more concentric rings.</p>
                <p>72. The theory of the vibrations of plates has not yet been put on a quite
                    satisfactory basis. The following law may, however, be regarded as confirmed by
                    experiment, viz., that when two different plates of the same substance present
                    the same nodal configuration, the numbers of vibrations are to each other
                    directly as the thicknesses, and inversely as the superficial areas.</p>
                <p>73. Paper, parchment, or any other thin membrane stretched over a square,
                    circular, &amp;c., frame, when in the vicinity of a sufficiently powerful
                    vibrating body, will, through the medium of the air, be itself made to vibrate
                    in unison, and, by using sand, as in previous instances, the nodal lines will be
                    depicted to the eye, and seen to vary in form, number, and position with the
                    tension of the plate and the pitch of the originating sound. The membrana
                    tympani or drum of the ear has, in like manner and on the same principles, the
                    property of repeating the vibrations of the external air which it communicates
                    to the internal parts of the ear.</p>
                <p>74. Rods vibrating longitudinally are, as we have already remarked, subject to
                    the laws of stationary waves. If, for instance, a wooden rod fixed at one end,
                    be rubbed near the top between the finger and thumb previously coated with
                    powdered resin, it will yield a fundamental note when it so vibrates as to have
                    only <hi rend="italic">one</hi> node (at the fixed extremity) and half a ventral
                    segment reaching from that extremity to the other, that is, when the length <hi
                    rend="italic">l</hi> of the V</p>
                <p>rod is ¼ λ, or λ = 4 <hi rend="italic">l</hi> and therefore <hi rend="italic">n
                    =</hi> V/4 <hi rend="italic">l</hi> But it may also give overtones corresponding
                    to 2, 3, &amp;c. nodes, the free end being always the middle of a ventral
                    segment, and for which therefore the lengths of waves are 4 <hi rend="italic"
                    >l</hi> /3, 4 <hi rend="italic">l</hi> /5.</p>
                <p>&amp;c. (as will be easily seen by referring to figs. in § 67, which may equally
                    represent transversal and longitudinal displacements). Hence, the fundamental
                    and harmonics of a rod such as we are now considering, have vibrations whose
                    rates are as the successive odd numbers.</p>
                <p>A series of like rods, each fixed at one end into a block of wood, and of lengths
                    bearing to each other, the ratios 1: <hi rend="superscript"> 8</hi> / <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 9</hi>: &amp;c. (as in § 61), will give the common scale when
                    rubbed in the manner already mentioned. This follows from the fundamental having
                    <hi rend="italic">n =</hi> V/4 <hi rend="italic">l,</hi> and therefore <hi
                    rend="italic">nx ∞</hi> 1/ <hi rend="italic">l.</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n129/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0129-0114"/>
                <p>Glass rods or tubes may also be made to vibrate longitudinally by means of a
                    moist piece of cloth; but it is advisable to clamp them firmly at the centre,
                    when each half will vibrate according to the same laws as the wooden rods above.
                    The existence of a motion of the particles of glass to and fro in the direction
                    of its length may be well exhibited, by allowing a small ball of stone or metal
                    suspended by a string to rest against one extremity of the rod, when, as soon as
                    the latter is made to sing by friction, the ball will be thrown off with
                    considerable violence.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> VIII.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Theory of Pipes.</hi></p>
                <p>75. The <hi rend="italic">longitudinal</hi> vibrations of air enclosed in pipes
                    are of greater practical importance than those of other bodies, because made
                    available to a very great extent for musical purposes. In the flute, horn,
                    trumpet, and other wind instruments, it is the contained air that forms the
                    essential medium for the production of sound, the wood or metal enclosing it
                    having no other effect but to modify the <hi rend="italic">timbre</hi> or
                    acoustic colour of the note.</p>
                <p>76. In dealing with the theory of pipes, we must treat the air precisely in the
                    same manner as we have dealt with elastic rods vibrating lengthwise, a pipe
                    stopped at both ends being regarded as equivalent to a rod fixed at both ends, a
                    pipe open at both ends to a rod free at both ends, and a pipe stopped at one end
                    and open at the other to a rod fixed at one end and free at the other. When
                    therefore the air within the pipe is anywhere displaced along the length of the
                    pipe, two waves travel thence in opposite directions, and being reflected at the
                    extremities of the pipe, there results a stationary wave with one or more fixed
                    nodal sections, on one side of which the air is at any moment being displaced in
                    one direction, while on the other side it is displaced in the opposite. Hence,
                    when the air on both sides of the node is moving in towards it, there is
                    condensation going on at the node, followed by rarefaction on the reversal of
                    the motion of the air. The full lines in annexed figs. are curves of <hi
                    rend="italic">displacements,</hi> the dotted lines curves of <hi rend="italic"
                    >velocity</hi> and <hi rend="italic">density (vid.</hi> § 10 and 14).</p>
                <p>As a stopped end prevents any motion of the air, a nodal section is always found
                    there. And as, at the open end, we may conceive the internal air to be
                    maintained at the same density as the external air, we may assume that such end
                    coincides with the middle of a ventral segment.</p>
                <p>From these assumptions, which form the basis of Bernouilli’s Theory of Pipes, we
                    infer:</p>
                <p>77. That in a pipe stopped at both ends, as in a rod fixed at both ends, the
                    fundamental note (fig. 25,1), corresponds to λ = 2 <hi rend="italic">l</hi>,</p>
                <p>V</p>
                <p>and therefore to <hi rend="italic">n =</hi> V/2 <hi rend="italic">l</hi>, V
                    denoting the velocity of sound in air, and the overtones to numbers of
                    vibrations = 2 <hi rend="italic">n</hi>, 3 <hi rend="italic">n</hi>, and so on.
                    Fig. 25, 2, represents the octave.</p>
                <p>78. That in a pipe open at both ends the same holds good as in the previous case.
                    For (fig. 26, 1) AC = ¼ λ , ∙. λ = 4 AC = 2 <hi rend="italic">l</hi>, and in
                    fig. 26, 2, AD = ¼ λ, and also = £ Z . ·. λ = <hi rend="italic">l</hi>, or ½ its
                    value for the fundamental; and similarly for the other harmonics.</p>
                <p>79. That in a pipe open at one end and stopped at the other (or, as it is usually
                    termed, a <hi rend="italic">stopped</hi> pipe, case § 77, being purely
                    imaginary), the fundamental note has <hi rend="italic">n =</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >V</hi></p>
                <p>V/4 <hi rend="italic">l</hi>, and the overtones corres-</p>
                <p>4i pond to <hi rend="italic">3n, 5n. . . .</hi></p>
                <p>For, in fig. 27, 1, AB or <hi rend="italic">l</hi> = ¼ λ, and in fig. 27, 2, CB
                    or ¼ λ is evidently = ⅓ AB or ⅓ <hi rend="italic">l</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi>
                    whence λ = <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">l,</hi> which being ⅓ of value of λ in previous case, shows that
                    the number of vibrations is three times greater. Similarly for the other
                    overtones.</p>
                <p>80. It follows from the above, that a given pipe (whether open or stopped) may be
                    made to emit, in addition to or in combination with its fundamental, a series of
                    overtones, which, in an open pipe, follow the natural numbers, and hence are the
                    octave, twelfth, &amp;c., but, in a <hi rend="italic">stopped pipe,</hi> follow
                    the <hi rend="italic">odd</hi> numbers, so as to want the octave and other notes
                    represented by the even numbers. The succession of overtones may be practically
                    obtained by properly regulating the force of the blast of air by which the
                    air-column is put into vibration.</p>
                <p>81. If the fundamental notes of two pipes of equal lengths, but of which one is
                    open, the other stopped, be compared together, they will be found to differ in
                    pitch by an octave, the stopped being the lower. This fact is in keeping with
                    the theory, for the numbers of vibrations being respectively V/2 <hi
                    rend="italic">l</hi> and V/4 <hi rend="italic">l</hi>, are in the ratio of 2 to
                    1.</p>
                <p>82. By altering the length of the same pipe, we can vary the pitch of the
                    fundamental at pleasure, since <hi rend="italic">n</hi> varies inversely as <hi
                    rend="italic">l.</hi> This is effected in the flute and some other wind
                    instruments by means of openings along part of the pipe, which, being closed or
                    opened by means of keys and of the fingers, increase or diminish the length of
                    the vibrating air-column. In this manner the successive notes of the scale are
                    usually obtained within the range of an octave. The scale is further extended by
                    bringing into play the higher harmonics.</p>
                <p>83. Since in an open pipe <hi rend="italic">n = V/2l,</hi> and therefore <hi
                    rend="italic">l = — ,</hi> if for V we put 1090 ft., and for <hi rend="italic"
                    >n</hi> 264, which is the number of vibrations per second usually assigned to
                    the note C, we get l <hi rend="italic">=</hi> 2 ft. very nearly. This,
                    accordingly, is the length of the so-called C open pipe. The C stopped pipe
                    must, by what has been stated above, be 4 feet in length.</p>
                <p>84. Conversely it is obvious that the velocity V of sound in air, and generally
                    in any gas, may be deduced from the equation V = 2 <hi rend="italic">nl,</hi>
                    and that if two pipes of equal length contain respectively air and any other
                    gas, the velocities in the two media being to each other directly as the number
                    of vibrations of the notes they respectively emit, we may, from the
                    well-ascertained value of the velocity in air, determine in this way the
                    velocities in other gases, and thence the values of their coefficients γ <hi
                    rend="italic">(vid.</hi> § 21).</p>
                <p>85. While the inferences drawn by means of Bernouilli’s theory agree, to a
                    certain extent, with actual observation, there are discrepancies between the two
                    which point to the existence of some flaw in one or both of the hypotheses on
                    which the theory rests. In truth, the conditions assumed by Bernouilli are such
                    as do not fully occur in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n130/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0130-0115"/> practice. The stopped extremity of a pipe is
                    always to some extent of a yielding nature, and does not therefore exactly
                    coincide with a nodal surface; nor can the internal air immediately adjoining
                    the open end be perfectly free from variation of density during the vibrations
                    of the whole mass, particularly so at the <hi rend="italic">embouchure,</hi>
                    where the blast is introduced by which the tone is originated. It would appear
                    from recent experiments that the pitch of a pipe is somewhat lower than the
                    above theory would indicate.</p>
                <p>86. The reed-pipe differs in many respects from the simple pipe which we have
                    been considering. A small elastic strip of metal, fixed at one extremity (the
                    <hi rend="italic">reed)</hi> lies over a slit of the same shape, and is set in
                    transverse vibration by a current of air acting underneath. If, as is the case
                    in the accordion and harmonium, the reed is unprovided with a pipe, the pitch of
                    its note is regulated altogether by the dimensions of the reed, in conformity
                    with the law of tranversely vibrating plates; although, it is to be remarked,
                    the note is really due to the vibrations of the air which alternately escapes
                    through the slit of the reed, and is prevented doing so exactly as often as the
                    reed executes a movement to and fro. The proper note of the reed itself is very
                    poor and faint.</p>
                <p>87. In the reed-pipe there is added above the reed a pipe the air in which
                    partakes of the vibratory motion, and improves the quality of the sound. The
                    pitch is, however, not affected by this pipe, unless it exceed a certain length
                    Z, when the pitch begins to fall, and continues to do so as <hi rend="italic"
                    >l</hi> is increased, till, when the length of pipe is 2Z, the note is again
                    restored to its original pitch, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>88. Μ. Weber, to whom we are indebted for these and other curious facts
                    respecting reed pipes, has explained them thus:—If the reed be exactly at that
                    part of the vibrating air-column where the air-displacements are at their
                    maximum, and where consequently the air suffers no variation of density during
                    the vibratory motion of the column, the oscillations of the reed are not at all
                    affected by the air-vibrations, and consequently the pitch of the reed-pipe is
                    the same as that of the reed itself. But if the reed be situated at any other
                    part of the air-column, and especially at a nodal section, where the air is
                    undergoing alternate condensation and rarefaction, then, when the airblast from
                    the wind chest pushes in the reed, the air in the pipe is in the act of
                    rarefaction, and consequently tends to accelerate the reed inwards, whereas the
                    elasticity of the reed tends in an opposite direction. When, again, the reed is
                    passing to the other extreme of its vibration, the air in the pipe is in the act
                    of condensation, and tends to accelerate the reed outwards or in the opposite
                    direction to the elasticity of the reed. Hence the reed is affected just as if
                    its elasticity, and therefore the rapidity of its vibrations, were diminished,
                    and thus the pitch is lowered.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> IX.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Singing Flames.</hi></p>
                <p>89. The <hi rend="italic">chemical</hi> or <hi rend="italic">gas harmonicon,</hi>
                    which consists of a small flame of hydrogen or of coal gas, burning at the lower
                    part of the interior of a glass tube, and giving out a very distinct note,
                    exhibits considerable analogy with the reed-pipe. For, as Sondhaus seems to have
                    established, the primary cause of the note lies in the oscillations of the gas
                    within the burner and the feeding-pipe, which therefore play exactly the same
                    part as does the reed portion of the reed-pipe. The air in the glass tube being
                    heated by the flame ascends, and the pressure above the flame being thence
                    diminished, the flame is forced upwards by the gas beneath, until an influx of
                    atmospheric air at the top of the tube forces the flame back. Thus a periodic
                    agitation of the flame ensues, accompanied by a corresponding disturbance of the
                    air-column in the glass tube. The size of the flame and its position within the
                    tube must be so regulated as to bring out the best possible note, which will
                    then be found to be the same as the air in the tube would itself emit, according
                    to the laws of pipes, allowance being made for the high temperature of the air.
                    A series of tubes may thus be arranged of suitable lengths to give the common
                    scale. It sometimes happens, particularly with short tubes, that the note will
                    not come out spontaneously, all that is required, then, is either by blowing
                    gently at the top of the tube, or by singing in unison with the <hi
                    rend="italic">expected</hi> note, to give to the air the requisite initial
                    movement.</p>
                <p>The flame, which burns steadily with a yellowish light before the tube sounds,
                    will, as soon as the note is heard, be seen to flicker up and down, changing
                    rapidly from yellow to blue and blue to yellow, its intensity also changing
                    periodically. These fluctuations are best seen by viewing the image of the flame
                    reflected by a small plane mirror, held in the hand and moved to and fro. Before
                    the note is heard, the image of the then quiescent flame, being impressed on
                    different points of the retina, appears as a continuous luminous strip; but,
                    when the harmonicon speaks, the various images become quite detached from one
                    another, showing that the portion of the retina over which the reflected light
                    passes is sensibly affected only at certain points of it, which evidently
                    correspond to the instants of time at which the flame, in its periodical
                    fluctuations, is at its brightest.</p>
                <p>90. Naked flames, that is, flames unaccompanied by tubes, may also give out
                    musical notes, and many singular instances are mentioned by Tyndall and others
                    of their sensitiveness to external sounds.</p>
                <p>91. Koenig of Paris has constructed an apparatus intended to indicate the modes
                    of vibration of the different parts of vibrating bodies, such as columns of air,
                    &amp;c., by means of flames, and to which he has given the name of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Flame Manometer.</hi> We will here describe its application to the
                    case of organ-pipes. An open pipe has three apertures along one side, one at the
                    middle, <hi rend="italic">o</hi> (fig. 28), <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> at a
                    node of the fundamental tone, and the two others, <hi rend="italic">a, b,</hi>
                    half way between <hi rend="italic">o</hi> and the extremities of the pipe, and
                    coinciding therefore with the nodes of the first overtone or octave. These
                    openings are closed by thin flexible membranes forming the ends of small boxes
                    or <hi rend="italic">capsules,</hi> the spaces within which communicate by
                    caoutchouc tubes with a coal-gas reservoir, and also by separate tubes with
                    small gas burners arranged on a vertical stand. The gas being introduced, and
                    the three flames kindled and adjusted to equal heights of about ¾of an inch; if
                    the pipe be made now to utter its first overtone, the flame connected with <hi
                    rend="italic">o</hi> will remain stationary and of the same brightness as
                    before, but those communicating with <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi> will become longer and thinner, and assume a bluish and
                    faint luminosity. But, if the fundamental be brought out of the pipe, then it is
                    <hi rend="italic">o’s</hi> flame that is violently affected, while those of <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> are scarcely affected at all.
                    If the flames be originally made less in height (say ⅓ inch), those of <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> in the former case, and of <hi
                    rend="italic">o</hi> in the latter, will be extinguished. These results are due
                    to the condensations and rarefactions of the air in the pipe which are at their
                    maximum at a node, causing the membrane placed there to vibrate outwards and
                    inwards, and hence to force more or less of the gas into the burner.</p>
                <p>In order to compare together the notes of different pipes, four plane reflecting
                    surfaces are connected together in the form of a cube, which is mounted on a
                    vertical axis about which it is capable of being turned round. Each pipe ia <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n131/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0131-0116"/> furnished with one opening, a membrane, &amp;c.
                    (as above), at its middle. As pointed out (§ 87), if any of the pipes be made to
                    sound, the reflector being at the same time put in motion, a series of separate
                    images will be seen. On sounding another pipe, whose fundamental is an octave
                    higher, we shall have a second line of images separated from each other by half
                    the interval of those in the former series. This is best observed when the two
                    flames are placed in the same vertical line. If the note of the second pipe is a
                    fifth higher than the first, and consequently its vibrations to those of the
                    first as 3 to 2, then the same space which contains two images of the lower note
                    will contain three of the higher, and so on, for other combinations. When more
                    complicated ratios are to be tested, it is preferable to connect both capsules
                    with the same burner, either with or without the reflector.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> X.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Communication of Vibrations.</hi></p>
                <p>92. The communication of sonorous vibrations from one body to another plays so
                    essential a part in acoustics that a few words must here be given to the
                    subject. It appears to be well established that while the vibrations of a solid
                    are in general most readily communicated to other solids in contact with it,
                    they are not so to liquids, and still less so to air and other aeriform fluids.
                    Thus, a tuning-fork is inaudible at any moderate distance unless applied to a
                    table, by whose extended surface the air can be more intensely affected. So
                    likewise a musical string sounds very poorly unless connected with a resonant
                    cavity or wooden chest, to the wood of which it first imparts its vibratory
                    motion, which then produces stationary waves in the continued air.</p>
                <p>93. A few years ago Μ. Kundt made known a method founded on the communicability
                    of vibration, by which the velocities of sound in different media may be
                    compared together with great facility. Take a glass tube 3 feet or upwards in
                    length, drop into it a small quantity of the fine powder of the club-moss or
                    lycopodium, and turn the tube round so as to spread the powder over the internal
                    surface of the tube. Stop both ends of the tube with corks, clamp it at its
                    centre, and rub one of its halves lengthwise with a moist cloth, so as to cause
                    the glass to sound a note. It will then be found that, the air within the tube
                    taking up the motion, and a stationary wave being formed in it, the powder is
                    driven off from the ventral segments and forms little heaps at the nodes. The
                    dust-heaps are, by the laws of stationary waves, separated therefore from each
                    other by intervals each equal to half the length of an air-wave, or λ/2. If,
                    then, the number of heaps = <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> and the length of the tube
                    = <hi rend="italic">l</hi>: λ = 2 <hi rend="italic">l/m</hi>.</p>
                <p>But, by the laws of longitudinal vibrations of rods, the length λ' of the
                    glass-wave = 4(<hi rend="italic">l/2)= 2l.</hi> Hence <hi rend="italic">=</hi>
                    λ'/λ <hi rend="italic">,</hi> that is, the number of dust-heaps is equal to the
                    ratio of the lengths of a wave of sound in glass and in air, and consequently to
                    the ratio of the velocities of sound in those media. (For the vibrations being
                    in unison, their number in a given time must be the same for the glass and the
                    V/λ'= V/λ'; V, V' being the velocities).</p>
                <p>Kundt found 16 to be the number of heaps; prior experiments of a different kind
                    had, as we have before mentioned, given this as the number of times that the
                    velocity of sound in glass exceeds its velocity in air.</p>
                <p>Instead of producing the air-vibrations by friction of the tube containing the
                    air, it is preferable to make use of a smaller tube or rod, furnished with a
                    cork at one end, which fits like a piston into the tube, and projecting at its
                    outer end through an opening in the cork which closes the airtube. The rod thus
                    inserted is the one which is rubbed longitudinally and communicates its
                    vibrations to the air in the enclosing tube. By means of an apparatus of this
                    kind, Kundt determined the ratio to the velocity of sound in air of its velocity
                    in various solids, and also (replacing the air in the tube by different gases)
                    of its velocity in these gases.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> XI.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Interference of Sound.</hi></p>
                <p>94. When two or more sonorous waves travel through the same medium, each particle
                    of the air being simultaneously affected by the disturbances due to the
                    different waves, moves in a different manner than it would if only acted on by
                    each wave singly. The waves are said mutually to interfere. We shall exemplify
                    this subject by considering the case of two waves travelling in the same
                    direction through the air. We shall then obviously be led to the following
                    results :—</p>
                <p>95. If the two waves are of equal length λ, and are in the same phase (that is,
                    each producing at any given moment the same state of motion in the
                    air-particles), their combined effect is equivalent to that of a wave of the
                    same length λ, but by which the excursions of the particles are increased, being
                    the sum of those due to the two component waves respectively.</p>
                <p>If the two interfering waves, being still of same length λ, be in opposite
                    phases, or so that one is in advance of the other by -, and consequently one
                    produces in the air the opposite state of motion to the other, then the
                    resultant wave is one of the same length λ, but by which the excursions of the
                    particles are decreased, being the difference between those due to the component
                    waves. If the amplitudes of vibration which thus mutually interfere are moreover
                    equal, the effect is the total mutual destruction of the vibratory motion.</p>
                <p>Thus we learn that two musical notes, of the same pitch, conveyed to the ear
                    through the air, will produce the effect of a single note of the same pitch, but
                    of increased loudness, if they are in the same phase, but affect the ear very
                    slightly, if at all, when in opposite phases. If the difference of phase be
                    varied gradually from zero to ½λ, the resulting sound will gradually decrease
                    from a maximum to a minimum.</p>
                <p>96. Among the many experimental confirmations which may be adduced of these
                    proportions, we will mention the following:—</p>
                <p>Take a circular plate, such as is available for the production of Chladni’s
                    figures (§ 71), and cut out of a sheet of pasteboard a piece of the shape ABOCD
                    (fig. 30), consisting of two circular quadrants of the same diameter as the
                    plate. Let, now, the plate be made in the usual manner to vibrate so as to
                    exhibit two nodal lines coinciding with two rectangular diameters. If the ear be
                    placed right above the centre of the plate, the sound will be scarcely audible.
                    But, if the pasteboard be interposed so as to intercept the vibrating segments
                    AOB, DOC, the note becomes much more distinct. The reason.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n132/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0132-0117"/>
                <p>of this is, that the segments of the plate AOD, BOC always vibrate in the same
                    direction, but oppositely to the segments AOB, DOC. Hence, when the pasteboard
                    is in its place, there are two waves of same phase starting from the two former
                    segments, and reaching the ear after equal distances of transmission through the
                    air, are again in the same phase, and produce on the car a conjunct impression.
                    But when the pasteboard is removed, then there is at the ear opposition of phase
                    between the first and the second pair of waves, and consequently a minimum of
                    sound.</p>
                <p>97. A tubular piece of wood shaped as in fig. 31, and having a piece of thin
                    membrane stretched over the opening at the top C, some dry sand being strewn
                    over the membrane, is so placed over a circular or rectangular vibrating plate,
                    that the ends A, B lie over the segments of the plate, such as AOD, COB in the
                    previous fig., which are in the same state of motion. The sand at C will be set
                    in violent movement. But if the same ends A, B, be placed over oppositely
                    vibrating segments (such as AOD, COD), the sand will be scarcely, if at all,
                    affected.</p>
                <p>98. If a tuning-fork in vibration be turned round before the ear, four positions
                    will be found in which it will be inaudible, owing to the mutual interference of
                    the oppositely vibrating prongs of the fork. On interposing the hand between the
                    ear and either prong of the fork when in one of those positions, the sound
                    becomes audible, because then one of the two interfering waves is cut off from
                    the ear. This experiment may be varied by holding the fork over a glass jar into
                    which water is poured to such a depth that the air-column within reinforces the
                    note of the fork when suitably placed and then turning the fork round.</p>
                <p>99. Helmholtz’s double syren (§ 51) is well calculated for the investigation of
                    the laws of interference of sound. For this purpose a simple mechanism is found
                    in the instrument, by means of which the fixed upper plate can be turned round
                    and placed in any position relatively to the lower one. If, now, the apparatus
                    be so set that the notes from the upper and lower chest are in unison, the upper
                    fixed plate may be placed in four positions, such as to cause the air-current to
                    be cut off in the one chest at the exact instant when it is freely passing
                    through the other, and <hi rend="italic">vice versa.</hi> The two waves,
                    therefore, being in opposite phases, neutralise one another, and the result is a
                    faint sound. On turning round the upper chest into any intermediate position,
                    the intensity of the sound will increase up to a maximum, which occurs when the
                    air in both chests is being admitted and cut off contemporaneously.</p>
                <p>100. If two pipes, in exact unison, and furnished with flame manometers, are in
                    communication with the same wind-chest, and the two flames be placed in the same
                    vertical line, on introducing the current from the bellows, we shall find that
                    the two lines of reflected images will be so related that each image in one lies
                    between two images in the other. This shows that the air-vibrations in one pipe
                    are always in an opposite phase to the other, or that condensation is taking
                    place in the one when rarefaction occurs in the other. This arises from the
                    current from the bellows passing alternately into the one and the other pipe.
                    There will also be a remarkable collapse of the sound when both pipes
                    communicate with the wind-chest compared with that produced from one pipe
                    alone.</p>
                <p>101. If the two interfering waves are such as produce vibrations whose numbers
                    per second are <hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >n'</hi> respectively, these being to each other in the ratio of two integers
                    <hi rend="italic">m</hi>, <hi rend="italic">m'</hi> when expressed in its lowest
                    terms, then the lengths of the waves λ, λ' being inversely as <hi rend="italic"
                    >n</hi> to n', will be to each other as <hi rend="italic">m'</hi>: <hi
                    rend="italic">m</hi>, and consequently <hi rend="italic">m</hi> λ = = <hi
                    rend="italic">m</hi> ' λ'. Particles therefore of the air separated by this
                    distance from each other will be in the same phase, that is, the length of the
                    <hi rend="italic">resultant</hi> wave will be <hi rend="italic">m</hi> λ or <hi
                    rend="italic">m' λ',</hi> and if N denote the corresponding number of vibrations
                    N = <hi rend="italic">n/m</hi> or <hi rend="italic">n'/m</hi> '.</p>
                <p>Thus, for the fundamental and its octave <hi rend="italic">n/n'</hi> = ½, and
                    therefore N = <hi rend="italic">n</hi> or <hi rend="italic">n</hi> /2 that is,
                    the note of interference is of the same pitch as the fundamental.</p>
                <p>For the fundamental and its major third, <hi rend="italic">n/n</hi> '= <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 4</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi>. Hence</p>
                <p>N = <hi rend="italic">n</hi> /4 or <hi rend="italic">n</hi> '/5, that is, the
                    resulting sound is two octaves lower than the fundametal.</p>
                <p>For the fundamental and its major sixth, <hi rend="italic">n/n</hi> ' = ⅗; N
                    therefore = or and the resulting sound is a twelfth below the lower of the two
                    interfering notes.</p>
                <p>If <hi rend="italic">m</hi> and <hi rend="italic">m'</hi> differ by 1, then N =
                    <hi rend="italic">n-n</hi> '; for <hi rend="italic">m-m'</hi> or 1 = <hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi> /N — <hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>
                    /N. Hence, if the ratio of the vibrations of two interfering sounds is
                    expressible in its lowest terms by numbers whose difference is unity, the
                    resulting note has a number of vibrations simply equal to the difference of
                    those of the interfering notes.</p>
                <p>The results stated in this section may be tested on a harmonium. Thus, if the
                    notes B, C, at the extreme right of the instrument be struck together, there
                    will be heard an interference note four octaves lower in pitch than the above C,
                    because the interval in question being a semitone, is 16/15, and, consequently,
                    by last case, the interference note is lower than the C by interval 1/16.</p>
                <p>Other notes may be heard resulting from the mutual interference of the
                    overtones.</p>
                <p>102. When two notes are not quite in tune, the resulting sound is found to
                    alternate between a maximum and minimum of loudness recurring periodically. To
                    these periodical alternations has been given the name of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Beats.</hi> Their origin is easily explicable. Suppose the two notes to
                    correspond to 200 and 203 vibrations per second; at some instant of time, the
                    air-particles, through which the waves are passing, will be similarly displaced
                    by both, and consequently the joint effect will be a sound of some intensity.
                    But, after this, the first or less rapidly vibrating note will fall behind the
                    other, and cause a diminution in the joint displacements of the particles, till,
                    after the lapse of ⅙ of a second, it will have fallen behind the other by ½ a
                    vibration. At this moment, therefore, opposite displacements will be produced of
                    the air-particles by the two notes, and the sound due to them will be at a
                    minimum. This will be followed by an increase of intensity until the lapse of
                    another sixth of a second, when the less rapidly vibrating note will have lost
                    another half-vibration relatively to the other, or one vibration reckoning from
                    the original period of time, and the two component vibrations will again
                    conspire and reproduce a maximum effect. Thus, an interval of ⅓ of a second
                    elapses between two successive maxima or beats, and there are produced three
                    beats per second. By similar reasoning it may be shown that the number of beats
                    per second is always equal to the difference between the numbers of vibrations
                    in the same time corresponding to the two interfering notes. The more,
                    therefore, these are out of tune, the more rapidly will the beats follow each
                    other.</p>
                <p>Beats are also heard, though less distinctly, when other concords such as <hi
                    rend="italic">thirds, fifths,</hi> &amp;c., are not perfectly in tune: thus, 200
                    vibrations aud 303 vibrations per second, which form, in combination, an
                    imperfect fifth, produce beats occurring at the rate of three per second.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n133/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0133-0118"/>
                <p>103. The phenomena of beats may be easily observed with two organ-pipes put
                    slightly out of tune by placing the hand near the open end of one of them, with
                    two musical strings on a resonant chest, or with two tuningforks of same pitch
                    held over a resonant cavity (such as a glass jar, <hi rend="italic">vid.</hi> §
                    97), one of the forks being put out of tune by loading one prong with a small
                    lump of bees’-wax. In the last instance, if the forks are fixed on one solid
                    piece of wood which can be grasped with the hand, the beats will be actually
                    felt by the hand. If one prong of each fork be furnished with a small plain
                    mirror, and a beam of light from a luminous point be reflected successively by
                    the two mirrors, so as to form an image on a distant screen, when one fork alone
                    is put in vibration, the image will move on the screen and be seen as a line of
                    a certain length. If both forks are in vibration, and are perfectly in tune,
                    this line may either be increased or diminished permanently in length, according
                    to the difference of phase between the two sets of vibrations. But if the forks
                    be not quite in tune, then the length of the image will be found to fluctuate
                    between a maximum and a minimum, thus making the beats sensible to the eye. The
                    vibrograph (§ 52, 53) is also well suited for the same purpose, and so in an
                    especial manner is Helmholtz’ double syren (§ 51), in which, by continually
                    turning round the upper box, a note is produced by it more or less out of tune
                    with the note formed by the lower chest, according as the handle is moved more
                    or less rapidly, and most audible beats ensue. The gas harmonica and the flame
                    manometer also afford excellent illustrations of the laws of beats.</p>
                <p>104. Advantage has been taken of these laws for the purpose of determining the
                    absolute number of vibrations per second corresponding to any given note in
                    music, whence may be derived the number for all the other notes (§ 45). The
                    human ear may be regarded as most correctly appreciating two notes differing by
                    an octave. Two tuningforks then are taken, giving respectively the note A and
                    its lower octave, and a number of other forks are prepared intermediate in pitch
                    to these, say 54, and by means of bees’-wax these are so tuned, that the first
                    gives four beats with the A fork, the second four beats with the fourth, and so
                    on up to the last, which also gives four beats with the A- <hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi> fork. Now, if n = the unknown number of vibrations for the note A, <hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi>- 4, <hi rend="italic">n</hi>- 8 . . . <hi rend="italic"
                    >n</hi>- 55 × 4, will be the numbers for all the successive forks down to the A
                    <hi rend="subscript"> -1</hi> fork, <hi rend="italic">n</hi> — 55 × 4</p>
                <p>which being an octave below A, we have = ⅜and consequently <hi rend="italic">n
                    =</hi> 440.</p>
                <p>105. Beats also afford an excellent practical guide in the tuning of instruments,
                    but more so for the higher notes of the register, inasmuch as the same number of
                    beats, that is, the same difference between the numbers of vibrations, for two
                    notes of high pitch, indicates greater deviation from perfect unison, than it
                    does for two notes of low pitch. Thus, two low notes of 32 and 30 vibrations
                    respectively, whose interval is therefore 32/30 or 16/15 <hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e</hi>., a semitone, give two beats per second, while the same number of
                    beats are given by notes of 32 × 16 (four octaves higher than the first of the
                    preceding) or 512 and 514 vibrations, which are only slightly out of tune.</p>
                <p>106. As the interval between two notes, and consequently the number of beats
                    increases, the effect on the ear becomes more and more unpleasant, and
                    degenerates at last into an irritating rattle. With the middle notes of the
                    musical register, this result occurs when the number of beats comes up to 20 or
                    30 per second, the musical interval between the two interfering notes being then
                    between half and a whole tone. Helmholtz attributes the disagreeable impression
                    of beats on the ear. to the same physiological cause to which is due the painful
                    effect on the eye of a faint flickering light, as, for instance, the light
                    streaming through a wooden paling with intervening openings when the individual
                    affected is passing alongside. In this case, the retina, which, when
                    continuously receiving the same amount of light, thereby loses its sensitiveness
                    in a great degree, is unable to do so.</p>
                <p>It is, however, remarked by the above-mentioned author that the same number of
                    beats, which has so irritating an effect when due to two notes in the middle of
                    the register, is not attended by the same result when due to notes of much lower
                    pitch. Thus, the notes C, D forming a tone give together 33 beats per second,
                    while a note two octaves lower than C also gives 33 beats with its fifth; yet
                    the former combination forms a discord, the latter a most pleasing concord.</p>
                <p>107. When the number of beats reaches to 132 or upwards per second, the result is
                    a continuous and not unpleasing impression on the ear, and it was formerly held
                    that the effect was always equivalent to that of a note having that number of
                    vibrations. Helmholtz has shown that this opinion is inaccurate, except when the
                    interfering tones are very loud, and consequently accompanied by very
                    considerable displacements of the particles of the vibrating medium. These
                    resultant tones being, as to their vibration-number, equal to the difference
                    between the numbers corresponding to the two primaries, are termed <hi
                    rend="italic">difference-tones,</hi> and may be best observed with the double
                    syren. The same author was led also, on theoretical grounds, to surmise the
                    formation of <hi rend="italic">summation-tones</hi> by the interference of two
                    loud primaries, the number of resultant vibrations being then equal to the sum
                    of the numbers for the two components, and appealed for experimental proof to
                    his syren. But, at the last meeting of the British Association (1872), Koenig,
                    the celebrated Parisian acoustician, maintained that the notes of the syren,
                    thus held to be summation-tones, were in reality the <hi rend="italic"
                    >differencetones</hi> of the harmonics.</p>
                <p>108. By reference to the laws of the interference of vibrations, Helmholtz has
                    been enabled to offer a highly satisfactory explanation of the cause whence
                    arises difference of quality or timbre or acoustic colour between different
                    sounds. He has shown conclusively that there are but few sounds which are of a
                    perfectly simple character, that is, in which the fundamental is not accompanied
                    by one or more overtones. Now, when a note is simple, there can be no jarring on
                    the ear, because there is no room for interference of sound. Hence, the softness
                    of the tuningfork when its fundamental is reinforced by a resonant cavity, and
                    also of the flute. The same character of softness belongs also to those
                    instruments in which the powerful harmonics are limited to the vibration ratios
                    2, 3 . . . 6 (§ 57, 80); because the mutual interference of the fundamental and
                    their harmonics give rise to concords only. The piano, the open organ pipe, the
                    violin, and the softer tones of the human voice, are of this class. But if the
                    <hi rend="italic">odd</hi> harmonics alone are present, as in the narrow stopped
                    organ pipe, and in the clarionet, then the sound is poor, and even nasal; and if
                    the higher harmonics beyond the sixth or seventh are very marked, the result is
                    very harsh (as in reed-pipes).</p>
                <p>109. The <hi rend="italic">human voice</hi> (for a description of the organ in
                    which it originates, we refer to Art. <hi rend="italic">Physiology— Voice and
                    Speech) is</hi> regarded by the best authorities as being analogous to a
                    reed-pipe, the vocal chords forming the reed, and the cavity of the mouth the
                    pipe, and, like the reed, is rich in harmonics, as many as sixteen having been
                    detected in a bass voice. But their number and relative intensities differ much
                    in different individuals, or even in the same person at different times; and it
                    is on this variety that, agreeably to Helmholtz<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n134/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0134-0119"/>’s theory of timbre, the peculiarities depend by
                    which any one voice may be unmistakably distinguished from every other. Voices
                    in which overtones abound are sharp, and even rough; those in which they are few
                    or faint, are soft and sweet. In every voice, however, the number and relative
                    intensity of the overtones depend on the form assumed by the cavity of the
                    mouth, which acts relatively to the vocal chords precisely as a <hi
                    rend="italic">resonator</hi> does to a tuning-fork, or a pipe to a reed. This
                    may be easily tested by holding a tuning-fork before the open mouth, when, by
                    giving to the cavity a suitable form, the fundamental or some overtone of the
                    fork may be heard distinctly reverberated from the interior of the mouth. Each
                    vowel sound, as Helmholtz has shown, is simply the result of the reinforcements
                    by the air in the cavity of the mouth, and its prolongation towards the larynx,
                    of one or in some cases two overtones of determinate pitch, contained in the
                    sound which proceeds from the vocal chords. Koenig assigns the following notes
                    as characteristic of the simpler vowel sounds (adopting the foreign
                    pronunciation) :—To U, the note B♭ below the line in the G clef, corresponding
                    to 225 vibrations per second; to O, the next higher octave, consequently of
                    double the number of vibrations, and thence ascending by octaves for A, E, and
                    I, the last of which is therefore characterised by a note of 3600 vibrations per
                    second.</p>
                <p>The above theory of vowel sounds may be satisfactorily confirmed by means of
                    tuning-forks, vibrating in front of resonant cavities, which can, by suitable
                    combination, be made to utter any vowel sound.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Works on Acoustics.</hi></p>
                <p>Chladni, <hi rend="italic">Traité</hi><hi rend="italic">d’</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Acoustique.</hi> Paris, 1809.</p>
                <p>Herschel, Sir John. <hi rend="italic">Encycl. Metrop.,</hi> art. “Sound.” London,
                    1830.</p>
                <p>Tyndall, <hi rend="italic">Lectures on Sound,</hi> 2d edit. London, 1869.
                    Helmholtz, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Lehre von der
                    Tonempfindungen,</hi> 3d edit.</p>
                <p>Braunschweig, 1870, of which there is a French translation, and an English one is
                    promised.</p>
                <p>Besides the above, some account of the subject is to be found in such general
                    works on Physics as Ganot’s, 14th edit., Paris, 1870, of which a translation is
                    published by Longmans, London; Deschanel’s <hi rend="italic">Natural
                    Philosophy,</hi> translated by Prof. Everett, London, 1873; Jamin, <hi
                    rend="italic">Cours ds Physique,</hi> 3d edit., Paris, 1871; Wülner, <hi
                    rend="italic">Physik,</hi> 2d edit., Leipzig, 1870. <hi rend="smallcaps">(d.
                    t.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
