<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0791-0748-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">AMPÈRE, André-Marie</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 748</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1004188">Lyceums</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:833325">Biscuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1144565">Teaching</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3p025">Currents</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4086360j">Biscuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vs6z">Teaching</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3p063">Lyceums</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n791/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AMPÈRE, <hi rend="smallcaps">André-Marie</hi></label>, the
                    founder of the science of electro-dynamics, was born at Lyons in January 1775.
                    He took a passionate delight in the pursuit of knowledge from his very infancy,
                    and is reported to have worked out lengthy arithmetical sums by means of pebbles
                    and biscuit-crumbs before he knew the figures. His father began to teach him
                    Latin, but left this off on discovering the boy’s greater inclination and
                    aptitude for mathematical studies. The young Ampère, however, soon resumed his
                    Latin lessons, to enable him to master the works of Euler and Bernouilli. In
                    later life he was accustomed to say that he knew as much about mathematics when
                    he was eighteen as ever he knew; but his reading embraced nearly the whole round
                    of knowledge,—history, travels, poetry, philosophy, and the natural sciences. At
                    this age he had read the whole of the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie,</hi> and
                    with such interest and attention that he could repeat passages from it fifty
                    years after. When Lyons was taken by the army of the Convention in 1793, the
                    father of Ampère, who, holding the office of <hi rend="italic">juge</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">paix,</hi> had stood out resolutely
                    against the previous révolu·</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n792/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0792-0749"/>
                <p>tionary excesses, was at once thrown into prison, and soon after perished on the
                    scaffold. This event produced such an impression on the susceptible mind of
                    Ampère, that he continued for more than a year in a state little removed from
                    idiocy. But Rousseau’s letters on botany falling into his hands, the subject
                    engrossed him, and roused him from his apathy. His passion for knowledge
                    returned. From botany he turned to the study of the classic poets, and to the
                    writing of verses himself. About this time (1796) an attachment sprang up, the
                    progress of which he naively recorded in a journal <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Amorum</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi> In 1799 he was happily married to the
                    object of his attachment. From about 1796 Ampère gave private lessons at Lyons
                    in mathematics, chemistry, and languages; and in 1801 he removed to Bourg, as
                    professor of physics and chemistry, leaving his ailing wife and infant son at
                    Lyons. His wife died in 1804. After two years’ absence he returned to Lyons, on
                    his appointment as professor of mathematics at the Lyceum. His small treatise,
                    <hi rend="italic">Considérations sur la Théorie Mathématique du Jeu</hi> (Lyons,
                    1802), in which he successfully solved a problem that had occupied Buffon,
                    Pascal, and others, and demonstrated that the chances of play are decidedly
                    against the habitual gambler, attracted considerable attention. It was this work
                    that brought him under the notice of Μ. Delambre, whose recommendation obtained
                    for him the Lyons appointment, and afterwards (1805) a subordinate position in
                    the Polytechnic School at Paris, where he was elected professor of analysis in
                    1809. Here he continued to prosecute his scientific researches and his
                    multifarious studies with unabated diligence. He was admitted a member of the
                    Institute in 1814. It is on the service that he rendered to science in
                    establishing the relations between electricity and magnetism, and in developing
                    the science of electro-magnetism, or, as he called it, electrodynamics, that
                    Ampère’s fame mainly rests. On the 11th of September 1820 he heard of the
                    discovery of Professor Oersted of Copenhagen, that a magnetic needle may be
                    deflected by a voltaic current. On the 18th of the same month he presented a
                    paper to the Academy, containing a far more complete exposition of the
                    phenomenon, which he had in the interval investigated by experiment, and showing
                    that magnetic defects can be produced, without magnets, by aid of electricity
                    alone. In particular he showed that two wires connecting the opposite poles of a
                    battery attract or repel each other according as the currents pass in the same
                    or in opposite directions. According to the theory of magnetism which Ampère’s
                    subsequent investigations led him to adopt, every molecule of magnetic matter is
                    acted on by a closed electric current, and magnetisation takes place in
                    proportion as the direction of these currents approaches parallelism. The whole
                    field thus opened up he explored with characteristic industry and care. He
                    anticipated the invention of the electric telegraph, having suggested in 1821 an
                    apparatus of the kind with a separate wire for each letter. Late in life he
                    prepared a remarkable work on the classification of the sciences, which was
                    published after his death. In addition to this and one or two works of less
                    importance, he wrote a great number of memoirs and papers that appeared in
                    scientific journals. He died at Marseilles in June 1836. The great amiability
                    and child-like simplicity of Ampère’s character are well brought out in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Journal</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Correspondence,</hi> published by Madame Chevreux (Paris, 1872).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
