<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0301-0280-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">AGENT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 280</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:936105">Functionals</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:936106">Functions</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1201065">Publications</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1083449">Publicity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b42z12p20">Agents</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cn3t">Functions</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n301/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AGENT</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Diplomacy, Commerce,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Jurisprudence,</hi> is a name applied generally to any
                    person who acts for another. It has probably been adopted from France, as its
                    function in modern civil law was otherwise expressed in Roman jurisprudence.
                    Ducange (s.v. <hi rend="italic">Agentes)</hi> tells us that in the later Roman
                    empire the officers who collected the grain in the provinces for the troops and
                    the household, and afterwards extended their functions so as to include those of
                    government postmasters or spies, came to be called <hi rend="italic"
                    >agentes</hi><hi rend="italic">in rebus,</hi> their earlier name having been <hi
                    rend="italic">frumentarii.</hi></p>
                <p>In <hi rend="italic">Diplomacy,</hi> a class of semi-ambassadors termed agents
                    have been employed generally between states of unequal power. The small
                    community might send an agent to propitiate some powerful government, and secure
                    its protection. A great power would, on the other hand, distribute its agents
                    among the petty states which it kept in clientage, to see that no counteracting
                    influence was at work among them. In this shape our Indian government keep
                    agencies in the protected and other neighbouring states. Similarly, though this
                    class does not fall within the scope of public international law, the
                    self-governing British colonies now employ agents to attend to their interests
                    and represent them in the mother country. The status of diplomatic agents, not
                    of the classes of ambassadors, envoys, ministers, or <hi rend="italic">charges
                    d’affaires,</hi> is extremely ill-defined and uncertain. (Phillimore’s <hi
                    rend="italic">International Law,</hi> ii. 246; Heffter <hi rend="italic"
                    >Europäisches Völkerrecht,</hi> § 222.) See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ambassador;
                    Diplomacy.</hi></p>
                <p>The law of <hi rend="smallcaps">Principal and Agent</hi> has its origin in the
                    law of mandate among the Romans, and fortunately even in England the spirit of
                    that system of jurisprudence pervades this branch of the law. The law of agency
                    is thus almost alike throughout the whole British empire, and a branch of the
                    British commercial code, in which it is of great importance that different
                    nations should understand each other’s system, differs only slightly from the
                    law of the rest of Europe.</p>
                <p>In a general view of the law of agency it is necessary to have regard to the
                    rights and duties of the principal, the agent, and the public. The agent should
                    not do what he has no authority for; yet if he be seen to have authority, those
                    with whom he deals should not be injured by secret and unusual conditions. The
                    employer is bound by what his agent does in his name, but the public are not
                    entitled to take advantage of obligations which are known to be unauthorised and
                    unusual. The agent is entitled to demand performance by the principal of the
                    obligations undertaken by him within the bounds of his commission, but he is not
                    entitled to pledge him with a recklessness which he would certainly avoid in the
                    management of his own affairs. It is in the regulation of these powers and
                    corresponding checks in such a manner that the legal principle shall apply to
                    daily practice, that the niceties of this branch of the law consist.</p>
                <p>Agents are of different kinds, according to their stipu lated r consuetudinary
                    powers. The main restraint in the possible powers of an agent is in the old
                    maxim, <hi rend="italic">delegatus non potest delegare,</hi> designed to check
                    the complexity that might be created by inquiries into repeatedly-deputed
                    responsibility. The agent cannot delegate his commission or put another in his
                    place; but in practice this principle is sometimes modified, for it so may arise
                    from the nature of his office that he is to employ other persons for the
                    accomplishment of certain objects. Thus, there is nothing to prevent a
                    commercial agent from sending a portion of the goods entrusted by him to his own
                    agent for disposai</p>
                <p>In the general case agency is constituted by the acceptance of the mandate or
                    authority to act for the principal, and the evidence of this may be either
                    verbal or in writing. The English statute of frauds requires an agent to have
                    authority in writing for the purposes of its 1st, 2d, and 3d clauses relating to
                    leases. “And it is a general rule, that an agent who has to execute a deed, or
                    to take or give livery or seisin, must be appointed by deed for that purpose.
                    Moreover, as a corporation aggregate can in general act only by deed, its agent
                    must be so appointed, though it would seem that some trifling agencies, even for
                    corporations, may be appointed without one.” (Smith’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mercantile Law,</hi> B. I. chap. iv.) It is a general rule that those
                    obligations which can only be undertaken by solemn formalities cannot be entered
                    on by a delegate who has not received his authority in writing. But it is often
                    constituted, at the same time that its extent is defined, by mere appointment to
                    some known and recognised function—as where one is appointed agent for a banking
                    establishment, factor for a merchant, broker, supercargo, traveller, or
                    attorney. In these cases, usage defines the powers granted to the agent; and the
                    employer will not readily be subjected to obligations going beyond the usual
                    functions of the office; nor will the public dealing with the agent be bound by
                    private instructions inconsistent with its usual character. While, however, the
                    public, ignorant of such secret limitations, are not bound to respect them, the
                    agent himself is liable for the consequences of transgressing them. Agency may
                    also be either created or enlarged by <hi rend="italic">implication.</hi> What
                    the agent has done with his principal’s consent the public are justified in
                    believing him authorised to continue doing. Thus, as a familiar instance, the
                    servant who has continued to purchase goods for his master at a particular shop
                    on credit is presumed to retain authority and trust, and pledges his master’s
                    credit in farther purchases, though he should, without the knowledge of the
                    shopkeeper, apply the articles to his own uses. The law is ever jealous in
                    admitting as accessories of a general appointment to any particular agency the
                    power to borrow money in the principal’s name, to give his name to bill
                    transactions, and to pledge him to guaranties; but all these acts may be
                    authorised by implication, or by being the continuation of a series of
                    transactions, of the same kind and in the same line of business, to which the
                    principal has given his sanction. Thus an employer may, by the previous sanction
                    of such operations, be liable for the bills or notes drawn, indorsed, and
                    accepted by his clerk or other mandatary; nay, may be responsible for the
                    obligations thus incurred after the mandatary’s dismissal, if the party dealing
                    with him knew that he was countenanced in such transactions, and had no reason
                    to suppose that he was dismissed. In questions of this kind the distinction
                    between a general and a special agent is important. A general agent is employed
                    to transact all his principal’s business of a particular kind, at a certain
                    place,—as a factor to buy and sell; a broker to negotiate contracts of a
                    particular kind; an attorney to transact his legal business; a shipmaster to do
                    all things relating to the employment of a ship. Such an agent’s power to do
                    everything usual in the line of business in which he is employed is not limited
                    by any private restriction or order unknown to the party with whom he is
                    dealing. On the contrary, it is incumbent on the party dealing with a particular
                    agent, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> one specially employed in a single
                    transaction, to ascertain the extent of his authority. The law applicable to a
                    mercantile agent’s power to pledge or otherwise dispose of the goods entrusted
                    to him <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n302/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0302-0281"/> being in an unsatisfactory state, a statutory
                    remedy was applied to it by an Act of 1825 (6 Geo. IV. c. 94), which required
                    amendment in 1842 (5 and 6 Vict. c. 39).</p>
                <p>The general object of these measures, which appear to extend to Scotland, is to
                    make transactions with an agent in possession of goods as safe as dealing with
                    the owner, to all who treat with him, as purchasers or otherwise, in good faith,
                    and in ignorance of his want of ownership. Thus, when an agent ships goods in
                    his own name, the consignee is entitled to a lien on them for any advances to
                    the agent, or liabilities on bills or notes, if he has not notice by the bill of
                    lading or otherwise at or before the time of the advance or receipt that such
                    person is not the actual and <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> owner. The
                    presumption in such cases is ownership; and the burden of disproving it, as well
                    as of showing that the consignee was aware of the mere agency, falls on the
                    person questioning the validity. By the statutes, the person entrusted with and
                    in possession of a bill of lading, dock warrant, warehouse-keeper’s certificate,
                    wharfinger’s certificate, or other delivery warrant, is held the owner of the
                    goods it represents, so as to render valid any transaction for their sale or
                    disposition of the goods, or the deposit or pledge thereof, or of any part
                    thereof, to parties ignorant of the limited ownership. Besides their effect in
                    rendering valid, in this more comprehensive manner, operations conducted under
                    the appearance and supposition of absolute ownership, the acts have separate
                    provisions for the security of those who deal with agents, knowing them to be
                    such. The acts, however, must be studied in their very words, which are not
                    remarkable for clearness. The following brief description of their general
                    effect, taken from Chitty’s <hi rend="italic">Collection of Statutes,</hi> may
                    be useful:—“First, where goods or documents for the delivery of goods are
                    pledged as a security for present or future advances, with the knowledge that
                    they are not the property of the factor, but without notice that he is acting
                    without authority, in such a case the pledgee acquires an absolute lien.
                    Secondly, where goods are pledged by a factor without notice to the pledgee that
                    they are the property of another, as a security for a pre-existing debt, in that
                    case the pledgee acquires the same right as the factor had. Thirdly, where a
                    contract to pledge is made in consideration of the delivery of other goods or
                    documents of title, upon which the person delivering them up had a lien for a
                    previous advance (which is deemed to be a contract for a present advance), in
                    that case the pledgee acquires an absolute lien to the extent of the value of
                    the goods given up.” The statutes are applicable only to proper mercantile
                    transactions, and not, for example, to advances upon the security of furniture
                    in a furnished house to the apparent owner. (See Smith’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Leading Cases,</hi> vol. i. p. 759 <hi rend="italic">sqq.,</hi> 6th ed.)</p>
                <p>The obligations of the principal are—to pay the agent’s remuneration, or, as it
                    is often called, <hi rend="italic">commission,</hi> the amount of which is fixed
                    by contract or the usage of trade; to pay all advances made by the agent in the
                    regular course of his employment; and to honour the obligations lawfully
                    undertaken for him. The agent is responsible for the possession of the proper
                    skill and means for carrying out the functions which he undertakes. He must
                    devote to the interests of his employer such care and attention as a man of
                    ordinary prudence bestows on his own—a duty capable of no more certain
                    definition, the application of it as a fixed rule being the function of a jury.
                    He is bound to observe the strictest good faith; and in some instances the law
                    interposes to remove him from temptation to sacrifice his employer’s interests
                    to his own: thus, when he is employed to buy, he must not be the seller; and
                    when employed to sell, he must not be the purchaser. He ought only to deal with
                    persons in good credit, but he is not responsible for their absolute solvency
                    unless he guarantee them. A mercantile agent guaranteeing the payments he treats
                    for is said to hold a <hi rend="italic">del credere</hi> commission.</p>
                <p>In Scotland the procurators or solicitors who act in the preparation of cases in
                    the various law-courts, and all who take out the attorney licence, are called
                    agents. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Attorney.</hi></p>
                <p>In France, the <hi rend="italic">Agents de Change</hi> were formerly the class
                    generally licensed for conducting all negotiations, as they were termed, whether
                    in commerce or the money market. Of late the term has been practically limited
                    to those who conduct, like our stockbrokers, transactions in public stock; and
                    it is understood that it is rather as speculators than as agents that the
                    majority of them adopt the profession. The laws and regulations as to <hi
                    rend="italic">courtiers,</hi> or those whose functions were more distinctly
                    confined to transactions in merchandise, have been mixed up with those
                    applicable to <hi rend="italic">agents de change.</hi> Down to the year 1572
                    both functions were free; but at that period, partly for financial reasons, a
                    system of licensing was adopted at the suggestion of the Chancellor l’Hôpital.
                    Among the other revolutionary measures of the year 1791, the professions of
                    agent and <hi rend="italic">courtier</hi> were again opened to the public. Many
                    of the financial convulsions of the ensuing years, which were due to more
                    serious causes, were attributed to this indiscriminate removal of restrictions,
                    and they were reimposed in 1801. From that period regulations have been made
                    from time to time as to the qualifications of agents, the security to be found
                    by them, and the like. They are now regarded as public officers, appointed, with
                    certain privileges and duties, by the government, to act as intermediaries in
                    negotiating transfers of public funds and commercial stocks, and for dealing in
                    metallic currency.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
