<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0108-0093-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ACHAIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 93</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:795626">Achaeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n108/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ACHAIA</label>. in <hi rend="italic">Ancient Geography,</hi>
                    a name differently applied at different periods. In the earliest times the name
                    was borne by a small district in the south of Thessaly, and was the first
                    residence of the Achaeans. At a later period <hi rend="italic">Achaia
                    Propria</hi> was a narrow tract of country in the north of the Peloponnesus,
                    running 65 miles along the Gulf of Corinth, and bounded by the Ionian Sea on the
                    W., by Elis and Arcadia on the S., and by Sicyonia on the E. On the south it is
                    separated from Arcadia by lofty mountains, but the plains between the mountains
                    and the sea are very fertile. Its chief town was Patrae. The name of Achaia was
                    afterwards employed to denote collectively the states that joined the Achaean
                    League. When Greece was subdued by the Romans, <hi rend="italic">Achaia</hi> was
                    the name given to the most southerly of the provinces into which they divided
                    the country, and included the <hi rend="italic">Peloponnesus,</hi> the greater
                    part of Greece Proper, and the islands.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Achaeans</hi><hi rend="italic">and the</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Achaean</hi><hi rend="italic">League.—</hi> The early inhabitants of Achaia
                    were called <hi rend="italic">Achaeans.</hi> The name was given also in those
                    times to some of the tribes occupying the eastern portions of the Peloponnesus,
                    particularly <hi rend="italic">Argos</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sparta.</hi>
                    Afterwards the inhabitants of Achaia Propria appropriated the name. This
                    republic was not considerable, in early times, as regards either the number of
                    its troops, its wealth, or the extent of its territory, but was famed for its
                    heroic virtues. The Crotonians and Sybarites, to re-establish order in their
                    towns, adopted the laws and customs of the Achaeans. After the famous battle of
                    Leuctra, a difference arose betwixt the Lacedaemonians and Thebant, who held the
                    virtue of this people in such veneration, thai they terminated the dispute by
                    their decision. The government of the Achaeans was democratical. They preserved
                    their liberty till the time of Philip and Alexander; but in the reign of these
                    princes, and afterwards, they were either subjected to the Macedonians, who had
                    made themselves masters of Greece, or oppressed by domestic tyrants. The Achaean
                    commonwealth consisted of twelve inconsiderable towns in Peloponnesus. About 280
                    years before Christ the republic of the Achaeans recovered its old institutions
                    and unanimity. This was the renewal of the ancient confederation, which
                    subsequently became so famous under the name of the <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Achaean</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">League</hi> —having for its object, not as
                    formerly a common worship, but a substantial political union. Though dating from
                    the year <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> 280, its importance<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n109/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0109-0094"/> may be referred to its connection with Aratus of
                    Sicyon, about 30 years later, as it was further augmented by the splendid
                    abilities of Philopoemen. Thus did this people, so celebrated in the heroic age,
                    once more emerge from comparative obscurity, and become the greatest among the
                    states of Greece in the last days of its national independence. The inhabitants
                    of Patrae and of Dyme were the first assertors of ancient liberty. The tyrants
                    were banished, and the towns again made one commonwealth. A public council was
                    then held, in which affairs of importance were discussed and determined; and a
                    register was provided for recording the transactions of the council. This
                    assembly had two presidents, who were nominated alternately by the different
                    towns. But instead of two presidents, they soon elected but one. Many
                    neighbouring towns, which admired the constitution of this republic, founded on
                    equality, liberty, the love of justice, and of the public good, were
                    incorporated with the Achaeans, and admitted to the full enjoyment of their laws
                    and privileges. The Achaean League affords the most perfect example in antiquity
                    of the federal form of government; and, allowing for difference of time and
                    place, its resemblance to that of the United States government is very
                    remarkable. (See Arts. <hi rend="smallcaps">Amphictyony</hi> and <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Federal Government;</hi> also Freeman’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Federal Government,</hi> 2 vols. 8vo. 1863, and <hi rend="italic">Comparative
                    Politics,</hi> Svo. 1873; Droysen, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Hellenismus,</hi> 2 vols.; Helwing, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">des Achaiischen Bundes.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
