<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0901-0543-0506-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALFRED, or Aelfred (9th edition, volume 1, page
                    506)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:887617">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015496">Meetings</term>
                    <term ref="fast:847566">Caring</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n543/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALFRED, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Aelfred</hi></label>, <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">the Great,</hi> the youngest son of Aethelwulf, king of the
                    West Saxons, was bom at Wantage in Berkshire in 849 A.D. At an early age he was
                    summoned to the assistance of his brother Aethelred against the Danes. These
                    formidable enemies, whose object hitherto had been mere plunder, were now aiming
                    at a permanent settlement in the country, and after ravaging and subduing
                    Northumbria, East Anglia, and the greater part of Mercia, they fell with their
                    united forces on Wessex itself. A series of encounters took place, in which
                    Alfred greatly distinguished himself, especially at Ashdown, where the Danes
                    were routed with great slaughter, and left several of their most famous leaders
                    dead on the field of battle. Aethelred dying in the midst of the straggle,
                    Alfred was unanimously elected king (871), in the twenty-second year of his age.
                    About a month after his accession he met the enemy at Wilton, where, after a
                    long and doubtful straggle, he was defeated. Both parties were now becoming
                    tired of the war. Immense loss had been suffered on both sides, and although the
                    Danes on the whole had been victorious, their victories had brought them no
                    substantial results. A treaty of peace was concluded, and the Danes withdrew to
                    London.</p>
                <p>On the cessation of hostilities, Alfred was enabled to turn his attention to
                    naval affairs. The sea was swarming with pirates, and their descents on the
                    coast kept the country in a state of perpetual alarm. To cope with them
                    successfully Alfred resolved to meet them on their own element, and a naval
                    victory which he gained over seven Danish rovers in 875 is the first on record
                    won by Englishmen. In the following year the peace of 871 was broken. An army of
                    Danes from East Anglia, under their king, Guthrum, sailing along the south
                    coast, landed in Wessex, seized upon Wareham, and afterwards upon Exeter, then
                    the centre of a disaffected Celtic population, and it was not till 877 that the
                    country was once more free from the invader.</p>
                <p>The year 878 was the most eventful in the course of Alfred’s reign. At
                    mid-winter, without any warning, the Danes came pouring into Wessex from the
                    north, seized Chippenham, and making it the centre of their operations, quickly
                    overran the country. Many of the inhabitants, in despair, fled into foreign
                    lands, and Alfred, totally unprepared to meet the storm, retired to the marshes
                    of Somerset. Never at any other period, either before or after, were his
                    fortunes so low, and the national existence itself was at stake. Had Alfred,
                    like his kinsman Burhed of Mercia, left his people in their hour of need, the
                    heathen Dane in all probability would have acted like the heathen Englishmen
                    before him—a new race would have possessed the land, and the names of England
                    and Englishmen would have disappeared from the page of history. Alfred’s
                    misfortunes only roused him to fresh exertions, and his military skill and
                    valour enabled him to carry his people in safety through this momentous crisis.
                    Fortifying himself at Athelney about Easter, he secretly matured his plans for
                    meeting the enemy, and seven weeks after, having collected his forces at Brixton
                    near Selwood, he rapidly advanced in a north-easterly direction, and was close
                    upon the Danes before they had any intelligence of his approach. A fierce
                    conflict ensued at Ethandun, now Edington, in which the Danes were entirely
                    defeated; and about fourteen days after this they were compelled to sue for
                    peace. By the treaty of Wedmore, Watling Street (the old road running across the
                    island from London to Chester and the Irish Channel) was to be the boundary
                    between Alfred and the Danes, the latter were to be vassals to the kings of
                    Wessex, and their chiefs to receive baptism. This treaty was observed by the
                    Danes with much greater fidelity than those of an earlier date had been. Guthrum
                    their king and about thirty of their chiefs were baptised at Wedmore, and
                    Alfred, who stood sponsor for Guthrum, gave him the name of Aethelstan. The
                    Danish army after this slowly withdrew, and eventually settled down peaceably in
                    East Anglia. The acceptance of Christianity by their chiefs seems indeed to have
                    broken for a time the fierce crusading energy which gave a special animus to the
                    piratical expeditions of the heathen Danes.</p>
                <p>As soon as peace had been concluded Alfred turned his attention to the internal
                    affairs of his kingdom. He vigorously set to work to put the country in a
                    complete state of defence. Old fortifications were repaired and nev <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n544/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0901-0544-0507"/> ones raised in suitable localities. The fleet
                    was brought into a state of greater efficiency, and it was Alfred indeed that
                    laid the foundation of England’s naval greatness. He cleared the land of the
                    bands of robbers that infested it, and took care that justice was impartially
                    administered to all his subjects, severely punishing any wilful perversion of it
                    on the part of the judges. In his code of laws, which is a compilation from
                    those of his predecessors, he wisely abstained from introducing much of his own,
                    giving as his reason that he was afraid it might not be accepted by posterity.
                    He greatly encouraged commerce, and took a lively interest in geographical
                    discovery. We have from his pen a minute account of two voyages of Ohthere,
                    especially of the one round the North Cape into the White Sea, and also of a
                    voyage of Wulfstan to the Baltic. And it is to Alfred that we are indebted for
                    the best account that has reached us of the Germany of the 9th century.</p>
                <p>Alfred’s devotion to learning, and his exertions in the cause of education are
                    among the most remarkable features of his reign. So deep was the popular
                    ignorance when Alfred ascended the throne that, according to his own testimony,
                    hardly any one south of the Thames could understand the ritual of the church or
                    translate a Latin letter. It was one of the strongest and most cherished of his
                    purposes that this state of matters should be entirely changed, and that every
                    free-born English youth who had the means should qualify himself to read English
                    correctly. In order to accomplish this, he rebuilt the monasteries which had
                    been cast down in the late wars, and which were the great centres of education
                    in those days, invited learned men from all quarters to his court, and by their
                    assistance completed a number of works for the diffusion of knowledge throughout
                    his dominions. These were not original compositions but free translations of
                    Latin authors that were held in much esteem at the time, and the fact that
                    Orosius and Bede are two of the works he selected, shows the high value he set
                    upon an acquaintance with history and geography. A copy of his version of
                    Gregory’s <hi rend="italic">Pastoral Care</hi> was sent to every diocese for the
                    benefit of the clergy. It is in the preface to that work that Alfred gives his
                    touching account of the decay of learning, and expresses his desire for its
                    revival. But the work which seems to have had the greatest attraction for him
                    was <hi rend="italic">The Consolations of Philosophy</hi> by Boethius. In his
                    translation of this work Alfred gives us more of his own original composition,
                    and a deeper insight into his thoughts and feelings, than in any other of his
                    works. His Manual or Handbook, which is known to have been in existence in the
                    12th century, is lost, and this is the more to be regretted since, besides the
                    extracts from Latin authors which it contained, it is believed that he had
                    inserted in it not a few compositions of his own.</p>
                <p>In occupations such as these fifteen years of comparative tranquillity, disturbed
                    now and then by troubles with the Danes, passed away. A fresh swarm from abroad
                    had landed in Kent in 885 and besieged Rochester, but on the king’s approach
                    they raised the siege and returned to their ships. The next eight years were
                    years of uninterrupted peace; but the Danes, suffering a severe defeat at the
                    hands of Arnulf, king of the East Franks, sailed for England in two divisions in
                    893. One of these divisions was under the command of the terrible Hastings.
                    Their arrival was a signal to the Danes of Northumbria and East Anglia, who rose
                    in great numbers to aid their kinsmen. Alfred, however, was better prepared to
                    meet the danger than he had formerly been. His towns were so strong that the
                    Danes seem studiously to have avoided them. A body of the enemy was routed by
                    Alfred at Farnham in Surrey. Another great host, moving to the west in the line
                    of the Thames, was followed by three of Alfred’s aldermen to Buttington in
                    Montgomeryshire and completely defeated. Those who escaped made their way to
                    Essex. Leaving their wives and children there, and receiving considerable
                    additions to their numbers, they crossed the country once more and established
                    themselves within the fortifications of the old Roman town of Chester, which was
                    then uninhabited. There they remained for the winter, when, provisions failing
                    them, they removed to Wales, and with the harvest of plunder they gathered there
                    they retreated into Essex by way of the friendly districts of Northumbria and
                    East Anglia. So rapid had their movements been that Alfred’s army was unable to
                    keep up with them. The same year (895), before winter set in, the Danes sailed
                    up the Thames into the Lea, and selecting an advantageous position on the banks
                    of the latter stream, constructed a fortress about 20 miles above London. As
                    this proved a considerable annoyance to the citizens, they attacked it the
                    following summer, but were repulsed with great loss. During harvest the king was
                    obliged to encamp in the neighbourhood of the city to protect the reapers while
                    gathering in their crops. He afterwards raised two forts on each side of the
                    Lea, and so effectually blocked up the passage of the river that the enemy
                    abandoned their vessels and proceeded to Bridgenorth on the Severn. In the
                    summer of 897 the great Danish host broke up, and part of them returned to the
                    continent. The rest dispersed through Northumbria and East Anglia, and for some
                    time gave Alfred no little trouble by their piratical excursions. By means of
                    vessels formed after a model of his own, of unusual length and speed, he
                    succeeded at last in curbing his Danish foes, but not till after a desperate
                    encounter with them on the south coast, in which the advantage was not all on
                    his side. The war was, as usual, accompanied by pestilence, and great numbers
                    perished, many being persons of the highest rank in the state. The rest of
                    Alfred’s reign, about which we know almost nothing, seems to have been passed in
                    peace. He died in the year 901, at the age of fifty-two, and was buried at
                    Winchester.</p>
                <p>The memory of Alfred has ever been gratefully cherished by his countrymen. There
                    never perhaps was a monarch so highly esteemed; and traditional stories of the
                    most fascinating description cluster around his name, in which he appears almost
                    to as much advantage as in real history. Institutions that existed long before
                    his time, but whose origin it is impossible to trace, have erroneously been
                    attributed to him; and in the times of Norman oppression, when the people were
                    groaning under the burden of slavery, they fondly called to mind the “Darling of
                    the English,” to whom they ascribed all those rights and privileges which they
                    so highly valued, and of which they had been unjustly deprived. Time but adds to
                    Alfred’s praises. With one consent our historians agree in characterising him as
                    the wisest, best, and greatest king that ever reigned in England.</p>
                <p>The following is a list of Alfred’s works :—</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Manual</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Handbook,</hi> of which no
                    copy is known to exist. 2. <hi rend="italic">Laws</hi> (see Wilkin’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Leges Anglo-</hi><hi rend="italic">Saxonicae,</hi> 1721, and
                    Thorpe’s <hi rend="italic">Ancient Laws and Institutes of England,</hi> London,
                    1840). Translations into Old English (Anglo-Saxon) of the following :—3. Bede’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History,</hi> edited by Wheloc, Cambridge,
                    1643-4, and by Smith, Cambridge, 1722. 4. <hi rend="italic">The Universal
                        History of</hi><hi rend="italic">Orosius,</hi> edited by Thorpe, London,
                    1857. 5. <hi rend="italic">The Consolations of Philosophy,</hi> by Boethius,
                    edited by Fox, London, 1864. 6. Gregory’s <hi rend="italic">Pastoral</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Care,</hi> edited by Sweet for the Early English Text Society,
                    London, 1871-2.</p>
                <p>For further information about Alfred see Pauli’s <hi rend="italic">Life of
                        Alfred</hi> and Freeman’s <hi rend="italic">Old English History</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">History of the Norman Conquest.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
