<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0630-0593-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALMERIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 593</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205660">Nevada</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1215269">Gibraltar</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:848634">Catalans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:994553">Lead</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1118724">Silk</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1122068">Soap</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kb2c">Lead</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39453">Silk</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n630/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALMERIA</label>, a modern province of Spain, comprehending
                    the eastern portion of the ancient kingdom of Granada. It is bounded on the N.
                    by Jaen and Murcia, on the E. and S. by Murcia and the Mediterranean, and on the
                    W. by Granada; with an area of about 3300 square miles. The province is
                    traversed by mountain ridges, some of them of considerable elevation, with
                    corresponding valleys and plains of great fertility. The principal sierras are
                    those of Maria, Almahilla, Cabrera, Almagrera, Gata, and Gador, and in the W.
                    some offshoots of the Sierra Nevada. The most considerable rivers are the
                    Almanzora, running from west to east, with a course of about 50 miles; the
                    Almeria, flowing from north-west to south-east; and the Adra from north to
                    south, watering the fertile district between the Sierra de Gador and the
                    Alpujarras. On the S. coast is the Gulf of Almeria, a spacious bay, 25 miles
                    wide at the entrance, and about 10 miles in depth. The climate of the province
                    is mild, except in the interior, where the winter is cold. On the coast rain
                    seldom falls, and south-west winds prevail. The inhabitants are principally
                    engaged in mining and agriculture. Many of the proprietors farm their own land,
                    the number of landed properties being 44,858, while the tenants are only 7365.
                    Of the area of the province, 376,698 acres are arable and pasture land; 13,538
                    acres vineyards; 5360 acres olive plantations; 39,797 acres cultivated mountain
                    and wood lands; and 1,686,738 acres uncultivated. There are 438,357 head of live
                    stock. All kinds of grain are raised in abundance. The common fruits are
                    plentiful, as well as oranges, lemons, and vines. Much excellent silk is
                    produced in the western districts; cotton is raised to some extent along the
                    coast, and the sugar-cane is also cultivated. Cattle are extensively bred; those
                    of the valley of the Almeria are especially remarkable for their size and
                    beauty. The province is one of the richest in minerals of all Spain, the
                    mountains yielding silver, mercury, lead, antimony, copper, and iron. The silver
                    mines of the Sierra de Almagrera, opened in 1839, produced in 1843 nearly
                    1,700,000 ounces; while the lead mines of the Sierra de Gador are computed to
                    have yielded, from 1795 to 1841 inclusive, 11,000,000 quintals of lead, and the
                    present annual output is from 30,000 to 40,000 tons of ore. In the Sierra de
                    Gata, jaspers and agates are found; in the Sierra Nevada, to the west, are the
                    celebrated quarries of Macael marble; and the Sierra Cabrera yields antimony,
                    malachite, gypsum, magnetic iron, &amp;c. The manufactures of the province
                    consist chiefly of esparto cordage, white-lead, shot, saltpetre, soap, leather,
                    and earthenware. The principal exports are lead, esparto, barilla, and soap;
                    while the imports include coal and machinery from England, woollen and cotton
                    stuffs from Catalonia, silk from Valencia and Malaga, and linen from Marseilles
                    and Gibraltar. From the want of adequate facilities for communication, the
                    development of the agricultural and mining resources of Almeria has not been so
                    rapid as might have been expected. The disturbances attending the revolution of
                    1868 have also had a prejudicial effect. Education is in a backward state, the
                    proportion of the population at school being only fifteen in the thousand.
                    Crime, although great, is not excessive, offences against the person forming the
                    greater number of the cases tried. The people generally are simple, sober, and
                    religious. Population in 1870, estimated at 361,553.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Almeria,</hi> the capital of the above province, lies on the
                    Gulf of Almeria, on the Mediterranean, 72 miles E.S.E. of Granada. From the
                    strength of the port it was deemed by the Moorish kings of Granada one of the
                    most valuable of their fortresses and their best commercial harbour. Sailing
                    hence, their cruisers overawed the Catalans and Italians, and their merchant
                    ships conveyed the produce of the country to Africa, Egypt, and Syria. In the
                    time of the Moors Almeria was the seat of hordes of pirates. The walls of the
                    town, and the Moorish fortress, or Alcazaba, overlooking it, as well as the
                    architecture of many of the houses, still attest its Moorish origin. It is
                    pretty well built, and has several handsome squares, although the streets are
                    generally narrow. Almeria is the seat of a bishop, and has a cathedral and
                    theological seminaries. Off the port there is good anchorage in 12 and 14
                    fathoms water; and in addition to its landward defences the place is protected
                    towards the sea by the forts of Trinidad and Tiro. In 1866, 46 vessels, of
                    21,603 tons, with cargoes, entered and cleared the port; and the annual value of
                    the exports is about £50,000. The manufactures are trifling, but there is a good
                    export trade in wine, soda, esparto, silk, and lead; while the imports consist
                    chiefly of coal and manufactured goods. Here there are also some mineral
                    springs. Population (1857), 27,036.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
