<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0901-0473-0438-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALABAMA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 1, page 438</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1130905">Spring</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:830297">Bending</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="20" ref="fastgeo:1204694">Alabama</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1204622">Georgia</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1207034">Mississippi</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205150">Florida</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hm52s7v">Production</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4901zk6v">Springs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n473/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALABAMA</label>, one of the Southern States of the North
                    American Union, lies between 30° 13' and 35° N. lat., and between 85° and 88°
                    35' W. long. It is bounded by Florida and the Gulf of Mexico on the S.,
                    Mississippi on the W., Tennessee on the N., and Georgia on the E.</p>
                <p>Its length is 330 miles, average breadth 154, and area 50,722 square miles. The
                    Alleghany range stretches into the northern portion of the state, but the
                    elevation is nowhere great; the centre is also hilly and broken; on the south,
                    however, for nearly 60 miles inland, the country is very flat, and raised but
                    little above the sea-level. The Alabama is the chief river of the state. It is
                    formed by the -junction of the Coosa and the Talapoosa, which unite about 10
                    miles above the city of Montgomery. Forty-five miles above Mobile the Alabama is
                    joined by the Tombigbee, and from that point is known as the Mobile River. It is
                    navigable from Mobile to Wetumpka, on the Coosa, some 460 miles. The Tombigbee
                    is navigable to Columbus, and the Black Warrior, one of its chief tributaries,
                    to Tuscaloosa. The Tennessee flows through the northern portion of the state,
                    and the Chattahoochee forms part of its eastern boundary. The climate of Alabama
                    is semi-tropical. The temperature ranges from 82° to 18° Fahr. in winter, and in
                    summer from 105° to 60°; the mean temperature for the year being a little over
                    60°. The average severity of the winter months is considered to have increased—a
                    result due, it is said, mainly to the felling of the forests, which gives more
                    unrestricted scope to the cold north-west winds from the Rocky Mountains. The
                    uplands are healthy, but the inhabitants of the low-lying lands are subject to
                    attacks of intermittent, bilious, and congestive fevers. The stratified rocks of
                    the state belong to the silurian, carboniferous, cretaceous, and tertiary
                    systems. The silurian strata throw up numerous mineral springs along the line of
                    the anticlinal axes, some of which, such as Blount Springs and the St Clair
                    Springs, are much resorted to for their health-giving properties. There are also
                    several noted springs arising from the tertiary beds, such as those of
                    Tallahatta and Bladon. Alabama possesses extensive coal deposits. Mr Tait, the
                    state commissioner for the industrial resources of Alabama, considers that the
                    area of the coal-lands in the state amounts to 5500 square miles, of which 5000
                    belong to the Warrior, and the remaining 500 to the Cahawba and Coosa fields.
                    Assuming that only one-half of this area can be worked to advantage, Mr Tait
                    further estimates the aggregate possible yield at 52,250,000,000 tons. At
                    present, however, the annual output probably does not exceed 12,000 tons. In
                    regard to iron, the natural wealth of Alabama is also very great. Mr Tait
                    asserts that a ridge of iron, of an average thickness of 15 feet, runs parallel
                    to one of the principal railway lines for a distance of 100 miles; and in other
                    parts of the country there are large deposits of ore, both red hematite and
                    blackband. The ores of Alabama are said to yield from 10 to 20 per cent. more
                    iron than those of Britain. Granite, marble, flagstones, roofing-slate, lime,
                    and porcelain clay, are among the other mineral products. A little gold has also
                    been found in the state.</p>
                <p>The soil of Alabama varies greatly in character, but is for the most part
                    productive to a greater or lesser extent, except in the south, where there are
                    considerable tracts of sandy, barren, and almost worthless soil. The forests are
                    mainly in the central and northern parts of the state, and embrace oaks,
                    poplars, cedars, chestnuts, pines, hickories, mulberries, elms, and cypresses.
                    The following table exhibits the chief agricultural statistics of Alabama for
                    1870, as compared with 1860, the year before the war:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1870.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1860.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Land in</p><p>Farms.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Improved, . . .
                            acres</p><p>Unimproved, . . ,,</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5,062,204</p><p>9,898,974</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6,385,724</p><p>12,718,821</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Live Stock on Farms.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Horses,</p><p>Mules and Asses, . .
                            .</p><p>Cattle,</p><p>Sheep,</p><p>Swine,</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>80,770</p><p>76,675</p><p>487,163</p><p>241,934</p><p>719,757</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>127,063</p><p>111,687</p><p>773,396</p><p>370,156</p><p>1,748,321</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Chief ( Products.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Indian Corn, . bushels</p><p>Wheat,
                            ... „</p><p>Rye, .... „</p><p>Oats, .... ,,</p><p>Potatoes, . .
                            ,,</p><p>Pease and Beans, ,,</p><p>Butter, . . lb</p><p>Cotton, . .
                            bales</p><p>Wool, ...</p><p>Rice lb</p><p>Tobacco, . .
                            ,,</p><p>Molasses, . . gallons</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>16,977,948</p><p>1,055,068</p><p>18,977 770,866 2,033,872 156,574
                            3,213,753 429,482 381,253 222,945 152,742 433,281</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>33,226,282</p><p>1,218,444</p><p>72,457</p><p>682,179</p><p>5,931,563</p><p>1,482,036</p><p>6,028,478</p><p>989,955</p><p>775,117</p><p>493,465</p><p>232,914</p><p>140,768</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Alabama possesses comparatively few manufactures. It is estimated that in 1870
                    the capital invested amounted to £1,140,806, and the total products in the same
                    year were valued at £2,608,124. There were in 1870 thirteen establishments for
                    the manufacture of cotton goods, whose products amounted in all to 2,843,000 lb,
                    including 4,518,403 yards of sheetings and shirtings, and 1,039,321 <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit01newyrich/page/n476/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0901-0476-0439"/> yards of ginghams and checks. In the same year
                    613 flour mills operated on 3,298,848 bushels of grain. There were 284 lumber
                    mills, producing 1,115,000 laths, 97,192 feet of lumber, and 1,422,000 shingles.
                    In the iron manufactures there has been a marked advance, which is the more
                    noticeable because several other industries have experienced a serious decline.
                    Thus, in 1850 the quantity of ore used for making pig-iron was only 1138 tons,
                    in 1860 it had risen to 3720 tons, and in 1870 to 11,350; the value of the
                    products being respectively .£4500, £12,918, and £42,051. Alabama has also
                    manufactories of rolled and cast iron; but the rise in the value of their
                    products is not so marked. There are, besides, tanneries, carriage and waggon
                    works, and machinery factories, in addition to industries of a local nature.
                    Mobile is the chief mercantile city of the state. In the years ending June 30,
                    1871 and 1872, 688 and 369 vessels (gross burden, 558,525 and 272,853 tons)
                    entered, and 711 and 369 (551,310 and 277,356 tons) cleared the port of Mobile.
                    Cotton was the principal article of export—the amount in 1871 being 287,074
                    bales, and in 1872, 137,977; of which 240,660 and 123,522 bales went to Great
                    Britain. Mobile is connected with the general network of railways of the United
                    States. A line runs from the city through Montgomery and on to Atlanta in
                    Georgia; another runs from Mobile to Meridian in Mississippi; a line crosses the
                    state from Meridian through Cahawba to Montgomery; a loop-line runs from
                    Montgomery to Troy, and proceeding round by Columbus in Georgia, rejoins the
                    main line at Opelika; from Selma a line proceeds north-easterly, following the
                    valley of the Coosa, and passing through Georgia and Tennessee; and another
                    traverses the valley of the Tennessee, from which a branch strikes off to the
                    north to join the Tennessee group of railways at Nashville. A line also connects
                    Mobile with New Orleans. The part of the line from Mobile to Montgomery between
                    Mobile and Tensas was completed under considerable engineering difficulties. It
                    crosses the Mobile river by a swing drawbridge 1000 feet in length, with a draw
                    of 260 feet; while the Tensas river bridge is built on cylindrical piers, each
                    span measuring 152 feet, and its total length 2084 feet. There are at present
                    1602 miles of railway and 2135 of telegraph lines in operation in Alabama.</p>
                <p>Alabama returns 8 members to Congress. The state government is vested in a
                    governor, Senate, and House of Representatives. The Senate consists of 33
                    members elected for four years, one half retiring every two years. The House of
                    Representatives consists of not more than 100 members, elected for two years,
                    and apportioned among the counties according to population, each county,
                    however, being entitled to at least one representative. The members of both
                    houses receive 16s. 8d. each per diem, and the governor £520, 16s. 8d. per
                    annum. The taxation in 1870 amounted to $2,982,932, and the public debt to
                    $13,277,154. In 1860 the taxation was only $851,171. The state is divided into
                    65 counties, and Montgomery is the capital The other principal towns are Mobile,
                    Tuscaloosa (the former capital), Florence, Huntsville, Selma, and Wetumpka.</p>
                <p>Alabama was first penetrated by the Spaniards in quest of gold in 1541, under the
                    celebrated leader De Soto. The natives defended themselves stubbornly, and in
                    their defence inflicted and sustained very severe losses. The present site of
                    Mobile was first occupied by the French in 1711. In 1763 the French possessions
                    east of the Mississippi, including Alabama, were ceded to England. Alabama was
                    originally included in Georgia, but in 1802 became part of the territory of
                    Mississippi. In 1813 the Creek Indians made a desperate effort to check the
                    encroachments of the Anglo-Saxons, but were eventually crushed in the battle of
                    Horse Shoe Bend by General Jackson, who compelled them to surrender
                    three-fourths of their territory. In 1819 Alabama was admitted into the Union as
                    an independent member of the confederation. It seceded in the year 1861, but
                    since the close of the war has been again admitted into the Union.</p>
                <p>The census of 1870 showed the following results :—Total population of Alabama,
                    996,992; coloured, 475,510; with 98 Indians. Of these, 987,030 were native born,
                    and 9962 foreign. In 1860 the population was 964,201, of whom 526,271 were
                    whites and 437,770 (435,080 slaves) were coloured; in 1820 (the year after
                    Alabama had been admitted into the Union) the numbers were—total, 127,901;
                    whites, 85,451; coloured, 42,450 (41,879 slaves). Of the total population in
                    1870, 488,738 were males (255,023 whites, 233,677 coloured, 38 Indians) and
                    508,254 females (respectively, 266,361, 241,833, 60). In regard to education,
                    there were in the state between 5 and 18 years of age, 173,273 males (91,989
                    whites, 81,274 coloured, and 10 Indians) and 169,703 females (89,798, 79,882,
                    and 23); of whom 77,139 have attended school (viz., 31,098 white and 7502
                    coloured males, and 30,226 white and 8313 coloured females). The returns give
                    2969 schools, with 2372 male and 992 female teachers. Of persons 10 years and
                    upwards, there were 349,771 returned as unable to read, and 383,012 as unable to
                    write.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
