<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0228-0211-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PANIZZI, Sir Anthony</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 211</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:997301">Librarians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1115813">Shepherds</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j79n">Librarians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n228/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PANIZZI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Anthony</hi></label>
                    (1797-1879), principal librarian of the British Museum, was born at Brescello in
                    the duchy of Modena, September 16, 1797. After taking his degree at the
                    university of Parma, he became an advocate, and speedily obtained considerable
                    practice. Always a fervent patriot, he was almost of necessity implicated in the
                    movement set on foot in 1821 to overturn the miserable Government of his native
                    duchy, and in October of that year barely escaped arrest by a precipitate
                    flight. He first established himself at Lugano, where he published an anonymous
                    and now excessively rare pamphlet <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n229/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0229-0212"/> generally known as <hi rend="italic">I</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Processi</hi><hi rend="italic">di Rubiera,</hi> an exposure of the
                    monstrous injustice and illegalities of the Modenese Government’s proceedings
                    against suspected persons. Expelled from Switzerland at the joint instance of
                    Austria, France, and Sardinia, he repaired to England, where he arrived in May
                    1823, in a state bordering upon destitution. His countryman Foscolo provided him
                    with introductions to Roscoe and Dr Shepherd, and by their aid he was enabled to
                    earn a subsistence in Liverpool by giving Italian lessons, while diligently
                    instructing himself in English. Roscoe further introduced him to Brougham, by
                    whose influence he was called to London to assume the professorship of Italian
                    in University College, upon the foundation of that institution in 1828. His
                    chair was almost a sinecure; but his manners, his culture, and his abilities
                    rapidly ingratiated him with the best London society; and in 1831 Brougham,
                    having become lord chancellor, used his <hi rend="italic">ex officio</hi>
                    position as a principal trustee of the British Museum to obtain for Panizzi the
                    post of an extra assistant librarian of the printed book department. At the same
                    time he was actively prosecuting the most important of his purely-literary
                    labours, his edition of Boiardo’s <hi rend="italic">Orlando Innamorato.</hi>
                    Boiardo’s fame had been eclipsed for three centuries by the adaptation of Berni;
                    and it is highly to the honour of Panizzi’s taste to have redeemed him from
                    oblivion, and restored to Italy one of the very best of her narrative poets. His
                    edition of the <hi rend="italic">Orlando Innamorato</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Orlando</hi><hi rend="italic">Furioso</hi> was published between
                    1830 and 1834, prefaced by a valuable essay on the influence of Celtic legends
                    on mediaeval romance, and dedicated to his benefactor Roscoe. In 1835 he edited
                    Boiardo’s minor poems, and was about the same time engaged in preparing a
                    catalogue of the library of the Royal Society, which led to a warm controversy.
                    Panizzi was shortly to find library work of a much more important and agreeable
                    description in the institution with which he was officially connected. The
                    unsatisfactory condition and illiberal management of the British Museum had long
                    excited discontent, and at length a trivial circumstance led to the appointment
                    of a parliamentary committee, which sat throughout the sessions of 1835-36, and
                    probed the condition of the institution very thoroughly. Panizzi’s principal
                    contributions to its inquiries as respected the library were an enormous mass of
                    statistics respecting foreign libraries collected by him upon the Continent, and
                    some admirable evidence on the catalogue of printed books then in contemplation.
                    In 1837 he became keeper of printed books upon the retirement of Mr Baber, and
                    immediately set himself to grapple with the special tasks imposed upon him by
                    the peculiar circumstances in which he found the library. The entire collection,
                    except the King’s Library, had to be removed from Montague House to the new
                    building; the readingroom service had to be reorganized; rules for the new
                    printed catalogue had to be prepared, and the catalogue itself undertaken. All
                    these tasks were successfully accomplished; but, although the rules of
                    cataloguing devised by Panizzi and his assistants have become ,the basis of
                    whatever has since been attempted in this department, the progress of
                    the-catalogue itself was slow. The first volume, comprising letter A, was
                    published in 1841, and from that time, although the catalogue was continued and
                    completed in MS., no attempt was made to print any more until, in 1881, the task
                    was resumed under the direction of the present principal librarian. The chief
                    cause of this comparative failure was injudicious interference with Panizzi,
                    occasioned by the impatience of the trustees and the public. Panizzi’s
                    appointment, as that of a foreigner, had from the first been highly unpopular.
                    He gradually broke down opposition, partly by his social influence, but far more
                    by the sterling merits of his administration, and his constant efforts to
                    improve the library. The most remarkable of these was his great report, printed
                    in 1845, upon the Museum’s extraordinary deficiencies in general literature,
                    which ultimately procured the increase of the annual grant for the purchase of
                    books to &lt;£10,000. In 1847 his friendship with the Right Hon. Thomas
                    Grenville led to the nation’s being enriched by the bequest of that gentleman’s
                    unique library, valued even then at £50,000. In 1847-49 a royal commission sat
                    to inquire into the general state of the Museum, and Panizzi was the centre of
                    the proceedings. His administration, fiercely attacked from a multitude of
                    quarters, was triumphantly vindicated in every point; and the inquiry had the
                    excellent effect, not merely of establishing his reputation, but of abolishing
                    the main source of maladministration, the anomalous position and illegitimate
                    influence of the secretary. Panizzi immediately became by far the most
                    influential official in the Museum, though he did not actually succeed to the
                    principal librarianship until 1856.</p>
                <p>It was thus as merely keeper of printed books that he conceived and carried out
                    the achievement by which he is probably best remembered, the erection of the new
                    library and reading-room. The want of space had become so crying an evil that
                    purchases were actually discouraged from lack of room in which to deposit the
                    books. Panizzi cast his eye on the empty quadrangle enclosed by the Museum
                    buildings, and conceived the daring idea of occupying it with a central cupola
                    too distant, and adjacent galleries too low, to obstruct the inner windows of
                    the original edifice. The cupola was to cover three hundred readers, the
                    galleries to provide storage for a million of books. The original design,
                    sketched by Panizzi’s own hand on April 18, 1852, was submitted to the trustees
                    on May 5; in May 1854 the necessary expenditure was sanctioned by parliament,
                    and the building was opened in May 1857. Its construction had involved a
                    multitude of ingenious arrangements, all of which had been contrived or
                    inspected by Panizzi with the genius for minute detail which he shared with so
                    many men equally remarkable for the general breadth of their conceptions, and
                    with the mechanical inventiveness of which he was continually giving proof.
                    There is probably no building in the world better adapted to the purpose which
                    it is intended to serve; and it is no discredit to the designer if, imposing as
                    it is, neither the space nor the funds at his disposal allowed him to plan it on
                    the colossal scale which its utility would have warranted.</p>
                <p>Panizzi succeeded Sir Henry Ellis as principal librarian in March 1856. The most
                    remarkable incidents of his administration were the great improvement effected
                    in the condition of the Museum staff by the recognition of the institution as a
                    branch of the civil service, and the decision, not carried out for long
                    afterwards, to remove the natural history collections to Kensington. Of this
                    questionable measure Panizzi was a warm advocate; he was heartily glad to be rid
                    of the naturalists. He had small love for science and its professors, and, as
                    his friend Macaulay said, “would at any time have given three elephants for one
                    Aldus.” Many important additions to the collections were made during his
                    administration, especially the Temple bequest of antiquities, and the
                    Halicarnassean sculptures discovered at Budrun by Mr C. T. Newton. Feeling the
                    effects of age and excessive labour, he expressed a wish to retire in 1865, but
                    remained some time longer in office at the instance of the trustees. He
                    ultimately retired in July 1866, receiving as a special mark of distinction a
                    pension equal to the full amount of his salary. He took a house in the immediate
                    neighbourhood of his cherished institution, and continued to interest himself
                    actively in its <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n230/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0230-0213"/> affairs until his death, which took place on
                    April 8, 1879. He had been created a K.C.B. in 1869.</p>
                <p>Along with Panizzi’s visible and palpable activity as the centre of energy at the
                    British Museum was another systematic activity no less engrossing and important,
                    but unacknowledged by himself and little suspected by the world. His devotion to
                    the Museum was rivalled by his devotion to his country, and his personal
                    influence with English Liberal statesmen enabled him to promote her cause by
                    judicious representations at critical periods. Throughout the revolutionary
                    movements of 1848-49, and again during the campaign of 1859 and the subsequent
                    transactions due to the union of Naples to the kingdom of Upper Italy, Panizzi
                    was in constant communication with the Italian patriots, and their confidential
                    representative with the English ministers. He laboured, according to
                    circumstances, now to excite now to mitigate the latter’s jealousy of France;
                    now to moderate their apprehensions of revolutionary excesses, now to secure
                    encouragement or connivance for Garibaldi. The letters addressed to him by
                    patriotic Italians, edited by his literary executor and biographer, Mr L. Fagan,
                    alone compose a thick volume. His own have not as yet been collected; but the
                    internal evidence of the'correspondence published attests the priceless value of
                    his services, and the boundless confidence reposed in his sagacity,
                    disinterestedness, and discretion. He was charitable to his exiled countrymen in
                    England, and, chiefly at his own expense, equipped a steamer, which was lost at
                    sea, to rescue the Neapolitan prisoners of state on the island of Santo Stefano.
                    His services were recognized by the offer of a senatorship and of the direction
                    of public instruction in Italy; but England, where he had been legally
                    naturalized, had become his adopted country, though in his latter years he
                    frequently visited the land qf his birth.</p>
                <p>Panizzi’s merits and defects were those of a potent nature. He was a man born to
                    rule, and in a free country would probably have devoted himself to public life
                    and become one of the leading statesmen of hi⅞ age. His administrative faculty
                    was extraordinary: to the widest grasp he united the minutest attention to
                    matters of detail. His will and perseverance were indomitable, but the vehemence
                    of his temper was mitigated by an ample endowment of tact and circumspection. He
                    was a powerful writer, a persuasive speaker, and an accomplished diplomatist. He
                    was undoubtedly arbitrary and despotic; in some few points upon which he had
                    hastily taken up wrong views, incurably prejudiced; in others, such as the
                    claims of science, somewhat perversely narrow-minded. But on the whole he was a
                    very great man, who, by introducing great ideas into the management of the
                    Museum, not only redeemed that institution from being a mere showplace, but
                    raised the standard of library administration all over England. His successors
                    may equal or surpass his achievements, but only on condition of labouring in his
                    spirit, a spirit which did not exist before him. His moral character was the
                    counterpart of his intellectual: he was warm hearted and magnanimous, extreme in
                    love and hate, a formidable enemy, but a devoted friend. The list of his
                    intimate friends is a long and brilliant one, including Lord Palmerston, Mr
                    Gladstone, Roscoe, Grenville, Macaulay, Lord Langdale and his family, Rutherfurd
                    (Lord Advocate), and above all, perhaps, Haywood, the translator of Kant. His
                    most celebrated friendship, however, is that with Prosper Mérimée, who, having
                    begun by seeking to enlist his influence with the English Government on behalf
                    of Napoleon III., discovered a congeniality of tastes which produced a
                    delightful correspondence. Mérimée’s part has been published by Mr Fagan;
                    Panizzi’s perished in the conflagration kindled by the Paris commune. The loss
                    is to be regretted rather on acount of the autobiographical than the literary
                    value of Panizzi’s share of the correspondence, although he was an accomplished
                    man of letters of the 18th century pattern. But no man of ability has more
                    completely exemplified the apophthegm of another distinguished person, that
                    success is won less by ability than by character.</p>
                <p>See L. Fagan, <hi rend="italic">Life of Sir Anthony Panizzi,</hi> 2 vols.,
                    London, 1880. (R. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
