<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0918-0539-0514-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PENZA (9th edition, volume 18, page 514)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sp8d">Tatars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f430">Timber</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1150988">Timber</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:851875">Chalk</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1143526">Tatars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n539/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PENZA</label>, a government of eastern Russia, bounded on the
                    N. by Nijni Novgorod, on the E. by Simbirsk, and on the S. and W. by Saratoff
                    and Tamboff, and having an area of 15,000 square miles. The surface is
                    undulating, with deep valleys and ravines, but even in its highest parts it does
                    not reach more than 600 to 900 feet above sealevel. It is chiefly made up of
                    Cretaceous sandstones, sands, marls, and chalk, covered in the east by Eocene
                    deposits. Chalk, potter’s clay, peat, and iron are the chief mineral products,
                    in the north. The soil is a black earth, more or less mixed with clay and sand;
                    the only marshes of any extent occur in the Krasnoslobodsk district; and
                    considerable sand-areas appear in the broad valleys of the larger rivers. There
                    are extensive forests in the north, but the south shows the characteristic
                    features of a steppeland. The government is watered by the Moksha, the Sura
                    (both navigable), and the Khoper, belonging respectively to the Oka, Volga, and
                    Don systems. Timber is floated down several smaller streams, while the Moksha
                    and Sura are important means of conveyance for grain, spirits, timber, metals,
                    and oils. The climate is harsh and continental, the average temperature at Penza
                    being only 39° <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 8 (12° <hi rend="superscript">
                        -</hi> 2 in January and 68° <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 5 in July).</p>
                <p>The population—1,356,600 in 1881, and in 1884 estimated at about
                    1,465,000—consists principally of Russians, mixed to some extent with
                    Mordvinians; there are also about 150,000 Mordvinians who are to a large extent
                    Russified; some 40,000 Mescheryaks, who have undergone the same process still
                    more fully; and 60,000 Tatars, who still keep their own religion, language, and
                    customs. The Russians profess the Greek faith, and very many, especially in the
                    north, are Raskolniks. Somewhat less than 10 per cent, of the population
                    (133,250 in 1881) live in towns; the chief occupation of the inhabitants is
                    agriculture, 61 per cent, of the soil being arable. Wheat and millet are raised
                    only to a limited extent, the chief crops being rye, oats, buckwheat, hemp,
                    potatoes, and beetroot. The averages for 1870-77 were 3,900,000 quarters of corn
                    and 1,779,200 bushels of potatoes. The chief centres of corn export are Penza,
                    Narovtchat, and Golovinshtchina. Market-gardening is successfully <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n540/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0918-0540-0515"/> carried on in several districts, and improved
                    varieties of fruit-trees are being introduced through the imperial botanical
                    garden at Penza and a private school of gardening in the Gorodishtche district.
                    Fourteen per cent, of the area is under meadows or grazing land; and in 1881
                    there were within the government 244,000 head of cattle, 383,000 horses, and
                    235,000 pigs. Sheep-breeding is especially developed in Tchembar and Insar
                    (670,000 sheep, including 72,000 of finer breeds, in 1881). The Mordvinians are
                    very partial to beekeeping. The forests (620,000 acres) are a considerable
                    source of wealth, especially in Krasnoslobodsk and Gorodishtche, whence timber,
                    a variety of wooden wares, and also pitch and tar are exported to the south. As
                    many as 30 per cent, of the adult male population leave the government in search
                    of employment, either on the Volga or in southern Russia.</p>
                <p>The manufactures are few, employing only 13,300 hands. The yearly returns in 1879
                    did not exceed 13,325,000 roubles (£1,332,500). The distilleries come first
                    (£973,200), followed by the woollen cloth industry (£237,000), the paper
                    industry (£37,200), tanneries, soap-works, glass-works, machine-works,
                    iron-works, and beetroot-sugar factories. Trade, which has been favoured by the
                    completion of the railway from Tula to Samara, is still limited to the export of
                    corn, spirits, timber, hemp-seed oil, tallow, hides, honey, wax, some woollen
                    cloth, potash, and cattle, the chief centres for trade being Penza, Nijni
                    Lomoff, Mokshan, Saransk, Krasnoslobodsk, and Golovinshtchina.</p>
                <p>The government is divided into ten districts, the chief towns of which are
                    :—Penza (41,650), Gorodishtche (3200), Insar (5230), Kerensk (12,450),
                    Krasnoslobodsk (7000), Mokshan (13,050), Narovtchat (5150), Nijni Lomoff
                    (10,500), Saransk (13,450), and Tchembar (5320). Troitsk (5700), Verkíinii
                    Lomoff (7300), and Sheshkéeff (3500) also have municipal institutions.</p>
                <p>The present government of Penza was formerly inhabited by Mordvinians, who had
                    the Mescheryaks in the west, the Bulgars in the north, ajιd the Burtases in the
                    south. In the 13th century these populations fell under the dominion of the
                    Tatars, with whom they fought against Moscow. As early as the 14th century they
                    possessed the town of Narovtchat. The Russians penetrated into the country in
                    the 16th century, founding the town of Mokshan in 1535, and several others in
                    the course of that and the following centuries. Penza was founded in the
                    beginning of the 17th century, the permanent Russian settlement dating as far
                    back as 1666. Its wooden fort, on the site of the present cathedral of the
                    Saviour, protected the neighbourhood against risings of the Mordvinians and
                    Mescheryaks. In 1776 it was taken by Pugatcheff. The town was almost totally
                    destroyed by the great conflagrations of 1836, 1839, and 1858.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
