<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0453-0432-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PAULI, Reinhold</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 432</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42z12q4d">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd23">Heroes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1011191">Mass</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1010775">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n453/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PAULI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Reinhold</hi></label>
                    (1823-1882), historian, was born at Berlin on 25th May 1823. From his mother,
                    who was of Huguenot descent, he derived a vivacious temperament; from his
                    father, a minister of the Reformed Church, sprung of a family of clergymen and
                    theological professors, he inherited strong religious convictions. He spent his
                    boyhood in Bremen, from whose republican citizens he early imbibed a hearty
                    admiration of liberal self-government, moral discipline, and extensive
                    sea-trade. With the exception of two semesters when he heard Dahlmann at Bonn,
                    he studied at the university of Berlin (1842-46), where he acquired a lifelong
                    predilection for the Hohenzollerns and for the civil service and army of
                    Prussia. Ranke was young Pauli’s model historian, but he had far too much
                    individuality to bind himself slavishly to any school. After having taken his
                    degree and passed the public schoolmaster’s examination, he became in 1847
                    private tutor in the family <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n454/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0454-0433"/> of Mr Bannatyne, a solicitor in Glasgow, and
                    stayed seven years in Great Britain. During 1849-52 he served as private
                    secretary to the Prussian ambassador Bunsen in London, and made the acquaintance
                    of many eminent politicians of the day and of distinguished antiquaries, such as
                    Kemble, Thorpe, and Hardy. Never a mere book-scholar, he saw various parts of
                    England with an observant eye, and followed public questions with warm interest.
                    He now conceived the plan of investigating the history of England in its
                    original sources. In this way he was the first faithfully to copy some of the
                    Anglo-Saxon annals; but, as soon as he learned that Thorpe was going to edit
                    them for the Master of the Rolls, he liberally committed his transcripts to him.
                    The roots of Great and Greater Britain appeared to him to lie in Anglo-Saxon,
                    not in Celtic, institutions, and therefore his first book was <hi rend="italic"
                    >Konig Aelfred</hi> (Berlin, 1851). Though critically destroying many
                    long-cherished legends, he described his hero’s character and times in warm
                    colours. The book was twice translated into English, and Lappenberg, the best
                    judge then living, declared its author worthy to continue his own <hi
                    rend="italic">Geschichte von</hi><hi rend="italic">England.</hi> Not without
                    material privations Pauli continued his stay in England, and between 1853 and
                    1858 published three large volumes, comprising the period from Henry II. to
                    Henry VIL In 1855 he became privat-docent at Bonn, and he obtained a
                    professorship at Rostock in 1857. Thence he removed in 1859 to Tübingen, where,
                    however, in 1866 he offended the Wurtemberg Government by vehemently denouncing
                    its Austrian policy in an essay which appeared during the Prussian war in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Preussische Jahrbücher.</hi> Exiled to a remote country
                    seminary, he preferred to resign. He now returned to his native country and
                    obtained in 1867 a post in the university of Marburg, which he once represented
                    in the Prussian Upper House. In 1870 he found an honourable position at
                    Göttingen, where the former dynastic union of Hanover with Great Britain had
                    left a splendid English library, and where Waitz had brought together a
                    flourishing historical school.</p>
                <p>Pauli’s later life was chiefly devoted to modern history, and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">Englands</hi> 1814-52, in 3 vols.
                    (Leipsic, 1864-75) made his name widely known. He fulfilled his duties as a
                    teacher and examiner and as a fellow of different learned societies with
                    punctual accuracy; he became member of the academies of Göttingen, Munich, and
                    Berlin, and honorary doctor of Oxford and Cambridge. He helped friends and
                    pupils with untiring kindness; in his happy and social home he was often visited
                    by distinguished English scholars. And he was for a whole generation a living
                    link between the historical literature of England and Germany, “those two
                    columns of the Teutonic world, which, for the benefit of human progress he
                    firmly believed in, he fondly hoped would never be torn asunder.” When suddenly
                    called away by a stroke of apoplexy on 3d June 1882, he was deeply lamented on
                    both sides of the Channel.</p>
                <p>Pauli’s <hi rend="italic">History of England</hi> was remarkable for its
                    research. Never before had the records, then piled up in the Tower without
                    calendars or indexes, been used in so full a way; never before had the
                    chronicles and memoirs been so thoroughly criticized. The short review of these
                    original sources, given in the appendices, formed a guide to the mediaeval
                    historiography of England, and was later on, when better editions appeared,
                    supplemented by Pauli’s critiques contributed to German periodicals. The main
                    narrative follows the king, but at the end of each reign the literary,
                    religious, social, economical, and especially the commercial features of the
                    period are cleverly grouped together. Though Pauli was no regular jurist, even
                    the development of the constitutional side of his subject was then superior to
                    the general standard. Indeed these parts, and these only, Pauli lived to see
                    without jealousy superseded by Gneist and Stubbs, while in every other respect
                    his work, then an immense advance upon Lingard, still remains the most solid of
                    its kind. It has never been translated, perhaps on account of its almost
                    annalistic form, and its contempt for the popular attractions of moralizing
                    remarks, philosophical speculation, or picturesque style. To gain new facts, to
                    show the way for further investigation, seemed to Pauli a worthier task than to
                    amuse the public with a brilliant story. The history is remarkable for the
                    completeness with which the author has used all reports, letters, and memoirs he
                    could lay his hands upon. He was also allowed to inspect private papers of
                    Cobden and of the Prussian ambassadors Bülow and Bunsen; and he knew something
                    by personal recollection. Still he openly confessed that this contemporary
                    history could be only preliminary, on account of the wide gaps in our knowledge
                    of the secret policy, and because “he felt, in dealing with the flowing formless
                    mass of living characters, as if he were touching hot lava that could not yet be
                    shaped into constructive material.” Nevertheless the carefully-weighed judgment
                    and the profound understanding of the manifold and tangled tendencies of modem
                    strife are simply astonishing, if we consider that the author was a foreigner.
                    Abroad no guide through the English history of the 19th century can rival this
                    work, while the English reader will find at least the chapters on foreign policy
                    to contain much that is new, and will be sure to admire the impartial views of a
                    distant but lofty and noble observer. Pauli had learned to love the organic
                    growth of the English constitution, and could not look without misgivings on the
                    radical destruction of its aristocratic basis.</p>
                <p>Besides a great many essays on the Middle Ages, of which only the popular ones
                    have been collected in <hi rend="italic">Bilder aus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Alt-England</hi> (Gotha, 1860; 2d ed. 1876, translated 1861), and in <hi
                    rend="italic">Aufsätze zur Englischen Geschichte</hi> (Leipsic, 1869; <hi
                    rend="italic">Neue Folge,</hi> edited by Hartwig, Leipsic, 1883), Pauli
                    published two monographs: “Grosseteste und Marsh,” in the Tübingen <hi
                    rend="italic">Program</hi> for 1864, and <hi rend="italic">Simon νon
                    Montfort</hi> (Tübingen, 1867). From a literary point of view these biographies
                    are the best things Pauli wrote, and in them he was successful in creating
                    figures of impressive character; but his general histories also usually centre
                    round a hero, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> Canning and Peel in his history of
                    England in our own times. Well versed in palaeography, Pauli discovered several
                    important memorials, and never despised the humbler task of an editor; he edited
                    Gower’s <hi rend="italic">Confessio</hi><hi rend="italic">Amantis</hi> (1857),
                    <hi rend="italic">The Libell of Englishe Policye of</hi> 1436 (1878), and three
                    tracts on political economy of the time of Henry VIII., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Transactions of the Göttingen Society,</hi> 1878. For the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Monumenta</hi><hi rend="italic">Germanise</hi><hi rend="italic">Historica</hi>
                    he furnished a quantity of MS. collations, and extracted conjointly with
                    Liebermann pieces of interest for Germany out of English historians before 1300
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">a,d.,</hi> which appeared in part in vol. xiii. (1881), and
                    in part will fill vol xxvii. For the Berlin Academy he selected and copied a
                    mass of records relating to Germany, mainly of the 14th century, which did
                    excellent service for the Hanseatic publications. For the Camden Society he had
                    prepared the account book of the Prussian crusade of Henry Earl of Derby in
                    1392, which, it is hoped, will be edited by an eminent English historian. He
                    contributed numberless reviews and detailed, often exhaustive, essays on minor
                    subjects of English history to Sybel’s <hi rend="italic">Historische
                    Zeitschrift, Preussische Jahrbücher, Grenzboten, Rundschau, Im Neuen Reich,
                    Forschungen</hi><hi rend="italic">zιιr</hi><hi rend="italic">Deutschen
                    Geschichte, Archiv für ältere deutsche Geschichtskunde, Hansische
                    Geschichtsblättsr, Zeitschrift für Kirchenrecht, Deutschs</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Litter</hi><hi rend="italic">aturzeitung, Göttingischs Nachrichten,
                    Göttingischs Anzeigen.</hi> These articles possess in some respects a very high
                    value as material for future scholars. Pauli’s last studies on Henry VIII. and
                    the Hanoverian succession, based on the discovery of the papers of Robethon, the
                    elector’s agent, are printed in the <hi rend="italic">Aufsätze, Neue
                    Folge.</hi></p>
                <p>Hartwig prefixed a sketch of Pauli’s life to the <hi rend="italic">Aufsätze, Neue
                    Folge,</hi> and Frensdoríf delivered a lecture upon him, printed in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Transactions</hi> of the Göttingen Society (1882). (F. L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
