<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0918-0799-0764-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PHILOLAUS (9th edition, volume 18, page 764)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1125500">Solids</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925173">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4377639r">Solids</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n799/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PHILOLAUS</label>, next to Archytas the most illustrious of
                    the Pythagorean philosophers, was born at Tarentum or, according to Diogenes
                    Laertius, at Crotona.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Boeckh places his life between the 70th and 95th Olympiads (496-396
                            B.C.). He was a contemporary of Socrates an&lt;l Democritus, but senior
                            to them, and wa# probably somewhat junior to Empedocles, so that his
                            birth may be placed at about 480.</p></note> He was said to have been
                    intimate with Democritus, and was probably one of his teachers. After the death
                    of Pythagoras great dissensions prevailed in the cities of lower Italy, which
                    were allayed only after the lapse of many years through the intervention of the
                    Achaeans. According to some accounts Philolaus was obliged to flee, and owed his
                    escape to his youthful energy. He took refuge first in Lucania, then in Greece;
                    he lived at Thebes, where he had for pupils Simmias and Cebes, who subsequently,
                    being still young men <hi rend="italic">{νεανίσκοι),</hi> were present at the
                    death of Socrates. Prior to this Philolaus had left Thebes and returned to
                    Italy, where he was the teacher of Archytas. Pythagoras published nothing, nor
                    did the other early Pythagoreans; the members of the brotherhood, moreover,
                    piously referred their discoveries back to their master; hence many doctrines
                    have been attributed to Pythagoras which were first propounded later in the
                    school. He entered deeply into the number-theory, which constituted the
                    distinctive feature of the Pythagorean philosophy, and in particular dwelt on
                    the properties inherent in the decad —the sum of the first four numbers,
                    consequently the fourth triangular number, the tetractys—which he called great,
                    all-powerful, and all-producing. The discovery of the regular solids is
                    attributed to Pythagoras by Eudemus, and Empedocles is stated to have been the
                    first who maintained that there were four elements. Philolaus, connecting these
                    ideas, held that the elementary nature of bodies depended on their form, and
                    assigned the tetrahedron to fire, the octahedron to air, the icosahedron to
                    water, and the cube to earth; the dodecahedron he assigned to a fifth element,
                    aether, or, as some think, to the universe. This theory indicates considerable
                    knowledge of geometry on the part of its author; it gave, moreover, a great
                    impulse to the study of that science, and many important results were arrived
                    at, so that Aristaeus, who lived before Euclid, was able to write a book on the
                    comparison of the five regular solids.</p>
                <p>Philolaus was the first to propound the doctrine of the motion of the earth;
                    some, however, attribute this doctrine to Pythagoras, but there is no evidence
                    in support of their view. Philolaus supposed that the sphere of the fixed stars,
                    the five planets, the sun, moon, and earth, all moved round the central fire,
                    which he called the hearth of the universe, the house of Zeus, and the mother of
                    the gods; but as these made up only nine revolving bodies he conceived, in
                    accordance with his number-theory, a tenth, which he called counter-earth, <hi
                        rend="italic">αντιχθwν.</hi> He was the first who published a book on the
                    Pythagorean doctrines, a treatise of which Plato made use in the composition of
                    his <hi rend="italic">Tirnaeus.</hi> This work of the Pythagorean, to which the
                    mystical name Bακχαt is sometimes given, seems to have consisted of three books:
                    (1) Hepì <hi rend="italic">κόσμον,</hi> containing a general account of the
                    origin and arrangement of the universe; (2) Hepì <hi rend="italic">φvσεως,</hi>
                    an exposition of the nature of numbers; (3) ∏qoi <hi rend="italic">ψnχηs,</hi>
                    o∏ the nature of the soul.</p>
                <p>See Boeckh, <hi rend="italic">Bhilolαos</hi><hi rend="italic">des Pythagoreers
                        Lehren nebst den Bruchstücken seines Werkes</hi> (Berlin, 1819); also
                    Fabricius, <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Graeca</hi>; Zeller, <hi rend="italic"
                        >History of Greek Philosophy</hi>; and Chaignet, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pythagore</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">la
                        Philosophic</hi><hi rend="italic">Pythagoricienne,contenant</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">les Fragments de Philolaüs</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">d’Architas</hi> (1873).</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n800/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0800-0765"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
