<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0463-0442-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PEACH</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 442</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vc7m">Peach</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47659p0d">Plum</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18t15">Seeds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68d53">Tubes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45717p37">Mildew</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j3q">Darwinism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1205406">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204082">Japan</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1055910">Peach</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:847816">Carpel</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1020821">Mildew</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n463/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PEACH</label>. By Bentham and Hooker the peach is included
                    under the genus <hi rend="italic">Prunus (Prunus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >persica),</hi> and its resemblance to the plum is indeed obvious; others have
                    classed it with the almond, <hi rend="italic">Amygdalus’,</hi> while others
                    again have considered it sufficiently distinct to constitute a genus of its own
                    under the name <hi rend="italic">Persica.</hi></p>
                <p>In general terms the peach may be said to be a mediumsized tree, with lanceolate,
                    stipulate leaves, borne on long, slender, relatively unbranched shoots, and with
                    the flowers arranged singly, or in groups of two or more, at intervals along the
                    shoots. The flowers have a hollow tube at the base bearing at -its free edge
                    five sepals, an equal number of petals, usually concave or spoon-shaped, pink or
                    white, and a great number of stamens. The pistil consists of a single carpel
                    with its ovary, style, stigma, and solitary ovule or twin ovules. This carpel
                    is, in the first instance, free within the flower-tube, but, as growth goes on,
                    the flowertube and the carpel become fused together into one mass, the flesh of
                    the peach, the inner layers of the carpel becoming woody to form the stone,
                    while the ovule ripens into the kernel or seed. This is exactly the structure of
                    the plum or apricot, and differs from that of the almond, which is identical in
                    the first instance, only in the circumstance that the fleshy part of the latter
                    eventually becomes dry and leathery and cracks open along a line called the
                    suture.</p>
                <p>The nectarine is a variation from the peach, mainly characterized by the
                    circumstance that, while the skin of the ripe fruit is downy in the peach, it is
                    shining and destitute of hairs in the nectarine. That there is no essential
                    difference between the two is, however, shown by the facts that the seeds of the
                    peach will produce nectarines, and <hi rend="italic">vice versa,</hi> and that
                    it is not very uncommon, though still exceptional, to see peaches and nectarines
                    on the same branch, and fruits which combine in themselves the characteristics
                    of both nectarines and peaches. The blossoms of the peach are formed the autumn
                    previous to their expansion, and this fact, together with the peculiarities of
                    their form and position, requires to be borne in mind by the gardener in his
                    pruning and training operations, as mentioned in <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Horticulture</hi> (vol. xii. pp. 272, 273). The only point of practical
                    interest requiring mention here is the very singular fact attested by all
                    peach-growers, that, while certain peaches are liable to the attacks of a
                    parasitic fungus known as mildew, others are not, showing a difference in
                    constitution analogous to that observed in the case of human beings, some of
                    whom will readily succumb to particular diseases, while others seem proof
                    against their attacks. In the case of the peach this peculiarity is in some way
                    connected with the presence of small glandular outgrowths on the stalk, or at
                    the base of the leaf. Some peaches have globular, others reniform glands, others
                    none at all, and these latter trees are much more subject to mildew than are
                    those provided with glands.</p>
                <p>The history of the peach, almond, and nectarine is interesting and important as
                    regards the question of the origin of species and the production and
                    perpetuation of varieties. As to the origin of the peach two views are held,
                    that of Alphonse de Candolle, who attributes all cultivated varieties to a
                    distinct species, probably of Chinese origin, and that adopted by many
                    naturalists, but more especially by Darwin, who looks upon the peach as a
                    modification of the almond. The importance of the subject demands that a summary
                    of the principal facts and inferences bearing on this question should be given.
                    In the first place, the peach as we now know it has been nowhere recognized in
                    the wild state. In the few instances where it is said to have been found wild
                    the probabilities are that the tree was an escape from cultivation. Aitchison,
                    however, gathered in the Hazárdarakht ravine in Afghanistan a form with
                    different-shaped fruit from that of the almond, being larger and flatter. “The
                    surface of the fruit,” he observes, “resembles that of the peach in texture and
                    colour; and the nut is quite distinct from that of 419 [the wild almond]. The
                    whole shrub resembles more what one might consider a wild form of the peach than
                    that of the almond.” It is admitted, however, by all competent botanists that
                    the almond is wild in the hotter and drier parts of the Mediterranean and
                    Levantine regions. Aitchison also mentions the almond as wild in some parts of
                    Afghanistan, where it is known to the natives as “bédám,” the same word that
                    they apply to the cultivated almond. The branches of the tree are carried by the
                    priests in religious ceremonies. It is not known as a wild plant in China or
                    Japan.</p>
                <p>As to the nectarine, of its origin as a variation from the peach there is
                    abundant evidence, as has already been mentioned; it is only requisite to add
                    the very important fact that the seeds of the nectarine, even when that
                    nectarine has been produced by bud-variation from a peach, will generally
                    produce nectarines, or, as gardeners say, “come true.”</p>
                <p>Darwin brings together the records of several cases, not only of gradations
                    between peaches and nectarines, but also of intermediate forms between the peach
                    and the almond. So far as we know, however, no case has yet been recorded of a
                    peach or a nectarine producing an almond, or <hi rend="italic">vice versa,</hi>
                    although if all have had a common origin such an event might be expected. Thus
                    the botanical evidence seems to indicate that the wild almond is the source of
                    cultivated almonds, peaches, and nectarines, and consequently that the peach was
                    introduced from Asia Minor or Persia, whence the name <hi rend="italic"
                    >Persica</hi> given to the peach; and Aitchison’s discovery in Afghanistan of a
                    form which reminded him of a wild peach lends additional force to this view.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, Alphonse de Candolle, from philological and other
                    considerations, considers the peach to be of Chinese origin.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n464/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0464-0443"/>
                <p>The peach has not, it is true, been found wild in China, but it has been
                    cultivated there from time immemorial; it has entered into the literature and
                    folk-lore of the people; and it is designated by a distinct name, “to” or “tao,”
                    a word found in the writings of Confucius five centuries before Christ, and even
                    in other writings dating from the 10th century before the Christian era. Though
                    now cultivated in India, and almost wild in some parts of the northwest, and, as
                    we have seen, probably also in Afghanistan, it has no Sanskrit name; it is not
                    mentioned in the Hebrew text of the Scriptures, nor in the earliest Greek times.
                    Xenophon makes no mention of the peach, though the Ten Thousand must have
                    traversed the country where, according to some, the peach is native, but
                    Theophrastus, a hundred years later, does speak of it as a Persian fruit, and De
                    Candolle suggests that it might have been introduced into Greece by Alexander.
                    According to his view, the seeds of the peach, cultivated for ages in China,
                    might have been carried by the Chinese into Kashmir, Bokhara, and Persia between
                    the period of the Sanskrit emigration and the Graeco-Persian period. Once
                    established, its cultivation would readily extend westward, or, on the other
                    hand, by Cabul to north-western India, where its cultivation is not ancient.
                    While the peach has been cultivated in China for thousands of years, the almond
                    does not grow wild in that country, and its introduction is supposed not to go
                    back farther than the Christian era.</p>
                <p>On the whole, we should be inclined to attribute greater weight to the evidence
                    from botanical sources than to that derived from philology, particularly since
                    the discovery both of the wild almond and of a form like a wild peach in
                    Afghanistan. It may, however, well be that both peach and almond are derived
                    from some preexisting and now extinct form whose descendants have spread over
                    the whole geographic area mentioned; but of course this is a mere speculation,
                    though indirect evidence in its support might be obtained from the nectarine, of
                    which no mention is made in ancient literature, and ιvhich, as we have seen,
                    originates from the peach and reproduces itself by seed, thus offering the
                    characteristics of a species in the act of developing itself. (Μ. T. Μ. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
