<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0464-0443-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PEACOCK, George</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 443</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1092555">Reformation</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1092647">Reformers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1078723">Progress</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1012154">Mathematicians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1065224">Planning</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bv7b36b">Reformers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b40r9m368">Algebra</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16x10">Plans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wk9g">Reformation</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47w67b9q">Mathematicians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n464/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PEACOCK, <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi></label>
                    (1791-1858), mathematician, was born at Thornton Hall, Denton, near Darlington,
                    9th April <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n465/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0465-0444"/> 1791. He was educated at Richmond, Yorkshire, and
                    entered Trinity College, Cambridge, in 1809. He was second wrangler in the
                    mathematical tripos of 1812 (Sir J. F. W. Herschel being senior), was elected
                    fellow of his college in 1814, and became assistant tutor and lecturer in 1815,
                    full tutor in 1823, and sole tutor of “his side” in 1835. Peacock distinguished
                    himself by his business capacity, and by his broad views of the duties and
                    functions of the educational institution in whose management he had so large a
                    share.</p>
                <p>Peacock was all his life an ardent educational reformer. While still an
                    undergraduate he formed a league with Herschel, Babbage, and Maule to conduct
                    the famous struggle of “d-ism <hi rend="italic">versus</hi> dot-age,” which
                    ended in the introduction into Cambridge of the Continental notation <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ιn</hi> the infinitesimal calcidus to the exclusion of the
                    fluxional notation (ý) of Newton. This was an important reform, not so much on
                    account of the mere change of notation (for nowadays mathematicians follow
                    Lagrange in using both these notations), but because it signified the opening to
                    the mathematicians of Cambridge of the vast storehouse of Continental
                    discoveries. Up to that time Cambridge mathematicians had been resting supinely
                    under the shadow of Newton, despising the Continental methods, but doing nothing
                    to demonstrate the power of their own. The analytical society thus formed in
                    1813 published various memoirs, and translated Lacroix’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Differential Calculus</hi> in 1816. Peacock powerfully aided the movement by
                    publishing in 1820 <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Examples of the Application
                    of the Differential and Integral Calculus,</hi> which remains a valuable
                    text-book to this day. He also took a great interest in the general question of
                    university education. In 1841 he published a pamphlet on the university
                    statutes, in which he indicated the necessity for reform; and in 1850 and 1855
                    he was a member of the commission of inquiry relative to the university of
                    Cambridge.</p>
                <p>In 1837 he was appointed Lowndean professor of astronomy. In 1839 he took the
                    degree of D.D., and the same year was appointed by Lord Melbourne to the deanery
                    of Ely. Without in any way neglecting his university duties, Peacock threw
                    himself with characteristic ardour into the duties of this new position. He
                    improved the sanitation of Ely, published in 1840 <hi rend="italic">Observations
                    on Plans for Cathedral Reform,</hi> and carried out extensive works of
                    restoration in his own cathedral. He was twice prolocutor of the lower house of
                    convocation for the province of Canterbury.</p>
                <p>This list by no means exhausts the sphere of Peacock’s activity. He was a prime
                    mover in the establishment of the Cambridge Astronomical Observatory, and in the
                    founding of the Cambridge Philosophical Society. He was a fellow of the Royal,
                    Royal Astronomical, Geological, and other scientific societies. In 1838, and
                    again in 1843, he was one of the commissioners for standards of weights and
                    measures; and he also furnished valuable information to the commissioners on
                    decimal coinage, a matter in which he took great interest. He died on the 8th
                    November 1858, before the university commission, in whose work he took so great
                    an'interest, had finished its labours.</p>
                <p>It will excite little surprise that a man of so many occupations should have left
                    more mark upon the men of his own day than upon the science of the succeeding
                    generation. Although Peacock was most distinguished and will be longest
                    remembered as a mathematician, it would be difficult to point to much work of
                    his which is of importance at the present day. His original contributions to
                    mathematical science were concerned chiefly with the philosophy of its first
                    principles. He did good service in systematizing the operational laws of
                    algebra, and in throwing light upon the nature and use of imaginaries. His work
                    in this field was, however, thrown into the shade by the later and
                    farther-reaching discoveries of Hamilton and Grassmann. Two great services he
                    did for mathematical education which deserve especial mention. He published,
                    first in 1830, and then in an enlarged form in 1842, a <hi rend="italic"
                    >Treatise on Algebra,</hi> in which he applied his philosophical ideas
                    concerning algebraical analysis to the elucidation of its elements. This
                    textbook was probably too far ahead of his age, for it does not seem to have
                    come into very general use; at all events, it might with great advantage be
                    studied by the teachers of elementary mathematics at the present day, and is
                    very much superior in method and arrangement to any of the English text-books at
                    present in vogue. The second great service was the publication in the <hi
                    rend="italic">British Association Reports</hi> for 1833 of his “Report on the
                    Recent Progress and Present State of certain branches of Analysis.” English
                    mathematicians of this generation will doubtless find on reading this brilliant
                    summary a good many dicta which they will call in question, and they will see a
                    good deal of evidence that Peacock did not always fully appreciate, or perhaps
                    always quite understand, the work of the foremost Continental mathematicians of
                    his time; but they will be ready to condone these shortcomings when they
                    remember that they were carried on the shoulders of Peacock and his “d-istic
                    league” out of the mire into which English mathematics had fallen, and that it ’
                    is but natural that they should catch a better view of the surrounding scenery
                    than did their bearer. Whatever its defects may be, Peacock’s report remains a
                    work of permanent value, one of the first and one of the best of those valuable
                    summaries of scientific progress which have enriched the annual volumes of the
                    British Association, and which would have justified its existence had it done
                    nothing else for the advancement of science.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
