<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0450-0429-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PAUL of Samosata</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 429</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1939177">Logos</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1023088">Minorities</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1023465">Minors</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n450/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PAUL <hi rend="smallcaps">of Samosata</hi></label>, bishop of
                    Antioch from about 260 A.D., is famous in church history as the author of the
                    last attempt to replace the doctrine of the essential (physical) divinity of
                    Christ by the old view of the human personality of the Redeemer. The effort was
                    not successful even within his own community. At an Oriental general council,
                    held at Antioch as early as the year 264, his teaching was investigated; but no
                    conclusion was come to because it was alleged Paul had been cunning enough to
                    disguise his real opinions. A second synod was equally abortive; but at a third
                    (probably in the year 268), after a discussion between Paul and a presbyter
                    named Mal-chion—a sophist of Antioch, and head of a scholastic institution—the
                    metropolitan was excommunicated and his successor appointed. Under the
                    protection of Zenobia, however, Paul continued in his office for four years
                    longer; and the church of Antioch was split into two factions. In the year 272
                    the city was taken by the emperor Aurelian, who decided in person that the
                    churchbuilding belonged to the bishop who was in epistolary communication with
                    the bishops of Rome and Italy. This decision of course proceeded on political
                    considerations; and indeed it is probable that behind the theological
                    controversy there had been all along a political disagreement, the opponents of
                    Paul being enemies of Zenobia and adherents of the Roman party. About the life
                    of Paul we know scarcely anything. His enemies, indeed, describe him as an
                    unspiritual prelate, an empty preacher, an arrogant man of the world, and a
                    crafty sophist; but this portrait must not be too readily accepted. We are told
                    that he preferred the title of <hi rend="italic">Ducenarius</hi> to that of
                    bishop. This probably implies that he actually was a <hi rend="italic"
                    >procurator</hi><hi rend="italic">ducenarius,</hi> a civil post of considerable
                    dignity, and we may well believe that he was very conscious of his position,
                    maintained its formalities with some pride, and used it to give effect to his
                    peculiar views. As an accomplished theologian he strenuously opposed the old
                    expositors, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> the theologians of Alexandria, and
                    prohibited the use in public worship of all those church hymns in which the
                    essential divinity of Christ found expression.</p>
                <p>His doctrine was no novelty, but merely a development of primitive Christian
                    belief as represented, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> by Hermas, and at a later
                    time by the so-called Alogi in Asia Minor, and the Theodotians and Artemonites
                    in Rome. Even in Syria it was not extinct at the end of the 3d century (see the
                    <hi rend="italic">Acta ArchelaÎ)</hi>; but in the great churches of the
                    empire—especially in the West and in Egypt—the Logos-Christology was already in
                    the ascendant. And, since the previous state of things had passed from memory,
                    it soon came to be regarded as “heresy” and “innovation” to think of Christ as
                    most Christians had thought in the 2d century. It was chiefly Origen and his
                    philosophical disciples, however, who had brought about the victory of the
                    Logos-Christology, and discredited contrary opinions not only as unchurchly but
                    also as unscientific. Thus the undertaking of Paul was no longer in harmony with
                    the times. And yet his much-abused doctrine, as is now more and more clearly
                    perceived, deserves the highest respect, inasmuch as it is an attempt to express
                    the significance of Christ’s person without the aid of cosmology or
                    philosophical theories. The leading outlines of his Christology are as follows.
                    God is to be conceived as one person; from Him, however, there proceeds
                    eternally as <hi rend="italic">force</hi> a Logos <hi rend="italic"
                    >(σοφία),</hi> who may be called “Son.” This Logos worked in the prophets, and
                    at last, in the highest degree and in a unique manner, in Jesus. Jesus is in His
                    own nature a man, originating in time; He is “from beneath.” But, by means of
                    inspiration and indwelling, the divine Logos worked upon Him “from above.” A
                    physical union is out of the question, because the Logos Himself is no <hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> α</hi><hi rend="italic">φυσιςT</hi> To this divine
                    endowment of Jesus corresponds His tried moral perfection. Through the
                    unchangeableness of His mind and will He became like God; through love He became
                    one with Him. For, said Paul, “the only kind of unity which can exist between
                    two persons is that of disposition and direction of will, which comes to pass
                    through love; only that which results from love has value, whatever is physical
                    is worthless.” Thus during all His life the Redeemer moved steadily onward, the
                    Father enabling Him to perform mighty works, and finally He proved His
                    indissoluble union in love with God by His death. As the reward of victory for
                    His love and for His work among men He has received from God the name which is
                    above every name; God has invested Him with divine honour, so that now we may
                    call Him “the God born of the virgin.” Since Jesus was eternally foreordained by
                    God, we may even speak of a pre-existence of Christ; and Paul goes <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n451/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0451-0430"/> so far as to use these words: “By the grace of
                    God, and through progressive development under trial, Christ became God.”</p>
                <p>Although Paul was excommunicated, his teaching did not remain altogether without
                    effect in the church. It had a marked influence on Lucian, and through him on
                    Arianism. But it is in the Christological statements of Theodore of Mopsuestia,
                    of Diodorus, and of Theodoret that we can most clearly recognize the influence
                    of the teaching of Paul of Samosata.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Sources.—</hi> Euseb., <hi rend="italic">H. E.,</hi> vii.
                    27-30. ^Coιnpare also the collection in Routh, <hi rend="italic">Reliη.
                    Sacr.</hi>, iii. pp. 286 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>, 300 <hi rend="italic">sq.,
                    326 sq. Literature. —</hi> Bernhardt, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des röm. Reiches</hi><hi rend="italic">seit dem Tode</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Valerian's,</hi> pp. 170 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> 178 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.,</hi> 306 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>; Hefele, <hi
                    rend="italic">Coηcilieηgesch.,</hi> 2d ed., p. 135; Lipsius, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chronologie der</hi><hi rend="italic">röm.</hi><hi rend="italic">Bischöfe</hi>
                    (1869); Feuerlin, <hi rend="italic">De haeresi Pauli Sam.</hi> (1741); Ehrlich,
                    <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">erroribus</hi><hi rend="italic">Pauli
                    Sam.</hi> (1745); Schwab, <hi rend="italic">Diss, de Pauli Sam. vita</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">atque doctrina</hi> (1839); Harnack, art. “Monarchianismus,” in
                    <hi rend="italic">Realencykl. f. Theol. u.</hi><hi rend="italic">Kirche,</hi> 2d
                    ed., x. p. 178 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> (A. HA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
