<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0918-0248-0231-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PAPYRUS (9th edition, volume 18, page 231)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205480">Niger</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fx74153">Documents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hx15x22">Merovingians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896108">Documentation</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115626">Sheets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n248/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PAPYRUS</label>, the paper reed, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cyperus Papyrus</hi> of Linnaeus, was in ancient times widely cultivated in
                    the Delta of Egypt, where it was used for various purposes, and especially as a
                    writing material. As, however, the plant is now extinct in Lower Egypt, it is
                    believed that it was not indigenous there, but was probably introduced from
                    Nubia, where it is found at the present time, as well as in Abyssinia.
                    Theophrastus <hi rend="italic">(Hist. Plant.,</hi> iv. 10) adds that it likewise
                    grew in Syria; and, according to Pliny, it was also a native plant of the Niger
                    and Euphrates. From one of its ancient Egyptian names, <hi rend="italic"
                        >P-apu,</hi> was derived its Greek title 7rατrυpos, Lat. <hi rend="italic"
                        >papyrus.</hi> By Herodotus it is always called <hi rend="italic"
                        >βυβλoς,</hi> a word which was apparently also of Egyptian origin. The first
                    accurate description of the plant is given by Theophrastus, from whom we learn
                    that it grew in shallows of 2 cubits (about 3 feet) or less, its main root being
                    of the thickness of a man’s wrist, and 10 cubits in length. From this root,
                    which lay horizontally, smaller roots pushed down into the mud, and the stem of
                    the plant sprang up to the height of 4 cubits, being triangular and tapering in
                    form. The tufted head or umbel is likened by Pliny to a thyrsus.</p>
                <p>The various uses to which the papyrus plant was applied are also enumerated by
                    Theophrastus. Of the head nothing could be made but garlands for the shrines of
                    the gods; but the wood of the root was employed in the manufacture of different
                    utensils as well as for fuel. Of the stem of the plant were made boats, sails,
                    mats, cloth, cords, and, above all, writing material (τά <hi rend="italic"
                        >βιβλία).</hi> The pith was also a common article of food, and was eaten
                    both cooked and in its natural state. Herodotus too notices its consumption as
                    food (ii. 92), and incidentally mentions that it provided the material of which
                    the priests’ sandals were made (ii. 37). He likewise refers to the use of byblus
                    as tow for caulking the seams of ships; and the statement of Theophrastus that
                    King Antigonus made the rigging of his fleet of the same material is illustrated
                    by the ship’s cable, <hi rend="italic">oπλov βvβλιvov,</hi> wherewith the doors
                    were fastened when Ulysses slew the suitors in his hall <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Odyss.,</hi> xxi. 390). That the plant was itself used also as the
                    principal material in the construction of light skiffs suitable for the
                    navigation of the pools and shallows of the Nile, and even of the river itself,
                    is shown by sculptures of the period of the fourth dynasty, in which men are
                    represented in the act of building a boat with stems cut from a neighbouring
                    plantation of papyrus (Lepsius, <hi rend="italic">Denkm.,</hi> ii. 12). It is to
                    boats of this description that Isaiah probably refers in the “vessels of
                    bulrushes upon the waters” (xviii. 2). If the Hebrew gome (**pi) also is to be
                    identified with the Egyptian papyrus, something may be said in favour of the
                    tradition that the bulrushes <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n249/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0918-0249-0232"/> of which the ark was composed in which the
                    infant Moses was laid, in the flags by the river’s brink, were in fact the
                    latter plant. Ancient authors have likewise referred to the adaptation of the
                    papyrus to other domestic purposes, both culinary and medicinal. But it seems
                    hardly credible that the <hi rend="italic">Cyperus Papyrus</hi> could alone have
                    sufficed for the many uses to which it is said to have been applied. Wilkinson
                    has pointed out <hi rend="italic">(Anc. Egyptians,</hi> ii. 121) that, the
                    cultivation of this variety being limited to certain districts, where, moreover,
                    it was a monopoly of the Government, it cannot have been employed for so many
                    purposes; and we may therefore conclude that several plants of the genus <hi
                        rend="italic">Cyperus</hi> were comprehended under the head of byblus or
                    papyrus—an opinion which is supported by the words of Strabo, who mentions both
                    inferior and superior qualities. The <hi rend="italic">Cyperus dives</hi> is
                    still grown in Egypt, and is used to this day for many of the purposes named by
                    ancient writers.</p>
                <p>The widespread use of papyrus as a writing material throughout the ancient world
                    is attested by early writers, and by documents and sculptures. In addition to
                    the names of the plant, which were also applied to the material, the latter was
                    also known as χάρτας, <hi rend="italic">charta.</hi> Papyrus rolls are
                    represented in ancient Egyptian wall-paintings; and extant examples of the rolls
                    themselves are sufficiently numerous. The most ancient of these, known, from the
                    name of its former owner, as the Prisse papyrus, and now preserved at Paris,
                    contains a work composed in the reign of a king of the fifth dynasty, and is
                    computed to be itself of the age of upwards of 2000 years B.c. The papyri
                    discovered in Egypt have generally been found in tombs, and in the hands, or
                    swathed with the bodies, of mummies. The ritual of the dead, which in its
                    entirety or in an abridged form was buried with every person of consequence from
                    the eighteenth dynasty to the Roman period, is most frequently the subject. And,
                    besides the ritual and religious rolls, there are the hieratic, civil and
                    literary, documents, and the demotic and enchorial papyri, relating generally to
                    sales of property. Coptic papyri usually contain Biblical or religious tracts or
                    monastic deeds.</p>
                <p>The early use of papyrus among the Greeks is proved by the reference of Herodotus
                    (v. 58) to its introduction among the lonians. An inscription of 407 B.c.
                    records the sale of two sheets (χάρται δυο) at Athens, for two drachmas and four
                    obols. Greek papyri have been found in Egypt of great importance both for their
                    palaeographical and literary worth. The first instalment which came to light, as
                    late as the year 1778, consisted of some fifty rolls, which were discovered in
                    the neighbourhood of Memphis; but all, with one single exception, were
                    carelessly destroyed. More fortunate were the documents found near the Serapeum
                    of Memphis, and connected with that temple; and further discoveries of valuable
                    texts of Homer, Hyperides, and other classical writers have rewarded later
                    searches (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Palaeography).</hi> The numerous rolls found
                    in the ruins of Herculaneum generally contain the less interesting works of
                    writers of the Epicurean school.</p>
                <p>Papyrus also made its way into Italy, but at how early a period there is nothing
                    to show. Under the empire its use must have been extensive, for not only was it
                    required for the production of books, but it was also universally employed for
                    domestic purposes, correspondence, and legal documents. So indispensable did it
                    become that it is reported that in the reign of Tiberius the scarcity and
                    dearness of the material, caused by a failure of the papyrus crop, nearly
                    brought on a riot (Pliny, <hi rend="italic">N.</hi><hi rend="italic">II.</hi>,
                    xiii. 13).</p>
                <p>The account which Pliny (A <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                        >H.,</hi> xiii. 11-13) has transmitted to us of the manufacture of the
                    writing material from the papyrus plant should be taken strictly to refer to the
                    process followed in his own time; but, with some differences in details, the
                    same general method of treatment had doubtlessly been practised from time
                    immemorial. His text, however, is so confused, both from obscurity of style and
                    from corruptions in the MSS., that there is much difference of opinion as to the
                    meaning of many words and phrases employed in his narrative, and their
                    application in particular points of detail. In one important particular,
                    however, affecting the primary construction of the material, there can no longer
                    be any doubt. The old idea that it was made from layers or pellicules growing
                    between the rind and a central stalk has been abandoned, as it has been proved
                    that the plant, like other reeds, contains only a cellular pith within the rind.
                    The stem was in fact cut into longitudinal strips for the purpose of being
                    converted into the writing material, those from the centre of the plant being
                    the broadest and most valuable. The strips <hi rend="italic">(philyrae),</hi>
                    which were cut with a sharp knife or some such instrument, were laid on a board
                    side by side to the required width, thus forming a layer <hi rend="italic"
                        >(scheda),</hi> across which another layer of shorter strips was laid at
                    right angles. The two layers thus “woven ”—Pliny uses the word <hi rend="italic"
                        >texere</hi> in describing this part of the process—formed a sheet <hi
                        rend="italic">(plagula,</hi> or net), which was then soaked in water of the
                    Nile. The mention of a particular water has caused trouble to the commentators.
                    Some have supposed that certain chemical properties of which the Nile water was
                    possessed acted as a glue or cement to cause the two layers to adhere; others,
                    with more reason, that glutinous matter contained in the material itself was
                    solved by the action of water, whether from the Nile or any other source; and
                    others again read in Pliny’s words an implication that a paste was actually
                    used. Be this as it may, the sheet was finally pressed and dried in the sun. Any
                    roughness was levelled by polishing with ivory or a smooth shell. But the
                    material was also subject to other defects, such as moisture lurking between the
                    layers, which might be detected by strokes of the mallet; spots or stains; and
                    spongy strips <hi rend="italic">(taeniae),</hi> in which the ink would run and
                    spoil the sheet. When such faults occurred, the papyrus must be re-made. To form
                    a roll the sheets were joined together with paste (glue being too hard), but not
                    more than twenty sheets in a roll <hi rend="italic">(scapus).</hi> As, however,
                    there are still extant rolls consisting of more than the prescribed number of
                    sheets, either the reading of <hi rend="italic">vicenae</hi> is corrupt, or the
                    number was not constant in all times. The best sheet formed the first or outside
                    sheet of the roll, and the others were joined on in order of quality, so that
                    the worst sheets were in the centre of the roll. This arrangement was adopted,
                    not for the purpose of fraudulently selling bad material under cover of the
                    better exterior, but in order that the outside of the roll should be composed of
                    that which would best stand wear and tear. Besides, in case of the entire roll
                    not being filled with the text, the unused and inferior sheets at the end could
                    be better spared, and so might be cut off.</p>
                <p>The different kinds of papyrus writing material and their dimensions are also
                    enumerated by Pliny. The best quality, formed from the middle and broadest
                    strips of the plant, was originally named <hi rend="italic">hieratica,</hi> but
                    afterwards, in flattery of the emperor Augustus, it was called, after him, <hi
                        rend="italic">Augzιsta</hi>; and the <hi rend="italic">charta Livia,</hi> or
                    second quality, was so named in honour of his wife. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >hieratica</hi> thus descended to the third rank. The first two were 13
                    digiti, or about 9⅜ inches in width; the <hi rend="italic">hieratica,</hi> 11
                    digiti or 8 inches. Next came the <hi rend="italic">charta</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >amphitheatrica,</hi> named after the principal place of its manufacture,
                    the amphitheatre of Alexandria, of 9 αigiti or 6⅜ inches wide. The <hi
                        rend="italic">charta Fanniana</hi> appears to have been a kind of papyrus
                    worked up from the <hi rend="italic">amphitheatrica,</hi> which by flattening
                    and other methods was increased in width by an inch, in the factory of a certain
                    Fannius at Rome. The <hi rend="italic">Saitica,</hi> which took its name from
                    the city of Sais, and w’as probably of 8 digiti or 5∣ inches, was of a common
                    description. The <hi rend="italic">Taeniotica,</hi> named apparently from the
                    place of its manufacture, a tongue of land (ταi∣dα) near Alexandria, was sold by
                    weight, and was of <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n250/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0918-0250-0233"/> uncertain width, perhaps from 4∣ to 5 inches.
                    And lastly there was the common packing-paper, the <hi rend="italic">charta
                        emporetica,</hi> of 6 digiti or <hi rend="italic">4</hi> j inches. Isidore
                        <hi rend="italic">(Etymol.,</hi> vi. 10) mentions yet another kind, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Corneliana,</hi> first made under C. Cornelius Gallus, prefect
                    of Egypt, which, however, may have ×been the same as the <hi rend="italic"
                        >amphitheatrica</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Fanniana.</hi> The name of the man
                    who had incurred the anger of Augustus may have been suppressed by the same
                    influence that expunged the episode of Gallus from the Fourth Géorgie (Birt, <hi
                        rend="italic">Antik. Buchwesen,</hi> p. 250). In the reign of the emperor
                    Claudius also another kind was introduced and entitled <hi rend="italic"
                        >Claudia.</hi> It had been found by experience that the <hi rend="italic"
                        >charta</hi><hi rend="italic">Aτιgusta</hi> was, from its fineness and
                    porous nature, ill suited for literary use; it was accordingly reserved for
                    correspondence only, and for other purposes was replaced by the new paper. The
                        <hi rend="italic">charta</hi><hi rend="italic">Claudia</hi> was made from a
                    composition of the first and second qualities, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Augusta,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Livia,</hi> a layer of the former
                    being backed with one of the latter; and the sheet was increased to nearly a
                    foot in width. The largest of all, however, was the <hi rend="italic"
                        >macrocollon,</hi> probably of good quality and equal to the hieratic, and a
                    cubit or nearly 18 inches wide. It was used by Cicero <hi rend="italic">(Epp. ad
                        Attic.,</hi> xiii. 25; xvi. 3). The width, however, proved inconvenient, and
                    the broad sheet was liable to injury by tearing.</p>
                <p>An interesting question arises as to the accuracy of the different measurements
                    given by Pliny. His figures regarding the width of the different kinds of papyri
                    have generally been understood to concern the width (or height) of the rolls, as
                    distinguished from their length. It has, however, been observed that in practice
                    the width of extant rolls does not tally in any satisfactory degree with Pliny’s
                    measurements; and a more plausible explanation has been lately offered (Birt,
                        <hi rend="italic">Antik. Buchwesen,</hi> pp. 251 <hi rend="italic"
                        >sq.</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> y</hi><hi rend="italic">)</hi> that
                    the breadth (not height) of the individual sheets of which the rolls aι½
                    composed is referred to.</p>
                <p>The first sheet of a roll was named <hi rend="italic">πρωτόκολΚον</hi>; the last,
                        <hi rend="italic">iσχaτoκoKKιov.</hi> Under the Romans, the former bore the
                    name of the comes largitionum, who had control of the manufacture, with the date
                    and name of place. It was the practice to cut away the portion thus marked; but
                    in case of legal documents this mutilation was forbidden by the laws of
                    Justinian. On the Arab conquest of Egypt in the 7th century, the manufacture was
                    continued, with the substitution of Arabic in marking the protocol. An instance
                    of one of these Arab signatures is preserved in a bull of Pope John VIII. of the
                    year 876.</p>
                <p>Varro’s statement, repeated by Pliny, that papyrus was first made in Alexander’s
                    time, should probably be taken to mean that its manufacture, which till then had
                    been a Government monopoly, was relieved from all restrictions. It is not
                    probable, however, that it was ever manufactured from the native plant anywhere
                    but in Egypt. At Rome there was certainly some kind of industry in papyrus, the
                        <hi rend="italic">charta Fanniana,</hi> already referred to, being an
                    instance in illustration. But it seems probable that this industry was confined
                    to the re-making of material imported into Italy, as in the case of the <hi
                        rend="italic">charta</hi><hi rend="italic">Claudia.</hi> This second
                    manufacture, however, is thought to have been detrimental to the papyrus, as it
                    would then have been in a dried condition requiring artificial aids, such as a
                    more liberal use of gum or paste, in the process. The more brittle condition of
                    the Latin papyri found at Herculaneum has been instanced as the evil result of
                    this re-making of the material.</p>
                <p>According to Strabo the Romans obtained the papyrus plant from Lake Trasimene and
                    other lakes of Etruria, but this statement is unsupported by any other authority
                    and appears to have been made in error. At a later period, however, a papyrus
                    was cultivated in Sicily, which has been identified by Pariatore with the Syrian
                    variety <hi rend="italic">(Cyperus syriacus'),</hi> far exceeding in height the
                    Egyptian plant, and having a more drooping head. It grew in the east and south
                    of the island, where it was probably introduced during the Arab occupation. It
                    was seen in the 10th century, by the Arab traveller Ibn-Haukal, in the
                    neighbourhood of Palermo, where it throve luxuriantly in the pools of the
                    Papireto, a stream to which it lent its name. From it paper was made for the
                    sultan’s use. But in the 13th century it began to fail, and in 1591 the drying
                    up of the Papireto caused the extinction of the plant in that district. It is
                    still to be seen at Syracuse, but it was probably transplanted thither at a
                    later time, and reared only as a curiosity, as there is no notice of it to be
                    found previous to 1674. It is with this Syracusan plant that some attempts have
                    been made in recent years to manufacture a writing material similar to ancient
                    papyrus.</p>
                <p>Even after the introduction of vellum, papyrus still continued in use among the
                    Romans, and was not entirely superseded until a late date. It ceased, however,
                    to be used for books sooner than for documents. In the 5th century St Augustine
                    apologizes for sending a letter written on vellum instead of the more usual
                    substance, papyrus <hi rend="italic">(Ep.</hi> xv.); and Cassiodorus <hi
                        rend="italic">(Farr.,</hi> xi. 38), writing in the 6th century, indulges in
                    a high-flown panegyric on the plant and its value, and refers to the abolition
                    of the tax on paper by the emperor Theodoric. Of mediaeval Greek papyri a very
                    few remains containing Biblical or patristic matter have survived, and one or
                    two fragments of Graeco-Latin glossaries have been published. Of Greek
                    documents, apart from monastic deeds discovered in Egypt, there are two which
                    are well known, viz., the fragmentary epistle of Constantine V. to Pepin le
                    Bref, of 753 or 756, now preserved at Paris, and the papyrus containing the
                    subscriptions to the council of Constantinople of 680, at Vienna. Mediaeval
                    Latin MSS. on papyrus in book form are still extant in different libraries of
                    Europe, viz.:—the Homilies of St Avitus, of the 6th century, at Paris; Sermons
                    and Epistles of St Augustine, of the 6th or 7th century, at Paris and Geneva;
                    works of Hilary, of the 6th century, at Vienna; fragments of the Digests, of the
                    6th century, at Pommersfeld; the Antiquities of Josephus, of the 7th century, at
                    Milan; Isidore, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Contemptu</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Mundi,</hi> of the 7th century, at St Gall; and the Register
                    of the Church of Ravenna, of the 10th century, at Munich. Of Latin documents on
                    papyrus <hi rend="italic">(tomus</hi> was the technical word of the Middle Ages
                    to designate such a document), the first to be mentioned are the fragments of
                    two imperial rescripts addressed to an official in Egypt in the 5th century. The
                    employment of this material in Italy for legal purposes is sufficiently
                    illustrated by the large number of documents which were preserved at Ravenna,
                    and date from the 5th to the 10th century. In the papal chancery too it was used
                    at an early date, evidence of its presence there being found in the biography of
                    Gregory I. But of the extant papal deeds the earliest to which an authentic date
                    can be attached is a bull of Stephen III. of the year 757, while the latest
                    appears to be one of 1004. There is evidence to show that in the 10th century
                    papyrus was used, to the exclusion of other materials, in papal deeds. In France
                    it was a common writing substance in the 6th century (Gregory of Tours, <hi
                        rend="italic">Hist. Franc.,</hi> V. 5). Of the Merovingian period there are
                    still extant several papyrus deeds, the earliest of the year 625, the latest of
                    692. Under Charlemagne and his successors it was not used. By the 12th century
                    the manufacture of papyrus had entirely ceased, as appears from a note by
                    Eustathius in his commentary on the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey,</hi> xxi.
                    390.</p>
                <p>See Melch. Guilandino’s commentary on the chapters of Pliny relating to papyrus,
                        <hi rend="italic">Papyrus, hoc</hi><hi rend="italic">est Commentarius,</hi>
                    &lt;fcc., Venice, 1572; Montfaucon, “Dissertation sur la plante appellée
                    Papyrus,’’ in the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi><hi rend="italic">de Γ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Académie</hi><hi rend="italic">des Inscriptions,</hi> 1729,
                    pp. 592-608; T. C. Tychsen, “DeChartae Papyraceae in Europa per medium aevum
                    usu,” in the <hi rend="italic">Comment. Soc. Reg.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Scient.</hi><hi rend="italic">Gottin&lt;</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                        j</hi><hi rend="italic">ensis,</hi> 1820, pp. 141-208; Dureau de la Malle,
                    “Mémoire sur le Papyrus,” in the <hi rend="italic">Mém.</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                        Γ</hi><hi rend="italic">Institut,</hi> 1851, pp. 140-183; Ph. Pariatore,
                    “Mémoire sur le Papyrus des anciens,” &amp;c., in the <hi rend="italic">Mém. à
                        VAcad, des</hi><hi rend="italic">Sei.,</hi> 1854, pp. 469 502; Bliimner, <hi
                        rend="italic">Technologie</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Terminologie</hi><hi rend="italic">der Gewerbe und Künste bei Griechen und
                        Römern,</hi> Leipsic, 1875, i. pp. 308-327; Ces. Paoli, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Del Papiro,</hi> Florence, 1878. See also W. Wattenbach, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Das Schriftwesen im Mittelalter,</hi> Leipsic, 1875, pp. 80-91; and T.
                    Birt, <hi rend="italic">Das antike Buchwesen,</hi> Berlin, 1882, pp. 223-273.
                    (E. Μ. T.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
