<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0429-0408-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PATMOS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 408</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1159314">Turkeys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1093581">Relationism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:917055">Evangelists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4222rc91">Turkey</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bk43">Levant</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n429/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PATMOS</label> (now pronounced by the natives “Patino”), an
                    island in the east of the Aegean Sea, one of the group of the Sporades, about 28
                    miles south-south-west of Samos. It lies in 37° 20' N. lat and 26° 35' E. long.
                    Its greatest length from north to south is about 10 miles, its greatest breadth
                    6, its circumference, owing to the winding nature of the coast, about 37. The
                    island, which is volcanic, is bare and rocky throughout; the hills, of which the
                    highest rises to about 950 feet, command magnificent views of the neighbouring
                    sea and islands. The woods which once covered the island have disappeared; of
                    the palms, from which it formerly received its Italian name of Palmessa, not
                    more than one is left. Some poor olive trees and a few specimens of the
                    mulberry, the fig, the orange, the lemon, the carob, the cypress, the oak, and
                    the pine here and there refresh by their verdure an eye wearied by the prospect
                    of barren mountains, only relieved in places by scrubby bushes or clumps of
                    thyme. The skill of the natives as seamen is proverbial in the archipelago. The
                    deeply-indented coast, here falling in huge cliffs sheer into the sea, there
                    retiring to form a beach and a harbour, is favourable to commerce, as in former
                    times it was to piracy. Of the numerous bays and harbours the chief is that of
                    La Scala, which, running far into the land on the eastern side, divides the
                    island into two nearly equal portions, a northern and a southern. A narrow
                    isthmus separates La Scala from the Bay of Merika on the west coast. Ón the belt
                    of land between the two bays, at the junction between the northern and southern
                    half of the island, stood the ancient town. To judge from its traces, it may
                    have contained 12,000 to 13,000 inhabitants. On the hill above are still to be
                    seen the massive remains of the citadel, built partly in the polygonal style
                    known as Cyclopean. The modern town stands on a hill-top in the southern half of
                    the island. A steep paved road leads to it in about twenty minutes from the port
                    of La Scala. The town clusters at the foot of the monastery of St John, which,
                    crowning the hill with its towers and battlements, resembles a fortress rather
                    than a monastery. Of the 600 MSS. once possessed by the library of the monastery
                    only 240 are left, badly preserved, and none of them of value. The houses of the
                    town are better built than those of the neighbouring islands, but the streets
                    are narrow and winding. The population is about 4000. The port of La Scala
                    contains about 140 houses, besides some old well-built magazines and some
                    potteries. Scattered over the island are about 300 chapels.</p>
                <p>Patmos is mentioned first by Thucydides (iii. 33) and afterwards by Strabo and
                    Pliny. From an inscription it has been inferred that the name was originally
                    Patnos. There are some grounds for the conjecture that the island was first
                    colonized by Carians. Another ancient inscription seems to show that the Ionians
                    also settled there at an early date. The chief, indeed the only, title of the
                    island to fame is that it was the place of banishment of St John the Evangelist,
                    who according to Jerome <hi rend="italic">{De Ser. III.,</hi> c. 9) and others,
                    was exiled thither under Domitian in 95 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> and
                    released about eighteen months afterwards under Nerva. Here he is said to have
                    written the Apocalypse; to the left of the road from La Scala to the town, about
                    half-way up the hill, a grotto is still shown (rð <hi rend="italic">στrη</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">aιov τηs</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">Aπoκaλυψeωs)</hi> in which the apostle is
                    said to have received the heavenly vision. It is reached through a small chapel
                    dedicated to St Anne. In the library of the monastery there is a Greek MS.
                    containing a curious history of St John, purporting to be by Prochorus, one of
                    his disciples but apparently composed in the 4th century. It narrates the
                    miracles wrought by the apostle during his stay on the island, but, strangely
                    enough, while describing how the Gospel was revealed to him in Patmos, it does
                    not so much as mention the Apocalypse. During the Dark Ages Patmos seems to have
                    been entirely deserted, probably on account of the pirates. In 1088 the emperor
                    Alexis Comnenus, by a golden bull, which is still preserved, granted the island
                    to St Christodulus for the purpose of founding a monastery. This was the origin
                    of the monastery of St John, which now owns the greater part of the southern
                    half of Patmos, as well as farms in Crete, Samos, and other neighbouring
                    islands. The embalmed body of the saintly founder is to be seen to this day in a
                    side chapel of the church. The number of the monks, which amounted to over a
                    hundred at the beginning of last century, is now much reduced. The abbot <hi
                    rend="italic">(hγotμevos)</hi> has the rank of a bishop, and is subject only to
                    the patriarch of Constantinople. There is a school in connexion with the
                    monastery which formerly enjoyed a high reputation in the Levant. The lay
                    population was originally confined by St Christodulus to the northern part of
                    the island, but at the beginning of the 13th century the people received
                    permission to build their houses near the monastery for protection against the
                    pirates. Hence arose the modern town. It was recruited by refugees from
                    Constantinople in 1453, and from Crete in 1669, when these places fell into the
                    hands of the Turks. The trade of the island seems to have been considerable. It
                    was in intercourse with Genoa and Venice that the port received its modern name
                    of La Scala; its ancient name seems to have been Phora. The island is subject to
                    Turkey; the governor is the pasha of Rhodes. The population is Greek. The women,
                    who are handsome, are chiefly engaged in knitting cotton stockings, which, along
                    with some pottery, form the chief exports of the island.</p>
                <p>See Tournefort, <hi rend="italic">Relation d'un Voyage du Levant,</hi> Lyons,
                    1717; Kal pole, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> (relating to Turkey), London,
                    1820; Ross, <hi rend="italic">Reisen auf den griechischen Inseln,</hi> Stuttgart
                    and Halle, 1840-52; and especially Guérin, <hi rend="italic">Description de
                    l'∏e</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Patmos,</hi> Paris,
                    1856.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
