<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0547-0522-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PERCY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 522</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198938">Rebellion</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:824307">Avars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1066938">Play</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n547/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PERCY</label>. This family, whose deeds are so prominent in
                    English history, claimed descent from one Manfred de Perci, who was said to have
                    come out of Denmark into Normandy before the adventure of the famous Rollo. But
                    it is more certain that two brothers, William and Serio de Percy, came into
                    England with William the Conqueror, who endowed his namesake the elder with vast
                    possessions in Hampshire, Lincolnshire, and Yorkshire, among which were
                    Topcliffe in the North Riding and Spofforth in the West Riding, the principal
                    seats of the family for many ages afterwards. This William deserves special
                    notice besides, since he refounded the noble abbey of Whitby, which had been
                    destroyed by the Danes,—obtaining a grant of the lordship from Hugh, earl of
                    Chester. Yet his piety would seem to have been of a rather unsteadfast
                    character, for, having endowed the abbey with certain lands, he resumed them in
                    order to reward a faithful dependant, till his brother Serio, the abbot,
                    complained to King William, and caused him to make restitution.</p>
                <p>The family, however, did not really descend in a direct male line from this
                    William; for in the reign of Henry II. his male descendants became extinct, and
                    the inheritance was divided for a time between two sisters, though by failure of
                    issue of one of them it was reunited in the next generation. Agnes, the sister
                    from whom all the subsequent Percies were descended, accepted as her husband
                    Josceline, a son of Geoffrey, duke of Louvain, on the express condition that he
                    and his posterity should bear the surname of Percy, and assume the arms of her
                    family, relinquishing their own. This Josceline was a brother of Adelais or
                    Alice of Louvain, the second queen of Henry I., and by an arrangement with his
                    sister, confirmed by Henry II. when duke of Normandy, he became possessed of the
                    honour of Petworth in Sussex. He was also castellan at Arundel, and held several
                    other important posts in the south of England. His son Richard and Richard’s son
                    William were among the barons who rose in arms against John and Henry III.
                    respectively; but the grandson made his peace with his sovereign, and had his
                    lands restored to him. It should be remarked, however, as a feature of the
                    times, that Richard de Percy was not the eldest but the youngest son of
                    Josceline, and that, according to modern notions, he was really a usurper, who
                    occupied the inheritance of a nephew; his right, however, passed undisputed. He
                    was one of the twenty-five barons appointed to enforce the observance of Magna
                    Charta.</p>
                <p>The next important member of the family is Henry de Percy, whom Edward I., after
                    the deposition of John Baliol, appointed governor of Galloway, and who was one
                    of his most active agents in the subjugation of Scotland, till the success of
                    Robert Bruce drove him out of Turnberry Castle, and made him withdraw into
                    England. He was rewarded by Edward II. with the barren title of earl of Carrick,
                    declared to be forfeited by the Scottish hero; and the same king appointed him
                    governor of the castles of Bamborough and Scarborough. But he himself made his
                    position strong in the north of England by purchasing lands from Anthony Beck,
                    bishop of Durham, among which was the honour of Alnwick, the principal seat of
                    the family ever since. His son, another Henry, took part in the league against
                    Edward H.’s favourites the Despensers, was in favour with Edward III., and
                    obtained from Edward Baliol as king of Scotland grants of Lochmaben, Annandale,
                    and Moffatdale, which he surrendered to the English king for the castle and
                    constableship of Jedburgh or Jed-worth, with the forest of Jed worth and some
                    neighbouring towns. A few years later, in fuller recompense of the unprofitable
                    gift of Baliol, a grant of 500 marks a year was made to him out of the old
                    customs at Berwick; and in 1346 he did splendid service to his sovereign by
                    defeating and taking prisoner David, king of Scotland, at the battle of
                    Neville’s Cross.</p>
                <p>To him succeeded another Henry Percy, a feudal baron like his predecessors, who
                    fought at Crécy during his father’s lifetime; and to him another Henry, λvho was
                    made earl of Northumberland at the coronation of Richard II. It may be remarked
                    incidentally that the succession of the name of Henry in this family is
                    altogether extraordinary. Eor three generations before this first earl of <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n548/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0548-0523"/> Northumberland, and for five different descents
                    after him (making altogether a period of 238 years), the head of the house
                    invariably was a Henry. Such a remarkable continuance of a single Christian name
                    would have been less surprising in later and more peaceful times, when we might
                    reasonably have expected the eldest born to succeed his father quietly through
                    many generations. But the first four earls of this family were all slain in
                    battle or in civil tumult, and the heir-apparent of the first, a Henry like the
                    rest, was cut off in the same way during his father’s lifetime. Was it that the
                    incessant activity due to Border raids and moonlight expeditions created in
                    these men a physical vigour of constitution which protected them to a large
                    extent against disease and infirmity <hi rend="italic">1</hi></p>
                <p>The first earl of Northumberland, certainly, had led a busy life enough, not only
                    on the Borders but elsewhere. He had been in the French wars of Edward III.; he
                    had been at times a warden of the marches against Scotland, or a commissioner to
                    treat for peace with that country. He had ravaged the lands of the earl of
                    Dunbar and had won Berwick. Powerful in the south as well as in the north, he
                    was the Lord Henry Percy who protected Wickliffe when cited before the
                    archbishop at St Paul’s. As earl of Northumberland he exhibited his independence
                    of Richard II. in a way characteristic of a northern baron. Sent for to court,
                    he neglected to come, was disgraced and banished, and thereupon fled to
                    Scotland. He repaired to Henry of Lancaster soon after his landing at Ravenspur,
                    and helped treacherously to decoy Richard II. into his hands at Conway.
                    Naturally he received great honour from Henry after he had become king. He was
                    made constable of England for life, and received a gift of the Isle of Man and a
                    number of important offices in Cheshire, Wales, and the borders of Scotland. He
                    was even appointed one of the commissioners for the marriage of the king’s
                    daughter Blanche with Louis, duke of Bavaria; and for the first three years of
                    the reign both he and his family seemed faithful to the new dynasty which they
                    had greatly helped to establish. In 1402 he and his brave son Henry, the
                    celebrated Hotspur, won the battle of Homildon Hill and took the earl of Douglas
                    prisoner. But immediately afterwards Harry Hotspur, whose character is so well
                    known through Shakespeare’s play of <hi rend="italic">Henry the Fourth,</hi>
                    resenting the king’s injustice to his brother-in-law, Sir Edmund Mortimer, who
                    had been taken prisoner by the Welsh, and whom Henry, for reasons of policy,
                    declined to ransom, entered into a league with Owen Glendower, in whose custody
                    Mortimer was, for a combined Avar against the king.</p>
                <p>The whole family of the Percies seem to have felt that their services to Henry of
                    Lancaster were ill requited. The earl himself joined the conspiracy. His brother
                    Thomas Percy, earl of Worcester (so created by Richard II. ), stood also to all
                    appearance in high favour with the king, who had entrusted him with the care of
                    his son Henry, prince of Wales. But he suddenly left the court and joined his
                    nephew in the north, both sending forth proclamations and raising the country.
                    The rebellion was crushed in the battle of Shrewsbury (1403), in which Hotspur
                    was slain, and the earl of Worcester was beheaded just after the fight, while
                    Northumberland was marching southwards to join with them. Having taken no active
                    part in the movement, the earl pretended that he had really been going to assist
                    the king, and had wished to avert hostilities. He afterwards went peaceably to
                    the king at York, and was placed in custody; but such was his power and
                    influence that next year he was acquitted of treason in full parliament, and had
                    all his honours and possessions restored to him. All confidence, however,
                    between him and the king was at an end, and in 1405 he joined the insurrection
                    of Archbishop Scrope, who, after being beheaded as a rebel, was venerated as a
                    martyr over the whole north of England. Then he fled to Scotland, aftenvards to
                    Wales, and in the end, returning to his own country, perished in a new rebellion
                    at Bramham Moor.</p>
                <p>The title and estates were thus forfeited. But, by an act no less gracious than
                    politic, Henry V. restored them to this earl’s grandson, then a prisoner with
                    the Scots, whose liberation he had no difficulty in procuring from the duke of
                    Albany during the time of James I.’s captivity. From that day the loyalty of the
                    family to the house of Lancaster was steadfast and undeviating. The second earl
                    died fighting for Henry VI. at the first battle of St Albans in 1455; the third
                    was slain in the bloody field of Towton (1461); the fourth was killed in
                    quelling an insurrection in the time of Henry VII. So strong was the Lancastrian
                    feeling of the family that even Sir Ralph Percy, a brother of the earl who fell
                    at Towton, though he had actually submitted once to Edward IV., turned again,
                    and when he fell at Hedgley Moor consoled himself with the thought that he had,
                    as he phrased it, “saved the bird in his bosom.”</p>
                <p>No wonder, then, that in Edward IV.’s days the title and estates of the family
                    were for a time taken away and given to Lord Montagu, brother of Warwick the
                    kingmaker. But the north was so accustomed to the rule of the Percies that in a
                    few years Edward saw the necessity of restoring them, and did so even at the
                    cost of alienating still further the powerful family of the Nevilles, who were
                    then already on the point of rebellion.</p>
                <p>A crisis occurred in the fortunes of the family in the reign of Henry VIII. on
                    the death of the sixth earl, whose two brothers, much against his will, had
                    taken part in the great insurrection called the “Pilgrimage of Grace.” A
                    thriftless man, of whom it is recorded that in his youth he was smitten with the
                    charms of Anne Boleyn, but was forced to give her up and marry a woman he did
                    not love, he died, childless, after selling many of the family estates and
                    granting the others to the king. The title was forfeited, and was granted by
                    Edward VI. to the ambitious Dudley, earl of Warwick, who was attainted in the
                    succeeding reign. It was restored in the days of Queen Elizabeth to Thomas
                    Percy, who, being a staunch Catholic, was one of the three earls who took the
                    lead in the celebrated “Rising in the North,” and was beheaded at York. His
                    brother Henry, who succeeded him, was no less unhappy. Involved in Throgmorton’s
                    conspiracy, he was committed to the Tower, and was supposed to have shot himself
                    in bed with a pistol found beside him; but there were grave suspicions that it
                    had been discharged by another hand. His son, the next earl, suffered like his
                    two predecessors for his attachment to the religion of his forefathers. The
                    crown lawyers sought in vain to implicate him in the Gunpowder Plot; but he was
                    imprisoned for fifteen years in the Tower and compelled to pay a fine of
                    £30,000. The son who next succeeded was a Parliamentary general in the Civil
                    War. At length, in 1670, the male line of this illustrious family became
                    extinct, just five hundred years after the marriage of Agnes de Percy with
                    Josceline of Louvain.</p>
                <p>Not one of the English noble houses is so distinguished as the Percies throughout
                    the whole range of English history. It is remarkable alike for its long unbroken
                    line, its high achievements, its general culture of arts and of letters.
                    Pre-eminent also, as remarked by Sir Harris Nicolas, for its alliances among the
                    peerage, it continues to this day, though represented once more by a female
                    branch. The present dukedom of Northumberland was created in 1766 in the family
                    of Smithson, who assumed the name of Percy and have borne it ever since. Sir
                    Hugh Smithson, who became the first duke, married a granddaughter of a daughter
                    of the last earl. <hi rend="smallcaps">(j. ga.)</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n549/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0549-0524"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
