<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0509-0488-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PENATES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 488</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cp19">Food</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892p9k">Spiritism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916316">Etruscans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:953769">Hearths</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:930458">Food</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:987926">Kitchens</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:820725">Atriums</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1117849">Shrines</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n509/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PENATES</label>, Roman gods of the store-room and kitchen,
                    derived their name from <hi rend="italic">penus,</hi> “eatables, food.” The
                    store-room over which they presided was, in old times, beside the <hi
                    rend="italic">atrium,</hi> the room which served as kitchen, parlour, and
                    bedroom in one; but in later times the storeroom was in the back part of the
                    house. It was sanctified by the presence of the Penates, and none but pure and
                    chaste persons might enter it, just as with the Hindus the kitchen is sacred and
                    inviolable. The family hearth, which anciently stood in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >atrium,</hi> was their altar; on it were placed their images, two in number,
                    for the Penates were always in pairs—the name does not occur in the
                    singular.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n510/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0510-0489"/>
                <p>They had no individual names, but were always known under the general
                    designation, Penates. Closely associated with the Penates were the Lares,
                    another species of domestic deity, who seem to have been the deified spirits of
                    deceased ancestors (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Lares).</hi> But while each family
                    had two Penates it had but one Lar. In the household shrine the image of the Lar
                    (dressed in a toga) was placed between the two images of the Penates, which were
                    represented as dancing and elevating a drinking-horn in token of joy and plenty.
                    The three images together were sometimes called Penates, sometimes Lares, and
                    either name was used metaphorically for “home.” The shrine stood originally in
                    the <hi rend="italic">•atrium,</hi> but when the hearth and the kitchen were
                    separated from the <hi rend="italic">atrium</hi> and removed to the back of the
                    house, and meals were taken in an upper story, the position of the shrine was
                    also shifted. In the houses at Pompeii it is sometimes in the kitchen, sometimes
                    in the rooms. In the later empire it was placed behind the house-door, and a
                    taper or lamp was kept burning before it. But the worship in the interior of the
                    house was also kept up even into Christian times; it was forbidden by an
                    ordinance of Theodosius (392 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.).</hi> The old Roman
                    used, in company with his children and slaves, to offer a morning sacrifice and
                    prayer to his household gods. Before meals the blessing of the gods was asked,
                    and after the meal, but before dessert, there was a short silence, and a portion
                    of food was placed on the hearth and burned. If the hearth and the images were
                    not in the eating-room, either the images were brought and put on the table, or
                    before the shrine was placed a table on which were set a salt-cellar, food, and
                    a burning lamp. Three days in the month, viz., the Calends, Nones, and Ides <hi
                    rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> the first, the fifth or seventh, and the thirteenth or
                    fifteenth), were set apart for special family worship, as were also the <hi
                    rend="italic">Caristia</hi> (2 2d February) and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Saturnalia</hi> in December. On these days as well as on such occasions as
                    birthdays, marriages, and safe returns from journeys, the images were crowned
                    and offerings made to them of cakes, honey, wine, incense, and sometimes a pig.
                    As each family had its own Penates, so the state, as a collection of families,
                    had its public Penates. Intermediate between the worship of the public and
                    private Penates were probably the rites <hi rend="italic">(sacra)</hi> observed
                    by each clan <hi rend="italic">(gens)</hi> or collection of families supposed to
                    be descended from a common ancestor. The other towns of Latium had their public
                    Penates as well as Rome. The sanctuary of the whole Latin league was at
                    Lavinium. To these Penates at Lavinium the Roman priests brought yearly
                    offerings, and the Roman consuls, praetors, and dictators sacrificed both when
                    they entered on and when they laid down their office. To them, too, the generals
                    sacrificed before departing for their provinces. Alba Longa, the real
                    mother-city of Latium, had also its ancient Penates, and the Romans maintained
                    the worship on the Alban Mount long after the destruction of Alba Longa. The
                    Penates had a temple of their own at Rome. It was on the Velia near the Forum,
                    and has by some been identified with the round vestibule of the church of SS.
                    Cosma e Damiano. In this and many other temples the Penates were rèpresented by
                    two images of youths seated holding spears. The Penates were also worshipped in
                    the neighbouring temple of Vesta. To distinguish the two worships, it has been
                    supposed that the Penates in the former temple were those of Latium, while those
                    in the temple of Vesta were the Penates proper of Rome. Certainly the worship of
                    the Penates, whose altar was the hearth and to whom the kitchen was sacred, was
                    closely connected with that of Vesta, goddess of the domestic hearth.</p>
                <p>The origin and nature of the Penates was a subject of much discussion to the
                    Romans themselves. They were traced to the mysterious worship of Samothrace:
                    Dardanus, it was said, took the Penates from Samothrace to Troy, and after the
                    destruction of Troy Aeneas brought them to Italy and established them at
                    Lavinium. From Lavinium Ascanius carried the worship to Alba Longa, and from
                    Alba Longa it was brought to Rome. Equally unsatisfactory with this attempt to
                    connect Roman religion with Greek legend are the vague and mystic speculations
                    in which the later Romans indulged respecting the nature of the Penates. Some
                    said they were the great gods to whom we owe breath, body, and reason, viz.,
                    Jupiter representing the middle ether, Juno the lowest air and the earth, and
                    Minerva the highest ether, to whom some added Mercury as the god of speech
                    (Servius, on <hi rend="italic">Aen.,</hi> ii. 296; Macrobius, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sat.,</hi> iii. 4, 8; Arnobius, <hi rend="italic">Λdv. Nat.,</hi> iii. 40).
                    Others identified them with Apollo and Neptune (Macrob., iii. 4, 6; Arnob., <hi
                    rend="italic">l.c.;</hi> Serv., on <hi rend="italic">Aen.,</hi> iii. 119). The
                    Etruscans held the Penates to be Ceres, Pales, and Fortuna, to whom others added
                    Genius Jovialis (Serv., on <hi rend="italic">Aen.,</hi> ii. 325; Arnob., <hi
                    rend="italic">l.cj).</hi> The late writer Martianus Capella records the view
                    that heaven was divided into sixteen regions, in the first of which were placed
                    the Penates along with Jupiter, the Lares, Ac. More fruitful than these misty
                    speculations is the suggestion, made by the ancients themselves, that the
                    worship of these family gods sprang from the ancient Roman custom (common to
                    many savage tribes) of burying the dead in the house. But this would account for
                    the worship of the Lares rather than of the Penates. A comparison with other
                    primitive religious beliefs suggests the conjecture that the Penates may be a
                    remnant of that fetishism or animism <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> the
                    attribution of life, thought, and feeling to all objects animate and inanimate)
                    in which many savage tribes exist to this day, and through which the higher
                    races have probably passed at some period of their history, whether we suppose
                    animism to be the primitive state of the human mind, or to be itself a
                    development from the worship of ancestors, as Mr Herbert Spencer believes, or
                    from some lower form of belief. The Roman <hi rend="italic">genii</hi> seem
                    certainly to have been fetishes, and the Penates were perhaps originally a
                    species of <hi rend="italic">genii.</hi> Thus the Penates, as simple gods of
                    food, are probably much more ancient than deities like Jupiter, Neptune, Apollo,
                    and Minerva, whose wide and varied attributes represent a power of abstraction
                    and generalization in the minds of their worshippers such as is not possessed by
                    very primitive men. With the Penates we may compare the kindly household gods of
                    old Germany; they too had their home on the kitchen hearth and received
                    offerings of food and clothing. In the castle of Hudemühlen (Hanover) there was
                    a kobold for whom a cover was always set on the table. In Lapland each house had
                    one or more spirits. The souls of the dead are regarded as house-spirits by the
                    Russians; they are represented as dwarfs, and are served with food and drink.
                    Each house in Servia has its patron-saint. In the mountains of Mysore every
                    house has its bhuta or guardian deity, to whom prayer and sacrifices are
                    offered. The Chinese god of the kitchen presents some curious analogies to the
                    Penates: incense and candles are burnt before him on the first and fifteenth of
                    the month; some families burn incense and candles before him daily; and on great
                    festivals, one of which is at the winter solstice (nearly corresponding to the
                    Saturnalia), he is served with cakes, pork, wine, incense, Ac., which are placed
                    on a table before him.</p>
                <p>See Hartung, <hi rend="italic">Die Religion</hi><hi rend="italic">der</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Römer</hi>; Hertzberg, <hi rend="italic">De diis Roman,
                    pair.</hi>; Preller, <hi rend="italic">Röm.</hi><hi rend="italic">Mythol.</hi>;
                    Marquardt, <hi rend="italic">Röm.</hi><hi rend="italic">Staats-νerwalt.,</hi>
                    vol. iii. For household gods of other peoples see Bastian, <hi rend="italic">Der
                    Mensch</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">der Geschichte,</hi> iii.
                    p. 202 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> (J. G. FR. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
