<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0918-0336-0315-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PARMENIDES of Elea (9th edition, volume 18, page
                    315)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1158235">Truth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1132936">Steins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978609">Ionians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n336/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PARMENIDES <hi rend="smallcaps">of Elea</hi></label>, the
                    most notable of the philosophers of the Eleatic succession, is said by Diogenes
                    Laertius (presumably on the authority of Apollodorus) to have been “in his
                    prime” in Olymp. 69 ( = 504-500 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.);</hi> whence it would
                    appear that he was born about 539. Plato indeed <hi rend="italic"
                        >{Parmenides,</hi> 127 B; compare <hi rend="italic">Theaetetus,</hi> 183 E,
                        <hi rend="italic">Sophist,</hi> 217 C) makes Socrates, who was born 470 or
                    469, see and hear Parmenides when the latter was about sixty-five years of age,
                    in which case he cannot have been born before 519; but, in the absence of
                    evidence that any such meeting took place, it is reasonable to regard this as
                    one of Plato’s many anachronisms. However this may be, Parmenides was a
                    contemporary, perhaps a somewhat younger contemporary, of Heraclitus, with whom
                    the first succession of physicists ended; while Anaxagoras and Empedocles, with
                    whom the second succession of physicists began, as well as Protagoras, the
                    earliest of those humanists whose rejection of physical research prepared the
                    way for the Platonic metaphysic, were very decidedly his juniors. Belonging, it
                    is said, to a rich and distinguished family, Parmenides attached himself, at any
                    rate for a time, to the aristocratic society or brotherhood which Pythagoras had
                    established at Croton; and accordingly one part of his system, the physical
                    part, is apparently Pythagorean. To Xenophanes, the founder of Eleaticism,—whom
                    he must have known, even if he was never in any strict sense of the word his
                    disciple,—Parmenides was, perhaps, more deeply indebted, as the theological
                    speculations of that thinker unquestionably suggested to him the theory of Being
                    and Not-Being, of the One and the Many, by which he sought to reconcile Ionian
                    monism with Italiote dualism. Tradition relates that Parmenides framed laws for
                    the Eleates, who each year took an oath to observe them.</p>
                <p>Parmenides embodied his tenets in a short poem called <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nature,</hi> of which fragments, amounting in all to about a hundred and
                    sixty lines, have been preserved in the writings of Sextus Empiricus,
                    Simplicius, and others. <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> is traditionally divided
                    into three parts—the * <hi rend="superscript"> l</hi> Proem,” “Truth” (τα τrpoς
                    dλι)0∈ιαv), and “Opinion” (τα <hi rend="italic">τrpoς</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >δόξαν).</hi> In “Truth,” starting from the formula “the Ent (or existent)
                    is, the Nonent (or non-existent) is not,” Parmenides attempted to distinguish
                    between the unity or universal element of nature and its variety or
                    particularity, insisting upon the reality of its unity, which is therefore the
                    object of knowledge, and upon the unreality of its variety, which is therefore
                    the object, not of knowledge, but of opinion. In “Opinion” he propounded a
                    theory of the world of seeming and its development, pointing out, however, that,
                    in accordance with the principles already laid down, these cosmological
                    speculations do not pretend to anything more than probability. In spite of the
                    contemptuous remarks of Cicero and Plutarch about Parmenides’s versification,
                        <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> is not without literary merit. The
                    introduction, though rugged, is forcible and picturesque; and the rest of the
                    poem is written in a simple and effective style suitable to the subject. It is,
                    however, a summary rather than an exposition, and its brevity sometimes leads to
                    obscurity. Partly for this reason, but partly also in consequence of the
                    mutilations and the corruptions of the text, the interpretation of the system
                    which <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> represents early became a matter of
                    controversy.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">“Proem.</hi> ”—In the “Proem” the poet describes his journey
                    from darkness to light. Borne in a whirling chariot, and attended by the
                    daughters of the Sun, he reaches a temple sacred to an unnamed goddess
                    (variously identified by the commentators with Nature, Wisdom, or Themis), by
                    whom the rest of the poem is spoken. He must learn all things, she tells him,
                    both truth, which is certain, and human opinions; for, though in human opinions
                    there can be no confidence, they must be studied notwithstanding for what they
                    are worth.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">“TruthP—“</hi> Truth” begins with the declaration of
                    Parmenides’s principle in opposition to the principles of his predecessors.
                    There are three ways of research, and three ways only. Of these, one asserts the
                    non-existence of the existent and the existence of the non-existent <hi
                        rend="italic">[i.e.</hi>, Thales, Anaximander, and Anaximenes suppose the
                    single element which they respectively postulate to be transformed into the
                    various sorts of matter which they discover in the world around them, thus
                    assuming the non-existence of that which is elemental and the existence of that
                    which is non-elemental]; another, pursued by “restless” persons, whose “road
                    returns upon itself,” assumes that a thing “is and is not,” “is the same and not
                    the same” [an obvious reference, as Bernays points out in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Rheinisches</hi><hi rend="italic">Museum,</hi> vii. 114 <hi rend="italic"
                        >sq.,</hi> to Heraclitus, the philosopher of flux]. These are ways of error,
                    because they confound existence and non-existence. In contrast to them the way
                    of truth starts from the proposition that “the Ent is, the Nonent is not.”</p>
                <p>On the strength of the fundamental distinction between the Ent and the Nonent,
                    the goddess next announces certain characteristics of the former. The Ent is
                    uncreated, for it cannot be derived either from the Ent or from the Nonent; it
                    is imperishable, for it cannot pass into the Nonent; it is whole, indivisible,
                    continuous, for nothing exists to break its continuity in space; it is
                    unchangable [for nothing exists to break its continuity in time]; it is perfect,
                    for there is nothing which it can want; it never was, nor will be, but only is;
                    it is evenly extended in every direction, and therefore a sphere, exactly
                    balanced; it is identical with thought <hi rend="italic">[he.,</hi> it is the
                    object, and the sole object, of thought as opposed to sensation, sensation being
                    concerned with variety and change].</p>
                <p>As then the Ent is one, invariable, and immutable, all plurality, variety, and
                    mutation belong to the Nonent. Whence it follows that all the states and
                    processes which we commonly recognize — generation and destruction, being and
                    not-being [predicated of things], change of place, alteration of colour, and the
                    like—are no more than empty words.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">“Opinion.”—</hi> The investigation of the Ent <hi rend="italic"
                        >[i.e.,</hi> the existent unity, extended throughout space and enduring
                    throughout time, which reason discovers beneath the variety and the mutability
                    of things] being now complete, it remains in “Opinion” to describe the plurality
                    of things, not as they are, for they are not, but as they seem to be. In the
                    phenomenal world then, there are, it has been thought [and Parmenides accepts
                    the theory, which appears to be of Pythagorean origin], two primary
                    elements—namely, fire, which is gentle, thin, homogeneous, and night [or earth],
                    which is dark, thick, heavy. Of these elements [which, according to Aristotle,
                    were, or rather were analogous to, the Ent and the Nonent respectively] all
                    things consist, and from them they derive their several characteristics. The
                    foundation for a cosmology having thus been laid in dualism, the poem went on to
                    describe the generation of “earth, and sun, and moon, and air that is common to
                    all, and the milky way, and furthest Olympus, and the glowing stars”; but the
                    scanty fragments which have survived suffice only to show that Parmenides
                    regarded the universe as a series of concentric rings or spheres composed of the
                    two primary elements and of combinations of them, the whole system being
                    directed by an unnamed goddess established at its centre. Next came a theory of
                    animal development. This again was followed by a psychology, which made mind
                    depend upon bodily structure, thought [as well as sensation, which was conceived
                    to differ from thought only in respect of its object] being the excess of the
                    one or the other of the two constituent elements, fire and night. “Such, opinion
                    tells us, was the generation, such is the present existence, such will be the
                    end, of those things to which men have given distinguishing names.”</p>
                <p>In the truism “the Ent is, the Nonent is not,” <hi rend="italic">δν eστι, μη oν
                        oυκ</hi><hi rend="italic">:στι,</hi> Parmenides breaks with his
                    predecessors, the physicists of the Ionian succession. Asking themselves—What is
                    the material universe? they had replied respectively—It is water, it is <hi
                        rend="italic">μeταξv τι,</hi> it is air, it is fire. Thus, while their
                    question meant, or ought to have meant, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n337/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0918-0337-0316"/> What is the single element which underlies
                    the apparent plurality of the material world? their answers, Parmenides
                    conceived, by attributing to the selected element various and varying qualities,
                    reintroduced the plurality which the question sought to eliminate. If we would
                    discover that which is common to all things at all times, we must, he submitted,
                    exclude the differences of things, whether simultaneous or successive. Hence,
                    whereas his predecessors had confounded that which is universally existent with
                    that which is not universally existent, he proposed to distinguish carefully
                    between that which is universally existent and that which is not universally
                    existent, between <hi rend="italic">5ν</hi> and <hi rend="italic">μη Sν.</hi>
                    The fundamental truism is the epigrammatic assertion of this distinction.</p>
                <p>In short, the single corporeal element of the Ionian physicists was, to borrow a
                    phrase .from Aristotle, a permanent ουσία having <hi rend="italic">πάθη</hi>
                    which change; but they either neglected the <hi rend="italic">πάθη</hi> or
                    confounded them with the ουσία. Parmenides sought to reduce the variety of
                    nature to a single corporeal element; but he strictly discriminated the
                    inconstant <hi rend="italic">πάθη</hi> from the constant ουσία, and,
                    understanding by “existence” universal, invariable, immutable being, refused to
                    attribute to the <hi rend="italic">πάθη</hi> anything more than the semblance of
                    existence.</p>
                <p>Having thus discriminated between the permanent unity of nature and its
                    superficial plurality, Parmenides proceeded to the separate investigation of the
                    Ent and the Nonent. The universality of the Ent, he conceived, necessarily
                    carries with it certain characteristics. It is one; it is eternal; it is whole
                    and continuous, both in time and in space; it is immovable and immutable; it is
                    limited, but limited only by itself; it is evenly extended in every direction,
                    and therefore spherical. These propositions having been reached, apart from
                    particular experience, by reflexion upon the fundamental principle, we have in
                    them, Parmenides conceived, a body of information resting upon a firm basis and
                    entitled to be called “truth.” Further, the information thus obtained is the sum
                    total of “truth ;” for, as “existence” in the strict sense of the word cannot be
                    attributed to anything besides the universal element, so nothing besides the
                    universal element can properly be said to be “known.”</p>
                <p>If Parmenides’s poem had had “Being” for its subject, it would doubtless have
                    ended at this point. Its subject is, however, “Nature”; and nature, besides its
                    unity, has also the semblance, if no more than the semblance, of plurality.
                    Hence the theory of the unity of nature is necessarily followed by a theory of
                    its seeming plurality, that is to say, of the variety and mutation of things.
                    The theory of plurality cannot indeed pretend to the certainty of the theory of
                    unity, being of necessity untrustworthy, because it is the partial and
                    inconstant representation of that which is partial and inconstant in nature.
                    But, as the material world includes, together with a real unity, the semblance
                    of plurality, so the theory of the material world includes, together with the
                    certain theory of the former, a probable theory of the latter. “Opinion” is then
                    no mere excrescence; it is the necessary sequel to “Truth.”</p>
                <p>Thus, whereas the Ionians, confounding the unity and the plurality of the
                    universe, had neglected plurality, and the Pythagoreans, contenting themselves
                    with the reduction of the variety of nature to a duality or a series of
                    dualities, had neglected unity, Parmenides, taking a hint from Xenophanes, made
                    the antagonistic doctrines supply one another’s deficiencies; for, as Xenophanes
                    in his theological system had recognized at once the unity of God and the
                    plurality of things, so Parmenides in his system of nature recognized at once
                    the rational unity of the Ent and the phenomenal plurality of the Nonent.</p>
                <p>The foregoing statement of Parmenides’s position differs from Zeller’s account of
                    it in two important particulars. First, whereas it has been assumed above that
                    Xenophanes was theologian rather than philosopher, whence it would seem to
                    follow that the philosophical doctrine of unity originated, not with him, but
                    with Parmenides, Zeller, supposing Xenophanes to have taught, not merely the
                    unity of God, but also the unity of Being, assigns to Parmenides no more than an
                    exacter conception of the doctrine of the unity of Being, the justification of
                    that doctrine, and the denial of the plurality and the mutability of things.
                    This view of the relations of Xenophanes and Parmenides is hardly borne out by
                    their writings; and, though ancient authorities may be quoted in its favour, it
                    would seem that in this case as in others they have fallen into the easy mistake
                    of confounding successive phases of doctrine, “construing the utterances of the
                    master in accordance with the principles of his scholar—the vague by the more
                    definite, the simpler by the more finished and elaborate theory” (W. H.
                    Thompson). Secondly, whereas it has been argued above that “Opinion” is
                    necessarily included in the system, Zeller, supposing Parmenides to deny the
                    Nonent even as a matter of opinion, regards that part of the poem wffiich has
                    opinion for its subject as no more than a revised and improved statement of the
                    views of opponents, introduced in order that the reader, having before him the
                    false doctrine as well as the true one, may be led the more certainly to embrace
                    the latter. In the judgment of the present writer, Parmenides, while he denied
                    the real existence of plurality, recognized its apparent existence, and
                    consequently, however little value he might attach to opinion, was bound to take
                    account of it: “pour celui même qui nie l’existence réelle de la nature,” says
                    Renouvier, “il reste encore à faire une histoire naturelle de l’apparence et de
                    l’illusion.”</p>
                <p>The teaching of Parmenides variously influenced both his immediate successors and
                    subsequent thinkers. By his recognition of an apparent plurality supplementary
                    to the real unity, he effected the transition from the monism of the first
                    physical succession to the pluralism of the second. While Empedocles and
                    Democritus are careful to emphasize their dissent from “Truth,” it is obvious
                    that “Opinion” is the basis of their cosmologies. The doctrine of the
                    deceitfulness of “the undiscerning eye and the echoing ear” soon established
                    itself, though the grounds upon which Anaxagoras, Empedocles, and Democritus
                    maintained it were not those which were alleged by Parmenides. Indirectly,
                    through the dialectic of his pupil and friend Zeno and otherwise, the doctrine
                    of the inadequacy of sensation led to the humanist movement, Λvhich for a time
                    threatened to put an end to philosophical and scientific speculation. But the
                    positive influence of Parmenides’s teaching was not yet exhausted. To say that
                    the Platonism of Plato’s later years, the Platonism of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Parmenides,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Philebus,</hi> and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Timaeus,</hi> is the philosophy of Parmenides enlarged and
                    reconstituted, may perhaps seem paradoxical in the face of the severe criticism
                    to which Eleaticism is subjected, not only in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Parmenides,</hi> but also in the <hi rend="italic">Sophist.</hi> The
                    criticism was, however, preparatory to a reconstruction. Thus may be explained
                    the selection of an Eleatic stranger to be the chief speaker in the latter, and
                    of Parmenides himself to take the lead in the former. In the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sophist</hi> criticism predominates over reconstruction, the Zenonian logic
                    being turned against the Parmenidean metaphysic in such a way as to show that
                    both the one and the other need revision: see 241 D, 244 B <hi rend="italic"
                        >sq.,</hi> 257 B <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> 258 D. In particular, Plato
                    taxes Parmenides with his inconsistency in attributing (as he certainly did) to
                    the fundamental unity extension and sphericity, so that “the worshipped <hi
                        rend="italic">3ν</hi> is after all a pitiful <hi rend="italic">μη oν</hi>”
                    (W. H. Thompson). In the <hi rend="italic">Parmenides</hi> reconstrue-tion<pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n338/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0918-0338-0317"/> predominates over criticism—the letter of
                    Eleaticism being here represented by Zeno, its spirit, as Plato conceived it, by
                    Parmenides. Not the least important of the results obtained in this dialogue is
                    the discovery that, whereas the doctrine of the “one” and the “many” is suicidal
                    and barren so long as the “solitary one” and the “indefinitely many” <hi
                        rend="italic">are</hi> absolutely separated (137 C <hi rend="italic"
                        >sq.</hi> and 163 B <hi rend="italic">sqf,</hi> it becomes consistent and
                    fruitful as soon as a “definite plurality” is interpolated between them (142 B
                        <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> 157 B <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> 160 B <hi
                        rend="italic">sqf.</hi> In short, Parmenides was no idealist, but Plato
                    recognized in him, and rightly, the precursor of idealism.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi> The fragments have been edited and
                    annotated by G. G. Fülleborn <hi rend="italic">{Fragmente</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >des Parmenides,</hi> Züllichau, 1795), C. A. Brandis <hi rend="italic"
                        >{Commentationes</hi><hi rend="italic">Eleaticae,</hi> Altona, 1813), S.
                    Karsten <hi rend="italic">{Philos. Graecor. Reliquiae,</hi> I., ii., Amsterdam,
                    1835), F. W. A. Mullach <hi rend="italic">{Aristotelis</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                        Melis. Xenoph.</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Gorg.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">disp,</hi><hi rend="italic">cum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Eleaticorum</hi><hi rend="italic">fragm.,</hi> Berlin, 1845; reprinted in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Fragmenta</hi><hi rend="italic">Philos. Graecor.,</hi>
                    Paris, 1860, i. 109-130), T. Vatke <hi rend="italic">{Parmenidis doctrina qualis
                        fuerit,</hi><hi rend="italic">diss, inaug.,</hi> Berlin, 1864), and H. Stein
                    (“Die Fragmente des Parmenides <hi rend="italic">πepi φυσeωsf</hi> in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Symbola Philologorum Bonnensium</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >in</hi><hi rend="italic">honorem</hi><hi rend="italic">F. Ritschelii
                        collecta,</hi> Leipsic, 1867, ii. 763- 806). The study of Karsten and Stein
                    jointly is recommended. The well-known <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Philosophise</hi><hi rend="italic">Gr. et</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Rom.</hi> of Ritter and Preller contains all the important
                    fragments. The extant remains have been translated into English hexameters by T.
                    Davidson <hi rend="italic">{Journal of Speculative Philosophy,</hi> St Louis,
                    Mo., 1870, iv. 1-16), and paraphrased in English prose by W. L. Courtney <hi
                        rend="italic">{Studies in Philosophy,</hi> London, 1882, pp. 1-25).</p>
                <p>The philosophical system has been treated by several of the writers already
                    mentioned, especially Brandis, Karsten, and Vatke, by F. Riaux <hi rend="italic"
                        >{Essai sur Parménide d’Élêe,</hi> Paris, 1840), and by the historians of
                    Greek philosophy, of whom it will suffice here to mention C. A. Brandis <hi
                        rend="italic">{Handb. d.</hi><hi rend="italic">Griechisch-Römischen
                        Philosophie,</hi> Berlin, 1835), G. W. F. Hegel (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Vorlesungen</hi><hi rend="italic">uber</hi><hi rend="italic">d.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">d. Philosophie,</hi> Berlin,
                    1840), Cn. Renouvier <hi rend="italic">{Manuel de Philosophie Ancienne,</hi>
                    Paris, 1844), L. Strümpell <hi rend="italic">{Gesch.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >d.</hi><hi rend="italic">theoretischen</hi><hi rend="italic">Philosophie
                        d.</hi><hi rend="italic">Griechen,</hi> Leipsic, 1854), J. F. Ferrier <hi
                        rend="italic">{Lectures</hi><hi rend="italic">on Greek Philosophy,</hi>
                    Edinburgh, 1866), J. E. Erdmann <hi rend="italic">{Grundriss</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">d. Gesch. d.</hi><hi rend="italic">Philosophie,</hi> 2d ed.,
                    Berlin, 1869), A. Schwegler <hi rend="italic">{Gesch.</hi><hi rend="italic">d.
                        Griech.</hi><hi rend="italic">Philos.,</hi> 2d ed., Tübingen, 1870), F.
                    Ueberweg <hi rend="italic">{Grundriss</hi><hi rend="italic">d. Gesch. d.
                        Philosophie,</hi> 4th ed., Berlin, 1871; English translation, 3ded., London,
                    1880), E. Zeller <hi rend="italic">{Die Philosophie d.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Griechen,</hi> 4th ed., Leipsic, 1876; English translation, <hi
                        rend="italic">Presocratic Philosophy,</hi> London, 1881). On the cosmology,
                    see A. B. Krische <hi rend="italic">{Die</hi><hi rend="italic">theologischen
                        Lehren</hi><hi rend="italic">d.</hi><hi rend="italic">Griechischen
                        Denker,</hi> Göttingen, 1840, pp. 97- 116). On the relations of Eleaticism
                    and Platonism, see W. H. Thompson, “On the Genuineness of Plato’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Sophist f</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Joιιr. of Philol.,</hi>
                    viii. 303 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> (H. JA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
