<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0793-0758-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PHILLIPS, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 758</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zd00">Surveys</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1139635">Surveys</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1139579">Surveying</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:933162">Fossilization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n793/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PHILLIPS, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1800-1874),
                    one of the foremost of the early geologists of England, was born 25th December
                    1800 at Marden in Wiltshire. His father belonged to an old Welsh family, but
                    settled in England as an officer of excise and married the sister of William
                    Smith, the “Father of English Geology.” Both parents dying when he was a child,
                    Phillips passed into the care of his uncle. Before his tenth year he had
                    attended four schools, until he entered the old school at Holt Spa, Wiltshire,
                    where he remained for five years, gaining among other acquisitions that taste
                    for classical learning which remained one of his distinguishing traits to the
                    end. From school he went to the house of the Rev. B. Richardson, an accomplished
                    naturalist, in whose charge he remained a year, and from whom he obtained not
                    only much knowledge but the strong bent towards the study of nature which
                    thenceforth became the master-pursuit of his life. His uncle, “Strata Smith,” at
                    that time lived in London, where he exercised the profession of a civil and
                    mining engineer, though a very large part of his time and earnings was given to
                    the preparation of those maps of England and the English counties on which his
                    fame now rests. In his zeal for geological pursuits Smith often neglected his
                    proper professional work, until, as his nephew said, “he had thrown into the
                    gulf of the Strata all his patrimony and all his little gains.” Eventually he
                    gave up his London house and wandered about the country, as the requirements of
                    his maps led him. From the time that young Phillips joined his uncle in London
                    he remained constantly with him, sharing in every piece of professional work, in
                    the preparation of every book and map, and in every tour for fresh geological
                    information. A youth so trained could not fail to become a geologist. In the
                    spring of 1824 Smith went to York to deliver a course of lectures on geology,
                    and his nephew accompanied him. This was the starting-point in Phillips’s
                    career. His extensive knowledge of natural science and especially of fossils was
                    now turned to account. He accepted engagements in the principal Yorkshire towns
                    to arrange their museums and give courses of lectures on the collections
                    contained therein. York became his residence, where he obtained the situation of
                    keeper of the Yorkshire Museum and secretary of the Yorkshire Philosophical
                    Society. From that centre he extended his operations to other towns beyond the
                    county; and in 1831 he included University College, London, in the sphere of his
                    activity. In that year the British Association for the Advancement of Science
                    was founded at York, and Phillips was one of the active minds who organized its
                    machinery. He became the assistant general secretary, a post of great labour and
                    proportionate usefulness, which he held for upwards of thirty years. In 1834 he
                    accepted the professorship of geology at King’s College, London, but retained
                    his post at York, coming up to London every year to give a course of lectures
                    there. This arrangement lasted for six years, until, in 1840, he resigned his
                    charge of the York Museum and was appointed one of the staff of the Geological
                    Survey of Great Britain under De la Beche. In this connexion he spent some time
                    in studying the Palaeozoic fossils of Devon, Cornwall, and west Somerset, of
                    which he published descriptions and illustrations. Thereafter he made a detailed
                    survey of the region of the Malvern Hills, of which he prepared the elaborate
                    account that appears in vol. ii. of the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> of the
                    Survey. His direct connexion with the National Survey was but of short duration,
                    for in 1844 he accepted the professorship of geology in the university of
                    Dublin. Nine years later, on the death of Strickland, who had acted as
                    substitute for Dr Buckland in the readership of geology in the university of
                    Oxford, Phillips succeeded to the post of deputy, and eventually, at the dean’s
                    death, became himself reader, a post singularly congenial to him, and which he
                    held up to the time of his own death, which was almost tragic in its suddenness.
                    He dined at All Souls’ College on 23d April 1874, but in retiring slipped and
                    fell headlong down a flight of stairs. Paralysis at once ensued, and he expired
                    on the afternoon <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n794/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0794-0759"/> of the next day. In 1864 he had been elected
                    president of the British Association.</p>
                <p>Phillips was distinguished among his contemporaries for the sweetness and bright
                    cheerfulness of his nature. He had great fluency as a speaker, and always spoke
                    in so pleasant and interesting a manner as to make him a welcome and indeed
                    indispensable interlocutor at the annual gatherings of the British Association.
                    His social gifts were not less conspicuous than his attainments in science. But
                    he was not a mere geologist. His sympathies went actively forth into the whole
                    domain of science, and he himself contributed largely to astronomical literature
                    as well as to meteorology.</p>
                <p>From the time when he wrote his first paper in 1826 “On the Direction of the
                    Diluvial Currents in Yorkshire” down to the last days of his life Phillips
                    continued a constant contributor to the literature of his science. The pages of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Geological Society,</hi> the <hi
                    rend="italic">Geological Magazine,</hi> and other publications of the day are
                    full of valuable essays by him. He was also the author of numerous separate
                    works, some of which had an extensive sale and were of great benefit in
                    extending a sound knowledge of geology. Among these may be specially mentioned:
                    <hi rend="italic">Illustrations of the Geology of Yorkshire</hi> (1835); <hi
                    rend="italic">A Treatise on Geology</hi> (1837- 39); <hi rend="italic">Memoirs
                    of William Smith, the Father of English Geology</hi> (1844); <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Rivers, Mountains, and Sea-Coast of Yorkshire</hi> (1853); <hi
                    rend="italic">Manual of Geology, Practical and Theoretical</hi> (1855); <hi
                    rend="italic">Life on the Earth: its Origin and Succession</hi> (1860); <hi
                    rend="italic">Vesuvius</hi> (1869); <hi rend="italic">Geology of Oxford and the
                    Thames Valley</hi> (1871). To these should be added his monographs in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> of the Geological Survey and the publications of the
                    Palaeontographical Society, and his geological sections and maps.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
