<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0825-0790-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PHILOPOeMEN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 790</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:795626">Achaeans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:882877">Cretans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:885243">Cupping</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198950">Revolt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r13x">Cupping</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gc8s">Fever</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n825/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PHILOPOeMEN</label>, “the last of the Greeks” as he was
                    called by an admiring Roman, was a leading champion of the Achaean League, which
                    preserved in Peloponnesus a last shred of Greek freedom. Sprung from an
                    illustrious Arcadian family, he was born at Megalopolis in Arcadia in 252 B.c.
                    His father Craugis dying in his infancy, Philopoemen was brought up by his
                    father’s friend Cleander, an exile from Mantinea. In his youth he associated
                    with Ecdemus and Megalophanes, who had studied the Academic philosophy under
                    Arcesilaus, and had proved themselves friends of freedom by helping to rid
                    Megalopolis and Sicyon of tyrants. Philopoemen soon distinguished himself in war
                    and the chase. Hard-featured but of an iron frame, simple and hardy in his way
                    of life, blunt and straightforward in speech and manner,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The simplicity of his manners is illustrated
                    by a tale like that <hi rend="italic">of</hi> Alfred an&lt;l the cakes, Plut.,
                    <hi rend="italic">Phil.,</hi> 2.</p></note> he was a born soldier, delighting in
                    war and careless of whatever did not bear on it. Thus he would not practise
                    wrestling because the athlete’s finely-strung habit of body is ill-fitted to
                    bear the strain of a soldier’s life. He read books of a martial and stirring
                    tone, like the poems of Homer, together with works on military history and
                    tactics. Epaminondas was his pattern, but he could not school his hot temper
                    into the unruffled patience of the Theban. Indeed we miss in this rugged soldier
                    that union of refinement at home with daring in the field which had stamped the
                    soldier-citizens of the best age of Greece. His leisure was devoted to the chase
                    or to the cultivation of his farm, where he worked like one of his hinds. In
                    222, when Cleomenes king of Sparta made himself master of Megalopolis by a night
                    attack, Philopoemen secured by his valour the retreat of the main body of the
                    citizens to Messene, and encouraged them to refuse the insidious invitation of
                    Cleomenes to return to their homes on condition of renouncing their connexion
                    with the Achaean League. Thus baffled, Cleomenes laid the city in ruins and
                    retired. At the battle of Sellasia (early summer 221), where Cleomenes was
                    defeated by the combined Achaean and Macedonian forces under Antigonus, king of
                    Macedonia, Philopoemen greatly distinguished himself by charging, without
                    orders, at the head of the Megalopolitan cavalry and thus saving from defeat the
                    wing on which he fought. His conduct won the admiration of Antigonus, who
                    offered him a command in the Macedonian army, but he declined it and went to the
                    wars in Crete. Returning after some time with fresh laurels, he was at once
                    chosen to command the Achaean cavalry, which, from an ill-mounted, raw, and
                    cowardly body he soon turned into a highly-trained and thoroughly efficient
                    force; at the head of it he overthrew the Aetolian and Elean horse, and slew
                    their commander with his own hand (209). He was elected general of the Achaean
                    League for the first time in 208. In this, the highest dignity of the
                    confederacy, he infused greater vigour and independence into the councils of the
                    League than had been shown by Aratus, who had leaned on Macedonia and trusted to
                    diplomacy rather than the sword. Philopoemen entirely changed the equipment and
                    tactics of the troops of the League, substituting complete armour, long lances
                    and large shields for the lighter arms hitherto in use, and adopting the
                    Macedonian phalanx as the fighting order. But he did more: by example and
                    precept he turned a nation of dandies into a nation of soldiers, who now spent
                    on arms and accoutrements the wealth they had before lavished on dinners and
                    dress. With the army thus transformed he defeated Machanidas, tyrant of Sparta,
                    at the battle of Mantinea. The tyrant fell by Philopaemen’s hand, Tegea was
                    taken, and Laconia ravaged. A bronze statue representing Philopoemen slaying
                    Machanidas was set up at Delphi by the Achaeans. At the Nemean festival which
                    followed the battle Philopoemen, then general for the second time, was hailed by
                    the people as the liberator of Greece. Jealous of the degree of independence to
                    ∖Λιich Philopoemen had raised the League, Philip king of Macedonia sent
                    emissaries to murder him, but they were foiled. So great was the terror of his
                    name that at the bare report that he was coming the Boeotians raised the siege
                    of Megara and fled. When Nabis, successor of Machanidas in the tyranny of
                    Sparta, seized Messene, Philopoemen, though he held no office at the time and
                    the general of the League refused to stir, collected his fellow-townsmen and
                    drove out the tyrant. In his third generalship (201-200) he mustered the Achaean
                    forces with great secrecy at Tegea and, invading Laconia, defeated the troops of
                    Nabis. The Romans were now about to cross the sea for the war with Philip of
                    Macedonia, and Philopoemen was the means of preventing the Achaeans from
                    concluding an alliance with Philip against Rome. At the expiry of his year of
                    office he sailed once more to Crete, where he successfully led the troops of the
                    Gortynians, beating the Cretans with their own weapons of craft and surprise.
                    Philopoemen did not return to Peloponnesus till after the Romans under
                    Flamininus had conquered Philip. He found the Romans and Achaeans making war on
                    Nabis and was again elected to the generalship (192). Nabis was besieging
                    Gythium, which with the other towns on the Laconian coast had been wrested from
                    him by the Romans, handed over l&gt;y them to the Spartan exiles, and attached
                    to the Achaean League. Being defeated in an attempt to relieve Gythium <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n826/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0826-0791"/> by sea, Philopoemen landed and surprised a part
                    of the tyrant’s forces not far from that town, burned their camp, and slew many.
                    After ravaging Laconia he marched on Sparta in the hope of compelling Nabis to
                    raise the siege. But Nabis took Gythium and awaited the Achaeans in a pass.
                    Philopoemen was surprised, but by skilful generalship he not only extricated
                    himself but routed the Spartans and cut off most of the fugitives. When Nabis
                    was assassinated Philopoemen hastened to Sparta and induced it to join the
                    Achaean League. In the same year (192) Antiochus, king of Asia, crossed into
                    Greece to fight the Romans. By the advice, or at least with the concurrence, of
                    Philopoemen the Achaeans rejected the king’s proposal that they should remain
                    neutral, and declared war against him and his allies the Aetolians. In the
                    following year Diophanes, general of the League, hearing that Sparta showed
                    signs of revolt, marched against it accompanied by Flamininus. Philopoemen had
                    remonstrated in vain against this step, and he now boldly threw himself into
                    Sparta, composed the disturbances, and closed the gates against Diophanes and
                    Flamininus. The grateful Spartans offered Philopoemen a splendid present, but he
                    bade them keep such bribes for their enemies. In 189 Philopoemen, again general,
                    proposed and carried in an assembly, which he summoned at Argos, a decree that
                    the general assembly of the League should meet in all the cities of the League
                    in rotation, instead of, as hitherto, at Aegeum only. This measure was obviously
                    meant to deprive Achaea of its position as head of the League, and to make the
                    allied cities more equal. In the same year the Spartans made an unsuccessful
                    attack on one of the maritime towns occupied by the exiles. As these towns were
                    under Achaean protection the League required Sparta to surrender the authors of
                    the attack. Far from complying, the Spartans put to death thirty partisans of
                    Philopoemen and renounced their connexion with the League. The Achaeans declared
                    war, and in the following spring (188) Philopoemen, having been re-elected
                    general, marched against Sparta, which was forced to pull down its walls, to
                    expel the foreign mercenaries and the slaves whom the tyrants had freed, to
                    exchange the laws and institutions of Lycurgus for those of the Achaeans, and,
                    lastly, to receive back the exiles. It would seem that on this occasion
                    Philopoemen allowed his hatred of the old enemy of Megalopolis to overpower his
                    judgment; his conduct was as unwise as it was cruel, for it afforded the
                    Romans—what Philopoemen had hitherto been careful not to furnish them with—a
                    pretext for meddling in the affairs of Greece. His treatment of Sparta was
                    censured by the senate, and Roman officers in Greece remonstrated with the
                    League on the subject. In 183, the last year of his life, Philopoemen was
                    general for the eighth time (his seventh generalship perhaps fell in 187, but
                    this is uncertain). He lay sick of a fever at Argos when word came that Messene,
                    under Dinocrates, had revolted from the League. At first he despatched his
                    friend arid partisan Lycortas to put down the revolt, then growing impatient, in
                    spite of the fever and his seventy years, he hurried in a single day to
                    Megalopolis, and, taking with him the cavalry of his native town, entered
                    Messenia and routed Dinocrates. But, the enemy being reinforced, he was
                    compelled to fall back over broken ground. In his anxiety to cover the retreat
                    of his troopers he was left alone, and, his horse stumbling, he was thrown to
                    the ground and taken prisoner. He was conducted with his arms pinioned through
                    the streets of Messene and cast into a dungeon. At nightfall on the second day
                    an executioner was sent to him with a cup of poison. Seeing the light and the
                    executioner standing by, Philopoemen sat up with difficulty, for he was weak,
                    and, taking the cup in his hand, he asked the man, What tidings of the cavalry?
                    Being told that they had mostly escaped, he bowed his head and said that it was
                    well. Then he drained the cup and lay down to die. Swift vengeance overtook his
                    murderers. The indignant Achaeans, under Lycortas, ravaged Messenia, and when
                    the capital surrendered all who had had part in the murder of Philopoemen were
                    obliged to kill themselves. Dinocrates had already committed suicide. The body
                    of Philopoemen was burned, and his bones conveyed to Megalopolis with every mark
                    of respect and sorrow, the urn, almost hidden in garlands, being borne by his
                    fellow-townsman, the historian Polybius. Numerous statues were set up and
                    honours decreed to him in the cities of the League. After the destruction of
                    Corinth by Mummius some one proposed to destroy the statues of a man who had
                    been no friend of the Romans · but the Roman general rejected the base
                    proposal.</p>
                <p>Philopaemen’s lot was cast in evil days. Hardly were the Achaeans freed by him
                    from Macedonia when they had to submit to Rome. His policy towards the Romans
                    was marked by a prudence and moderation hardly to be expected from one of his
                    passionate nature. He saw that the final subjugation of Greece was inevitable,
                    but he did his best to delay it, not by a war which would only have precipitated
                    the catastrophe, but by giving the Romans no ground for interference, and by
                    resisting their encroachments, so far as this could be done, by an appeal to
                    reason and justice.</p>
                <p>Our authorities for the life of Philopoemen are Polybius, Livy, Plutarch, and
                    Pausanias. Polybius’s work on Philopoemen was in three book , but it is lost.
                    Plutarch’s biography, like the account in Pausanias (viii. 49-51), is based on
                    Polybius. ' (J. G. FR.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
