<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0854-0819-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PHOTIUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 819</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:828168">Basil</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1038470">Nomocanon</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:814767">Armenians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1212489">Bulgaria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n854/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PHOTIUS</label>, patriarch of Constantinople from 857 to 867
                    and again from 877 to 886 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> the most eminent
                    literary and ecclesiastical character of his age, was probably born between 820
                    and 825. If we could credit the assertions of his adversaries, his father, an
                    official of the imperial court, named Sergius, was of heathen extraction, and
                    his mother, Irene, a faithless nun. It is more certain that he displayed from an
                    earlyage the most extraordinary talent and appetite for knowledge, and that,
                    having mastered whatever Greek literature could give him (Latin and Hebrew he
                    never acquired), he began to teach with distinguished success grammar, rhetoric,
                    divinity, and philosophy. The way to public life was probably opened for him by
                    the brilliant marriage of his maternal uncle to the princess Irene, sister of
                    the empress Theodora, who, upon the death of her husband Theophilus in 842, had
                    assumed the regency of the empire. Photius became captain of the guard and
                    subsequently first imperial secretary. Somewhere about 850 he was entrusted with
                    a mission to the “Assyrians,” by whom the Saracens must be meant, possibly to
                    the court of the caliph of Baghdad. Just previous to his departure on this
                    mission he compiled his <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Myriobibl·ion,</hi> the noblest monument of his erudition, and, from the number
                    of classical authors whose writings it has partially preserved, by much the most
                    important of his works.</p>
                <p>Some time after his return from this embassy an unexpected path was opened to
                    Photius’s ambition by the dissensions between the patriarch Ignatius and Bardas,
                    the uncle of the youthful emperor Michael III., who had succeeded to the regency
                    on the disgrace of Theodora. Ignatius, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n855/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0855-0820"/> a man of austere morals,and apparently not exempt
                    from spiritual pride, had excommunicated Bardas on the ground of an alleged
                    incestuous connexion with his daughter-in-law. Bardas retorted by an accusation
                    of a conspiracy. Ignatius was arrested and imprisoned (November 857), and upon
                    his refusing to resign was illegally deposed, when Photius, receiving all the
                    necessary sacerdotal orders within six days, was installed as patriarch in his
                    place. This sudden elevation of a layman to the highest ecclesiastical office
                    could not but provoke scandal, even though the laic, as was actually the case,
                    might be the first theologian of his age. Ignatius, continuing to refuse the
                    abdication which could alone have given it a semblance of legality, was treated
                    with extreme severity, and a violent persecution broke out against his
                    adherents. Photius urged clemency in his epistles to Bardas, probably with
                    sincerity, but shrank from taking the only step which could have effectually
                    repressed the persecution and healed the schism,—the resignation of the
                    patriarchate. In judging his conduct, however, two circumstances have to be
                    borne in mind,—the fact that the party of Ignatius dwindled away so rapidly as
                    to flatter Photius with the hope of its extinction, and the espousal of his
                    competitor’s cause by Nicholas, bishop of Rome, in a manner highly offensive to
                    the independent feeling of the Eastern Church. Photius felt himself the champion
                    of Eastern Christianity against Latin pretensions; and, when in 863 Nicholas
                    finally anathematized and deposed him, he replied by a counter-excommunication.
                    He also sought to ally himself with Western bishops who had been displaced or
                    suspended by the arrogant Nicholas, and with the latter’s secular adversaries,
                    while at the same time he was more honourably engaged in endeavours to reunite
                    the Armenians to the Eastern Church, in combating the Paulicians, and in
                    successful missions to the Russians and Bulgarians. While these transactions
                    were proceeding the situation was suddenly changed by the murder of Photius’s
                    patron, Caesar Bardas, by order of the emperor Michael, who was himself
                    assassinated by his colleague Basil in the following year (867). The fall of
                    Photius immediately ensued, but the attendant circumstances are exceedingly
                    obscure. According to Georgius Hamartolus, or rather his continuator, the cause
                    was Photius’s stern reproof of the crime by which Basil had obtained the throne.
                    As the only definite testimony of any kind, this statement cannot be wholly
                    disregarded, but it is certainly difficult to reconcile it with the general
                    suppleness of Photius in his relations with the Byzantine court. Whatever the
                    cause, Photius was removed from his office and banished about the end of
                    September 867, a few days after the accession of Basil, and the deposed
                    Ignatius, brought back from his exile, was reinstated on 23d November. The
                    convocation of a general council followed, to give the restoration of Ignatius a
                    character of indisputable legality. This synod, regarded by the Latins as the
                    eighth oecumenical council, but rejected as such by the Greeks, met in October
                    869. The attendance of Eastern bishops was relatively very small; Photius’s
                    friends and creatures generally remained faithful to him; and the ostentatious
                    patronage of Pope Hadrian must have been irritating to the Orientals. Photius,
                    when brought before the assembly, maintained a dignified silence, which
                    perplexed his accusers, but could not avert his condemnation. It seems,
                    nevertheless, to have been generally felt that the proceedings of the council
                    were entitled to little moral weight. The usurper, for such he unquestionably
                    was, had successfully identified himself with the cause of his church and
                    nation. In his captivity, which, notwithstanding his complaints, the extent of
                    his correspondence proves to have been mild, he maintained the same unbending
                    spirit, and rejected all overtures of compromise. About 876 he was suddenly
                    recalled to Constantinople and entrusted with the education of Basil’s children.
                    A tale of his having regained favour by forging an illustrious genealogy for the
                    upstart emperor may be dismissed without hesitation as an invention of his
                    enemies. The cause was in all probability Basil’s recognition of the fact that
                    he had disgraced and banished the ablest man in his dominions, and the best
                    qualified to fill the patriarchate upon the decease of the aged Ignatius. This
                    event soon occurred, probably in October 877, and after a decent show of
                    reluctance Photius again filled the patriarchal throne. According to his own
                    account, which there seems no reason to discredit, he had become fully
                    reconciled to his predecessor, and had shown him much kindness. Photius now
                    proceeded to obtain the formal recognition of the Christian world. In November
                    879 a synod, considered by the Greeks as the-eighth oecumenical council, and far
                    more numerously attended than the one by which he had been deposed, was convened
                    at Constantinople. The legates of Pope John VIII. attended, prepared to
                    acknowledge Photius as legitimate patriarch, a concession for which John was so
                    much censured by Latin opinion that Baronins rather fancifully explains the
                    legend of Pope Joan by the contempt excited by his want of spirit. John,
                    however, was firm on the other two points which had long been contested between
                    the Eastern and Western Churches, the ecclesiastical jurisdiction over Bulgaria
                    and the introduction of the ‘‘filioque” clause into the creed. He disowned his
                    legates, who had shown a tendency to yield, again excommunicated Photius, and
                    thus kindled smouldering ill-will into the open hostility which has never been
                    appeased to this day. Strong in the support of the council, Photius simply
                    ignored him. He has been accused of interpolating John’s letters, a charge not
                    improbable in itself, but which can neither be proved nor disproved at this
                    date. At the height of glory and success he was suddenly precipitated from his
                    dignity by another palace revolution. Archbishop Theodore Santa-baren, his
                    confidant and favourite, had accused Basil’s son, Leo, of a conspiracy against
                    his father. Leo owed his liberty and eyesight to Photius’s entreaties;
                    nevertheless, on his accession in 886, he involved his benefactor in the ruin of
                    his accuser. Arrested, degraded from the patriarchate, banished to the monastery
                    of Bordi in Armenia, Photius, as if by magic, disappears from history. No
                    letters of this period of his life are extant, which leads to the inference that
                    his imprisonment was severe. The precise date of his death is not known, but it
                    is said to have occurred on 6th February 891.</p>
                <p>For long after Photius’s death his memory was held in no special honour by his
                    countrymen. His literary merits were obscured by the growing barbarism of the
                    times, and the anarchy and apparent decrepitude of the Roman Church made his
                    protest against its pretensions seem superfluous. But, when, in the crusading
                    age, the Greek Church and state were alike in danger from Latin encroachments,
                    Photius became a national hero, and is at present regarded as little short of a
                    saint. To this character he has not the least pretension. Few men, it is
                    probable, have been more atrociously calumniated; but, when every specific
                    statement to his prejudice has been rejected, he still appears on a general
                    review of his actions worldly, crafty, and unscrupulous. Yet, however short he
                    may fall of the standard of an Athanasius or a Luther, he shows to no little
                    advantage when regarded as an ecclesiastical statesman. His firmness was heroic,
                    his sagacity profound and far-seeing; he supported good and evil fortune with
                    equal dignity; and his fall was on both occasions due to revolutions beyond his
                    control. If his original elevation to the patriarchate was unquestionably
                    irregular, his re-enthronement was no less certainly legal; he began as a
                    usurper and ended as a patriot. His zeal for the promotion of learning,
                    education, and missions was most genuine, and fruitful in good. In erudition,
                    literary power, and force and versatility of intellect he far surpassed every
                    contemporary. The records of his actions are so imperfect or so prejudiced that
                    in endeavouring to judge his personal character we have to rely principally upon
                    the internal evidence of his own letters. With every allowance for their <hi
                    rend="italic">ex parte</hi> and rhetorical character and the writer’s manifest
                    desire to display <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n856/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0856-0821"/> himself in the most favourable light, they
                    nevertheless seem to afford sufficient testimony of a magnanimous spirit and a
                    feeling heart.</p>
                <p>The most important of the works of Photius is his renowned <hi rend="italic"
                    >Myriobiblion,</hi> a collection of extracts from and abridgments of 280 volumes
                    of classical authors, the originals of which are now to a great extent lost.
                    Dictated in haste immediately before his departure on his Eastern embassy, it is
                    open to the charges of imperfect recollection and hasty criticism, but these are
                    as nothing in comparison with its merits. It is especially rich in extracts from
                    historical writers. To Photius we are indebted for almost all we possess of
                    Ctesias, Memnon, Conon, the lost books of Diodorus Siculus, and the lost
                    writings of Arrian. Theology and ecclesiastical history are also very fully
                    represented. The best edition is Bekker’s (Berlin, 1824-25), which, however, has
                    neither notes nor a Latin version. The next of his works in importance is the
                    <hi rend="italic">Amphilochia,</hi> a collection of 333 questions and answers on
                    difficult points in Scripture, addressed to Amphilochius, archbishop of Cyzicus.
                    This valuable work has exposed Photius to charges of plagiarism, which, as he
                    does not claim entire originality, are wholly undeserved. The only complete
                    edition is that published by Sophocles (Economus at Athens in 1858. Photius is
                    further author of a <hi rend="italic">Lexicon</hi> (London, 1822), of a <hi
                    rend="italic">Nomocanon</hi> or harmony of the ecclesiastical canons with the
                    imperial edicts relating to the discipline of the church, a work of great
                    authority, but based on the labours of his predecessors, and of numerous
                    theological writings. The more important of these are his treatise <hi
                    rend="italic">Against the Paulicians,</hi> in four books, and his controversy
                    with the Latins on the procession of the Holy Spirit. His <hi rend="italic"
                    >Epistles</hi> are valuable from their contents, but the style is often affected
                    or unsuitable to the subject. The most complete edition is Valetta’s (London,
                    1864). Many of Photius’s works yet remain in manuscript. The only complete
                    edition is Bishop Malou’s in Migne’s <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Graeca,</hi>
                    and this is very imperfect and unsatisfactory.</p>
                <p>After the allusions in his own writings the chief contemporary authority for the
                    life of Photius is his bitter enemy Nicetas the Paphlagonian, the biographer of
                    his rival Ignatius. In modern times his life has been written with great
                    prejudice and animosity by Baronins, and by Weguelin in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Memoirs of the Berlin Academy,</hi> and more fairly by Hankins <hi
                    rend="italic">(De</hi><hi rend="italic">Byzantinarum Rerum Scriptoribus,</hi>
                    pt. 1). But all previous writers are superseded by the classical work of
                    Cardinal Hergenrother, <hi rend="italic">Photius, Patriarch von
                    Constantinopel</hi> (3 vols., Ratisbon, 1867-69). As a dignitary of the Roman
                    Catholic Church Cardinal Hergenrother is inevitably biassed against Photius as
                    an ecclesiastic, but his natural candour and sympathy with intellectual eminence
                    have made him just to the man, while his investigation of all purely historical
                    and literary questions is industrious and exhaustive in the highest degree. (R.
                    G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
