<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0846-0811-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PHONETICS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 811</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hv6n">Defectives</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xg7p">Gills</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1129153">Speech</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n846/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PHONETICS</label> (τά <hi rend="italic">φωνητικά,</hi> the
                    matters pertaining to the voice, <hi rend="italic">φωνη)</hi> is the science and
                    art of the production of sounds, including cries, by means of the organs of
                    speech in man and their analogues in other animals.</p>
                <p>This very extensive subject may be divided into the following three parts. (1)
                    <hi rend="italic">Anatomical,</hi> the accurate description of all the organs
                    employed, emissive (lungs, with the muscles acting on them, trachea, larynx,
                    pharynx, mouth and its parts, nose and its passages, -with its closing valve the
                    uvula) and receptive (the ear, external and internal, and parts of the brain
                    with which the auditory nerve communicates). As all voice-sounds are produced by
                    imitation, defects in the receptive organs entail defects in the action of the
                    emissive. The congenitally deaf are consequently mute. (2) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Physiological,</hi> the co-ordinated action of the parts just referred to in
                    hearing and uttering sounds, and especially expiration and inspiration, with
                    laryngeal, oral, and nasal actions, and the relation of these actions to the
                    will (on these see <hi rend="smallcaps">Voice).</hi> (3) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Acoustical,</hi> with especial reference to the action of double membranous
                    reeds, as in the glottis; the effects of resonance chambers, both fixed and
                    variable in shape and size, open and closed, single and combined, and of the
                    passage of air, more or less in a state of sonorous vibration, through tubes of
                    variable lengths and widths, with walls of variable hardness, and with or
                    without the interposition of semi-viscous fluids, as well as of flapping,
                    smacking, or vibrating parts, and of other obstructions; also investigations
                    into the nature, production<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n847/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0847-0812"/>, and appreciation of qualities of tone, and their
                    gradual but rapid gliding one into another, as well as into the nature of
                    sympathetic vibration, not only of the different cavities filled with air in the
                    organs of speech but of the solid bony parts, and also the softer cartilages,
                    sinews, and muscles connecting and supporting them. This part of the subject,
                    which is far from having been fully investigated at present, has two main
                    subdivisions—(a) <hi rend="italic">musical,</hi> regarding the nature and
                    properties of musical sound, and especially song, with their varieties due to
                    force, pitch, and quality, as partly investigated in Helmholtz’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Sensations of Tone</hi>; (ð) <hi rend="italic">rhetorical,</hi>
                    regarding the mechanism of speaking as distinct from singing, the blending and
                    differentiation of qualities of tone, partly musical and partly unmusical, with
                    constantly variable and ill-defined pitch and force, influenced by feeling; this
                    subdivision embraces speech in particular, its special sounds for conveying
                    thought and feeling, with their constantly-shifting characters, and also cries
                    of joy and pain, as well as, properly speaking, the cries of the lower animals
                    by which they communicate with those of the same kind; hence it comprehends also
                    language, elocution, and philology in their fundamental constitution.</p>
                <p>In a more restricted sense, applied solely to human beings and to articulate
                    significant sounds (that is, exclusive of cries of pain and pleasure, or the
                    inarticulate and often unconscious noises of snoring, snuffling, gargling,
                    panting, laughing, crying, sobbing, sneezing, and the like), the term
                    “phonetics” is used to designate a work on the enumeration, evaluation,
                    relations, classification, analysis, and synthesis of <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Speech-Sounds</hi><hi rend="italic">(q-v.),—</hi> that is, of the sounds
                    actually used in speech for conveying and recording thought by different nations
                    and tribes, together with a means of fixing them by visible signs. The alphabet
                    has followed speech-sounds with very halting steps. It is only in quite recent
                    times that sufficient knowledge of the nature of speech has been obtained to
                    enable us in some measure to understand and unravel the mysteries of the old
                    enigmatic forms, and thus to construct a securer basis for philology than the
                    guesses on which it once rested.</p>
                <p>In a still more restricted and popular sense the term “phonetics” has been
                    recently used for attempts to construct a new practical alphabet for English or
                    other individual languages, or for several such languages simultaneously, with a
                    view either of superseding the alphabets at present in use, or of improving
                    their employment, or, at any rate, of facilitating the generally very difficult
                    tasks of teaching and learning to read and write. Attempts of this kind are by
                    no means recent: witness Loys Meigret, <hi rend="italic">Traite touchant
                    le</hi><hi rend="italic">commνn vsa(je de l</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic"
                    >escrιtνre</hi><hi rend="italic">francoise</hi> (1545); Sir Thomas Smith, <hi
                    rend="italic">De recta</hi><hi rend="italic">et emendata</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >linguae Aηglicae</hi><hi rend="italic">scriptione</hi> (1568); J. Hart, <hi
                    rend="italic">An</hi><hi rend="italic">orthographie,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >conteyning the due order and reason, howe to write or painte thimage of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">mannes</hi><hi rend="italic">voice, most like to the life or
                    nature</hi> (1569); [William] Bullokars <hi rend="italic">Booke at large for the
                    Amendment of</hi><hi rend="italic">Orthographie</hi><hi rend="italic">for
                    English speech</hi> (1580); Alexander Gill (master of St Paul’s school, London,
                    when Milton was there), <hi rend="italic">Logoηomia Anglica: qud</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">gentis sermo</hi><hi rend="italic">faciUas</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >addiscitur</hi> (1619 and 1621); Charles Butler, <hi rend="italic">The English
                    Grammar, or the Institution of Letters, Syllables, and Words in the English
                    tongue</hi> (1633). All these works are more or less printed in the orthography
                    proposed, and each orthography is different. They are described and illustrated
                    in A. J. Ellis’s <hi rend="italic">Early English Pronunciation,</hi> parts i.
                    and iii. It is, however, not necessary in this place to go beyond attempts made
                    by persons still living. In 1847, after three years of experiments, Isaac Pitman
                    and Alexander John Ellis brought out their phonotypy, consisting of twenty-three
                    old types and seventeen new ones, with which, among much other matter, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Bible</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Phonetic News</hi> newspaper
                    were printed in 1849, and extensive experiments were made, showing that reading
                    in this alphabet could be rapidly taught, and that when children had learned to
                    read phonotypy well they could easily learn to read in ordinary spelling. The
                    new letters were subsequently much and frequently altered in meaning by Pitman,
                    who in 1884 still produced a <hi rend="italic">Phonetic Journal</hi> weekly in
                    his present phonotypy. Very numerous forms of phonotypy, following either the
                    old or the new edition, have also appeared in America. Many other systems have
                    been tried by accenting, italicizing, supernumbering, or diacritically marking
                    the letters to make the ordinary letters of English spelling convey their
                    sounds. Almost every new “pronouncing dictionary” has its own method. This last
                    plan has been, on the whole, successfully applied for teaching to read by many
                    writers. In order to avoid new types, or even accented letters, and yet have a
                    practical phonetic alphabet for English and its dialects, Ellis prefixed to part
                    iii. of his <hi rend="italic">Early English Pronunciation</hi> (1871) an account
                    of “Glossic, a new system of spelling intended to be used concurrently with the
                    existing English orthography, in order to remedy some of its defects without
                    detracting from its value.” This has been extensively used by the English
                    Dialect Society and in Ellis’s works on <hi rend="italic">Pronunciation for
                    Singers</hi> (1877) and <hi rend="italic">Speech in Song</hi> (1878), in which
                    it is fully explained and used in complete practical accounts of the phonology
                    of English, German, French, Italian, and Spanish. Henry Sweet, in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Handbook of Phonetics</hi> (Oxford, 1878), proposed his “Broad
                    Romic,” admitting, however, a feλv inverted letters. Subsequently, the English
                    Spelling Reform Association was started, and great numbers of new attempts at
                    phonetic alphabets for English only were made, which will be found described and
                    illustrated at full length in W. R. Evans’s <hi rend="italic">Spelling
                    Experimenter and Phonetic Investigator</hi> (2 vols., September 1880 to April
                    1883). There is also an American spelling reform association. But neither
                    association has as yet agreed upon a new alphabet. In 1881 the Philological
                    Society of London approved of certain “partial corrections of English spelling”
                    submitted by Sweet, and these are more or less used in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Proceedings</hi> of that society, as edited by Sweet, and are generally
                    approved by the American association, but they are not by any means an entirely
                    phonetic scheme. In the books referred to, and particularly Evans’s, the whole
                    of this special branch of the subject of phonetics, so far as English is
                    concerned, may be sufficiently examined. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. j.
                    e*.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
