<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0435-0414-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PAU</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 414</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:943029">Glass</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:937852">Gardening</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:937845">Gardeners</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kn24">Glass</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mj7p">Beams</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x59s">Calvinism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n435/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PAU</label>, a city of France, formerly the capital of Béarn,
                    and now the chief town of the department of Basses Pyrénées, and the seat of a
                    court of appeal, is situated in 43° 17' N. lat. and 0° 23' W. long., on the edge
                    of a plateau 130 feet above the right bank of the Gave de Pau (a left-hand
                    affluent of the Adour), at a height of about 620 feet above the sea. It thus
                    enjoys an admirable view of the Pyrenees, which rise about 25 miles to the
                    south. A small stream, the Hédas, flowing in a deep ravine and crossed by
                    several bridges, divides the city into two parts. The older and larger is
                    enclosed between the Hédas, the Gave, and its other tributary the Ousse, and
                    ends with the castle in the west, while the new districts stretch northward in
                    the direction of the <hi rend="italic">landes</hi> of Pont-long. The modern
                    importance of Pau is due to its climate, which makes it a great winter
                    health-resort. The most striking characteristic is the stillness of the air,
                    resulting from the peculiarly sheltered situation. The town is built on a sandy
                    soil, and the line of the streets running east and west is favourable to
                    ventilation. The average rainfall is about 40 inches, and the mean winter
                    temperature is 44°, the mean for the year being 62°.</p>
                <p>Apart from an export flour-trade and some manufactures of chocolate and Béarn
                    linen, the inhabitants of Pau depend entirely on their four thousand
                    winter-visitors. Place Royale (in the centre of which, instead of the older
                    statue of Louis XIV., now stands Raggi’s statue of Henry IV., with bas-reliefs
                    by Etex) is admired for the view which it affords over the valley of the Gave
                    and the Pyrenees; it is connected by a fine boulevard with the castle gardens.
                    Beyond the castle a park of thirty acres planted with beech trees stretches
                    along the high bank of the Gave. The castle is bounded on the north and west by
                    the Hédas, on the south by a canal drawn from the Gave, and on the east by a
                    moat 30 feet deep; access is obtained by three bridges, that across the Hédas
                    being of ancient construction. The castle is flanked by six square towers:
                    south-east is that of Gaston Phaebus (113 feet high); north-east is the tower of
                    Montauset or Montoiseau, so called because reached by removable ladders; east,
                    the new tower; north-west, that of Billères; and on the west are those of
                    Mazères. Another to the south is named after the mint in which Calvin used to
                    preach.</p>
                <p>In the gardens to the west of the castle stand a statue of Gaston Phaebus by
                    Triquety and two porphyry vases presented by Bernadotte king of Sweden, who was
                    born at Pau. In the castle court is a well 223 feet deep, with 100 feet of
                    water; but it has been closed since 1855 On the ground-floor is the old hall of
                    the estates of Béarn, 85 feet long and 36 feet wide, adorned with a white marble
                    statue of Henry IV., and magnificent Flemish tapestries ordered by Francis I.
                    Several of the upper chambers are adorned with Flemish, Brussels, or Gobelin
                    tapestry, with tables in Swedish porphyry, Sèvres vases, fine coffers (notably a
                    Gothic coffer from Jerusalem), arm-chairs of the 16 th century, Venetian and St
                    Gobain glass, &amp;c.; but the most interesting room is that in which Henry IV.
                    was born, still containing his mother’s bed (from the castle of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n436/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0436-0415"/> Richelieu) and his own cradle made of a
                    tortoise-shell. In the keep is a library of 6000 volumes, mainly of works
                    relating to Henry IV. The two Gothic churches of St Jacques and St Martin are
                    both modern; but the latter is of note for the height and elegance of its tower,
                    its stained glass, and the fine Pyrenean marbles used in the high altar, the
                    baldachin, and the sanctuary. Besides the state Protestant church (Église
                    Française Réformée) there are Presbyterian, Anglican, and Russian places of
                    worship. The population of Pau (about 6000 at the close of the 18th century) was
                    27,300 in 1871, and 29,971 in 1881.</p>
                <p>Pau derives its name from the “pale” (in Langue d’Oc “paü ”) or palisade
                    surrounding the old castle mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">fors</hi> of Ossau
                    in 1221. By the erection (1363) of the present castle Gaston Phoebus made the
                    town a place of importance, but the viscounts of Beam continued to reside at
                    Orthez till the reign of Gaston XI., when the states of Béarn were united at
                    Pau. Gaston’s grandson and successoι Francis Phoebus, became king of Navarre in
                    1479. Margaret of Valois, who married Henry d’Albret, embellished the castle and
                    gardens, and made her court one of the most brilliant of the time. In the
                    religious disturbances under her daughter, J eanne d’Albret, several Catholic
                    nobles were put to death in the castle as rebels. In 1572, while a prisoner,
                    Henry (afterwards IV. of France) restored the Catholic religion in Béarn, but
                    the provincial estates met at Pau and rejected the decree, which Henry himself
                    cancelled when he obtained his freedom. Pau continued to be the capital till
                    1620, though in 1614 the states of France demanded the union of Béarn and Basse
                    Navarre with the French crown. When Louis XIII. entered the town in 1620 he
                    restored the Catholic clergy to their privileges and possessions, disbanded the
                    forces of Béarn, and caused the parliament of Pau to register the edict of
                    union. The castle was occupied by Abd-el-Kader during part of his captivity.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
