<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0918-0459-0438-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PAVIA (9th edition, volume 18, page 438)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937258">Gallicisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1105547">Sardinians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:938081">Garrisons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133812">Stone</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z186">Gallicisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n873131">Carthusians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rz2q">Cistercians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20f90">Carolingians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x31n">Tombs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n459/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PAVIA</label>, a city of Italy, the chief town of a province,
                    and a bishop’s see, is situated at a height of 270 feet above the sea-level, 22⅛
                    miles by rail south of Milan, on the left bank of the Ticino, about 2 miles
                    above its junction with the Po. The railway from Milan to Genoa, which is there
                    joined by lines from Cremona, &amp;c., crosses the river on a fine bridge
                    constructed in 1865; and, farther down, the city is connected with the suburban
                    village of Ticino by a remarkable brick-built covered bridge dating from the
                    14th century. Though it has lost its importance as a fortified town, and no
                    longer deserves the designation of “City of the Hundred Towers,” Pavia is still
                    for the most part surrounded by its ramparts, which in a circuit of about 3∣
                    miles enclose an area of 400 acres. Several of its buildings are of great
                    architectural interest. The basilica of San Michele is one of the finest
                    specimens extant of the Lombard style (cf. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Architecture,</hi> vol. ii. p. 435), and as it was within its walls that
                    the crown was placed on the head of the “kings of Italy,” from whom the house of
                    Savoy claims to be descended, it has received the legal title of Basilica Reale
                    (royal decree of 1863). A careful restoration has since been effected. The
                    cathedral of San Stefano, of which the first stone was laid by Bishop Ascanio
                    Sforza in 1488, is still unfinished, the original design by Cristoforo Rocchi, a
                    pupil of Bramante, consisting of a central octagon from which four arms
                    projected so as to form a cross. In the interior is the tomb of St Augustine, a
                    remarkable specimen of 14th-century sculpture, which presents the saint
                    life-size in pontifical robes, and is surrounded by a profusion of bas-reliefs
                    and minor figures representing saints of his order, liberal arts, and cardinal
                    virtues—in all, 420 heads. The relics which it enshrines are said to have been
                    brought from Hippo to Sardinia by African refugees, purchased in 724 by
                    Liutprand, and deposited in the now ruined church of San Pietro in Ciel d’Oro,
                    and thence transferred to the cathedral subsequent to their rediscovery in 1695.
                    Beneath the high altar is the tomb of Boetius, whose remains were also brought
                    from San Pietro; and from the roof of the building is suspended the lance of
                    Roland (Orlando).<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                            famous Certosa of Pavia, one of the most magnificent monasteries in the
                            world, is not situated within the city, but at a distance of about 5
                            miles towards the north. Its founder, Gian Galeazzo Visconti (to whom we
                            also owe the Milan cathedral), laid the first stone on 27th August 1396,
                            and the building was nominally finished in 1542. A parallelogram, about
                            140 yards long by 110 broad, is surrounded on all sides by a lofty
                            cloister formed of 123 arches. The church, whose marble façade is more
                            richly decorated than any other in north Italy, is in the form of a
                            Latin cross, 253 feet long by 177 feet wide, with three naves and a vast
                            octagonal dome. In the south transept stands the mausoleum, in Carrara
                            marble, of Gian Galeazzo Visconti, designed by Galeazzo Pellegrini in
                            1490; and in the north transept are the marble statues of Lodovico
                            Sforza il Moro and his consort Beatrice by Cristoforo Solari. The
                            Carthusian monks, to whom the monastery was entrusted from the first by
                            its founder, were bound to employ a certain proportion of their annual
                            revenue in prosecuting the work till its completion; and even after 1542
                            they voluntarily continued to expend large sums on further decoration.
                            The Certosa of Pavia is thus a practical text-book of Italian art for
                            well-nigh three centuries (see Durelli, <hi rend="italic">La</hi><hi
                                rend="italic">Certosa</hi><hi rend="italic">di Pavia,</hi> Milan,
                            1823; and Gruner’s <hi rend="italic">Fresco Decorations,</hi> 1854, and
                                <hi rend="italic">Terra Cotta Architecture in North Italy,</hi>
                            1867). <pb corresp="kp-eb0918-0460-0439" xml:id="pbn9439"/> The
                            Carthusians were expelled in 1782, and, after being held for a time by
                            Cistercians (1784) and Carmelites (1798), the monastery was closed in
                            1810; but it was restored to the Carthusians in 1843, and was exempted
                            from confiscation in 1866. The lead was all stripped from the roof in
                            1797 by order of the French Directory; but the building as a whole is
                            still in excellent preservation.</p></note> Of <pb corresp="pbn9439"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n460/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0918-0460-0439"/> secular edifices in Pavia the most noteworthy
                    is the palace or castle of the Visconti, begun in 1360 for Galeazzo II. It is a
                    vast quadrangle, presenting to the outside heavy fronts of massive masonry, but
                    in the 15th and 16th centuries it was as remarkable for sumptuousness as for
                    strength. Originally there was a square tower at each corner; two were destroyed
                    by the French artillery in 1527.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>See Professor Magenta’s monograph, <hi rend="italic">I
                                Visconti e gli Sforza nel Castello di Pavia,</hi> Milan, 1884, 2
                            vols., folio.</p></note> The university of Pavia (formally constituted
                    in 1361 by the emperor Charles IV., but claiming to have its first origin in a
                    school founded by Charlemagne) has faculties of law, medicine, and science. The
                    professors number between forty and fifty, but the students have decreased from
                    1475 in 1860 to 604 in 1881-82. Among its subsidiary establishments are two
                    colleges—the Borromeo and the Ghislieri—founded respectively by Archbishop
                    Borromeo (1563) and Pope Pius V. (1569) for the gratuitous maintenance of a
                    certain number of poor students; a museum of natural history, instituted in 1772
                    under Spallanzani; a botanical garden, commenced in 1774; an agricultural
                    garden, bestowed on the university by Napoleon in 1806; and the oldest
                    anatomical cabinet in Italy. The university library was founded by Maria Theresa
                    in 1754; the famous collection of books which Gian Galeazzo brought together by
                    the aid of Petrarch was carried off to Blois by the French in 1500. The civil
                    hospital of San Matteo is a large and flourishing institution, dating from 1449;
                    like the Borromeo and Ghislieri colleges, it has large landed estates in the
                    circondario. Comparatively few manufactures are prosecuted in Pavia, but there
                    is considerable trade by water as well as by rail, barges being able to pass
                    down the Po to the Adriatic and along the canal to Milan. The population of the
                    city was 27,885 in 1871 and 27,792 in 1881, or, including the suburbs Ticino,
                    Calvenzano, and Borgorato, 29,836; that of the commune was 29,618 in 1871 and
                    29,941 in 1881.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> Ticinum—it was not till the close of the 7th
                    century that the city was called Papia or Pavia—was a place of some importance
                    under the Roman empire, having, according to Pliny, been founded by two Gallic
                    tribes at the time of the first Gallic immigration into Italy. It was at Ticinum
                    that Augustus met the funeral procession of Drusus; and Claudius II. was first
                    saluted emperor by the garrison in the city. Ravaged by Attila in 452 and by
                    Odoacer in 476, Ticinum was, after 489, raised to much more than its former
                    position by Theodoric the Goth, who restored its fortifications and made it the
                    seat of a royal palace. From Theodoric’s successors it was recovered for the
                    Eastern empire by Narses; but the imperial garrison, after a siege of more than
                    three years, was obliged by famine to surrender to the Lombards in 573, and
                    Ticinum-Pavia became, as the capital of the Lombard kingdom, one of the leading
                    cities of Italy. By the conquest of Pavia and the capture of Desiderius in 774
                    Charlemagne completely destroyed the Lombard supremacy; but the city continued
                    to be the centre of the Carolingian power in Italy, and a royal residence was
                    built in the neighbourhood (Corteolona on the Olona). It was in San Michele
                    Maggiore in Pavia that Berengar of Friuli and his quasi-regal successors down to
                    Berengar II. and Adalbert II. were crowned “kings of Italy.” Under the reign of
                    the first the city was sacked and burned by the Hungarians, and the bishop was
                    among those who perished in the flames. At Pavia was celebrated in 951 the
                    marriage of Otto I. and Adelheid (Adelaide), which exercised so important an
                    influence on the relations of the empire and Italy; but, when the succession to
                    the crown of Italy came to be disputed between the emperor Henry II. and Harduin
                    of Ivrea, the city sided strongly with the latter. Laid in ruins by Henry, who
                    was attacked by the citizens on the night after his coronation in 1004, it was
                    none the less ready to close its gates on Conrad the Salic in 1026. The jealousy
                    which had meanwhile been growing up between Pavia and Milan having in 1056
                    broken out into open war, Pavia in the long run had recourse to the hated
                    emperors to aid her against her now more hated rival; and for the most part she
                    remained, through all the broils and revolutions of the time, attached to the
                    Ghibelline party till the latter part of the 14th century. From 1360, when
                    Galeazzo was appointed imperial vicar by Charles IV., Pavia became practically a
                    possession of the Visconti family, and in due course formed part of the duchy of
                    Milan. For the success which attended its insurrection against the French
                    garrison in 1499 it paid a terrible penalty in 1500, being both given over to
                    pillage and forced to furnish a contribution of 50,000 gold crowns. Having been
                    strongly fortified by Charles V., the city was in 1525 able to bid defiance to
                    Francis I., who was so disastrously beaten in the vicinity; but two years later
                    the French under Lautrec subjected it to a sack of seven days. In 1655 Prince
                    Thomas of Savoy invested Pavia with an army of 20,000 Frenchmen, but had to
                    withdraw after fifty-two days’ siege. During the 18th century the city had its
                    full share of the wars. The Austrians under Prince Eugène occupied it in 1706,
                    the French in 1733, and the French and Spaniards in 1745; and the Austrians were
                    again in possession from 1746 till 1796. In May of that year it was seized for
                    the French republic by Napoleon, who, to punish it for an insurrection,
                    condemned it to three hours’ pillage. The revolutionary movement of February
                    1848 was crushed by the Austrians and the university was closed; and, though the
                    Sardinian forces obtained possession in March, the Austrians soon recovered
                    their ground. It was not till 1859 that Pavia passed with the rest of Lombardy
                    to the Sardinian crown.</p>
                <p>At several periods Pavia has been the centre of great intellectual activity. It
                    was in a tower which, previous to 1584, stood near the church of Dell’
                    Annunziata that Boetius wrote his <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Consolatione</hi><hi rend="italic">Philosophise</hi>; the legal school of
                    Pavia was rendered celebrated in the 11th century by Lanfranc (afterwards
                    archbishop of Canterbury); Christopher Columbus studied at the university about
                    1447; and printing was introduced in 1471. Two of the bishops of Pavia have been
                    raised to the papal throne as John XIV. and Julius III. Lanfranc, Pope John
                    XIV., Porta the anatomist, and Cremona the mathematician were bom in the
                    city.</p>
                <p>See Breventano, <hi rend="italic">I</hi><hi rend="italic">storia</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">di Pavia,</hi> 1570; Marroni, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">ecclesia et episcopis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >papiensibus</hi><hi rend="italic">commentarius,</hi> 1757; Capsoni, <hi
                        rend="italic">Mem. star, di Pavia,</hi> 1782; Carpa-neîli, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Compendio</hi><hi rend="italic">istorico delie cose pavesi,</hi> 1817; and
                    various monographs by the local antiquarians Magenta and Dell’ Acqua.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
