<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0693-0664-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PERSONAL ESTATE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 664</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4w950q6z">Fraud</term>
                    <term n="17" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r05m">Sale</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sc8g">Money</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:933786">Fraud</term>
                    <term n="17" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1115271">Sharing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207035">Louisiana</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204739">Maryland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n693/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PERSONAL ESTATE</label>. Strictly speaking, the term <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Estate</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> is confined in English
                    law to the extent of interest which can exist in real property. But “personal
                    estate” is a term often conveniently, if not accurately, applied to all property
                    that is not real property. The division of property into real and personal
                    represents in a great measure the division into immovable and movable
                    incidentally recognized in Roman law and generally adopted since. “The only
                    natural classification of the objects of enjoyment, the only classification
                    which corresponds with an essential difference in the subject-matter, is that
                    which divides them into moveables and immoveables” (Maine, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ancient Law,</hi> ch. viii.). “Things personal,” according to Blackstone, “are
                    goods, money, and all other moveables which may attend the owner’s person
                    wherever he thinks proper to go” <hi rend="italic">(Comm.,</hi> vol. ii. p. 16).
                    This identification of things personal with movables, though logical in theory,
                    does not, as will be seen, perfectly express the English law, owing to the
                    somewhat anomalous position of chattels real. In England real property is
                    supposed to be superior in dignity to personal property, which was originally of
                    little importance from a legal point of view. This view is the result of feudal
                    ideas, and had no place in the Roman system, in which immovables and movables
                    were dealt with as far as possible in the same manner, and descended according
                    to the same rules. The law of personal property has developed more rapidly and
                    freely than that of real property, as it is of more modern growth and has not
                    been affected by the notion of tenure. The main differences between real and
                    personal property which still exist in England are these. (1) In real property
                    there can be nothing more than limited ownership (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Estate);</hi> there can be no estate properly so called in personal property,
                    and it may be held in complete ownership. There is nothing corresponding to an
                    estate-tail in personal property; words which in real property would create an
                    estate-tail will give an absolute interest in personalty. A life-interest may,
                    however, be given in personalty, except in articles <hi rend="italic">quae
                    ipso</hi><hi rend="italic">usu consumuntur.</hi> Limitations of personal
                    property, equally with those of real property, fall within the rule against
                    perpetuities. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Real Estate.)</hi> (2) Personal property
                    is not subject to various incidents of real property, such as rent, dower, or
                    escheat. (3) On the death of the owner intestate real property descends to the
                    heir; personal property is divided according to the Statute of Distributions.
                    (4) Real property as a general rule must be transferred by deed; personal
                    property does not need so solemn a mode of transfer. (5) Contracts relating to
                    real property must be in writing by the Statute of Frauds, 29 Car. II. c. 3, s.
                    4; contracts relating to personal property need only be in writing when it is
                    expressly so provided by statute, as, for instance, in the cases falling under
                    s. 17 of the Statute of Frauds. (6) A will of lands need not be proved, but a
                    will of personalty or of personal and real property together must be proved in
                    order to give a title to those claiming under it. (7) Devises of real estate
                    fall as a rule within the Mortmain Act, 9 Geo. II. c. 36 (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Charities, Corporation)</hi>; bequests of personal property,
                    other than chattels real, are not within the Act. (8) Mortgages of real property
                    need not generally be registered; mortgages of personal property for the most
                    part require registration under the Bills of Sale Acts (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Pledge;</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Bill of Sale,</hi> vol. iii. p. 674).</p>
                <p>Personal estate is divided in English law into <hi rend="italic">chattels</hi><pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n694/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0694-0665"/><hi rend="italic">real</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >chattels personal</hi>; the latter are again divided into <hi rend="italic"
                    >choses in possession</hi> and <hi rend="italic">choses in action.</hi> Chattels
                    real are personal interests in real estate, which, though they are annexed to
                    land, still descend in the same manner as personal estate. Blackstone speaks of
                    them as being “of a mongrel amphibious nature.” Examples are a term of years,
                    the next presentation to a benefice, an estate <hi rend="italic">pur autre
                    vie,</hi> and money due upon a mortgage. Under the head of chattels personal
                    fall all kinds of property other than real estate and chattels real. In cases of
                    bequest to a charity the terms pure and impure or mixed personalty are often
                    used. The latter class is almost conterminous with chattels real. It falls as a
                    rule within the Mortmain Act. A chose in action denotes the right of recovery by
                    legal proceedings of that which, when recovered, becomes a chose in possession.
                    Choses in action were before the Judicature Acts either legal, as debts (whether
                    arising from contract or tort), recoverable in a court of law, or equitable, as
                    legacies (residuary personal estate of a deceased person), or money in the
                    funds. A legal chose in action was not assignable. A consequence of this view
                    was that until 1875 (subject to one or two statutory exceptions, such as actions
                    on policies of insurance) an action on an assigned chose in action must have
                    been brought at law in the name of the assignor, though the sum recovered
                    belonged in equity to the assignee, and in equity he might have sued in his own
                    name, making the assignor a party as co-plaintiff or as defendant. The
                    Judicature Acts have made the distinction drawn between legal and equitable
                    choses in action of no importance. The Judicature Act, 1873, 36 and 37 Vict. c.
                    66, s. 25, (6), enacts that the legal right to a debt or other legal chose in
                    action may be passed by absolute assignment in writing under the hand of the
                    assignor. The old law as to the reduction into possession by a husband of his
                    wife’s choses in action (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Husband and Wife)</hi> seems
                    to have been practically rendered obsolete by the Married Women’s Property Act,
                    1882. Blackstone, who is followed by Mr Joshua Williams <hi rend="italic">{Law
                    of Personal Property),</hi> recognizes a further division of <hi rend="italic"
                    >incorporeal personal property,</hi> standing between choses in action and
                    choses in possession, and including personal annuities, stocks and shares,
                    patents, and copyrights.</p>
                <p>Interest in personal property may be either absolute or qualified. The latter
                    case is illustrated by animals <hi rend="italic">ferae naturae,</hi> in which
                    property is only coextensive with detention. Personal estate may be acquired by
                    occupancy (including the <hi rend="italic">accessio, commixtio,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">confusio</hi> of Roman law), by invention, as patent and
                    copyright, or by transfer, either by the act of the law (as in bankruptcy,
                    judgment, and intestacy), or by the act of the party (as in gift, contract, and
                    will).</p>
                <p>There are several cases in which, by statute or otherwise, property is taken out
                    of the class of real or personal to which it seems naturally to belong. By the
                    operation of the equitable doctrine of conversion money directed to be employed
                    in the purchase of land, or land directed to be turned into money, is in general
                    regarded as that species of property into which it is directed to be converted.
                    An example of property <hi rend="italic">prima</hi><hi rend="italic">facie</hi>
                    real which is treated as personal is an estate <hi rend="italic">pur autre
                    vie,</hi> which, since 14 Geo. II. c. 20, s. 9 (now replaced by 1 Vict. c. 26,
                    s. 6), is distributable as personal estate in the absence of a special occupant.
                    Examples of property <hi rend="italic">prima</hi><hi rend="italic">fade</hi>
                    personal which is treated as real are <hi rend="smallcaps">Fixtures</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">{q.v.),</hi> heirlooms, such as deeds and family portraits, and
                    shares in some of the older companies, as the New River Company, which are real
                    estate by statute. In ordinary cases shares in companies are personal estate,
                    unless the shareholders have individually some interest in the land as land.</p>
                <p>The terms <hi rend="italic">heritable</hi> and <hi rend="italic">movable</hi> of
                    Scotch law to a great extent correspond with the real and personal of English
                    law. The main points of difference are these. (1) Leases are heritable as to the
                    succession to the lessee, unless the destination expressly exclude heirs, but
                    are movable as to the fisk. (2) Money due on mortgages and securities on land is
                    personalty in England. At common law in Scotland debts secured on heritable
                    property are themselves heritable. But by 31 and 32 Vict. c. 101, s. 117,
                    heritable securities are movable as far as regards the succession of the
                    creditor, unless executors are expressly excluded. They still, however, remain
                    heritable <hi rend="italic">quoad fiseum,</hi> as between husband and wife, in
                    computing legitim, and as far as regards the succession of the debtor. (3) Up to
                    1868 the heir of heritage succeeded to certain movable goods called heirship
                    movables, which bore a strong likeness to the heirlooms of English law. This
                    right of the heir was abolished by 31 and 32 Vict. c. 101, s. 160. (4)
                    Annuities, as having <hi rend="italic">traetum</hi><hi rend="italic">futuri
                    temporis,</hi> are heritable, and an obligation to pay them falls upon the heir
                    of the deceased (Watson, <hi rend="italic">Law Diet., s.v.</hi>
                    “Annuities”).</p>
                <p>The law in the United States agrees in most respects with that of England.
                    Heirlooms are unknown, one reason being, no doubt, that the importance of
                    title-deeds is much less than it is in England, owing to the operation of the
                    Registration Acts. Long terms in some States have annexed to them the properties
                    of freehold estates. Thus in Massachusetts, if the original term be a hundred or
                    more years, it is deemed a fee as long as fifty years remain unexpired <hi
                    rend="italic">(Mass. Gem Stat.,</hi> c. 90, § 20). In the same State estates <hi
                    rend="italic">pur aτιtre vie</hi> descend like real property <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Gem Stat.,</hi> c. 91, § 1). In New York and New Jersey an estate <hi
                    rend="italic">pτιr autre vie</hi> is deemed a freehold only during the life of
                    the grantee; after his death it becomes a chattel real. In other States the heir
                    has a <hi rend="italic">scintilla</hi> of interest as special occupant (Kent,
                    <hi rend="italic">Comm.,</hi> vol. iv. p. 27). In some States railway
                    rolling-stock is considered as purely personal, in others it has been held to be
                    a fixture, and so to partake of the nature of real property. Shares in some of
                    the early American corporations were, like New River shares in England, made
                    real estate by statute, as in the case of the Cape Sable Company in Maryland
                    (Schouler, <hi rend="italic">Law of Personal Property,</hi> vol. i. p. 619). In
                    Louisiana animals employed in husbandry are, and slaves were, regarded as
                    immovables. Pews in churches are generally real property, but in some States
                    they are made personal property by statute, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> in
                    Massachusetts <hi rend="italic">(Gem</hi><hi rend="italic">Stak,</hi> c. 30, §
                    38). The assignment of choses in action is generally permitted, and is in most
                    States regulated by statute. The circuit court has no jurisdiction in the case
                    of an assigned chose in action unless a suit might have been prosecuted in that
                    court if no assignment had been made <hi rend="italic">(Revised</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Stak</hi><hi rend="italic">of U. S.,</hi> tit. xiii. § 629). (J.
                    W+.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
