<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0918-0715-0684-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PESHAWAR (9th edition, volume 18, page 684)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1118436">Sikhs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:798948">Afghans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f47h185">Pathans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62g2p">Sikhs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh0c">Afghans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n715/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PESHAWAR</label>,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>The division of this name comprises the three districts
                            of Peshawar, Kohat, and Hazara, with an area of 8381 square miles. In
                            1881 it had a population of 1,181,289—males 649,509, females 531,780. By
                            religion 1,101,095 were Moslems, 68,992 Hindus, 6724 Sikhs, 4390
                            Christians, and 88 others.</p></note> or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Peshawur,</hi> a district in the lieutenant-governorship of the Punjab,
                    with an area of 2504 square miles, situated in the extreme north-western corner
                    of British India, between 33° 50' and 34° 30' N. lat. and 71° 30' and 72° 50' E.
                    long. Except on the south-east, where the Indus flows, it is encircled by
                    mountains, and is bounded on the N. by the Mohmand, Utman Khel, and other hills,
                    E. by the Indus, S. by the Khatak and Afridi Hills, and W. by the Khyber
                    Mountains. It forms an important part of the frontier of the Punjab, being
                    crossed by the great route from India to Cabul. The only hills of any
                    consequence in the district are the Khatak Hills, a continuation of the Afridi
                    Hills, which are themselves a spur of the great Sufed Koh range. The plain
                    consists of alluvial deposits of silt and gravel, and throughout the whole
                    valley its surface is studded with water-worn shingle or boulders. The district
                    presents, especially in its western and central portions, an appearance of great
                    beauty: it is covered with luxuriant vegetation, which is relieved by the
                    meanderings of the numerous canals and set off by its bare stony surroundings
                    and the far distant snowy peaks. Its rivers, all tributaries of the Indus, are
                    the Cabul, Swat, Bara, Budni, and Ludnai. The district is naturally fertile and
                    well watered, and the valley is entirely drained by the Cabul river. The
                    temperature ranges from a minimum of 17° in February to a maximum of 137° in
                    July. The average rainfall is about 14 inches.</p>
                <p>According to the census of 1881 the population was 592,674, of whom 329,524 were
                    males and 263,150 females. The people are mostly Afghans and almost entirely of
                    the Moslem religion, no less than 546,117 being Mohammedans, while Hindus
                    numbered only 39,321, Christians 4088, Sikhs 3103, and others 45. The largest
                    tribe in the district is that of the Pathans, of whom in 1881 there were
                    276,656. The Moslem portion of the population is occupied chiefly in agriculture
                    and the rearing of cattle, while the Hindus are engaged in trade as bankers,
                    merchants, and shopkeepers. The prevailing languages are the Urdu and
                    Pushtu.</p>
                <p>Out of the total area of 2504 square miles 1414 are cultivated and 470 are
                    returned as cultivable. The chief products are wheat, barley, maize, millet.
                    Peshawar also produces some of the finest rice in the world, known as “Bara
                    rice,” named after the river by which the ground yielding it is irrigated. Since
                    the district came into British possession its trade has increased considerably.
                    The principal foreign markets with which it deals are Cabul and Bokhara; the
                    imports from the former are chiefly silk, nuts and fruits, skins, timber, dyes,
                    and spices, and from the latter gold bullion and gold thread, which go
                    principally to Bombay. The exports consist mainly of piece goods, tea, fancy
                    wares, sugar, salt, and spices. The chief manufactures are Peshawar scarves,
                    celebrated throughout India for their fine texture and tasteful colouring,
                    leather goods, cutlery, the preparation of snuff, and a great deal of
                    broadcloth. . The gross revenue of the district in 1882-83 was £95,931, of which
                    the land revenue contributed £68,201.</p>
                <p>Peshawar in 1881 had five towns with a population exceeding 5000, namely Peshawar
                    (see below); Nowshera, 12,963; Tangi, 9037: Maira Parang, 8874; and Charsadda,
                    8363.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> The first authentic
                    record of the tribes seated about Peshawar is in the time of Mahmud. What little
                    is heard of them before then points to their being a bold and independent race.
                    Buddhism was introduced into the district in the reign of Asoka, 263 B.C., and
                    one of his rock edicts still exists. From the time of Sabuktagin, governor of
                    Khorasan, in 978 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> who took possession of the
                    country up to the Indus, Peshawar became the scene of fierce contests. Mahmud,
                    his son, was the first Moslem conqueror of Hindustan, and succeeded in
                    converting the Pathans to the Mohammedan faith; and this tribe remained true to
                    him in all his subsequent engagements with the infidels. The last decisive
                    battle of Mahmud with the Hindus was fought on the plains of Chach in Rawal
                    Pindi, where he totally defeated Anang Pal, the last champion of the Hindu creed
                    and nationality in the north. For a century and more after Mahmud’s death (1028)
                    Peshawar continued to be a province of Ghazni; and under his numerous successors
                    it acquired great importance, becoming the centre of their dominions, which were
                    extended to Lahore. Timur’s invasion of India at the close of the 13th century
                    did not disturb the district or the tribes about it, but a century later the
                    Khakhai Pathans, a body of roaming adventurers, invaded the district in three
                    main clans—the Yusafzai, Gigianis, and Muhammadzai—and obtained permission from
                    the Dilazaks, who then held it, to settle on a portion of their waste lands.
                    Quarrelling with the Dilazaks, they routed them and swept them into the
                    neighbouring district of Hazara. The Gigianis then settled in the fertile strip
                    of land about the confluence of the Swat and the Cabul; the Muhammadzai took
                    Hashtnagar, and the Yusafzai the remainder of the country north of the Cabul
                    river. For some time these tribes remained unmolested, but in 1519 Babar,
                    fifteen years after his capture of Cabul, allied himself with the injured
                    Dilazaks and subdued the Afghans of Peshawar. After his death in 1530 the
                    country was the scene of constant feuds, which ended in the Dilazaks being
                    completely ousted. The yeaι∙ 1553 marks the last immigration of Afghans into the
                    district. In 1587 Akbar came to the throne. During the next three reigns the
                    valley rendered an unwilling allegiance to the central authority, and in the
                    reign of Aurangzeb the Pathans succeeded in freeing themselves from Mogul
                    supremacy. In 1738 Nadir Shah held possession of the district, and under the
                    succeeding Durani dynasty it was often the residence of the Cabul court. On the
                    death of Timur Shah in 1793 the throne was left to be contended for by his sons,
                    whose adventurous enterprises and varied fortunes form a romantic page in
                    Oriental history. In 1818 the Sikhs advanced into the valley and overran the
                    whole district to the foot of the hills; and the country continued to be ravaged
                    by them until it at last fell into their hands, when they ruled it with their
                    usual severity. In 1848 the district became an integral portion of British
                    India, and, except for its connexion with the mutiny in 1857, there is little
                    else of importance to notice.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
