<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0570-0545-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PERIPATETICS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 545</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1004188">Lyceums</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:915833">Ethics</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1432098">Soul</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1091282">Reasoning</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3p063">Lyceums</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z31nq7b">Ethics</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n570/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PERIPATETICS</label> was the name given in antiquity to the
                    followers of Aristotle, from their master’s habit of walking up and down as he
                    lectured conversationally to his pupils. Others derive the name from the <hi
                    rend="italic">περίπατος,</hi> or covered walk of the Lyceum. An account of the
                    Aristotelian philosophy will be found in the articles <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Aristotle, Ethics, Logic,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysic.</hi> Here
                    it must suffice to recall those features of the system which mainly conditioned
                    the development of the school. Aristotle’s central conception is the correlative
                    opposition of form and matter. This may be called the supreme category under
                    which he views the world; it is the point where, as Zeller puts it, Aristotle’s
                    system at once refutes and completes the Platonic doctrine of the “idea” in its
                    relation to phenomena. But Aristotle did not succeed in expelling the dualism
                    which he blamed in Plato. His deity is pure form, and dwells in abstract
                    self-contemplation withdrawn from the actual life of the world. The development
                    of the world remains, therefore, unrelated to the divine subject. In Aristotle’s
                    doctrine of man, precisely the same difficulty is experienced in connecting the
                    active or passionless reason with the individual life, the latter being a
                    process of development bound up with sense, imagination, and desire. The soul is
                    originally defined as the entelechy of the body, and, moreover, not of body in
                    general but of its particular body. It is impossible, therefore, from this point
                    of view to speak of soul and body as separate entities. Yet Aristotle holds that
                    besides the individual mind, which is all things potentially —which <hi
                    rend="italic">becomes</hi> all things—there is superinduced upon the process of
                    development the active or creative reason, the pure actuality (ev∈pγ∈ια) which
                    the development presupposes as its necessary <hi rend="italic">prius,</hi> just
                    as the world-process presupposes God. This reason is “separable,” and is said to
                    enter “from without” when it unites itself to the process of individual life. It
                    must therefore exist before the individual, and it alone outlasts the death of
                    the body; to it alone properly belong the titles of “immortal” and “divine.” But
                    its relation to the universal divine reason was not handled by Aristotle at all.
                    The question was destined to become the <hi rend="italic">crux</hi> of his
                    commentators. In general it is evident that, if reason in man be identified with
                    the process of natural development (and there is Aristotelian warrant for
                    declaring these to be simply two aspects of the same thing), we drift into a
                    purely naturalistic or materialistic doctrine. On the other hand, the doctrine
                    of the “active reason” may be maintained, but what Aristotle left vague may be
                    further defined. The rational soul of each individual may be explicitly
                    identified with the divine reason. This leads to the denial of individual
                    immortality and the doctrine of one immortal impersonal reason, such as we find,
                    for example, in the rationalistic pantheism of Averroes. A third position is
                    possible, if the statements of Aristotle be left in their original vagueness.
                    Aristotle may then be interpreted as supporting monotheism and the immortality
                    of separate rational souls. This was the reading adopted by the orthodox
                    scholastic Aristotelians, as well as by those early Peripatetics who contented
                    themselves with paraphrasing their master’s doctrine.</p>
                <p>Aristotle’s immediate successors, Theophrastus, who presided over the Lyceum from
                    322 to 288 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> and Eudemus of Rhodes, were
                    distinguished by a learned diligence rather than by original speculative power.
                    They made no innovations upon the main doctrines of their master, and their
                    industry is chiefly directed to supplementing his works in minor particulars.
                    Thus they amplified the Aristotelian logic by the theory of the hypothetical and
                    disjunctive syllogism, and added to the first figure of the categorical
                    syllogism the five moods out of which the fourth figure was afterwards
                    constructed. The impulse towards natural science and the systematizing of
                    empirical details which distinguished Aristotle from Plato was shared by
                    Theophrastus. His two works on the <hi rend="italic">History of Plants</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Causes of Plants</hi> prove him to have been a careful and
                    acute observer. The same turn for detail is observable in his ethics, where, to
                    judge from the imperfect evidence of the <hi rend="italic">Characters,</hi> he
                    elaborated still further Aristotle’s portraiture of the virtues and their
                    relative vices. In his doctrine of virtue the distinctive Peripatetic position
                    regarding the importance of external goods was defended by him with emphasis
                    against the assaults of the Stoics. He appears to have laid even more stress on
                    this point than Aristotle himself, being doubtless led to do so, partly by the
                    heat of controversy and partly by the importance which leisure and freedom from
                    harassing cares naturally assumed to a man of his studious temperament. The
                    metaphysical <hi rend="italic">άπορ'ιαι</hi> of Theophrastus which have come
                    down to us show that he was fully alive to the difficulties that start up round
                    many of the Aristotelian definitions. But we are ignorant how he proposed to
                    meet his own criticisms; and they do not appear to have suggested to him an
                    actual departure from his master’s doctrine, much less any radical
                    transformation of it. In the difficulties which he raises with reference to the
                    relation of the active and the passive reason, as well as in his ascription of
                    the physical predicate of motion to the activity of the soul, we may perhaps
                    detect a leaning towards a naturalistic interpretation. The tendency of Eudemus,
                    on the other hand, is more towards the theological or Platonic side of
                    Aristotle’s philosophy. The <hi rend="italic">Eudemian Ethics</hi> (which, with
                    the possible exception of the three books common to this treatise and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Nicomachean Ethics,</hi> there need be no hesitation in ascribing
                    to Eudemus) expressly identify Aristotle’s ultimate ethical ideal of <hi
                    rend="italic">θεωρία</hi> with the knowledge and contemplation of God. And this
                    supplies Eudemus with a standard for the determination of the mean by reason,
                    which Aristotle demanded, but himself left vague. Whatever furthers us in our
                    progress towards a knowledge of God is good; every hindrance is evil. The same
                    spirit may be traced in the author of the chapters which appear as an appendix
                    to book i. of Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">Metaphysics.</hi> They have been
                    attributed to Pasicles, the nephew of Eudemus. For the rest, Eudemus shows even
                    less philosophical independence than Theophrastus. Among the Peripatetics of the
                    first generation who had been personal disciples of Aristotle, the other chief
                    names are those of Aristoxenus of Tarentum and Dicaearchus of Messene.
                    Aristoxenus, “the musician,” who had formerly belonged to the Pythagorean
                    school, maintained the position, already combated by Plato in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Phaedo,</hi> that the soul is to be regarded as nothing more than
                    the harmony of the body. Dicaearchus agreed with his friend in this naturalistic
                    rendering of the Aristotelian entelechy, and is recorded to have argued formally
                    against the immortality of the soul.</p>
                <p>The naturalistic tendency of the school reached its full expression in Strato of
                    Lampsacus, who succeeded Theophrastus as head of the Lyceum, and occupied that
                    position for eighteen years (287-269 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.).</hi> His
                    predilection for natural science earned for him in antiquity the title of “the
                    physicist.” He is the most independent, and was probably the ablest, of the
                    earlier Peripatetics. His system is based upon the formal denial of a
                    transcendent deity. Cicero attributes to him the saying that he did not require
                    the aid of the gods in the construction of the universe; in other words, he
                    reduced the formation of the world to the operation of natural forces. We have
                    evidence that he did not substitute an immanent world-soul for Aristotle’s
                    extra-mundane deity; he recognized nothing beyond natural necessity. He was at
                    issue, however, with the atomistic materialism of Democritus in regard to its
                    twin assump <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n571/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0571-0546"/> tions of absolute atoms and infinite space. His
                    own speculations led him rather to lay stress on the qualitative aspect of the
                    world. The true explanation of things was to be found, according to Strato, in
                    the forces which produced their attributes, and he followed Aristotle in
                    deducing all phenomena from the fundamental attributes or elements of heat and
                    cold. His psychological doctrine explained all the functions of the soul as
                    modes of motion, and denied any separation of the reason from the faculties of
                    sense-perception. He appealed in this connexion to the statement of Aristotle
                    that we are unable to think without a sense-image.</p>
                <p>The successors of Strato in the headship of the Lyceum were Lyco, Aristo of Ceos,
                    Critolaus (who, with Carneades the Academic and Diogenes the Stoic, undertook in
                    155 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> the famous embassy to Rome, more important in
                    its philosophical than in its political bearings), Diodorus of Tyre, and
                    Erymneus, who brings the philosophic succession down to about the year 100 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> Other Peripatetics belonging to this period are
                    Hieronymus of Rhodes, Prytanis, and Phormio, the <hi rend="italic">delirus
                    senex</hi> who attempted to instruct Hannibal in the art of war. Sotion,
                    Hermippus, and Satyrus were historians rather than philosophers. Heraclides
                    Lembus, Agatharchides, and Antisthenes of Rhodes are names to us and nothing
                    more. The philosophic unfruitfulness of the school during this whole period is
                    expressly charged against it by Strabo, who explains it by his well-known story
                    of the disappearance of Aristotle’s writings after the death of Theophrastus.
                    But it is impossible that this story should be true in the shape in which it is
                    told by Strabo; and a sufficient explanation of the barrenness of the school may
                    be found in the general circumstances of the time. From the outset the
                    characteristic of the Aristotelian philosophy had been its disinterested
                    scientific character; but the age was one for which speculation as such had lost
                    its attractiveness. At such a time it was natural, therefore, that the
                    Peripatetic school should suffer more than the others. It had also in practical
                    matters taken up a mediatizing position, so that it lacked the attractions
                    which, in the case of extreme views, enlist supporters and inspire them with
                    propagandist zeal. The fact, at all events, is not to be denied that, after
                    Strato, the Peripatetic school has no thinker of any note to show for about 200
                    years. With Strato, moreover, the scientific activity of the school has an end;
                    when it received a new infusion of life its activity took another direction.
                    Strato accuses the Peripatetics of this period of devoting themselves to the
                    tricking out of commonplaces. This seems in great measure true of those who
                    still occupied themselves with philosophy; they cultivated ethics and rhetoric,
                    and were noted for the elegance of their style. But the majority followed the
                    current of the time, and gave themselves up to the historical, philological, and
                    grammatical studies which mark the Alexandrian age.</p>
                <p>Early in the 1st century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> all the philosophic
                    schools began to be invaded by a spirit of eclecticism. This was partly the
                    natural result of the decay of speculative interest and partly due to the
                    unconscious influence of Rome upon the philosophers. The Roman mind measured
                    philosophy, like other things, by the standard of practical utility. As an
                    instrument of education, and especially as the inculcator of moral principles,
                    the Roman welcomed and appreciated philosophy; but his general point of view was
                    naively put by the proconsul Gellius (about 70 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi>
                    who proposed to the representatives of the schools in Athens that they should
                    settle their differences amicably, at the same time offering his personal
                    services as mediator. Though the well-meant proposal was not accepted, this
                    atmosphere of indifference imperceptibly influenced the attitude of the
                    contending schools to one another. Thus Boethus the Stoic deserted the pantheism
                    of his school and assigned the deity, as Aristotle had done, to the highest
                    sphere. He 1ikewise embraced the Peripatetic doctrine of the eternity of the
                    world. A similar approximation to Peripateticism is seen in Panaetius. About the
                    same time, Antiochus of Ascalon,founder of the so-called fifth Academy, tried to
                    combine Plato, Aristotle, and Zeno, asserting that they differed only in words.
                    Meanwhile the Peripatetic school may be said to have taken a new departure and a
                    new lease of life. The impulse was due to Andronicus of Rhodes, the well-known
                    editor of Aristotle’s works, who presided over the Lyceum towards the middle of
                    the 1st century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> His critical edition indicated to
                    the later Peripatetics the direction in which they could profitably work, and
                    the school devoted itself henceforth almost exclusively to the writing of
                    commentaries on Aristotle. Boethus of Sidon and Aristo of Alexandria carried on
                    the work of interpretation begun by Andronicus. Boethus appears, like many of
                    his predecessors, to have taken the naturalistic view of Aristotle’s doctrines,
                    and even in some respects to have approximated to the Stoic materialism.
                    Staseas, Cratippus, and Nicolaus of Damascus need only be named as belonging to
                    this century. The most interesting Peripatetic work of the period is the
                    treatise <hi rend="italic">De Mundo,</hi> which has come down to us under
                    Aristotle’s name, but which internal evidence obliges us to assign to a date
                    later than the writings of the Stoic Posidonius. The interest of the treatise
                    lies in the evidence it affords within the Peripatetic school of the eclectic
                    tendency which was then in the air. The admixture of Stoic elements is so great
                    that some critics have attributed the work to a Stoic author; but the writer’s
                    Peripateticism seems to be the more fundamental constituent of his doctrine.</p>
                <p>Our knowledge of the Peripatetic school during the first two centuries of the
                    Christian era is very fragmentary; but those of its representatives of whom
                    anything is known confined themselves entirely to commenting upon the different
                    treatises of Aristotle. Thus Alexander of Aegae, the teacher of Nero, commented
                    on the <hi rend="italic">Categories</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">De
                    Caelo.</hi> In the 2d century Aspasius and Adrastus wrote numerous commentaries.
                    The latter also treated of the order of the Aristotelian writings in a separate
                    work. Somewhat later, Herminus, Achaicus, and Sosigenes commented on the logical
                    treatises. Aristocles of Messene, the teacher of Alexander of Aphrodisias, was
                    the author of a complete critical history of Greek philosophy. This second phase
                    of the activity of the school closes with the comprehensive labours of Alexander
                    of Aphrodisias, the exegete <hi rend="italic">par excellence,</hi> called
                    sometimes the second Aristotle. He became head of the Lyceum during the reign of
                    Septimius Severus, some time between 198 and 211 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi>
                    Alexander’s interpretation proceeds throughout upon the naturalistic lines which
                    have already become familiar to us. Aristotle had maintained that the individual
                    alone is real, and had nevertheless asserted that the universal is the proper
                    object of knowledge. Alexander seeks consistency by holding to the first
                    position alone. The individual is prior to the universal, he says, not only “for
                    us,” but also in itself, and universals are abstractions which have merely a
                    subjective existence in the intelligence which abstracts them. Even the deity
                    must be brought under the conception of individual substance. Such an
                    interpretation enables us to understand how it was possible, at a later date,
                    for Aristotle to be regarded as the father of Nominalism. Form, Alexander
                    proceeds, is everywhere indivisible from matter. Hence the soul is inseparable
                    from the body whose soul or form it is. Reason or intellect is bound up with the
                    other faculties. It exists primarily in man only as a disposition or
                    capacity—voυs <hi rend="italic">υλικός</hi><hi rend="italic">κα,'ι</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">φυσικός</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n572/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0572-0547"/> is afterwards developed into actual intelligence
                    — vous <hi rend="italic">iπlκτητoς—</hi> the <hi rend="italic">intellectus
                    acquisitus</hi> of the Scholastics. The active reason—vous <hi rend="italic"
                    >ποιητικός</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> which effects this development is,
                    according to Alexander, no part of the soul, but simply the divine reason acting
                    upon it. The influence of God upon nature is elsewhere reduced by Alexander, as
                    far as possible, to a mechanical process. Aristotle’s ethico-mystical conception
                    of God as the ultimate and transcendent object of desire is set aside; and the
                    influence of the deity is represented simply as a diffusion of force, first into
                    the heavens and thence downwards, each lower element receiving less according to
                    its greater distance from the source. The commentaries of the Aphrodisian formed
                    the foundation of the Arabian and Scholastic study of Aristotle. Soon after
                    Alexander’s death the Peripatetic school was merged, like all others, in the
                    Neoplatonic. Neoplatonists like Porphyry, Iamblichus, Themistius, Dexippus,
                    Syrianus, Ammonius, Simplicius, and Philoponus carried on the work of commenting
                    on Aristotle till the final disappearance of Greek philosophy. For the further
                    history of Aristotelianism, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Arabian Philosophy</hi> and
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Scholasticism.</hi></p>
                <p>The authorities on whom we depend for our knowledge of the Peripatetics are
                    collected and sifted with exhaustive care by Zeller in the relative sections of
                    his <hi rend="italic">Philosophie der Griechen</hi> (ii. 2 and iii. 1). (A.
                    SE.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
