<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0338-0317-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PARMIGIANO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 317</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47w67561">Visions</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93k3f">Madonna</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hx2m">Piers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96091f">Arches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4wp9t89t">Frescoes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:813061">Arches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:876969">Contracts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:827285">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1063893">Piers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n338/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PARMIGIANO</label> (1504-1540). The name of this celebrated
                    painter of the Lombard school was, in full, Girolamo Francesco Maria Mazzuoli,
                    or Mazzola; he dropped the name Girolamo, and was only known as Francesco. He
                    has been more commonly named II Parmigiano (or its diminutive, Il Parmigianino),
                    from his native city, Parma. Francesco, born on 11th January 1504, was the son
                    of a painter. Losing his father in early childhood, he was brought up by two
                    uncles, also painters, Michele and Pier-Ilario Mazzola. His faculty for the art
                    developed at a very boyish age, and he addicted himself to the style of
                    Correggio, who visited Parma in 1519. He did not, however, become an imitator of
                    Correggio; his style in its maturity may be regarded as a fusion of Correggio
                    with Raphael and Giulio Romano, and thus fairly original. Even at the age of
                    fourteen (Vasari says sixteen) he had painted a Baptism of Christ, surprisingly
                    mature. Before the .age of nineteen, when he migrated to Rome, he had covered
                    with frescos seven chapels in the church of S. Giovanni Evangelista, Parma.
                    Prior to starting for the city of the popes in 1523, he deemed it expedient to
                    execute some specimen pictures. One of these was a portrait of himself as seen
                    in a convex mirror, with all the details of divergent perspective, &amp;c.,
                    wonderfully exact,—a work which, both from this curiosity of treatment and from
                    the beauty of the sitter—for Parmigiano was then “more like an angel than a man
                    ”—could not fail to attract. Arrived in Rome, he presented his specimen pictures
                    to the pope, Clement VIL, who gladly and admiringly accepted them, and assigned
                    to the youthful genius the painting of the Sala de’ Pontefici, the ceilings of
                    which had been already decorated by Giovanni da Udine. Patrons were willing to
                    regard him as a second Raphael for art and for sweetness of manner, and he was
                    almost as skilful at lute-playing as at painting; but, while fortune was winning
                    him with her most insinuating smiles, the utter ruin of the sack by the
                    Constable de Bourbon and his German and other soldiers overtook both Rome and
                    Parmigiano. At the date of this hideous catastrophe he was engaged in painting
                    that large picture which now figures in the London National Gallery, the Vision
                    of St Jerome (with the Baptist pointing upward and backward to the Madonna and
                    infant Jesus in the sky). It is said that through all the crash and peril of
                    this barbarian irruption Parmigiano sat quietly before his vast panel, painting
                    as if nothing had happened. A band of German soldiery burst into his apartment,
                    breathing fire and slaughter; but, struck with amazement at the sight, and with
                    some reverence for art and her votary (the other events of the siege forbid us
                    to suppose that reverence for religion had any part in it), they calmed down,
                    and afforded the painter all the protection that he needed at the moment. Their
                    captain, being something of a connoisseur, exacted his tribute, however—a large
                    number of designs. Rome was now no place for Parmigiano. He left with his uncle,
                    intending apparently to return to Parma; but, staying in Bologna, he settled
                    down there for a while, and was induced to remain three or four years. Here he
                    painted for the nuns of St Margaret his most celebrated altarpiece (now in the
                    Academy of Bologna), the Madonna and Child, with Margaret and other saints. This
                    work became the idol of the Caracci and their school—Guido professing his
                    preference for it even over the St Cecilia of Raphael.</p>
                <p>Spite of the great disaster of Rome, the life of Mazzola had hitherto been fairly
                    prosperous—the admiration which he excited being proportionate to his charm of
                    person and manner, and to the precocity and brilliancy (rather than depth) of
                    his genius; but from this time forward he became an unfortunate, and it would
                    appear a soured and self-neglectful, man. Greatly to his chagrin, a number of
                    his drawings were stolen by his assistant for engraving purposes, Antonio da
                    Trento. He painted, from observation without sittings, a portrait of the emperor
                    Charles V. crowned by Fame, but through some mismanagement lost the advantages
                    which it had bidden fair to procure him. In 1531 he returned to Parma, and was
                    commissioned to execute an extensive series of frescos in the choir of the <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n339/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0339-0318"/> church of S. Maria della Steccata. These were to
                    be completed in November 1532; and half-payment, 200 golden scudi, was made to
                    him in advance. A ceding was allotted to him, and an arch in front of the
                    ceiling; on the arch he painted six figures—two of them in full colour, and four
                    in monochrome—Adam, Eve, some Virtues, and the famous figure (monochrome) of
                    Moses about to shatter the tables of the law. But, after five or six years from
                    the date of the contract, Parmigiano had barely made a good beginning with his
                    stipulated work. According to Vasari, he neglected painting in favour of
                    alchemy—he laboured over futile attempts to “congeal mercury,” being in a hurry
                    to get rich anyhθλv. It is rather difficult to believe that the various graphic
                    and caustic phrases which Vasari bestows upon this theory of the facts of
                    Mazzola’s life are altogether gratuitous and wide of the mark; nevertheless the
                    painter’s principal biographer, the Padre Affò, undertook to refute Vasari’s
                    statements, and most subsequent writers have accepted Affò’s conclusions.
                    Whatever the cause, Parmigiano failed to fulfil his contract, and was imprisoned
                    in default. Promising to amend, he was released; but, instead of redeeming his
                    pledge, he decamped to Casal Maggiore, in the territory of Cremona. Here,
                    according even to Vasari, he relinquished alchemy, and resumed painting; yet he
                    still hankered (or is said by Vasari to have hankered) after his retorts and
                    furnaces, lost all his brightness, and presented a dim, poverty-stricken,
                    hirsute, and uncivilized aspect. A fever carried him off on 24th August 1540,
                    before he had completed his thirty-seventh year. By his own desire, he was
                    buried naked in the church of the Servites called La Fontana, near Casal
                    Maggiore.</p>
                <p>Grace lias always and rightly been regarded as the chief artistic endowment of
                    Parmigiano,—grace which is genuine as an expression of the painter’s nature, but
                    partakes partly of the artificial and affected in its developments. “Un po’ di
                    grazia del Parmigianino” (a little, or, as we might say, just a spice, of
                    Parmigianino’s grace) was among the ingredients which Agostino Caracci’s famed
                    sonnet desiderates for a perfect picture. Mazzola constantly made many studies
                    of the same figure, in order to get the most graceful attainable form, movement,
                    and drapery—the last being a point in which he was very successful. The
                    proportions of his figures are over-long for the truth of nature —the stature,
                    fingers, and neck; one of his Madonnas, now in the Pitti Gallery, is currently
                    named “La Madonna del collo lungo.” He used to ponder long over a picture, and
                    construct it in his head before he began actual work upon it; he then proceeded
                    rapidly, with a resolute pencil, his great exercise in drawing standing him in
                    good stead. His pictures were executed with diligence and finish, although he
                    was not on the whole a sedulous worker. Neither expression nor colour is a
                    strong point in his works; the figures in his compositions are generally few—the
                    chief exception being the picture of Christ Preaching to the Multitude. He was
                    good at portraits and at landscape backgrounds, and famous for drawings; he
                    etched a few plates, being apparently the earliest Italian painter who was also
                    an etcher; but the statement that he produced several woodcuts does not seem
                    to.be correct.</p>
                <p>The most admired easel-picture of Parmigiano is the Cupid Making a Bow, with two
                    children at his feet, one crying, and the other 1 ιughing. This was painted in
                    1536 for Francesco Boiardi of Parma, and is now in the gallery of Vienna. There
                    are various replicas of it, and some of these may perhaps be from Mazzola’s own
                    han I. Of his portrait-painting, two interesting examples are the likeness of
                    Amerigo Vespucci (after whom America is named) in the Studj Gallery of Naples,
                    and the painter’s own portrait in the Uffizi of Florence. One of Parmigiano's
                    principal pupils was his cousin, Girolamo di Michele Mazzola; probably some of
                    the works attributed to Francesco are really by Girolamo. (W. Μ. R.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
