<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0259-0246-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUÉRIN, Georges Maurice de</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 246</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1104803">Sand</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:850627">Centaurs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r48v">Passions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n259/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUÉRIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Georges Maurice de</hi></label>
                    (1810-1839), a French poet, whose few compositions in prose and verse, published
                    posthumously, show him to have possessed a true and rare genius, was descended
                    from a noble but poor family, and was born at the chateau of Le Cayla in
                    Languedoc, 4th August 1810. He was educated with a view to the church at a
                    religious seminary at Toulouse, and then at the Collège Stanislas, Paris, after
                    which he procured entrance to the society at La Chesnaye in Brittany, founded by
                    Lamennais, bishop of Rennes. Here his most intimate companions were persons
                    whose tastes were literary rather than ecclesiastical; and his dreamy and
                    meditative temperament found its solace and happiness more in intercourse with
                    nature than in theological study or the exercises of piety. It was therefore
                    only after great hesitation, and without being satisfied as to his religious
                    vocation, that under the influence of Lamennais he joined the new religious
                    order in August 1833; and when, in September of the same year, Lamennais, who
                    had come under the displeasure of Rome, severed connexion with the society,
                    Guérin’s doubts as to his vocation returned in full force, and on the 7th
                    October he renounced his novitiate. Early in the following year he went to
                    Paris, where he obtained an engagement on the periodical press, but finding it
                    impossible to submit to the mental drudgery of continuous literary work he
                    became a teacher at the Collège Stanislas. In November 1838 he married a Creole
                    lady of some fortune; but a few months afterwards he was attacked by a malady
                    which proved to be consumption, and which terminated by death his short period
                    of leisure and happiness, 19th July 1839. In the <hi rend="italic">Revue des
                    Deux Mondes</hi> for May 15, 1840, there appeared a notice of Guérin by George
                    Sand, to which she added two fragments of his writings—one a composition in
                    prose entitled the <hi rend="italic">Centaur,</hi> and the other a short poem.
                    His <hi rend="italic">Reliquiae,</hi> including the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Centaur,</hi> his journal, a number of his letters, and several poems edited by
                    G. S. Trébutien, and accompanied with a biographical and critical notice by
                    Sainte-Beuve, appeared in 1860 in two volumes; and a translation of it was
                    published at New York in 1867. Though Guérin was essentially a poet, his prose
                    is more striking and original than his poetry. Its peculiar and unique charm
                    arises from his strong and absorbing passion for nature, a passion whose
                    intensity reached almost to adoration and worship, but in which the pagan was
                    more prominent than the moral element. According to Sainte-Beuve, “no French
                    poet or painter has rendered so well the feeling for nature—the feeling not so
                    much for details as for the <hi rend="italic">ensemble</hi> and the divine
                    universality, the feeling for the origin of things and the sovereign principle
                    of life.”</p>
                <p>The name of <hi rend="smallcaps">Eugénie</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Guérin</hi> (1805-1848), the sister of Maurice, cannot be
                    omitted from any notice of him, if only on account of the ties of love that
                    united them; but her <hi rend="italic">Journals,</hi> published in 1861, English
                    translation 1865, and her <hi rend="italic">Lettres,</hi> published in 1864,
                    English traυsla tion 1865, indicated the possession of gifts of as rare an order
                    as those of her brother, though of a somewhat different kind. In her case
                    mysticism assumed a form more strictly religious, and she continued to mourn her
                    brother’s loss of his early Catholic faith. Five years older than he, she
                    cherished a love for him which was blended with a somewhat motherly anxiety. In
                    him she centred her chief earthly hopes, and after his death her only remaining
                    earthly purpose was to rescue his name from oblivion by the collection and
                    publication of the scattered fragments of his writings. She died, however, on
                    the 31st May 1848, before her task was completed.</p>
                <p>See the notices by George Sand and Sainte-Beuve referred to above; Sainte-Beuve,
                    <hi rend="italic">Causeries du lundi,</hi> vol. xii., and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nouveaux lundis,</hi> vol. iii.; G. Merlct, <hi rend="italic">Causeries sur les
                    femmes et les livres,</hi> Paris, 1865; Selden, <hi rend="italic">P Esprit des
                    femmes de notre temps,</hi> Paris, 1864; Marelle, <hi rend="italic">Eugénie et
                    Maurice de Guérin,</hi> Berlin, 1869; Harriet Parr, <hi rend="italic">Μ.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">and E.</hi><hi rend="italic">de Guérin: a</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >monograph,</hi> London, 1870; and Matthew Arnold's essays on Maurice and
                    Eugénie de Guérin, in his <hi rend="italic">Essays in Criticism.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
