<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0218-0207-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GROOT, Gerhard</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 207</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:803903">Aix</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j67907c">Secularism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4154dq9v">Cloisters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2s98r">Augustinians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n873131">Carthusians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n218/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GROOT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Gerhard</hi></label> (1340-1384),
                    in Latin <hi rend="italic">Gerardus Magnus,</hi> founder of the society of
                    “Brethren of the Common Life,” was born in October, 1340, at Deventer, where his
                    father held a good civic position. Other forms of the family name are Groote,
                    Groet, and Groete. At the close of his school education, received partly at
                    Deventer and partly at Aix-la-Chapelle and Cologne, Gerhard (“Gerrit” or
                    “Geert”) in his fifteenth year entered the university of Paris, where lie became
                    firmly attached to the nominalism then in vogue, and where he made distinguished
                    progress in almost all the branches of learning then cultivated,—canon law,
                    medicine, astrology, and even magic being added to the theology and philosophy
                    of the schoolmen. Shortly after his graduation in 1358, he returned to his
                    father’s house at Deventer, where, however, his stay was comparatively brief. We
                    next hear of him as learning and teaching in Cologne; according to one account
                    he studied also at Prague; and in 1366 he visited, on public business it is
                    presumed, the papal court at Avignon. About this time he was appointed io a
                    couple of canonries at Utrecht and Aix-la-Chapelle respectively, and the life of
                    the brilliant young scholar was rapidly becoming luxurious, secular, and
                    selfish, when a great spiritual change passed over him which <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n219/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0219-0208"/> resulted in a final renunciation of every worldly
                    enjoyment. Tl1i3 conversion, which took place in 1374, appears to have been due
                    partly to the effects of a dangerous illness, and partly to the influence of the
                    learned and pious prior of the Carthusian monastery at Munnikhuizen near
                    Arnheim, who had seriously remonstrated with him on the vanity of his life.
                    During the next five years he devoted a considerable portion of his time to
                    repeated and prolonged visits to the monastery of tjιe Augustinian canons
                    regular at Viridis Vallis (Groenendael near Brussels), whose prior, Johann
                    Ruysbroeck, a man of deep though somewhat mystical piety and of considerable
                    literary power, could not fail to impress those who came in contact with him,
                    and many of whose special views are unmistakably reproduced in the writings of
                    Groot and his “fratres devoti.” Between 1374 and 1379 Gerhard had also spent
                    some three years in all at Munnikhuizen in study and prayer; and in the course
                    of the last-mentioned year he left the privacy of the cloister, and having
                    received ordination a3 a deacon, became a missionary preacher within the diocese
                    of Utrecht. The succes3 which followed his labours, not only in the town of
                    Utrecht itself, but also in Zwolle, Kämpen, Leyden, Delft, Gouda, Amsterdam, and
                    many other places, was immense; according to Thomas a Kempis, the people left
                    their business and their meals to hear his sermons, so that the churches could
                    not hold the crowds that flocked wherever he came. The impartiality of the
                    censures, however, which he directed, not only against the prevailing sin3 of
                    the laity, but also against the heresy, simony, avarice, and impurity of the
                    secular and regular clergy, soon provoked the uncompromising hostility of the
                    entire body of the latter; and accusations of heterodoxy speedily began to be
                    brought against him. It was in vain that Groot emitted a <hi rend="italic"
                    >Publica Protestatio,</hi> in which he declared that Jesus Christ was the great
                    subject of his discourses, that in all of them he believed himself to be in
                    harmony with the Catholic doctrine, and that he willingly subjected them to the
                    candid judgment of the Roman Church. By a skilfully framed episcopal edict of
                    1383, which excluded from the pulpit all who had not received priest’s orders,
                    his public preaching wa3 brought abruptly to an end; an appeal to Urban VI. was
                    made in vain. Compelled thus to search for some other field of usefulness,
                    Groot, in conjunction with his friend Florentius, a canon of Utrecht, began to
                    superintend the labours of certain young men who employed themselves in
                    transcribing manuscripts of church fathers and other authors; from time to time
                    as they met to receive payment for their work, he sought to edify them with
                    religious exhortation. Ultimately the idea suggested itself that the little band
                    might throw their earning3 into a common fund and live together according to a
                    fixed rule. The house of Florentius forthwith became a cloister of “fratres
                    vitae communis,” who were speedily joined by many new members, both clerical and
                    lay, practised in a considerable variety of handicrafts; the general rule of the
                    Augustinian order was adopted; it was also agreed that their daily bread should
                    be shared in common, and that it should be earned, not begged. Groot’s private
                    estate sufficed for the establishment on like principles of a sisterhood who
                    supported themselves by spinning, weaving, and needlework. After a comparatively
                    brief life of singular energy, patience, and selfdenial, Groot fell a victim to
                    the plague at Deventer on the 20th of August 1384. Within fifty years of his
                    death the “Brethren of the Common Life,” also called “Fratres bonae voluntatis”
                    or “Fratres Collationarii,” numbered seventeen collegiate churches in the
                    Netherlands, and contributed somewhat extensively to theological literature.
                    Thomas a Kempis, who wrote a <hi rend="italic">Vita Gerhardi Magni,</hi> was
                    trained under Gerhard himself at Deventer. The order disappeared at the time of
                    the Reformation.</p>
                <p>For a very clear and full account of the life of Groot, with an analytic and
                    exhaustive catalogue of his extant works, reference may be made to the article
                    on the “Brethren of the Common Life,” by Hirsche, in Herzog’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Real</hi><hi rend="italic">Eneyklopädie,</hi> ii. 679-696 (1878). The principal
                    original authority is the work of Thomas a Kempis already referred to. See also
                    Ullmann’s <hi rend="italic">Reformers before the Reformation,</hi> whose
                    somewhat <hi rend="italic">ex parte</hi> exposition of Groot’s theological
                    views, however, must be taken with reservations.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
