<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0012-0003-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GOUJON, Jean (9th edition, volume 11, page 3)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x31n">Tombs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1152439">Tombs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:962708">Huguenots</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n12/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GOUJON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jean</hi></label>, was the most
                    distinguished sculptor produced by France during the 16th century. Although some
                    evidence has been offered in favour of the date 1520 <hi rend="italic">(Archives
                        de</hi><hi rend="italic">l’Art français,</hi> vol. iii. p. 350), the time
                    and place of his birth are still uncertain. The first mention of his name occurs
                    in the accounts of the church of St Maclou at Rouen in the year 1540, and in the
                    following year he was employed at the cathedral of the same town, where he added
                    to the tomb of Cardinal d’Amboise a statue of his nephew Georges, afterwards
                    removed. The tomb of Louis de Brezé, executed some time after 1545, has also
                    been attributed to Goujon, but there is no evidence in point, nor even any
                    tradition, of the fact. On leaving Rouen, Goujon was employed by Pierre Lescot,
                    the celebrated architect of the Louvre, on the restorations of St Germain
                    l’Auxerrois; the building accounts—some of which for the years 1542- 44 were
                    discovered by M. de Laborde on a piece of parchment binding—specify as his work,
                    not only the carvings of the pulpit (Louvre), but also a Notre Dame de Piété,
                    now lost. In 1547 appeared Martin’s French translation of Vitruvius, the
                    illustrations of which were due, the translator tells us in his “Dedication to
                    the King” to Goujon, “naguères architecte de Monseigneur le Connétable, et
                    maintenant un des vôtres.” We learn from this statement, not only that Goujon
                    had been taken into the royal service on the accession of Henry II., but also
                    that he had been previously employed under Bullant on the chateau of Éeouen. At
                    the Louvre, Goujon, under the direction of Lescot, executed the carvings of the
                    south-west angle of the court, the reliefs of the Escalier Henri II., and the
                    Tribune des Cariatides. About a year before the execution of the Caryatides, for
                    which Goujon received 737 livres on September 5, 1550, he produced, according to
                    unbroken tradition, the reliefs of the Fontaine des Innocents (Louvre, and <hi
                        rend="italic">in situ);</hi> after which he is supposed to have been
                    occupied in work destined for the decoration of the chateau of Anet, then
                    building for Diana of Poitiers. Unfortunately the building accounts of Anet have
                    disappeared, but tradition not only ascribes to Goujon the <hi rend="italic"
                        >chef d’oeuvre</hi> of French sculpture, the Diane Chasseresse now in the
                    Louvre, but asserts that he also executed a vast number of other works of equal
                    importance, destroyed or lost since 1792. In 1555 his name appears again in the
                    Louvre accounts, and continues to do so every succeeding year up to 1561, when
                    all trace of him is lost. In the course of this year an attempt was made to turn
                    out of the royal employment all those who were suspected of Huguenot tendencies.
                    Goujon has always been claimed as a Reformer; it is consequently possible that
                    he was one of the victims of this attack. We should therefore probably ascribe
                    the work attributed to him in the Hôtel Carnavalet <hi rend="italic">(in
                        situ),</hi> together with much else executed in various parts of Paris—but
                    now dispersed or destroyed—to a period intervening between the date of his
                    dismissal from the Louvre and his death (of which there is no evidence), which
                    is said to have taken place during the St Bartholomew massacre in 1572. Goujon’s
                    work is remarkable—as may be observed in the sculpture of the Louvre—for its
                    perfect harmony with the architectural lines which it was intended to enrich or
                    accompany, and is distinguished in a supreme degree by that elegance which was
                    the leading characteristic of the school of which he was the chief
                    representative. His treatment of the nude (Diane Chasseresse), both in style of
                    line and choice of forms, attains a degree of accomplished perfection which, in
                    its complete fulfilment of the proposed—though very different—ideal, comes
                    nearer to the character of tranquil achievement, which marks all classic art,
                    than any other work of modern times.</p>
                <p>Engravings after Goujon will be found in Cicognara’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Storia</hi><hi rend="italic">della Scultura,</hi> and in Μ. de Clarac’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Musée</hi><hi rend="italic">du Louvre.</hi> Μ. Berty has given
                    a brief notice of his life and works in <hi rend="italic">Grands architectes
                        français de la Renaissance</hi>; and a fuller account will be found in Mrs
                    Pattison’s <hi rend="italic">Renaissance of Art in France.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
