<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0061-0052-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GRANVELLA, Antoine (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    52)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1027556">Motley</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n61/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GRANVELLA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Antoine</hi></label><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Perkenot,</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Cardinal de</hi>
                    (1517-1586), one of the ablest and most influential of the princes of the church
                    during the great political and ecclesiastical movements which immediately
                    followed the appearance of Protestantism in Europe, was born 20th August, 1517,
                    at Ornans, Burgundy, where his father, Nicolas Perrenot de Granvella, who
                    afterwards became chancellor of the empire under Charles V., was at that time
                    engaged in practice as a junior at the provincial bar. On the completion of his
                    studies in law at Padua and in divinity at Louvain, he for a short time held a
                    canonry at Besançon, but his talents had already marked him for a higher sphere,
                    and he was promoted to the bishopric of Arras when barely twenty-three (1540).
                    In his episcopal capacity he attended several diets of the empire, as well as
                    the opening meetings of the council of Trent; and the influence of his father,
                    now become chancellor, led to his being entrusted with many difficult and
                    delicate pieces of public business, in the execution of which he developed a
                    rare native talent for diplomacy, and at the same time acquired an intimate
                    acquaintance with most of the currents of European politics. One of his
                    specially noteworthy performances was the settlement of the terms of peace after
                    the defeat of the Smalkaldic league at Mühlberg in 1547, a settlement in which,
                    to say the least, some particularly sharp practice was exhibited. In 1550 he
                    succeeded his father in the offices of secretary of state and chancellor of the
                    empire; in this capacity he attended Charles in the war with Maurice,
                    accompanied him in the flight from Innsbruck, and afterwards drew up the treaty
                    of Passau (August 1552). In the following year he conducted the negotiations for
                    the marriage of Mary of England and Philip of Spain, to whom in 1555, on the
                    abdication of the emperor, he transferred his services. In April 1559 Granvella
                    was one ofthe Spanish commissioners who arranged the peace of Cateau Cambresis,
                    and on Philip’s withdrawal from the Netherlands in August of the same year he
                    was appointed prime minister to the regent, Margaret of Parma. The policy of
                    repression which in this capacity he pursued during the next five years secured
                    for him many tangible rewards; in 1560 he was elevated to the archiépiscopal see
                    of Malines, and in 1561 he received the cardinal’s hat; but the growing
                    hostility of a people whose moral and religious convictions he had studiously
                    set himself to trample under foot, ultimately made it impossible for him to
                    continue in the Low Countries; and by the advice of his royal master he in 1564
                    retired to Franche Comté. Nominally this withdrawal was only of a temporary
                    character, but it proved to be final. The following six years were spent in
                    comparative quiet, which was devoted chiefly to study and to the society of
                    learned men; but in 1570 Granvella, at the call of Philip, resumed public life
                    by accepting a mission to Rome as representative of the interests of Spain in
                    framing the proposed treaty of alliance with Venice and the papal see against
                    the Turks. In the same year he was advanced to the viceroyalty of Naples, a post
                    of some difficulty and danger, which for five years he occupied with ability and
                    success. Summoned to Madrid in 1575, to be president of the supreme council of
                    Italy and afterwards of that of Castile, he still continued to find ample scope
                    for his rare aptitudes. Among the more delicate negotiations of his later years
                    were those of 1580, which had for their object the ultimate union of the crowns
                    of Spain and Portugal, and those of 1584, which resulted in a check to France by
                    the marriage of the Spanish infanta to Duke Philip of Savoy. In the same year he
                    was made archbishop of Besançon, but meanwhile a lingering disease had laid an
                    unrelenting grasp upon his iron frame; he never was enthroned, but died at
                    Madrid, 21st September 1586. His body was removed to Besançon, where his father
                    had been buried before him.</p>
                <p>Numerous letters and memoirs of Granvella are preserved in the archives of
                    Besançon. These were to some extent made use of by Prosper Levéque in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Mémoires pour servir</hi> (1753), as well as by the Abbé
                    Boisot in the <hi rend="italic">Tresor</hi><hi rend="italic">de Granvella.</hi>
                    A commission for publishing the whole of the letters and memoirs was appointed
                    by Guizot in 1834, and the result has been the issue of nine volumes of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Papiers d'État</hi><hi rend="italic">du Cardinal de
                        Granvellc,</hi> edited by Weiss (1841-1852). They form a part of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Collection de documents</hi><hi rend="italic">inédits sur
                        l'histoire de France.</hi> See also the anonymous <hi rend="italic"
                        >Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">du Cardinal de Granville,</hi> attributed to
                    Courehetet D’Esnans (Paris, 1761), and Motley’s <hi rend="italic">Rise of the
                        Dutch Republic.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
