<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0191-0180-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GREGORY, St, of Nyssa</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 180</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:828168">Basil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:814376">Arianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1180677">Workmanship</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1739809">Manichaeans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198492">Faith</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f8z">Faith</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s33k">Creeds</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp12">Prayer</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v36q">Arianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756s76">Prayers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n191/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GREGORY, <hi rend="smallcaps">St, of Nyssa</hi></label>, one
                    of the great Cappadocians, and designated by one of the later oecumenical
                    coùncils as “a father of fathers,” was a younger brother of St Basil, and was
                    born (probably) at Neocaesarea about 331 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> For his
                    education, which was the best that could be got at that time, he appears to have
                    been chiefly indebted to his elder brother. At a comparatively early age he
                    entered the church, and held for some time the office of anagnost or reader;
                    subsequently he manifested a desire to devote himself to the secular life as a
                    rhetorician; but this impulse was checked by the earnest remonstrances of
                    Gregory Nazianzen. Finally, in 371 or 372 he was ordained by his brother Basil
                    to the bishopric of Nyssa, a small town in Cappadocia. Here he is usually said
                    (but on inadequate data) to have adopted the opinion then gaining ground in
                    favour of the celibacy of the clergy, and to have separated from his wife
                    Theosebia, who became a deaconess in the church. His strict orthodoxy on the
                    subject of the Trinity and the Incarnation, together with his vigorous
                    eloquence, combined to make him peculiarly obnoxious to the Arian faction, which
                    was at that time in the ascendant through the protection of the emperor Valens;
                    and in 375, on the ground of alleged irregularities in his election, and in the
                    administration of the finances of his diocese, he was driven into exile, whence
                    he did not return till the publication of the edict of Gratian in 378. Shortly
                    afterwards he took part <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n192/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0192-0181"/> in the proceedings of the synod which met at
                    Antioch in Caria, principally in connexion with the Meletian schism. At the
                    great oecumenical council held at Constantinople in 381, he was a conspicuous
                    champion of the orthodox faith; according to Nicephorus, indeed, the additions
                    made to the Nicene creed were entirely due to his suggestion, but this statement
                    is of doubtful authority. That his eloquence was highly appreciated is shown by
                    the facts that he pronounced the discourse at the consecration of Gregory of
                    Nazianzus, and that he was chosen to deliver the funeral oration on the death of
                    Meletius the first president of the council. In the following year, moreover
                    (382), he was commissioned by the council to inspect and set in order the
                    churches of Arabia, in connexion with which mission he also visited Jerusalem.
                    The impressions he gathered from this journey may, in part at least, be gathered
                    from his famous letter <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Euntibus
                    Hierosolyma,</hi> in which an opinion strongly unfavourable to pilgrimages is
                    expressed. In 383 he was probably again in Constantinople; where in 385 he
                    pronounced the funeral orations of the princess Pulcheria and afterwards of the
                    empress Placilla. Once more we read of him in 394 as having been present in that
                    metropolis at the synod held under the presidency of Nectarius to settle a
                    controversy which had arisen among the bishops of Arabia; in the same year he
                    assisted at the consecration of the fine new church of the apostles at
                    Chalcedon, on which occasion there is reason to believe that his discourse
                    commonly but wrongly known as that ε⅛ <hi rend="italic">την</hi> εαυτού
                    χ∈ιpoτovιαy wa3 delivered. The exact date of his death is unknown; some
                    authorities refer it to 396, others to 400. His festival is observed by the
                    Greek Church on January 10th; in the Western martyrologies he is commemorated on
                    March 9 th.</p>
                <p>Gregory of Nyssa is generally admitted to have excelled both his brother Basil
                    and Gregory of Nazianzus alike in the natural vigour of his intellect and in the
                    wide extent of his acquirements. His teaching though strictly trinitarian, shows
                    considerable freedom and originality of thought; in many points his mental and
                    spiritual affinities with Origen show themselves with advantage; though in one
                    particular—namely, in his doctrine of <hi rend="italic">i∙ποκατiστασιs</hi> or
                    final restoration—his views have since been repudiated by the orthodox. His
                    style has been frequently praised by competent authorities for sweetness,
                    richness, and elegance. His numerous works may be classified under five
                    heads:—(1.) Treatises in doctrinal and polemical theology. Of these the most
                    important is that <hi rend="italic">Against Eunοmius</hi> in twelve books. Its
                    doctrinal thesis (which is supported with great philosophic acumen and
                    rhetorical power) is the divinity and consubstantiality of the Word;
                    incidentally the character of Basil, which Eunomius had aspersed, is vindicated,
                    and the heretic himself is held up to scorn and contempt. This is the work
                    which, most probably in a shorter draft, was read by its author when at
                    Constantinople before Gregory Nazianzen and Jerome in 381 (Jerome, <hi
                    rend="italic">De Vir. III.,</hi> 128). To the same class belong the treatise <hi
                    rend="italic">To Aι</hi><hi rend="italic">∣</hi><hi rend="italic">lavius,</hi>
                    against the tritheists; <hi rend="italic">On Faith,</hi> against the Arians; <hi
                    rend="italic">On Common Notions,</hi> in explanation of the terms in current
                    employment with regard to the Trinity; <hi rend="italic">Ten Syllogisms,</hi>
                    against the Manichaeans; <hi rend="italic">To Theophilus,</hi> against the
                    Apollinarians; an <hi rend="italic">Antirrhetic</hi> against the same; <hi
                    rend="italic">Against Fate,</hi> a disputation with a heathen philosopher; the
                    <hi rend="italic">Oratio</hi><hi rend="italic">Catechetica Magna</hi>; and the
                    dialogue <hi rend="italic">De Anima</hi><hi rend="italic">et Resurrectione.</hi>
                    (2.) Practical treatises. To this category belong the tracts <hi rend="italic"
                    >On Virginity</hi> and <hi rend="italic">On Pilgrimages·,</hi> as also the <hi
                    rend="italic">Canonical Epistle</hi> upon the rules of penance. (3.) Expository
                    and homiletical works, including the <hi rend="italic">Hexaemeron,</hi> and
                    several series of discourses <hi rend="italic">On the Workmanship) of Man, On
                    the Inscriptions of the Psalms, On the Sixth Psalm, On the first three Chapters
                    of Ecclesiastes, On Canticles, On the Lord's Prayer,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >On the Eight Beatitudes.</hi> (4. ) Biographical, consisting chiefly of funeral
                    orations. (5.) Letters. The only complete editions of the whole works are those
                    by Fronton le Duc (Fronto Ducaeus, Paris, 1615; with additions, 1618 and 1638)
                    and by Migne. Of the new edition projected by F. Oehler only the first volume,
                    containing the <hi rend="italic">Opera</hi><hi rend="italic">Dogmatica,</hi> has
                    appeared (1865). There have been numerous editions of several single treatises,
                    as for example of the <hi rend="italic">Gratio</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Catechetica, De</hi><hi rend="italic">Precatione,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">De
                    Anima</hi><hi rend="italic">et Resurrectione.</hi> See the monograph by Rupp <hi
                    rend="italic">(Gregors, des Bischofs von Nyssa,</hi><hi rend="italic">Leben und
                    Meinungen,</hi> Leipsic, 1834), and compare Heyns <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Disputatio</hi><hi rend="italic">historico-theologica de Greg. Nyss.,</hi>
                    1835), Moller <hi rend="italic">(Grcgorii Nyss.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >doctrinam</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">hominis natura et
                    illustravit et</hi><hi rend="italic">cum Origeniana</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >comparavit,</hi> 1854), and Stigler, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Psychologie</hi><hi rend="italic">des h. Gregors von Nyssa</hi>
                    (Ratisbon, 1857).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
