<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0206-0195-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GRIFFIN, Gerald (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    195)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k35mj2c">Griffin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq8b">Tides</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:998850">Limericks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947931">Griffins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150792">Tides</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n206/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GRIFFIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Gerald</hi></label>
                    (1803-1840), an Irish novelist and dramatic writer, was descended from a family
                    of good position, and was born at Limerick 12th December 1803. He was the
                    youngest of nine sons. After attending for some time the school of an eccentric
                    preceptor in Limerick, he, on the removal of the family in 1810 to Fairy Lawn, a
                    country place on the banks of the Shannon, was placed under the instruction of a
                    private tutor, but in 1814 he returned to Limerick to attend a classical school.
                    In his youth his devotion seems to have been pretty equally divided between
                    books and out-door recreations with the rod and gun. His parents and a portion
                    of the family emigrated in 1820 to America, but he and some others were left
                    with an elder brother who was settled as a medical practitioner at Adar⅛ near
                    Limerick, and under his direction Gerald made some progress in medical studies
                    with the view of adopting that profession. It would appear, however, that very
                    soon his intentions underwent a change, for, besides devoting a large part of
                    his time to literary composition, he as early as his eighteenth year undertook
                    for a short time the editorship of a newspaper in Limerick. Having completed a
                    tragedy, <hi rend="italic">Aguire,</hi> which was highly lauded by his friends,
                    he finally in 1823 set out for London with the purpose of “revolutionizing the
                    dramatic taste of the time by writing for the stage.” Notwithstanding, however,
                    the efforts and recommendations of the novelist Banim, who showed him great
                    kindness, he found no manager willing to accept any of his plays; and for a
                    considerable period he had such a hard and wearisome struggle with poverty and
                    disappointment as permanently to injure his health. For some time he barely
                    supported himself by reporting trials for the newspapers and by various kinds of
                    hack work; but his prospects began to brighten a little when he obtained
                    occupation as a parliamentary reporter, and gradually the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Literary Gazette,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Hews of Literature,</hi> and
                    other periodicals of standing began to look upon his contributions with favour.
                    Some of his dramatic pieces were accepted also by one of the theatres: and the
                    publication in 1827 of a series of <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n207/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0207-0196"/> tales under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Holland Tide</hi> was so successful that he at once set about the
                    preparation of a similar series, which appeared the same year in two volumes
                    under the title of <hi rend="italic">Tales of the Munster Festivals,</hi> and
                    were still more popular. In 1828 appeared the <hi rend="italic">Collegians,</hi>
                    afterwards so successfully adapted for the stage under the title of the <hi
                        rend="italic">CοUeen Bawn.</hi> It is said to have been the favourite novel
                    of O’Connell; and, besides exhibiting that masterly delineation of both the
                    pathetic and the humorous features of Irish character already shown in his other
                    works, it was written with a verve and a dramatic intensity and realism far
                    surpassing all his previous or subsequent efforts. His principal other works are
                        <hi rend="italic">The Invasion, The Rivals, Tracey’s Ambition,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">The Tales of Five Senses.</hi> He is also the author of a
                    number of lyrics which are generally pervaded by a tender and sad cast of
                    sentiment. When Griffin appeared to have achieved the literary success for which
                    he had had such a hard struggle, he began to feel a growing distaste for his
                    profession. He became doubtful as to the moral influence of his writings, and as
                    to whether on that account he had not been “misspending his time ;” and
                    ultimately he came to the conclusion that his true sphere of duty was to be
                    found within the walls of a monastery,—a resolve doubtless partly attributable
                    to the state of his health. He was admitted into a Dublin monastery in September
                    1838 under the name of Brother Joseph, and in the following summer he removed to
                    Cork, where he died of typhus fever 12th June 1840. Previous to adopting the
                    monastic habit he burned all his manuscripts; but <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gisippus,</hi> a tragedy which he had composed in his twenty-fifth year,
                    accidentally escaped destruction, and in 1842 was put on the Drury Lane stage by
                    Mr Macready, and acted with great success. The collected works of Gerald Griffin
                    were published in 1843 in eight volumes, with a memoir by his brother. See also
                        <hi rend="italic">Dublin University Magazine</hi> for February 1844.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
