<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0165-0154-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GREEK CHURCH, The, or more properly the Eastern
                    Church</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 154</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1141359">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1939192">Metropolitans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="17" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204622">Georgia</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206063">Lebanon</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="24" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n165/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GREEK CHURCH, <hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi>, or more properly
                    the Eastern Church</label>, is both the source and background of the Western.
                    Christianity arose in the East, and Greek was the language of the Scriptures and
                    early services of the church, but when Latin Christianity established itself in
                    Europe and Africa, and when the old Roman empire fell in two, and the eastern
                    half became separate in government, interests, and ideas from the western, the
                    term Greek or Eastern Church acquired gradually a fixed meaning. It denoted the
                    church which included the patriarchates of Antioch, Alexandria, Jerusalem, and
                    Constantinople, and their dependencies. The ecclesiastical division of the early
                    church, at least within the empire, was based upon the civil. Constantine
                    introduced a new partition of the empire into dioceses, and the church adopted a
                    similar division. The bishop of the chief city in each diocese naturally rose to
                    a pre-eminence, and was commonly called <hi rend="italic">exarch—</hi> a title
                    borrowed from the civil jurisdiction. In process of time the common title <hi
                    rend="italic">patriarch</hi> was restricted to the most eminent of these
                    exarchs, and councils decided who were worthy of the dignity. The council of
                    Nicaea recognized three patriarchs —the bishops of Rome, Alexandria, and
                    Antioch. To these were afterwards added the bishops of Constantinople and
                    Jerusalem. When the empire was divided, there was one patriarch in the West, the
                    bishop of Rome, while in the East there were at first two, then four, and
                    latterly five. This geographical fact has had a great deal to do in determining
                    the character of the Eastern Church. It is not a despotic monarchy governed from
                    one centre and by a monarch in whom plenitude of power resides. It is an
                    oligarchy of patriarchs. It is based, of course, on the great body of bishops;
                    but episcopal rule, through the various grades of metropolitan, primate, exarch,
                    attains to sovereignty only in the five patriarchal thrones. Each patriarch is,
                    within his diocese, what the Gallican theory makes the pope in the universal
                    church. He is supreme, and not amenable to any of his brother patriarchs, but is
                    within the jurisdiction of an oecumenical synod. This makes the Greek Church
                    quite distinct in government and traditions of polity from the Western. It has
                    ever been the policy of Rome to efface national distinctions, but under the
                    shadow of the Eastern Church national churches have grown and flourished.
                    Revolts against Rome have always implied a repudiation of the ruling principles
                    of Ultramontanism; but the schismatic churches of the Eaβt have always
                    reproduced the ecclesiastical polity of the church which they have deserted.</p>
                <p>The Greek Church, like the Roman, soon spread out far beyond the imperial
                    dioceses which at first fixed its boundaries, but,unlike the Roman, it did not
                    keep for Christianity all the lands it had once laid hold of. What Rome
                    Christianized, with the exception of Africa, remained Christian. The old empire
                    was overrun by the barbarians, but the conquered empire imposed its law and its
                    religion upon its conquerors, and pagan and heretic became in the end Catholic
                    Christians. In the East it was otherwise. The empire naintained itself long and
                    died hard; but its decline and fall meant not merely the overthrow of the
                    supremacy of the emperors of the East, it meant also the destruction of
                    civilization and the submergence of Christianity. In the West, German and Saxon,
                    and Goth and Lombard, became Christian law-abiding peoples. In the E⅛st Arab and
                    Kurd, the Seljuk and Ottoman Turk, remained what they were before they swarmed
                    over the Eastern empire, and could never be taught either law or gospel. It is
                    true that the Eastern Church more than made up for her losses by her missionary
                    enterprise, but she never conquered her conquerors, and the historian is too apt
                    to speak of her past glories and forget her present strength. The same reason
                    also makes it difficult to describe, with any accuracy, the extent of the Greek
                    Church She has shifted her position so often that to describe her extent at any
                    one period must be misleading. The church never at any one period occupied all
                    the territories she has possessed.</p>
                <p>The patriarchate of Constantinople included the imperial dioceses of Pontus,
                    Asia, Thrace, and Eastern Illyricum— <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> speaking
                    roughly, the greater part of Asia Minor, European Turkey, and Greece, with a
                    small portion of Austria. The imperial diocese of Pontus was governed by the
                    exarch of Caesarea, who ruled over thirteen metropolitans with more than 100
                    suffragans; now there are nine metropolitans (Kaisariéh, Nisi, Angouri, Niksar,
                    Amasia, Isinid, Kadi-kiov, Broussa, Iznik), and one archbishopric (Trebizond),
                    but the suffragans seem to have disappeared. Asia was governed by the exarch of
                    Ephesus, who ruled over twelve metropolitans with more than 350 suffragan
                    bishops. Of these there remain Ephesus, with its suffragans Aidene and Chisme,
                    Smyrna, Artaki, Marmora, Allah Shehr, Rhodes, Samos, Khio, Cos, Paronaxia,
                    Santorina, Andro, Milo, Lero, Scarpanto, Sephanto, Imbro, Lemno, Metelini,
                    Molivo, Myra, and Konieh. In Asia Minor the church maintains but a small remnant
                    of her former greatness; in Europe it is otherwise. The old outlines, however,
                    are effaced wherever the Christian races have emancipated themselves from the
                    Turkish rule, and the national churches of Greece, Servia, and Roumania have
                    reorganized themselves on a new basis. Where the Turkish rule still prevails the
                    church retains her old organization, but greatly impaired. The national churches
                    of Russia, Georgia, and Armenia are offshoots from the patriarchate of
                    Constantinople, but quite independent of its jurisdiction.</p>
                <p>The patriarchate of Antioch has undergone most changes in extent of jurisdiction,
                    arising from the transfer of sees to Jerusalem, from the progress of the
                    schismatic churches of the East, and from the conquests of the Mahometans. At
                    the height of his power the patriarch of Antioch ruled over 12 metropolitans and
                    250 suffragan bishops. Tn the time of the first crusade 153 still survived; now
                    there are scarcely 20. Most of those that remain are called either metropolitan
                    or archiépiscopal sees, but they have few or no suffragans. In Syria there are
                    still Antioch, Aleppo, Laodicea, and Arcadia; in Phoenicia, Tyre and Sidon,
                    Beyrout, Tripolis, Emesa, and Heliopolis; in Cilicia, Adana; in Syria,
                    Epiphania; in Isauria, Seleucia; in Cyprus, Famagosta, with Piscopa, Baffo,
                    Neapolis, Limasol, and Nicosia as suffragan sees. Cyprus has been independent of
                    Antioch, however, since the council of Ephesus. Antioch also had jurisdiction
                    beyond the bounds of the empire over Chaldaea and India, and the missionaries of
                    Antioch seem to have preached Christianity in the borders of China. The
                    Chaldaean Church now, however, is almost entirely Nestorian. The Thomas
                    Christians of India do not belong to the Orthodox Greek Church. In Syria the
                    Jacobites are more numerous than the Orthodox; while the Maronites of Lebanon
                    have become subject to Rome.</p>
                <p>In the earlier period of the church, ecclesiastical followed civil divisions so
                    closely that Jerusalem, in spite of the sacred associations connected with it,
                    was merely an ordinary bishopric dependent on the metropolitan of Caesarea,
                    Ambitious prelates had from time to time endeavoured to advance the pretensions
                    of their see, but it was not until the council of Chalcedon, in 451, that
                    Jerusalem was made a patriarchate with jurisdiction over Palestine. From this
                    time on to the inroad of the Saracens, the patriarchate of Jerusalem was highly
                    prosperous. It ruled over three metro-&gt; politans with eighty suffragans. The
                    modern patriarch has seven suffragans, all of whom enjoy the titles of
                    metropolitan or archbishop,—Caesarea, Scythopolis (Bethshan), Petra, Ptolemais,
                    Sinai, Nablous, Samaria. The patriarchs, however, are non-resident (they live in
                    Constantinople), and the primate of Palestine is the metropolitan of
                    Caesarea.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n166/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0166-0155"/>
                <p>The patriarch of Alexandria in ancient times possessed much more power than the
                    others, and the church ruled by him was much more centralized. He had no
                    metropolitans. His hundred suffragans were ordinary bishops. This perhaps in
                    part accounts for the decay of the Orthodox church in Egypt; at present there is
                    no bishop but the patriarch, The Christians in Egypt are for the most part
                    Monophysites. The church of Nubia has been blotted out. The church of Aethiopia
                    or Abyssinia is Monophysite, and acknowledges the Jacobite patriarch of
                    Cairo.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">History.—</hi><hi rend="italic">Controversies and
                    Schisms.—</hi> To describe the controversies of the Greek Church is to write the
                    history of the church of the first five centuries; in a short sketch like this
                    all that can be done is to mention those causes of division which led (1) to the
                    formation of the schismatic churches of the East, and (2) to the open rupture
                    with Latin Christianity.</p>
                <p>The great dogmatic work of the Greek Church was the definition of that portion of
                    the creed of Christendom which concerns <hi rend="italic">theology proper,—</hi>
                    the doctrines of the essential nature of the Godhead, and the doctrine of the
                    Godhead in relation with manhood in the incarnation, while it fell to the Latin
                    Church to define <hi rend="italic">anthropology,</hi> or the doctrine of man’s
                    nature and needs. The controversies which concern us are all about the person of
                    Christ, the Theanthropos, for they alone are represented in the schismatic
                    churches of the East. These controversies are most easily described, at least
                    for our purpose, by reference to the oecumenical councils Df the ancient and
                    undivided church.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Pise of Sects.—</hi> All the churches of the East, schismatic
                    as well as orthodox, accept unreservedly the decrees of the first two councils.
                    The schismatic churches protest against the additions made to the creeds of
                    Nicaea and Constantinople by succeeding councils. The Nicaeo-Constantinopolitan
                    creed declared that Christ was <hi rend="italic">consubstantial (fμοονσιοs)</hi>
                    with the Father, and that He <hi rend="italic">had become man
                    (⅛ανθρω7rησας).</hi> Disputes arose when theologians tried to explain the latter
                    phrase. These differences took two separate and extreme types, the one of which
                    forcibly separated the two natures so as to deny anything like a real union,
                    while the other insisted upon a mixture of the two, or an absorption of the
                    human in the divine. The former was the creed of Chaldaea and the latter the
                    creed of Egypt; Chaldaea was the home of Nestorianism, Egypt the land of
                    Monophysitism. The Nestorians accept the decisions of the first two councils,
                    and reject the decrees of all the rest as unwarranted alterations of the creed
                    of Nicaea. The Monophysite3 accept the first three councils, but reject the
                    decree of Chalcedon and all that come after it.</p>
                <p>The council of Ephesus, the third oecumenical, had insisted upon applying the
                    term Theotokos to the Virgin Mary, and this was repeated in the symbol of
                    Chalcedon, which says that Christ was born of the Virgin Mary, the Theotokos,
                    “according to the manhood.” The same symbolalso declares that Christ is “to be
                    acknowledged in two natures, . . . indivisibly and inseparably.” Hence the
                    Nestorians, who insisted upon the duality of the natures to such a degree as to
                    lose sight of the unity of the person, and who rejected the term Theotokos,
                    repudiated the decrees both of Ephesus and of Chalcedon, and upon the
                    promulgation of the decrees of Chalcedon formally separated from the church.
                    Nestorianism had sprung from an exaggeration of the theology of the school of
                    Antioch, and the schism weakened that patriarchate and its dependencies. It took
                    root in Chaldaea, and became very powerful. No small part of the literature and
                    science of the Mahometan Arabs came from Nestorian teachers, and Nestorian
                    Christianity spread widely. “It was successfully preached to the Bactrians, th⅛
                    Huns, the Persians, the Indians, the Persarmenians, the Medes, the Elamites. The
                    barbaric churches from the Gulf of Persia to the Caspian Sea were almost
                    infinite. . . . The Malabar coast and the Isles of the Ocean, Zocotra and
                    Ceylon, were peopled with an increasing number of Christians. The missionaries
                    of Balkh and Samarcand pursued without fear the footsteps of the roving Tartar,
                    and insinuated themselves into the valleys of the Imaus and the banks of the
                    Selinga.” Their principal bishop took the title of patriarch of Babylon. His
                    seat was later removed to Baghdad and then to Mosul; it is now at Julamerik in
                    Kurdistan. In the 11th century he ruled over twenty-five metropolitans, and his
                    jurisdiction extended from the Tigris to China, from Lake Baikal to South India.
                    Persecutions weakened the church, Timur almost extirpated it. In the 16th
                    century a schism occurred; many of the Nestorians yielded obedience to Rome. The
                    Roman Nestorians are usually called Chaldaeans, though all lay claim to the
                    title. At present the patriarch rules over two metropolitans and sixteen
                    suffragan bishops. The Nestorians dwell principally in Kurdistan, though many
                    are found in Mesopotamia and in India. In the latter country they are numerous
                    on the Malabar coast, and are called Thomas Christians.</p>
                <p>The council of Chalcedon, the fourth oecumenical, declared that Christis to be
                    acknowledged “in two natures— unconfusedly, unchangeably,” and therefore decided
                    against the opinions of all who either believed that the divinity is the sole
                    nature of Christ, or who, rejecting this, taught only one composite nature of
                    Christ (one nature and one person, instead of two natures and one person). The
                    advocates of the one nature theory were called Monophysites, and they gave rise
                    to numerous sects, and to at least three separate national churches—the
                    Jacobites of Syria, the Copts of Egypt, and the Abyssinian Church.</p>
                <p>The term “Jacobite” (from Jacobus Baradaeus, a Syrian theologian) is properly
                    confined to the Syrian Monophysites, but is sometimes used to denote all the
                    various divisions of this heresy, The Jacobites therefore accept the first three
                    councils and reject those that follow. The Armenian Church does the same, and it
                    is common to class the Armenians with the Jacobites, while some theologians have
                    made them more heretical than the Jacobites of Syria and Egypt (Neale, <hi
                    rend="italic">Holy Eastern Church, Patriarchate of Alexandria,</hi> pp. 8-10).
                    This, however, seems a wrong opinion, and the Armenians ought to be reckoned as
                    Orthodox (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Armenian Church).</hi> Apart, however, from
                    theological criticism, the Jacobites are arranged under three
                    patriarchates—Antioch, Alexandria, and Armenia. Antioch and Alexandria have
                    intercommunion, but Armenia, in spite of times of reconciliation, stands apart.
                    Under the patriarch of Alexandria is the metran or metropolitan of Abyssinia,
                    and under the patriarch of Antioch the maphrian or primate of the East. The
                    Jacobites or Copts of Egypt greatly outnumber the members of the Orthodox Greek
                    Church there. The patriarch assumes jurisdiction over Egypt, Jerusalem, Nubia,
                    Abyssinia, and the Pentapolis. He now resides in Cairo, and is chosen by lot in
                    a council of all the bishops from a number of monks recommended by four convents
                    to whom belongs this privilege. He has for suffragans the bishops of Menouf,
                    Sherkeyeh, Behnese, Fayoum, Miniyeh, Senabau, Manfalout, Siout, Abuteg,
                    Aschumin, Esne, Kauss and Nekada, and Khartoum. He has besides jurisdiction over
                    twenty-six monasteries, and rules nominally over the Church of Abyssinia.</p>
                <p>The Syrian Jacobites also form a patriarchate—the patriarchate of Antioch. While
                    Antioch belonged to the empire the persecution of the state drove the Jacobite
                    patriarch from the city. He settled at Amida, now called Caramit, which is still
                    the ecclesiastical centre. The second dignitary is the maphrian (fruitbearer) of
                    the East, who was originally a missionary bishop to the regions east of the
                    Tigris. He is now settled at Mosul. The Syrian Jacobites <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n167/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0167-0156"/> could at one time boast 20 metropolitans and 103
                    bishops; now there are only 5 metropolitans (Caramit, Mosul, Maadan, Aleppo, and
                    Jerusalem) without suffragans.</p>
                <p>The decisions of Chalcedon, which were the occasion of the formation of all these
                    sects outside, did not put an end to Christological controversy inside the
                    Orthodox Greek Church. The most prominent question which emerged in attempting
                    to define further the person of Christ was whether the will belonged to the
                    nature or the person, or, as it came to be stated, whether Christ had two wills
                    or only one. The church in the sixth oecumenical council at Constantinople
                    declared that Christ had two wills. The Monotheletes refused to submit, and the
                    result was the formation of another schismatic church—the Maronite Church of the
                    Lebanon range. The Maronites, however, in the 12 th century were reconciled to
                    Rome, and cannot now be said to belong to the Greek Church.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Confli</hi><hi rend="italic">t with Rome.—</hi> The relation of
                    the Greek Church to the Roman may be described a3 one of growing estrangement
                    from the 5th to the 11th century, and a series of abortive attempts at
                    reconciliation since the latter date. The estrangement and final rupture may be
                    traced to the overweening pretensions of the Roman bishops and to Western
                    innovation in the doctrine of the Holy Spirit, accompanied by an alteration of
                    creed. In the early church three bishops stood forth prominently, principally
                    from the political eminence of the cities in which they ruled—the bishops of
                    Rome, Alexandria, and Antioch. The transfer of the seit of empire from Rome to
                    Constantinople gave the bishops of Rome a possible rival in the patriarch of
                    Constantinople, but the absence of an overawing court and meddling statesmen did
                    more than recoup the loss to the head of the Roman Church. The theological
                    calmness of the West, amid the violent theological disputes which troubled the
                    Eastern patriarchates, and the statesmanlike wisdom of Rome’s greater bishops,
                    combined to give a unique position to the pope, which councils in vain strove to
                    shake, and which in time of difficulty the Eastern patriarchs were fain to
                    acknowledge and make use of, however they might protest against it and the
                    conclusions deduced from it But this pre-eminence, or rather the Roman idea of
                    what was involved in it, was never acknowledged in the East; to prese it upon
                    the Eastern patriarchs was to prepare the way for separation, to insist upon it
                    in times of irritation was to cause a schism. The theological genius of the East
                    wa3 different from that of the West. The Greek theology had its roots in Greek
                    philosophy, while a great deal of Western theology was based on Roman law. The
                    Greek fathers succeeded the Sophists, the Latin theologians succeeded the Roman
                    advocates (Stanley’s <hi rend="italic">East. Ch.,</hi> ch. i.). This gave rise
                    to misunderstandings, and at last led to two widely separate ways of regarding
                    and defining one important doctrine—the procession of the Holy Spirit from the
                    Father or from the Father and the Son. Political jealousies and interests
                    intensified the disputes, and at last, after many premonitory symptoms, the
                    final break came in 1054, when Leo. IX. smote Michael Cerularius and the whole
                    of the Eastern Church with an excommunication. There had been mutual
                    excommunications before, but they had not resulted in permanent schisms. “It was
                    scarce two centuries since anathemas had been exchanged between Adrian I. and
                    Photius, between Photius and Nicholas I. The sixth council had formally
                    anathematized Honorius I. by name. There had been great violence of language in
                    the 6th century between Gregory I. and John the Faster, and not many years
                    before that the name of Vigilius had been deliberately erased from every one of
                    the diptychs of the Eastern Church’’ (Ffoulkes’s <hi rend="italic">Christendom's
                    Divisions,</hi> i. § 17). Now, however, the separation was final, and the
                    ostensible cause of its finality was the introduction by the Latins of two words
                    <hi rend="italic">filioque</hi> into the creed. It is this addition which was
                    and which still remains the permanent cause of separation. Ffoulkes has pointed
                    out in his second volume (ch. 1-3) that there was a resumption of intercourse
                    more than once between Rome and Constantinople after 1054, and that the
                    overbearing character of the Norman crusaders, and finally the horrors of the
                    sack of Constantinople in the fourth crusade, were the real causes of the
                    permanent estrangement. It is undeniable, however, that the <hi rend="italic"
                    >filioque</hi> question has always come up to bar the way in any subsequent
                    attempts at intercommunion. The theological question involved is a very small
                    one, but it brings out clearly the opposing characteristics of Eastern and
                    Western theology, and so has acquired an importance far beyond its own worth.
                    The question is really one about the relations subsisting between the persons of
                    the Trinity and their hypostatical properties. The Western Church affirms that
                    the Holy Spirit “proceeds from” the Father and from the Son. It believes that
                    the Spirit of the Father must be the Spirit of the Son also. Such a theory seems
                    alone able to satisfy the practical instincts of the West, which did not concern
                    itself with the metaphysical aspect of the Trinity, but with Godhead in its
                    relation to redeemed humanity. The Eastern Church affirms that the Holy Spirit
                    proceeds from the Father only. The Eastern theologian thinks that the Western
                    double procession degrades the Deity and destroys the perfection of the Trinity.
                    The double procession, in his eyes, means two active principles (αiτιαι) in the
                    Deity, and it means also that there is a confusion between the hypostatical
                    properties; a property possessed by the Father and distinctive of the First
                    Person is attributed also to the Second. This is the theological, and there is
                    conjoined with it an historical and moral dispute. The Greeks allege that the
                    addition of the words <hi rend="italic">filioque</hi> was made, not only without
                    authority, and therefore unwarrantably, but also for the purpose of forcing a
                    rupture between East and West in the interests of the barbarian empire of the
                    West.</p>
                <p>Attempts at reconciliation were made frcm time to time afterwards, but were
                    always wrecked on the two points of papal supremacy, when it meant the right to
                    impose Western usages upon the East, and of the addition to the creed. First
                    there was the negotiation between Γope Gregory IX. and the Greek patriarch
                    Germanus. The Latin conditions were practically recognition of papal
                    jurisdiction, the use of unleavened bread enforced on the Greeks, and the Greeks
                    to be permitted to omit <hi rend="italic">filioque</hi> on condition that they
                    burnt all books written against the Western doctrine. The Greek patriarch
                    refused the terms. Then came negotiations under Innocent IV. and Clement IV., in
                    which the popes proposed the same conditions as Gregory IX., with additions.
                    These proposals were rejected by the Greeks, who regarded them as attempts to
                    enforce new creeds on their church.</p>
                <p>The negotiations at the council of Lyons (1274) were, strictly speaking, between
                    the pope and the Greek emperor, and were more political than ecclesiastical.
                    Michael Palaeologus ruled in Constantinople while Baldwin II., the last of the
                    Latin emperors, was an exile in Europe. I’alaeologus wished the pope to
                    acknowledge his title to be emperor of the East, and in return promised
                    submission to the papal supremacy and the union of the Greek with the Latin
                    Church on the pope’s own terms. This enforced union lasted only during the
                    lifetime of the emperor. The only other attempt at union which requires to be
                    mentioned is that made at the council of Florence. It was really suggested by
                    the political weakness of the Byzantine empire and the dread of the approach of
                    the Turks. John Palaeologus the emperor, Joseph the patriarch of Constantinople,
                    and several Greek bishops came to Italy and appeared at the council of
                    Florence—the papal council, the rival of the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n168/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0168-0157"/> council of Basel. As on former occasions the
                    Greeks were at first deceived by false representations; they were betrayed into
                    recognition of papal supremacy, and tricked into signing what could afterwards
                    be represented as a submission to Western doctrine. The natural consequences
                    followed,—a repudiation of what had been done; and the Greek bishops on their
                    way home took care to make emphatic their ritualistic differences from Rome.
                    Soon after came the fall of Constantinople, and with this event an end to the
                    political reasons for the submission of the Greek clergy. Rome’s schemes for a
                    uniou which meant an unconditional submission on the part of the Greeks did not
                    cease, however, but they were no longer attempted on a grand scale. Jesuit
                    missionaries after the Reformation stirred up schisms in some parts of the
                    Eastern Church, and in Austria and Poland many of the Greeks were compelled to
                    submit themselves to the see of Rome. The result of these schemes lias been what
                    is called the <hi rend="italic">Unia,</hi> or the United Greeks. These various
                    unions have commonly arisen from dissensions among the Greeks themselves when a
                    portion of the dissentients have made submission to Rome. Rome commonly promised
                    to allow them to enjoy their own liturgies and rites of worship, but usually
                    broke her promises. This was done so systematically that the college of the
                    Propaganda prints what profess to be the old liturgies of the Eastern churches,
                    which are really so interpolated as to bring them surreptitiously into harmony
                    with the Western rites. This is done so universally that it is impossible to
                    trust to any professedly Eastern creed or service-book printed at the office of
                    the Propaganda in Rome.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Differentiation of National Churches included in the Orthodox
                    Greek Church.—</hi> Mr Finlay, in his <hi rend="italic">History of Greece,</hi>
                    has shown that there has been always a very close relation between the church
                    and national life. Christianity from the first connected itself with the social
                    organization of the people, and therefore in every province assumed the language
                    and the usages of the locality. In this way it was able to command at once
                    individual attachment and universal power. This feeling died down to some extent
                    when Constantine made use of the church to consolidate his empire. But it
                    revived under the persecution of the Arian emperors. The struggle against
                    Arianism was not merely a struggle for orthodoxy. Athanasius was really at the
                    head of a national Greek party resisting the domination of a Latin-speaking
                    court. From this time onwards Greek patriotism and Greek orthodoxy have been
                    almost convertible terms, and this led naturally to revolts against Greek
                    supremacy in the days of Justinian and other emperors. Dean Stanley is probably
                    correct when he describes the heretical churches of the East as the ancient
                    national churches of Egypt, Syria, and Armenia in revolt against supposed
                    innovations in the earlier faith imposed on them by Greek supremacy. In the
                    East, as in Scotland, the history of the church is the key to the history of the
                    nation, and in the freedom of the church the Greek saw the freedom and supremacy
                    of his race. For this very reason Orthodox Eastern Christians of alien race felt
                    compelled to resist Greek domination by means of independent ecclesiastical
                    organization, and the structure of the church rather favoured than interfered
                    with the coexistence of separate national churches professing the same faith.
                    Another circumstance favoured the creation of separate national churches. While
                    the Greek empire lasted the Greek emperors had a right of investiture on the
                    election of a new patriarch, and this right was retained by the Turkish sultans
                    after the conquest of Constantinople. The Russian people, for example, could not
                    contemplate with calmness as the head of their church a bishop appointed by the
                    hereditary enemy of their country. In this way the jealousies of race and the
                    necessities of nations have produced various national churches which are
                    independent or autocephalous, and yet are one in doctrine with the Orthodox
                    Greek Church. The most important of these are the churchee of Russia, Georgia,
                    Servia, Roumania, Greece, and Montenegro. The churches of Russia and Georgia
                    have been united.</p>
                <p>The Church of Russia dates from 992, when Prince Vladimir and his people accepted
                    Christianity. The metropolitan, who was subject to the patriarch of
                    Constantinople, resided at Kieff on the Dnieper. During the Tartar invasion the
                    metropolis was destroyed, and Vladimir became the ecclesiastical capital. In
                    1320 the metropolitans fixed their seat at Moscow. In 1582 Jeremiah, patriarch
                    of Constantinople, raised Job, 46th metropolitan, to the patriarchal dignity;
                    and the act was afterwards confirmed by a general council of the East. In this
                    way the Russian Church became autocephalous, and its patriarch had immense
                    power. In 1700 Peter the Great forbade the election of a new patriarch, and in
                    1721 he established the Holy Governing Synod to supply the place of the
                    patriarch. This body now governs the Russian Church, and consists of five or six
                    bishops, one or two other ecclesiastics of dignity, and several laymen, all
                    appointed by the emperor. The Church of Georgia, which has existed from a very
                    early period, and was dependent first on the patriarch of Antioch and then on
                    the patriarch of Constantinople, has since 1801 been incorporated in the Russian
                    Church. Its head, the archbishop of Tiflis, is a member of the Holy Governing
                    Synod, with the title of exarch, and having under him four suffragans. Russia is
                    divided for ecclesiastical purposes into eparchies of three classes, each of
                    which is ruled over by a bishop. There are three eparchies of the first class,
                    ruled by the metropolitans of Kieff, Novogorod and St Petersburg, and Moscow.
                    The steady increase of the Russian Church makes it difficult to detail with
                    exactness the number of bishops belonging to the three classes; but, according
                    to the report presented to the Holy Governing Synod in 1876, there are, in
                    addition to the three eparchies of the first class, twenty-one of the second,
                    thirty-three of the third, and six vicariates. These sixty-three bishops possess
                    diocesan authority; and there are besides, excluding the exarchate of Georgia,
                    fifty-six bishops ruling over monasteries.</p>
                <p>The Church of Servia has undergone great changes. I n mediseval times, when
                    Servia was a strong kingdom, the head of the church invariably claimed the title
                    and authority of patriarch. In 1810, when Kara George achieved the independence
                    of the kingdom, the archbishop of Carlowitz in Hungary was recognized as the
                    head of the church, but in 1830 the national church was reconstituted and
                    declared to be autocephalous. In 1838 the seat of government was removed to
                    Belgrade, and the metropolitan of Belgrade is now the head of the Servian
                    Church, though his right is still disputed by the archbishop of Carlowitz. He
                    has under him as suffragans the bishops of Shabatz, Csatsäk, and Uschize, the
                    last of whom resides at Karanowatz. Election to the episcopate is subject to the
                    veto of the prince and of the patriarch of Constantinople. The extension of
                    Servia under the provisions of the treaty of Berlin will probably cause some
                    ecclesiastical changes.</p>
                <p>Before the union of the two provinces of Moldavia and Wallachia, the Orthodox
                    Greek Church was ruled by two metropolitans—the one at Jassy and the other at
                    Bucharest. Since the independence of the united provinces there has been a
                    long-continued conflict, which had for its design, not merely to throw off the
                    supremacy of the patriarch of Constantinople, but to curb the influence of the
                    higher clergy, and to assert the pre-eminence of the Slavonic over the Greek
                    element. The result has been that the state, aided by the lower clergy and the
                    people, has thrown off the supremacy of Constantinople, united the church under
                    one metropolitan of Roumania, who has under him the metropolitan of Moldavia and
                    six bishops, confiscated the property of most of the convents, which were
                    centres of Greek influence, published liturgies either in the Slavonic or in the
                    Roumanian language, and asserted the supremacy of the state.</p>
                <p>The constitution of the Church of Modern Greece is the result of the peculiar
                    position of the patriarch of Constantinople. The war of liberation was
                    sympathized in, not merely by the inhabitants of Greece, but by all the
                    Greek-speaking Christians in the East. But the patriarch was in the hands of the
                    Turks; he had been appointed by the sultan, and he was compelled by the Turkish
                    authorities to ban the movement for freedom. When the Greeks achieved
                    independence they refused to be subject ecclesiastically to a patriarch who was
                    nominated by the sultan (June 9, 1828); and, to add to their difficulties, there
                    were in the country twenty-two bishops who had been consecrated by the
                    patriarch, twelve bishops w ho had been consecrated irregularly during the war,
                    and about twenty bishops who had been deprived of their sees during the
                    troubles— <hi rend="italic">i.c.,</hi> fifty-three bishops claimed to be
                    provided for. In these circumstances the Government and people resolved that
                    there should be ten diocesan bishops and forty additional provisional sees. They
                    also resolved that the church should be governed after the fashion of the
                    Russian Church by a synod; and they deereed that the king of Greece was to be
                    head of the church. All these ideas were <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n169/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0169-0158"/> carried out with some modifications, and
                    gradually. The patriarch of Constantinople in 1850 acknowledged the independence
                    of the church, which gradually grew to be more independent of the state. The
                    provisional sees were not all merged in the ten proposed dioceses. Greece at
                    present is divided into four exarchies:—(1) the Continent and Euboea—divided
                    into eight sees, of four archbishops and four bishops; (2) the
                    Peloponnesus—divided into twelve sees, of six archbishops and six bishops; (3)
                    the islands of the Aegean Sea—governed by one archbishop and three bishops; and
                    (4) the Ionian Islands—governed by five archbishops. The Greek Church in Greece
                    includes a good many monasteries; but the number has been diminished since the
                    war of liberation, and a great many of those that remain have been made use of
                    for the purposes of education. Many of these convents are dependent on the
                    celebrated ancient monasteries of Athos, Sinai, and Jerusalem. The Greek Church
                    has done and is doing a great deal for the cause of education in Greece.</p>
                <p>The bitter enmity which subsists between the people of the Black Mountain and the
                    Turks made them from the beginning repudiate the authority of the patriarch of
                    Constantinople, and the church is nominally independent. It is, however, very
                    closely allied to the Russian Church. Up to the year 1852 the spiritual and the
                    civil authority were vested in one individual, and the prince-bishops were
                    always chosen from the family of Petrowitsch, but in that year the prince-bishop
                    Danilo married, and demitted his episcopal functions. Since then there has been
                    a bishop of Montenegro who has metropolitan functions. He has no suffragan
                    bishops, but rales over three arch-priests and a large number of inferior
                    clergy. He is consecrated by the Holy Governing Synod of the Russian Church.</p>
                <p>The Church of Bulgaria demanded independence about fifteen years ago, and has
                    practically enjoyed it since 1858, although it has not yet obtained recognition.
                    It is governed by an exarch who, while recognizing the supremacy of the
                    patriarch of Constantinople, refuses to allow him to interfere in any way in the
                    internal government of the church. It is still under excommunication by the
                    patriarch. The new rights which Bulgaria has acquired under the treaty of Berlin
                    will probably lead to a rearrangement of the church.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Doctrines and Creeds.</hi> —The Greek Church has no creeds
                    in the modern Western use of the word, no <hi rend="italic">normative</hi>
                    summaries of what must be believed. It has preserved the older idea that a creed
                    is an adoring confession of the church engaged in worship; and, when occasion
                    called for more, the belief of the church was expressed more by way of public
                    testimony than in symbolical books. Still the doctrines of the church can be
                    gathered from these confessions of faith. The Greek creeds may be roughly placed
                    in two classes,—the oecumenical creeds of the early undivided church, and later
                    testimonies defining the position of the Orthodox Church of the East with regard
                    to the belief of the Roman Catholic and of Protestant Churches. These
                    testimonies were called forth mainly by the protest of Greek theologians against
                    Jesuitism on the one hand and against the reforming tendencies of Cyril Lucaris
                    on the other. The Orthodox Greek Church adopts the doctrinal decisions of the
                    seven oecumenical councils, together with the canons of the Concilium
                    Quinisextum or second Trullan council; and they further hold that all these
                    definitions and canons are simply explanations and enforcements of the
                    Nicaeo-Constantinopolitan creed and the decrees of the first council of Nicaea.
                    The first four councils settled the orthodox faith on the doctrines of the
                    Trinity and of the Incarnation; the fifth supplemented the decisions of the
                    first four. The sixth declared against Monotheletism; the seventh sanctioned the
                    worship (δoυλ∈ια not <hi rend="italic">αληθινή λατρεία)</hi> of images; the
                    council held in the Trullus (a saloon in the palace at Constantinople)
                    supplemented by canons of discipline the doctrinal decrees of the fifth and
                    sixth councils.</p>
                <p>The Reformation of the 16 th century was not without effect on the Greek Church.
                    Some of the Reformers, notably Melanch th on, expected to effect a reunion of
                    Christendom by means of the Greeks, cherishing the same hopeβ as the modern Old
                    Catholic divines and their English sympathizers. Melanchthon himself sent a
                    Greek translation of the Augsburg Confession to Joasaph, patriarch of
                    Constantinople, and some years afterwards Jacob Andreae and Martin Crusius began
                    a correspondence with Jeremiah, patriarch of Constantinople, in which they asked
                    an official expression of his opinions about Lutheran doctrine. The result was
                    that Jeremiah answered in his <hi rend="italic">Censura Omentalis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Ecclesi&lt;x</hi> condemning the distinctive principles of
                    Lutheranism.</p>
                <p>The reformatory movement of Cyril Lucaris brought the Greek Church face to face
                    with Reformation theology. Cyril was a learned Cretan, who, having travelled
                    extensively in Europe, and having become acquainted with and devoted to the
                    Reformed faith, was afterwards elected patriarch of Alexandria in 1602 and
                    patriarch of Constantinople in 1621. He conceived the plan of reforming the
                    Eastern Church by bringing its doctrines into harmony with those of Calvinism,
                    and by sending able young Greek theologians to Switzerland, Holland, and England
                    to study Protestant theology. His scheme of reform was opposed chiefly by the
                    intrigues of the Jesuits. He was five times deposed, and five times reinstated.
                    In the end he was murdered by the Turks at the instigation of the Jesuits. The
                    church anathematized his doctrines, and in its later testimonies repudiated his
                    confession on the one hand and Jesuit ideas on the other. The most important of
                    these testimonies are (1) the Orthodox confession or catechism of Peter Mogilas,
                    confirmed by the Eastern patriarchs and by the synod of Jerusalem (1643), and
                    (2) the decree of the synod of Jerusalem or the confession of Dositheus (1672).
                    Besides these, the catechisms of the Russian Church should be consulted,
                    especially the catechism of Philaret, which since 1839 has been used in all the
                    churches and schools in Russia. Founding on these doctrinal sources the teaching
                    of the Orthodox Greek Church is :—<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>This summary has been taken, with corrections, from Winer.
                    Small capitals denote differences from Roman Catholic, italics differences from
                    Protestant doctrine.</p></note></p>
                <p>Christianity is a Divine revelation communicated to mankind through Christ; its
                    saving truths are to be learned from the Bible <hi rend="italic">and
                    tradition,</hi> the former having been written, <hi rend="italic">and the latter
                    maintained uncorrupted</hi> through the influence of the Holy Spirit; <hi
                    rend="italic">the interpretation of the Bible belongs to the Church, which is
                    taught by the Holy Spirit,</hi> but every believer may read the Scriptures.</p>
                <p>According to the Christian revelation, God is a Trinity, that is, the Divine
                    Essence exists in Three Persons, perfectly equal in nature and dignity, the
                    Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghost; <hi rend="smallcaps">the Holy Ghost
                    proceeds from the Father only.</hi> Besides the Triune God there is no other
                    object of divine worship, <hi rend="italic">but homage</hi> (5ιrep- δoυλlα) <hi
                    rend="italic">may be paid to the Virgin Mary, and reverence</hi> (δoυλla) <hi
                    rend="italic">to the saints and to their pictures and relics.</hi></p>
                <p>Man is born with a corrupt bias which was not his at creation; the first man,
                    when created, possessed <hi rend="smallcaps">immortality, perfect wisdom,
                    and</hi> A WILL <hi rend="smallcaps">regulated by reason.</hi> Through the first
                    sin Adam and his posterity lost <hi rend="smallcaps">immortality, and his will
                    received a bias towards evil.</hi> In this natural state man, who even before he
                    actually sins is a sinner before God by original or inherited sin, commits
                    manifold actual transgressions; <hi rend="italic">but he is not absolutely
                    without power of will towards good, and is not always doing evil.</hi></p>
                <p>Christ, the Son of God, became man in two natures, which internally and
                    inseparably united make One Person, and, according to the eternal purpose of
                    God, has obtained for man reconciliation with God, and eternal life, inasmuch as
                    He by His vicarious death has made satisfaction to God for the world’s sins, and
                    this satisfaction was PERFECTLY COMMENSURATE WITH THE SINS OF THE W0RLD. Man is
                    made partaker of reconciliation in spiritual regeneration, which he attains to,
                    being led and kept by the Holy Ghost. This divine help is offered <hi
                    rend="italic">to all men without distinction, and may be rejected.</hi> In order
                    to attain to salvation, man is justified, and when so justified <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">can do no more than the commands of God.</hi> He may fall from
                    a state of grace through mortal sin.</p>
                <p>Regeneration is offered by the word of God and in the sacraments, <hi
                    rend="italic">which under visible signs communicate God’s invisible grace to
                    Christians when administered cum</hi><hi rend="italic">intentione.</hi> There
                    are <hi rend="italic">seven</hi> mysteries or sacraments. Baptism <hi
                    rend="italic">entirely destroys</hi> original sin. In the Eucharist the true
                    body and blood of Christ are <hi rend="italic">substantially present, and the
                    elements are changed into the substance of Christ, whose body and blood are
                    corporeally partaken of by communicants.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">All</hi>
                    Christians should receive the bread and the <hi rend="smallcaps">wine.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">The Eucharist is also an expiatory sacrifice.</hi> The new birth
                    when lost may be restored through repentance, which is not merely (-1) sincere
                    sorrow, but also (2) <hi rend="italic">confession of each individual sin to the
                    priest, and</hi> (3) <hi rend="italic">the discharge of penances imposed by the
                    priest for the removal of the temporal punishment which may have been imposed by
                    God and the Church. Penance accompanied by the judicial absolution of the priest
                    makes a true sacrament.</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n170/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0170-0159"/>
                <p>The Church of Christ is the fellowship of <hi rend="smallcaps">all those who
                    accept</hi> AND PROFESS ALL THE ARTICLES OF FAITH TRANSMITTED BY THE <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Apostles and approved by General Synods.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Without this visible Church there is no salvation.</hi> It is under the abiding
                    influence of the Holy Ghost, and <hi rend="italic">therefore cannot err in
                    matters of faith.</hi> Specially appointed persons are necessary in the service
                    of the Church, <hi rend="italic">aud they form a threefold order, distinct
                    jure</hi><hi rend="italic">divino</hi><hi rend="italic">from other Christians,
                    of Bishops, Priests, and Beacons.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">The four Patriarchs,
                    of equal dignity, have the highest rank among the bishops, and the
                    bishops</hi><hi rend="italic">united in a General Council represent the Church
                    and infallibly decide,</hi> under the guidance of the Holy Ghost, all matters of
                    faith and ecclesiastical life. All ministers of Christ must be regularly called
                    and appointed to their office, and are consecrated <hi rend="italic">by the
                    sacrament of orders. Bishops must be unmarried,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >priests and deacons must not contract</hi> A <hi rend="smallcaps">second
                    marriage. To</hi> all priests in common belongs, besides the preaching of the
                    word, the administration of the six <hi rend="smallcaps">sacraments,</hi>
                    —BAPTISM, CONFIRMATION, PENANCE, EUCHARIST, MATRIMONY, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >unction of the sick.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">bishops</hi> alone can
                    administer the <hi rend="italic">sacrament</hi> of orders.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical ceremonies are part of the divine service; most
                    of them have apostolic origin; and those connected with the sacrament must not
                    be omitted by priests under pain of mortal sin.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Liturgy
                    and Worship.</hi> —The ancient liturgies of the Eastern Church were very
                    numerous, and have been frequently classified. Neale makes three divisions—the
                    liturgy of Jerusalem or of St James, that of Alexandria or of St Mark, and that
                    of Edessa or of St Thaddaeus; and Daniel substantially agrees with him. The same
                    passion for uniformity which suppressed the Gallican and Mozarabic liturgies in
                    the West led to the almost exclusive use of the liturgy of St James in the East.
                    It is used in two forms, a shorter revised by Chrysostom, and a longer called
                    the liturgy of St Basil. This liturgy and the service generally are either in
                    Old Greek or in Old Slavonic—and frequent disputes have arisen in particular
                    districts about the language tobe employed. Both sacred languages differ from
                    the language of the people, but it cannot be said that in the Eastern Church
                    worship is conducted in an unknown tongue,—“the actual difference,” says Neale,
                    “may be about that between Chaucer’s English and our own.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Monastic Life.</hi> —Monastic life was introduced into
                    Christianity in the East, and has always remained a prominent feature in Greek
                    Christianity. The monks usually follow the rule of St Basil, but some
                    monasteries, notably that of Sinai, obey the rule of St Anthony. The monks are
                    of three classes :— <hi rend="italic">κovvoβιaκoi,</hi> who live together in a
                    monastery ruled over by a <hi rend="italic">ηγovμevoς</hi> OΓ <hi rend="italic"
                    >αρχιμανδρίτης’,</hi><hi rend="italic">avaχωρητai,</hi> who live either in a
                    cloister apart from the other monks or among the laity; and <hi rend="italic"
                    >άσκηταί,</hi> who are hermits. The nuns, virgins or widows, all follow the rule
                    of St Basil. There are three great convents—at Jerusalem, Sinai, and Mount
                    Athos; each has a great number of daughter monasteries throughout the East. Many
                    monasteries are presided over by bishops, and many monks are in priests’ and
                    deacons’ orders. Monks alone are eligible for election to bishoprics and the
                    higher offices in the Eastern Church.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">Number of
                            Adherents.—</hi> These can only be given approximately :—</p><p>Orthodox
                            Greek Church in Turkey 10,000,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>,, „ Roumania 4,529,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>„ „ Servia 1,345,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>,, „ Montenegro 130,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>&gt;» „ Greece 1,310,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>» „ Austria 3,000,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">
                            h</hi><hi rend="italic">n</hi> Russia (including Poland,</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Siberia, and the Caucasus)
                            58,000,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>78,314,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>To these may be added :—</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Russian Dissenters 1 051
                            000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Armenians δ’οοο’οοο</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Nestoι∙ians (including the Thomas
                            Christians of India)... 36θ'θθθ</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Syrian Jacobites 90 oθo</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Copts 191 n∩∏</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Abyssinians 1 9n0 n∩n</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="subscript"> ττ</hi>
                            5,822,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>United Greeks (chiefly in Austria and
                            Poland) 4,670,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>See the common books on Church History, as those of Neander, Gieseler, Robertson,
                    &amp;c. Special mention may be made of Schrockh’s <hi rend="italic">Christliche
                    Kirchengeschichte,</hi> and the various collections of councils, <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> Mansi’s or, for English readers, Hefele’s <hi
                    rend="italic">History of the Councils,</hi> translated in Clark’s series. For
                    the controversies which gave rise to the schismatic churches, consult F. C.
                    Baur, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Christliche Lehre von der
                    Dreieinigkeit</hi>; Dörner, <hi rend="italic">History of the Doctrine of the
                    Person of Christ,</hi> translated in Clark’s series; J. H. Newman, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Arians of the Fourth Century,</hi> Swainson, <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Apostles' and Nicene Creeds.</hi> For the <hi rend="italic">Filioque</hi>
                    controversy Walch, <hi rend="italic">Historia Controversiae</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Processu Spiritus Sancti,</hi> and the
                    works of Swete and Langen, may be referred to, also Schaff’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of the Creeds of Christendom.</hi> The following are devoted specially
                    to the history and condition of the Eastern Church:—Μ. Le Quien, <hi
                    rend="italic">Oriens Christianus·,</hi> Asseman, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bibliotheca</hi><hi rend="italic">Orientalis·,</hi> Stanley’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Eastern Church·,</hi> and, above all, J. Μ. Neale, <hi rend="italic">The Holy
                    Eastern Church {General Introduction,</hi> 2 vols.; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Patriarchate of Alexandria,</hi> 2 vols.; and, published posthumously in 1873,
                    <hi rend="italic">Patriarchate of Antioch,</hi> 1 vol.). For liturgy, see
                    Daniel, <hi rend="italic">Codex Liturgicus Eccl. Univ, in</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Epitomen redactus,</hi><hi rend="italic">4</hi> vols., 1847-55, and the shorter
                    works of Neale and Littledale; Renaudot, <hi rend="italic">Collectio</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Liturgiarum Orient.·,</hi> Leo Allatius, <hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">libris</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >rebus Eccles.</hi><hi rend="italic">Graecarum Dissertationes.</hi> For
                    hymnology, see Daniel, <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Hymnologicus, 4</hi> vols.,
                    and Neale’s translations of <hi rend="italic">Eastern Hymns</hi>; and for
                    creeds, the collections of Kimmel, Gass, and Schaff. (T. Μ. L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
