<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0270-0257-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUIDO of Arezzo</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 257</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1025507">Monks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:827285">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1103279">Sacrum</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4416t25p">Doubt</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hq6h">Musicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n270/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUIDO <hi rend="smallcaps">of Arezzo</hi></label>, an Italian
                    monk of the 11th century, has by many been called the father of modern music,
                    and a portrait of him in the refectory of the monastery of Avellana bears the
                    inscription “Beatus Guido, inventor musicae.” Although these statements are
                    manifestly exaggerated, it is none the less true that Guido’s reforms mark an
                    enormous progress in the notation as well as in the teaching of music. Of his
                    life little is known, and that little is chiefly derived from the dedicatory
                    letters prefixed to two of h’s treatises and addressed respectively to Bishop
                    Theodald (not Theobald, as Burney writes the name) of Arezzo, and Michael, a
                    monk of Pomposa and Guido’s pupil and friend. Occasional references to the
                    celebrated musician in the works of his contemporaries are, however, by no means
                    rare, and from these it may be conjectured with all but absolute certainty that
                    Guido was born in the last decade of the 10th century. The place of his birth
                    is, beyond a doubt, Arezzo; for on the title-page of all his works he is styled
                    <hi rend="italic">Guido Aretiιvιιs,</hi> or simply <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aretinus.</hi> At his first appearance in history Guido was a monk in the
                    Benedictine monastery of Pomposa, and it was there that he invented his
                    educational method, by means of which, according to his own statement, a pupil
                    might learn within five months what formerly it would have taken him ten years
                    to acquire. Envy and jealousy, however, were his only reward, and by these he
                    was compelled to leave his monastery—“inde est, quod me vides prolixis finibus
                    exulatum,” as he says himself in the second of the letters above referred to.
                    According to one account, he travelled as far as Bremen, called there by
                    Archbishop Hermann in order to reform the musical service. But this statement
                    has been doubted, for chronological and other reasons.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n271/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0271-0258"/>
                <p>Certain it is that not long after his flight from Pomposa Guido was living at
                    Arezzo, and it was here that, about 1030, he received an invitation to Rome from
                    Pope John XIX. He obeyed the summons, and the pope himself became his first and
                    apparently one of his most proficient pupils. But in spite of his success Guido
                    could not be induced to remain in Rome, the insalubrious air of which seems to
                    have affected his health. In Rome he met agιin his former superior, the abbot of
                    Pomposa, who seems to have repented of his conduct towards Guido, and to have
                    induced him to return to Pomposa; and here all authentic records of Guido’s life
                    cease. We only know that he died, on May 17, 1050, as prior of Avellana, a
                    monastery of the Camaldulians; such at least is the statement of the chroniclers
                    of that order. It ought, however, to be added that the 0amaldulian3 claim the
                    celebrated musician as wholly their own, and altogether deny his connexion with
                    the Benedictines. It is quite in accordance with the semi-mythical character of
                    Guido’s life that a great many inventions belonging to earlier as well as to
                    later times have been attributed to him, in the same way as Charlemagne, Arthur,
                    and Roland have been mιde responsible for the dee de and exploits of other kings
                    and heroes. His eulogists declare that before him church music was in a state of
                    utter barbarism, wholly ignoring the achievements of Gregory the Great, Hucbald,
                    and others. The notation of music by means of the <hi rend="italic">neumce</hi>
                    also, although very imperfect for practical purposes, at any rate served to give
                    permanence to the composer’s thoughts. There is, however, no doubt that in the
                    latter respect Guido’s method shows an enormous progress. It was he who
                    invented, or at least for the first time systematically used, the lines of the
                    staff, and the intervals or <hi rend="italic">spatia</hi> between them, and thus
                    fixed the principle of modern notation; and the value of thiβ innovation for
                    educational and general artistic purposes cannot be overrated. There is also
                    little doubt that the names of the first six notes of the scale, <hi
                    rend="italic">ut, re, mi, fa, sol, lα,</hi> still in use among Romance nations,
                    were introduced by Guido, although he seems to have used them in a relative
                    rather than in an absolute sense. It is well known that these words are the
                    first syllables of six Hues of a hyrnιι addressed to St John the Baptist, which
                    may be given here :—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ut</hi> queant laxis resonare fibris</p>
                <p>3/ïra gestorum ∕αmuli tuorum, <hi rend="italic">Solve</hi> polluti Zabii
                    reatum,</p>
                <p>Sancte Joannes.</p>
                <p>In addition to this Guido is generally credited with the introduction of the F
                    clef. But perhaps more important than all this is the thoroughly practical tone
                    which Guido assumes in his theoretical writings, aud which differs greatly from
                    the clumsy scholasticism of his contemporaries and predecessors.</p>
                <p>The most important of Guido’s treatises, and those which are generally
                    acknowledged to be authentic, are <hi rend="italic">Micrologus Guidonis
                    de</hi><hi rend="italic">disciplina artis musicae,</hi> dedicated to Bishop
                    Theodald of Arezzo, and comprising a complete theory of music, in 20 chapters;
                    <hi rend="italic">Musicae G</hi><hi rend="italic">tιi&lt;ionis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">régulas rhythmicae in</hi><hi rend="italic">antiphonarii sui
                    prologum prolatae,</hi> written in trochaic decasyllabics of anything but
                    classical structure; <hi rend="italic">Aliae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Guidonis</hi><hi rend="italic">rcgulae</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ignoto cantu, identidem</hi><hi rend="italic">in
                    antiphonarii</hi><hi rend="italic">sui prologum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >prolatce∙,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Epistola</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Guidonis</hi><hi rend="italic">Michaeli</hi><hi rend="italic">monacho</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">ignoto</hi><hi rend="italic">can'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">u,</hi> already referred to. These are published in the second
                    volume of Gerbert’s <hi rend="italic">Scriptores ecclesiastici</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">musica sacra.</hi> A very important
                    manuscript unknown to Gerbert (the <hi rend="italic">Codex</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Bibliothecae</hi><hi rend="italic">Uticensis,</hi> in the Paris library)
                    contains, besides minor treatises, an antij&gt;ħonarium and gradual undoubtedly
                    belonging to Guido. A comprehensive but very uncritical life of Guido has been
                    written by Luigi Angeloni <hi rend="italic">(Sopra</hi><hi rend="italic">la
                    vita, d∙c., di Guido d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Arezzo).</hi> Of infinitely
                    greater importance are the studies on the subject by Herr Kiesewetter and by Μ.
                    Bottée de Toulmoιι. Burney’s <hi rend="italic">General History of Music,</hi>
                    and Fétis’s <hi rend="italic">Biographie des Musiciens</hi> should also be
                    consulted. A comprehensive and admirable account of Guido’s life and work by Dr
                    W. Langhans may be found in the fourth volume of Mendel’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Musikalisches Conversations-Lexikon.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
