<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0362-0343-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUYTON DE MORVEAU (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    343)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pv6bf2m">Phlogiston</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1061179">Phlogiston</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:841533">Bulls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833880">Blacks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833576">Black</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n362/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUYTON DE MORVEAU</label>, Louis <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Bernard, Baron</hi> (1737-1816), a distinguished French chemist, was born
                    January 4, 1737, at Dijon, in the university of which town his father was
                    professor of civil law. As a boy <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n363/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0363-0344"/> he evinced a remarkable aptitude for
                    practical mechanics. On leaving college at the age of sixteen he became a law
                    student in the university of Dijon, and after three years he was sent to Paris
                    to acquire a knowledge of practice at the bar. He obtained in his twenty-fourth
                    year the office of advocate-general in the parliament of Dijon, of which he
                    fulfilled the duties till 1782. Before long, piqued by a slighting remark of Dr
                    Chardenon of Dijon, made in reply to a criticism at the close of a lecture on
                    chemistry, De Morveau set himself to acquire a thorough knowledge of that
                    science. With “practice for his master, and melted crucibles and retorts for
                    tutors,” as he once observed to Baumé, he speedily obtained such a mastery over
                    his subject as to draw from Chardenon the public acknowledgment that he was
                    “born to be an honour to chemistry.” In 1772 he published at Dijon the <hi
                        rend="italic">Digressions</hi><hi rend="italic">Academiques,</hi> in which
                    were set forth his views with respect to phlogiston and the phenomena of
                    crystallization; and in 1773 he discovered the efficacy of hydrochloric acid gas
                    as an atmospheric disinfectant. <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> He was the means,
                    in 1774, of founding in Dijon courses of public lectures on mineralogy, materia
                    medica, and chemistry, the last of which he himself during thirteen years
                    gratuitously delivered. It would appear that his fellow-citizens were as yet far
                    from holding exalted views with regard to the prerogatives of science. Accusing
                    him of “presumptuously disarming the hand of the Supreme Being,” they about this
                    time sought to destroy his lightning conductors at the house of the academy, and
                    were restrained from carrying out their intentions only by the assurance of M.
                    Maret, the secretary of that institution, “that the astonishing virtue of the
                    apparatus resided in the gilded point, which had purposely been sent from Rome
                    by the Holy Father.” In 1777-78 appeared the <hi rend="italic">Piemens</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Chymie</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Théorique et</hi><hi rend="italic">Pratique</hi> (3 vols. 12mo) of De
                    Morveau, Maret, and Durande, a work highly appreciated by their contemporaries.
                    The chemical articles in vol. i. of the section “Chymie, Pharmacie, et
                    Metallurgie” of the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie Méthodique</hi> (1786), as
                    also some few of those of vol. ii. (1792), were from the pen of De Morveau. Of
                    these the longest is a masterly exposition of the facts and conclusions that had
                    up to that time been arrived at by chemists on the subject of acids.</p>
                <p>De Morveau’s first essay on a new chemical nomenclature, the origin of the
                    present system, was published in the <hi rend="italic">Journal de Physique</hi>
                    for May 1782, and was the subject of much adverse criticism. Repairing to Paris,
                    the author successfully met the objections of his opponents; and in 1787, in
                    conjunction with Lavoisier, Berthollet, and Fourcroy, he published <hi
                        rend="italic">Méthode d'une</hi><hi rend="italic">Nomenclature</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Chimique,</hi> the principles of which were speedily adopted
                    by chemists throughout Europe. Constantly in communication with the leaders of
                    the Lavoisierian school of chemistry in Paris, which he frequently visited, De
                    Morveau soon became convinced of the untenableness of the old phlogistic
                    doctrines, his reasons for renouncing which are stated in his volume of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Encyclopédie Méthodique,</hi> p. 625, <hi rend="italic"
                        >sqq.</hi> With Lavoisier, Laplace, Monge, Berthollet, and</p>
                <p>Fourcroy, he in 1788 produced a French translation of Kirwan’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Essay on Phlogiston,</hi> with annotations effectually disposing of the
                    author’s arguments against the new chemistry. The first manufactory of carbonate
                    of soda in France was established by De Morveau in 1783. In 1791 he represented
                    the department of Côte d ’ Or in the Legislative Assembly, and next year in the
                    National Convention, of which he was re-elected a member in 1795. Having already
                    become famous for aeronautical experiments at Dijon in 1783-84, he was appointed
                    in 1794 to superintend the construction of balloons for military purposes (see
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Aeronautics,</hi> vol. i. p. 199). About the same time
                    he rendered important service to his country by perfecting the processes for the
                    manufacture of gunpowder and saltpetre. In 1796 De Morveau was made a member of
                    the Institute. He retired from political life in 1797, and in 1798 became
                    provisional director of the Polytechnic School, in the foundation of which he
                    had been actively concerned. He held during 1800-14 the appointment of master of
                    the mint, received in 1803 the cross of the legion of honour, and was made in
                    1805 an officer of the same order, and in 1811 a baron of the French empire. He
                    died January 2, 1816.</p>
                <p>Besides the above mentioned and other works, and numerous scientific papers in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi><hi rend="italic">académique</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de Dijon,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Joιιrn. de Physique,
                        Journ. de l'</hi><hi rend="italic">École Polytechnique, Mém.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">l'institut, Joum. des Savants, Bull.
                        dcsSci. de la Soc. Philomatique,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ann. de
                        Chimie,</hi> to which last he was one of the principal contributors, De
                    Morveau wrote— <hi rend="italic">Mémoire sur</hi><hi rend="italic">ι</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">éducation publique,</hi> 1762; a satirical poem entitled <hi
                        rend="italic">Le Rat Iconoclaste, ou le Jésuite croqué,</hi> 1763; <hi
                        rend="italic">Discours publics et Éloges, 1TV&gt;-Ü2.; Plaidoyers sur
                        plusieurs questions de droit,</hi> 1785; <hi rend="italic">Traité des moyens
                        de désinfecter l'air,</hi> 1801, &amp;c.; <hi rend="italic">Rapport fait à
                        l'Institut sur la</hi><hi rend="italic">restmiration</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >du tableau de Raphaël connu sous le nom de la Vierge de</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Foligno</hi> (with Vincent, Tannay, and Berthollet), 1802; <hi
                        rend="italic">Mém. sur les mortiers,</hi> &amp;c., 1805; various
                    governmental reports; and translations, with notes, of treatises by Bergman,
                    Scheele, and Black.</p>
                <p>See Berthollet, “Discours,” <hi rend="italic">Inst. R. de France,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Funérailles,</hi> &lt;fcc., 1816; A. B. Granville, <hi
                        rend="italic">An Account of the Life and Writings of Baron Guyton de
                        Morveau, F.R.S.,</hi> 1817; T. Thomson, <hi rend="italic">Hist, of
                        Chemistry,</hi> ii. 1831; <hi rend="italic">Biog. Univ,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Portative</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                        Contemporains,</hi> iii. p. 701,1834; and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Chemistry,</hi> vol. v. pp. 464, 466. (F. H. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
