<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0352-0333-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUSTAVUS I</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 333</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198950">Revolt</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1139996">Swedes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:887617">Danes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106459">Scandinavians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vt81">Swedes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205503">Finland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204556">Norway</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n352/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUSTAVUS I</label>. (c. 1496-1560), king of Sweden, commonly
                    known as <hi rend="smallcaps">Gustavus Vasa,</hi> the surname being derived from
                    the family arms, which were a bundle or sheaf, is justly celebrated as the
                    founder of modern Sweden; he delivered it from the yoke of Denmark, introduced
                    the Reformation, established law and order, and laid the foundation of its
                    industrial prosperity. His family name was Ericson; he was born about 1496 of a
                    noble bouse; and he was related to the powerful family of Sture. Gustavus was at
                    a very early age called upon to suffer for his country. Sweden was still joined
                    to the other Scandinavian kingdoms under the union of Calmar, Denmark being the
                    leading state. Sweden was a reluctant member of this union, and King Christian
                    of Denmark was obliged to maintain his supremacy with a high hand. In an
                    expedition to Stockholm this king treacherously carried off the young Gustavus
                    and other nobles as hostages to Denmark. After being detained in Jutland for
                    above a year, Gustavus managed to escape in disguise to Lübeck, and the great
                    Hanse town, ever jealous of the power of Denmark, furnished him with the mea∏3
                    of returning to Sweden, where he landed in 1520. He had now formed the
                    resolution to deliver his country from the oppression of the Danes. He went
                    about from place to place trying to incite the people to revolt, but on all
                    hands he met with apathy and even resistance. For some time his life was in
                    extreme danger; he was hunted by the Danish authorities, and worked in disguise
                    on the farms and in the mines of Dalecarlia. The barn in which he threshed corn
                    is preserved as a state monument. He was on the point of fleeing over the hills
                    into Norway, when tidings came of the Blood-bath of Stockholm, in which ninety
                    of the nobles and leading men of Sweden, including the father of Gustavus
                    himself, were executed by the Danish king. This deed roused the slumbering
                    patriotism of the Swedes, especially of the hardy people of Dalecarlia, who now
                    chose Gustavus as their leader (1520). They repeatedly defeated the Danish
                    forces, and took the principal towns. By 1523 Stockholm was taken and Sweden
                    delivered from the Danish yoke. At a great diet held at Strengnâs in that year
                    Gustavus was elected king of Sweden. Finland was speedily recovered. After
                    liberating his country, Gustavus set himself to the far harder task of reforming
                    and settling it. Sweden was in a very backward and disorderly condition. The
                    nobles had great power and many selfish privileges; the clergy were wealthy, and
                    in the war of freedom had taken the side of the Danes; the peasants were poor
                    and discontented. There was little respect for law; the whole country was
                    demoralized and disorganized. The reforms of Gustavus began with the church. The
                    two brothers Peterson had already introduced the doctrines of Luther, and the
                    chancellor Anderson had translated the New Testament into the native tongue.
                    Vasa encouraged their efforts; in a great diet held at Westerâs in 1527 he
                    succeeded under the threat of abdicating in passing measures, by which the lands
                    of the bishops were placed at his disposal, and full liberty was granted of
                    preaching the gospel; but the support of the nobles had to be gained by a share
                    of the spoils. The Reformation soon took deep root, but the troubles of Gustavus
                    continued. He required to deal with a turbulent nobility; he had to beat off the
                    exiled king of Denmark; thrice he needed to pacify a revolt in Dalecarlia; and
                    he was forced to put forth the whole strength of his kingdom to quell a
                    peasants’ war in the south. The pretensions of Lübeck, which had given him real
                    help in the war of freedom, and to which he owed a considerable sum of money,
                    involved him in a war, by which he curtailed their commercial privileges. In all
                    these difficulties Gustavus bore himself with equal energy and wisdom. In 1544
                    his position was so secure that the elective sovereignty was changed by the diet
                    into an hereditary one. From this time till his death in 1560, except an
                    unimportant war with Russia on the Finnish frontier, there was little to disturb
                    the quiet progress of Sweden. Gustavus’s home policy made an era in Swedish
                    history. Law, order, and national spirit were encouraged and developed; schools
                    were everywhere establishéd, roads made, and foreign trade extended by
                    advantageous commercial treaties with England and Holland. Nothing was too
                    homely or minute for the supervision of the king; he was ready to encourage,
                    scold, or instruct, whenever an opportunity offered in any department of
                    industry. He even established model farms. His second and best-loved queen
                    Margaret had a dairy farm on which twenty-two maidens tended the cows. While he
                    avoided foreign war he did not neglect national defence; he left an excellent
                    army of 15,000 men, and he created a considerable naval force. Altogether, few
                    kings have done so much for any country as Gustavus Vasa did for Sweden. He was
                    succeeded by his son Eric.</p>
                <p>See Geijer’s <hi rend="italic">History of the Swedes</hi>; also an anonymous <hi
                    rend="italic">History of Gustavus Vasa,</hi> London, 1852.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
