<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0334-0315-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUNNY (9th edition, volume 11, page 315)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825435">Bags</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825390">Bagging</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1939163">Jute</term>
                    <term ref="fast:985280">Jutes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28g7v">Cloth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f7g">Bagging</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c24qr4p">Jute</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n334/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUNNY</label>. This name is applied to cloth or bags made of
                    jute, and is supposed to be derived from <hi rend="italic">ganga</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">gania</hi> of Rumphius, or from <hi rend="italic">gonia,</hi>
                    a vernacular name of the <hi rend="italic">Crotolaria</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >juncea</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> a plant common in Madras. One of the
                    first notices of the term itself is to bo found in Knox’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ceylon,</hi> in which he says: “The filaments at the bottom of the stem
                    [coir from the cocoa-nut husk <hi rend="italic">(Cocos nuciferα)</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">∖</hi> may be made into a coarse cloth called günny, which is
                    used for bags and similar purposes.” <hi rend="smallcaps">Jute</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> is the fibre of two species of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Corchorus, C.</hi><hi rend="italic">capsularis</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >C.</hi><hi rend="italic">olitorius,</hi> one species of which, probably the
                    latter, has long been known as the Jew’s mallow, from the fact that the leaves
                    have long been used in Palestine, Egypt, and Arabia as a potherb.</p>
                <p>The seeds of the jute plant are sown in April or May and the plant is cut down
                    close to the roots just before flowering. The tops are then clipped off and the
                    stems made into bundles, which are placed in tanks or ditches and covered with
                    turf or other heavy substance^ to keep the bundles under water. Here they are
                    watched anxiously day by day till the fibre separates easily from the central
                    woody portion. The period of retching or soaking takes from eight to ten days;
                    if allowed to remain too long, the fibre rapidly decays. In drying also the
                    fibre generally becomes of a deeper colour. When the fibre is ready for
                    manipulation, the operator descends into the tank or ditch, and taking 10 to 15
                    bundles, strips off the barky fibre and washes thoroughly, and by a dexterous
                    movement of the wrist spreads and separates the fibres over the surface of the
                    water. The fibre soon becomes clean, and is hung over bamboo framework to dry.
                    The fibre thus obtained is fine, long, and silky, but the short staple and the
                    portion near the root held in the hand of the operator during washing, which
                    frequently has bark attached, are the portions generally selected to make gunny
                    bags or cloth of.</p>
                <p>The kind of cloth known as gunny, tat, choti, &amp;c., is woven in various
                    lengths and widths for use as bedding, bags, &lt;fec., and formerly, more than
                    at present, every man, woman, and child, boatmen, husbandmen, and others, in
                    their spare moments, distaff in hand, wove gunny cloth. Even the Hindu widow,
                    saved from death and despised by all, made her life less miserable by making
                    gunny cloth, and thus rendering herself to an extent independent of her family.
                    On the eastern frontier women are clothed in it, and the poor cover themselves
                    with it at night. In the Malayan Archipelago it is no unusual sight to see a
                    poor Chinese coolie with a dress made of gunny cloth. The great and most
                    important use, however, to which gunny cloth is applied is in making bags
                    wherein to pack rice, linseed, sugar, cotton, and other products for
                    shipment.</p>
                <p>As soon as this cheap, strong, and serviceable material became known, the
                    manufacture speedily assumed enormous proportions, and vast quantities of jute
                    were imported into Dundee for the manufacture of gunny <hi rend="superscript">
                        z</hi> bags and cloth alone. The Dundee mills, in the early period of this
                    trade, had only Indian hand-woven gunnies to compete with. The introduction of
                    the latest machinery of the most approved patterns into Bengal, the chief seat
                    of this industry in India, has, however, had the effect of giving India the
                    opportunity of competing with the Dundee mills on advantageous<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n335/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0335-0316"/> terms, and now India supplies vast quantities
                    of gunnies to Europe, Egypt, Ceylon, the Malayan Archipelago, China, and the
                    United States. In America alone it is computed that the annual average outturn
                    of cotton is 3,500,000 bales, each bale requiring 6 yards of wrapping material,
                    and of this one-third at least is supplied in gunny cloth. In 1872-73 6,105,275
                    gunnies and 64,347 pieces were exported from India, whilst in 1876-77, during a
                    period of eleven months, 30,110,616 gunny bags and 5,262,835 yards of gunny
                    cloth were exported to foreign countries. These figures do not include what is
                    sent coastwise or what is used for packing exported Indian produce.</p>
                <p>Bombay too has machinery for weaving jute, but has not as yet done much to
                    compete with Bengal, and indeed there appears little hope for Bombay unless
                    large quantities of jute can be made to grow on the spot, since, apart from the
                    cost of carriage, the juices in the jute plant, as in many other plants, become
                    resinified by drying, and therefore require operating upon whilst perfectly
                    fresh, being attended after treatment with more difficulty in manipulation and a
                    less outturn of fibre.</p>
                <p>The excellent gunny bags sent to England are often used for repacking for
                    exportation, and large quantities find their way to paper mills.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
