<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0360-0341-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUYON, or Guion (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    341)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025853">Months</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103801">Sales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r05m">Sale</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v3p">Sales</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp12">Prayer</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756s76">Prayers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n360/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUYON, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Guion</hi></label>, <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Jeanne Marie Bouvières</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">de la
                        Mothe</hi> (1648-1717), a leading exponent of the quietistic mysticism of
                    the 17th century, was born of wealthy and aristocratic parents at Montargis
                    (dep. Loiret), on the 13th of April 1648. From infancy a sickly and excitable
                    child, she was at the age of two years and a half placed for a short time under
                    the charge of the Ursuline nuns of Montargis, andin 1652 she became resident in
                    the Benedictine convent for a somewhat longer period; but the state of her
                    health rendered it neβessary that she should again be taken home, where for a
                    time she was left almost exclusively to the care of domestics. From her seventh
                    to her tenth year she was once more with the Ursulines, and after another short
                    interval at home she next passed eight months in the Dominican cloister, where
                    she spent much time in reading the Bible, and in committing large portions of it
                    to memory. In her 12th year she communicated for the first time, and also began
                    to form some acquaintance with the writings of St Francis de Sales and of his
                    disciple Madame de Chantal, “la Sainte de Monthélon.” In imitation of the
                    latter, she tells us in her autobiography that she at this time carried the name
                    of the Saviour visibly inscribed on her person, subjected herself to severe
                    bodily austerities, and made a solemn vow ever to aim at the highest perfection
                    in an absolute surrender of her will to God. She earnestly wished also to take
                    the veil, and in fact made an attempt, by means of a forged letter purporting to
                    be signed by her mother, to gain admission into the order of the Visitation of
                    Mary, but her father interfered. In 1663 she removed along with her parents to
                    Paris, and went much into society, where her youth, beauty, and talent secured
                    for her a very flattering reception; in the following year, before she was quite
                    sixteen, she was married to M. Guyon, a man of some wealth and position, but of
                    weak health, and twenty-two years her senior. The union, on her side at least,
                    had not been dictated by love; her husband’s affection, though probably genuine
                    enough, appears to have been of a somewhat tepid kind; and disparity of age, as
                    well as wide differences of taste and habit between herself and M. Guyon,
                    combined with other circumstances, such as the jealousy of her mother-in-law,
                    and her own eager temper, to make her married life anything but happy. She
                    “began to eat the bread of sorrow and to mingle her drink with tears,” and her
                    lonely and desolate heart was not comforted until it found quiet in God. It was
                    in her twenty-first year, on the 22d of July 1668, she tells us, that, after
                    much reading of Thomas a Kempis, St Francis de Sales, and other religious
                    writers, much spiritual conversation with those who knew best about the
                    mysteries of the “inner life” and the happiness of the state of “recollection in
                    God,” much groping in deep darkness, and much wrestling in agonized <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n361/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0361-0342"/> prayer, she at last experienced the change of
                    heart which filled her with joy and peace in the life of faith. The words in
                    which she describes that crisis, if indeed they are not coloured by later
                    experiences, are interesting and important, as showing that thus early she had
                    already reached all that was distinctive of her quietism. “Nothing was more easy
                    to me now than to practise prayer. Hours passed away like moments, while I could
                    hardly do anything else but pray. The fervency of my love allowed me no
                    intermission. It was a prayer of rejoicing and of possession, wherein the taste
                    of God was so great, so pure, unblended, and uninterrupted, that it drew and
                    absorbed the powers of the soul into a profound recollection, a state of
                    confiding and affectionate rest in God, existing without intellectual effort.
                    For I had now no sight but of Jesus Christ alone. All else was excluded in order
                    to love with greater purity and energy, without any motives or reasons for
                    loving which were of a selfish nature.” In the months and year3 that followed
                    she learned by much experience how difficult it is to keep even such heights as
                    the soul has already gained; but her aim, ever more clearly seen and more
                    steadily followed, continued to be “entire consecration,” “perfect faith and
                    love.” Amongst those who were helpful to her during this period was Geneviève
                    Granger, the prioress of a Benedictine community in Paris, under whose influence
                    she, on July 22 (St Mary Magdalene’s day), 1672, drew up a solemn act of
                    consecration, sealed with her ring and signed with her blood, in which she
                    surrendered herself to Christ as His spouse, accepting as a part of her marriage
                    portion “the temptations and sorrows, the crosses and the contempt, which fell
                    to Him.” In the beginning of 1674 she passed into a state of “privation” or
                    “desolation,” which she considers to have continued with but slight variations
                    for somewhat more than six years; during the whole of this period, however, she
                    had the benefit of the spiritual direction of Bertot, a kindred spirit, whose
                    mystical writings she afterwards edited. On the 21st of July 1676 she was left a
                    widow, with three surviving children,—two sons and an infant daughter,—and began
                    to live a life of still deeper seclusion and isolation than before, interesting
                    herself, however, in works of charity, and in the education of her family; in
                    connexion with the latter occupation she commenced and made some progress in the
                    study of Latin. Her temptations and crosses continued nevertheless to multiply;
                    she began to lose hope, and to regard herself as wholly forsaken by God; in her
                    deep despondency she began to correspond with Francis de la Combe, superior of
                    the Barnabites at Thonon, Savoy, with whom she had ten years before become
                    acquainted, and in whom she had even then recognized a sympathizing spirit. On
                    the 22d of July 1680 she tells us her soul was delivered from all its pains.
                    “From the time of the first letter from Father La Combe, I began to recover a
                    new life. I was then, indeed, only like a dead person raised up, who is in the
                    beginning of his restoration, and is raised up to a life of hope rather than of
                    actual possession; but on thÎ3 day I was restored, as it were, to perfect life
                    and set wholly at liberty. I was no longer depressed, no longer borne down under
                    the burden of sorrow. I had thought God lost, and lost for ever; but I found Him
                    again. And He returned to me with unspeakable magnificence and purity. In a
                    wonderful manner, difficult to explain, all that which had been taken from me
                    was not only restored, but restored with increase and with new advantages.” In
                    this changed state of feeling she began to revolve new plans for the disposal of
                    the remainder of her earthly life. She for some time thought of winding up her
                    worldly affairs and taking the veil; but her duty towards her children,
                    especially the two younger, seemed to prohibit that step. Several proposals of
                    marriage were also received, but rejected. Gradually, in the course of 1681, she
                    had almost, though with hesitation, reached the conclusion that she was called
                    to active religioue work, and the field to which inward intimations seemed to
                    point was that part of France and Savoy which borders on Geneva, if not Geneva
                    itself. The advice of D’Aranthon, titular bishop of Geneva, was asked and
                    obtained; he approved of the proposal. After making some important arrangements
                    with regard to her property, and entrusting her two sons to the care of suitable
                    guardians, she accordingly secretly left Paris accompanied only by three female
                    attendants and her daughter, then a child of five years of age. The party
                    arrived at Annecy on the 21st of July; on the following day, at the tomb of St
                    Francis de Sales, Madame Guyon renewed her spiritual marriage with the Redeemer;
                    and finally she fixed her abode at Gex under the spiritual care of D’Aranthon,
                    by whom La Combe was assigned to her as her director in the place of Bertot, who
                    had died some time before. Here she at once began her benevolent labours,
                    tending the sick and poor, praying with them and giving them religious
                    instruction; yet still it seemed to her as if the “seal of her mission was not
                    yet broken.” Something within her whispered that she had not yet found the great
                    and special work to which God had been calling her. Amongst other things the
                    state of her director caused her much solicitude. She saw that he had much, but
                    felt that he ought to have more. Her vocation at last was revealed to her, to
                    become to him a spiritual mother, and her efforts towards the fulfilment of that
                    vocation were not in vain; La Combe at last became possessed with the doctrine
                    of present sanctification by faith in the Saviour, and began to preach
                    accordingly. Opposition and persecution almost immediately began; Bishop
                    D’Aranthon did not fail to take notice of the new doctrine, though on this
                    occasion it escaped formal condemnation by the authorities at Rome; seeing,
                    however, that Madame Guyon was the real author of the heresy, if heresy it was
                    (and it certainly seemed to involve a theory of perfectionism hardly compatible
                    with Catholicism), lie resolved that she should not continue her activities
                    within his diocese unless she should consent to accept a sphere where the
                    facilities for doctrinal propagandism w 0uld be less than those for the exercise
                    of ordinary benevolence. He accordingly proposed that she should give what
                    property still remained within her control to a religious house at Gex, and that
                    she should herself become prioress; this proposal, however, she declined,
                    chiefly on the general ground that it did not seem to be in accordance with the
                    designs of God in regard to her. The alienation of the bishop now made her stay
                    at Gex to be far from comfortable; and accordingly, at the close of a residence
                    of rather more than six months, she removed early in 1682 to Thonon, apparently
                    in the expectation of being near her adviser La Combe. Here she remained for
                    upwards of two years, engaged in religious work of various kinds, especially in
                    spiritual conversation with the people of the neighbourhood, and in tending a
                    small hospital which, at the suggestion of her director and with the assistance
                    of some benevolent ladies of Thonon, she had formed. Meanwhile her doctrines of
                    “pure love” and of that “fixed state” which consists in the complete
                    identification of the human will with the will of God were taking more definite
                    shape; and in 1683 they first found literary expression in <hi rend="italic">Les
                        Torrens,</hi> probably the best of her writings, and really in some respects
                    a fine performance, which describes the progress of the soul from the
                    commencement of its inward life to its union with God, by a reference to
                    “streams or torrents flowing from the mountain tops with greater or less
                    rapidity and with greater or less directness, and mingling at last in the
                    ocean.” Although Madame Guyon was not herself conscious of any disharmony with
                    the teaching and practice of the Catholic Church, her <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n362/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0362-0343"/> doctrines could hardly fail to be regarded by
                    the ordinary orthodoxy of that time as more or less hostile to the generally
                    accepted views as to the nature and mode of sanctification, and as to the normal
                    state of the graciously renewed heart; at Thonon they soon gave deep offence,
                    and ultimately it was intimated both to her and to La Combe, on the part of
                    Bishop D’Aranthon, that both must leave the diocese. Her next resting place for
                    a few weeks was Turin, whence, in the autumn of 1684, she removed to Grenoble,
                    where she again became a centre of attraction and influence. Here, for the
                    direction of the many who flocked to her for instruction and advice, she wrote
                    and circulated her <hi rend="italic">Moyen</hi><hi rend="italic">court</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">et très</hi><hi rend="italic">facile</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                        faire oraison,</hi> a treatise in which she pointed out, doubtless in a
                    manner highly susceptible of misconstruction, that prayer might often well be
                    both silent and wordless.. The commencement of her commentaries on the Bible
                    also dates from this stay in Grenoble. Her numerous and popular “conférences” or
                    meetings for conversation and prayer or “self-recollection in God,” and the
                    effect produced by the <hi rend="italic">Moyen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >court</hi><hi rend="italic">de faire oraison,</hi> however, speedily
                    excited ecclesiastical opposition similar to that which she had already
                    encountered at Gex, and although the biehop (Camus) was himself disposed to be
                    tolerant, if not friendly, she was ultimately constrained, in the spring of
                    1686, to yield to strong representations, and seek an abode elsewhere. Nice,
                    Genoa, and Vercelli (where she again met La Combe) were visited in turn; but it
                    was finally resolved, with the advice and concurrence of her friends, that Paris
                    now offered itself as the field of labour most suited to her powers. Here
                    accordingly she arrived on the 22d of July 1686, and soon she and her teaching
                    began to meet with a very favourable reception in the higher circles of society.
                    But meanwhile the doctrine of Molinos and the <hi rend="italic">Guida</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Spirituale</hi> had been formally condemned by the Inquisition
                    at Rome, and the sentence had been taken up as a signal, especially in France,
                    for the persecution of all suspected quietists. In October 1687 La Combe was
                    suddenly arrested by a royal “lettre de cachet” and committed to the Bastile;
                    and by the same authority Madame Guyon herself was, three months later (29th
                    January 1688), ordered to be detained as a prisoner in the convent of St Marie
                    in the Faubourg Sainte Antoine. The charges brought against her were the
                    maintenance of heretical opinions; the holding of private religious assemblies,
                    contrary to the practice and rules of the Catholic Church, for the spread of
                    these opinions; the publication of a dangerous book containing opinions similar
                    to those of the <hi rend="italic">Spiritual Guide</hi> of Molinos; and
                    correspondence with Molinos. These, however, were not destined to come to a
                    definite issue, for through influence which friends succeeded in bringing to
                    bear upon Madame de Maintenon a release was obtained in the following October.
                    Madame Guyon now went to live for the most part with her daughter, who had
                    become the Comtesse de Vaux, at the family seat in the neighbourhood of Paris;
                    but while on a visit with the duchess of Charost she became acquainted with
                    Fénelon, and a considerable correspondence began. Her influence continuing to
                    make itself felt at Paris, Dijon, Versailles, and other places, especially in
                    the institution of St Cyr, founded by Madame de Maintenon in 1686, the attention
                    of theologians was drawn afresh to the “new spirituality,” as it was called; and
                    among others both the Port-Royalist Nicole and Bossuet, bishop of Meaux, sought
                    personal interviews. The latter, to whom she had submitted not only all her
                    printed works but also the manuscript of an autobiography which she had written
                    when in confinement in 1688, after more than one long conference, is understood
                    to have expressed himself as on the whole satisfied of her orthodoxy; but the
                    publication by Nicole of the <hi rend="italic">Refutation</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >des principales Erreurs des</hi><hi rend="italic">Quietistes</hi> appears
                    to have had an exciting influence on the public mind; rumours prejudicial not
                    only to the orthodoxy of Madam Guyon’s faith, but also to the purity of her
                    life, were industriously spread, and caused great scandal in the highest
                    quarters, so that at last she was constrained to write to Madame de Maintenon
                    requesting that a number of suitable persons might be selected for the purpose
                    of judging both of her doctrine and her morals, and offering at the same time to
                    submit to any degree of confinement and restraint until it should please the
                    king to appoint such persons. A commission ∙was duly nominated, consisting of
                    Bossuet, Bishop (afterwards Cardinal) De Noailles, and Tronson, the superior of
                    St Sulpice. To this tribunal she at their request submitted <hi rend="italic"
                        >∖</hi><hi rend="italic">ho,</hi><hi rend="italic">Moyen</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Court,Les Torrens,</hi> and the manuscripts of her
                    commentaries along with her autobiography, to which she added her <hi
                        rend="italic">Justification.</hi> The outcome of many deliberations,
                    extending over some months, was the preparation of twenty-four articles, usually
                    called the “Articles of Issy,” relating to the doctrine of “pure love.” Her
                    refusal to sign a “condemnation of religious errors,” as drawn up and presented
                    to her by Bossuet in a pastoral ordinance and letter, now led to an open rupture
                    which resulted in her reimprisonment, on this occasion at Vincennes, on the 27th
                    of December 1695. Bossuet now set himself to prepare his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Instruction</hi><hi rend="italic">sur les étais</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">oraison,</hi> which he submitted before
                    publication to De Noailles, and, amongst others, to Fénelon for approval. The
                    latter after reading the manuscript withheld his imprimatur, not on account of
                    its doctrine (with which he did not disagree), but on account of its
                    personalities, which he held to be uncalled for and unjust. Almost forced thus
                    into the position of a champion of Madame Guyon, he published in 1697 his <hi
                        rend="italic">Maximes des Saintes,</hi> a statement of the leading
                    principles laid down by approved writers on the subject of the higher inward
                    experience and of holy living. In the course of the controversy which followed
                    several important works appeared, which can only be alluded to here; the
                    dispute, as is well known, issued in the formal condemnation of Fénelon (12th
                    March 1699), in which achievement the hostility to Madame Guyon seems to have
                    almost exhausted itself. She was not released, however, until 1702, in which
                    year she was banished to Blois, where the remainder of her life was spent.
                    Numbers of persons of all ranks, and many of them from foreign countries,
                    visited her in this retirement: and both in correspondence and conversation she
                    continued to manifest considerable activity, although feeling herself “called on
                    to glorify God by submission and by private prayer, rather than by active
                    labours.” She heard mass daily, received the sacrament every alternate day, and
                    died in full communion with the Roman Catholic Church, after an illness of three
                    months, on the 9th of June 1717.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lα Vie de Madame de la Mothe Guyon,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >écrite</hi><hi rend="italic">par</hi><hi rend="italic">elle-même,</hi>
                    first appeared at Cologne in 1720. It is based upon the autobiography which at
                    the instance of La Combe she is known to have written during her imprisonment in
                    1688; it afterwards received additions and corrections from her own hands, and
                    was finally entrusted to a confidential friend on the understanding that it
                    should not be published until after her death. In addition to <hi rend="italic"
                        >Les Torrens</hi><hi rend="italic">Spirituels,</hi> and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Moyen</hi><hi rend="italic">court</hi><hi rend="italic">et
                        très</hi><hi rend="italic">facile</hi><hi rend="italic">de faire
                        oraison,</hi> which were published in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Opuscules</hi><hi rend="italic">Spirituels</hi> in 1704, there appeared in
                    her lifetime the <hi rend="italic">Poésies Spirituelles</hi> (1689); and <hi
                        rend="italic">La Bible,</hi><hi rend="italic">traduite en français,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">aves</hi><hi rend="italic">des Explications et des Réflexions
                        qui regardent la Vie Intérieure</hi> (1715). There are also several volumes
                    of <hi rend="italic">Lettres Chrétiennes et Spirituelles,</hi> addressed by her
                    to Metternich, Fénelon, and other correspondents, many of them distinguished.
                    The edition of the collected <hi rend="italic">Oeuvres</hi> extends to 40 vols.
                    (1767-1791 ). English and German translations of the various works are numerous.
                    Apart from the <hi rend="italic">Autobiography,</hi> the only memoir of Madame
                    Guyon as yet in existence, is the diffuse but somewhat vague and meagre <hi
                        rend="italic">Life,</hi> by Thomas C. Upham (1854). (J. S. BL.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
