<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0013-0004-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GOURD</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 4</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:935548">Fruit</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:945122">Gourds</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:884910">Cucurbita</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n13/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GOURD</label>, a name given to various plants of the order
                    <hi rend="italic">Cuxurbitaceoe,</hi> but more strictly applied to those
                    belonging to the genus <hi rend="italic">Cucurbita,</hi> monoecious trailing
                    herbs of annual duration, with long succulent stems furnished with tendrils, and
                    large, rough, palmately-lobed leaves; the flowers, reticulated with veins, are
                    generally large and of a bright yellow or orange colour, the barren ones with
                    the stamens united; the fertile are followed by the large, succulent fruit that
                    gives the gourds their chief economic value. Many varieties of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cucurbita</hi> are under cultivation in tropical and temperate climates,
                    especially in southern Asia; but it is extremely difficult to refer them to
                    definite specific groups, on account of the facility with which they hybridize;
                    while it is very doubtful whether any of the original forms now exist in the
                    wild state. M. Naudin, who made a careful and interesting series of observations
                    upon this genus, came to the conclusion that all varieties known in European
                    gardens might be referred to six original species; probably three, or at most
                    four, have furnished the edible kinds in ordinary cultivation; and, as all these
                    appear occasionally to hybridize, their limits must be regarded as very
                    uncertain. Adopting the specific names usually given to the more familiar forms,
                    the most important of the gourds, from an economic point of view, is perhaps <hi
                    rend="italic">C. maxima,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Potiron Jaune</hi> of the
                    French, the red and yellow gourd of British gardeners, the spheroidal fruit of
                    which is remarkable for its enormous size: the colour of the somewhat rough rind
                    varies from white to bright yellow, while in some kinds it remains green; the
                    fleshy interior is of a deep yellow or orange tint. This valuable gourd is grown
                    extensively in southern Asia and Europe. In Turkey and Asia Minor it yields, at
                    some periods of the year, an important article of diet to the people; immense
                    quantities are sold in the markets of Constantinople, where in the winter the
                    heaps of one variety with a white rind are described by Walsh as resembling
                    mounds of snowballs. The yellow kind attains occasionally a weight of upwards of
                    240 lb. It grows well in central Europe and the United States, while in the
                    south of England it will produce its gigantic fruit in perfection in hot
                    summers. The yellow flesh of this gourd and its numerous varieties yields a
                    considerable amount of nutri ment, and is the more valuable as the fruit can be
                    kept, even in warm climatee, for a long time. In France and in the East it is
                    much used in soups and ragouts, while simply boiled it forms a substitute for
                    other table vegetables; the taβte has been compared to that of a young carrot.
                    In some countries the larger kinds are employed as cattle food. The seeds yield
                    by expression a large quantity of a bland oil, which is used for the same
                    purposes as that of the poppy and olive. The “mammoth” gourds of English and
                    American gardeners appear to belong to this species, or to hybrids between it
                    and another valuable member of the group, the pumpkin, <hi rend="italic">C.
                    Pepo,</hi> well known in English cottage gardens, and largely cultivated in
                    continental Europe and North America. The pumpkin varies much in form, being
                    sometimes nearly globular, but more generally oblong or ovoid in shape; the rind
                    is smooth, and very variable in colour. This gourd is a useful plant to the
                    American backwoods farmer, yielding, both in the ripe and unripe condition, a
                    valuable fodder for his cattle and pigs, being frequently planted at intervals
                    among the maize that constitutes his chief crop. The larger kinds acquire a
                    weight of from 40 to 80 B⅛, but smaller varieties are in more esteem for garden
                    culture. When ripe, the pumpkin is boiled or baked, or made into various kinds
                    of pie, alone or mixed with other fruit; while small and green, it may be eaten
                    like the vegetable marrow. Some of the variëties of <hi rend="italic">C. maxima
                    and Pepo</hi> contain a considerable quantity of sugar, amounting in the
                    sweetest kinds to 4 or 5 per cent., and in the hot plains of Hungary efforts
                    have been made to make use of them as a commercial source of sugar. The young
                    shoots of both these large gourds may be given to cattle, and admit of being
                    eaten as a green vegetable when boiled. The vegetable marrow, <hi rend="italic"
                    >C. ovifera,</hi> regarded by Naud in as a variety of <hi rend="italic">C.
                    Pepo,</hi> is much esteemed in England for the delicate flavour of its fruit,
                    which is eaten boiled, in the immature state, as a pleasant summer vegetable. A
                    large number of varieties are in cultivation,—the larger oblong or pear-shaped
                    kinds growing a foot or more in length, while some are comparatively small. This
                    useful esculent will succeed in any warm and open situation, if planted over a
                    small trench filled with manure; it is often trained over the fences of cottage
                    gardens, and may be sometimes seen flourishing on the sunny side of railway
                    cuttings in the south of England. <hi rend="italic">C.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Melopepo,</hi> is the squash or bush gourd, a favourite vegetable in the United
                    States and in parts of continental Europe, but less cultivated in Britain than
                    the preceding. It has a somewhat different habit from most of the family, having
                    more rigid shoots and a tendency towards a shrubby mode of growth; the fruit,
                    yellowish when ripe, is smaller than the pumpkin, and of various shapes, usually
                    with many angles or projections; some sorts resemble a turban, others
                    many-cornered hats, whence fanciful names have been applied to them. The number
                    of kinds is considerable, especially in the United States, where the squashes
                    are much cultivated; the larger kinds are grown as food for pigs and cattle,
                    besides being valued as table esculents; for cooking they should be used in the
                    unripe condition. Many smaller gourds are cultivated in India and other hot
                    climates, and some have been introduced into English gardens, rather for the
                    beauty of their fruit and foliage than for their esculent qualities. Among these
                    is <hi rend="italic">C. Aurantia,</hi> the orange gourd, bearing a spheroidal
                    fruit, like a large orange in form and colour; in Britain It is generally too
                    bitter to be palatable, though applied to culinary purposes in Turkey and the
                    Levant. <hi rend="italic">C. ρyτi,∙</hi><hi rend="italic">formis,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">C. verrucosa,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">C. moschata</hi> are
                    likewise occasionally eaten, especially in the immature state; and several other
                    gourds are used as esculents in India and the neighbouring countries.</p>
                <p>The bottle-gourds are now generally placed in a separate genus, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lagenaria,</hi> chiefly differing from <hi rend="italic">Cucurbita</hi> in the
                    anthers being free instead of adherent. The bottle-gourd properly so-called, <hi
                    rend="italic">L. vulgaris,</hi> is a climbing plant with downy, heart-shaped
                    leaves and beautiful white flowers: the remarkable fruit first begins to grow in
                    the form of an elongated cylinder, but gradually widens towards the extremity,
                    until, when ripe, it resembles a flask with a narrow neck and large rounded
                    bulb; it sometimes attains a length of 7 feet. When ripe, the pulp is removed
                    from the neck, and the interior cleared by leaving water standing in it; the
                    woody rind that remains is used as a bottle: or the lower part is cut off and
                    cleared out, forming a basin-like vessel applied to the same domestic purposes
                    as the calabash <hi rend="italic">{Crescentia)</hi> of the West Indies; the
                    smaller varieties, divided length-wise, form spoons. The ripe fruit is apt to be
                    bitter and cathartic, but while immature it is eaten by the Arabs and Turks.
                    When about the “size of a small cucumber,” Lane says, it is stuffed with rice
                    and minced meat, flavoured with pepper, onions, &amp;c., and then boiled, <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n14/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0014-0005"/> forming a favourite dish with Eastern epicures.
                    The elongated snake-gourdä of India and China <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Trichosanthes)</hi> are said to be used in curries and stews.</p>
                <p>All the gourds have a tendency to secrete the cathartic principle <hi
                    rend="italic">colocynthin,</hi> and in many varieties of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cucurbita</hi> and the allied genera it is often elaborated to such an extent
                    as to render them unwholesome, or even poisonous. The seeds of some species
                    possess rather strong anthelmintic properties; those of the common pumpkin are
                    frequently administered in America as a vermifuge. The cultivation of gourds
                    commenced far beyond the dawn of history, and the esculent species have become
                    so modified by culture that the original plants from which they have descended
                    can no longer be traced. The abundance of varieties in India would seem to
                    indicate that-part of Asia as the birthplace of the present edible forms; but
                    some appear to have been cultivated in all the hotter regions of that continent,
                    and in North Africa, from the earliest ages, while the Romans were familiar with
                    at least certain kinds of <hi rend="italic">Cucurbita,</hi> and with the
                    bottle-gourd. It is even doubtful whether the culture of gourds had not spread
                    to the American continent before its discovery by Europeans; for the Indian
                    tribes of the interior were certainly in possession of some kinds at a date so
                    early that it is difficult to believe they had received them from the settlers.
                    Dr Asa Gray has even suggested that some of these esculent forms may possibly
                    have been indigenous to the American plains.</p>
                <p>Most of the annual gourds may be grown successfully in Britain. They are usually
                    raised in hotbeds or under frames, and planted out in rich soil in the early
                    summer as soon as the nights become warm. The more ornamental kinds may be
                    trained over trellis-work, a favourite mode of displaying them in the East; but
                    the situation must be sheltered and sunny. Even the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lagenarioe</hi> will sometimes produce fine fruit when so treated in the
                    southern counties, (c. p. J.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
