<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0195-0184-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GRENOBLE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 184</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:937852">Gardening</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:933759">Franks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:821579">Austrians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tw1v">Cost</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n195/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GRENOBLE</label>, a fortified city of France, formerly the
                    chief town of Dauphiné and now of the department of the Isère, lies 58 miles E.
                    of Lyons, in 45° 11' 57" N. lat. and 5° 43' 29" E. long. Few of the cities of
                    France have a finer situation. The Isère unites with the Drac a few miles
                    further down, and the broad and fertile valley through which the rivers flow is
                    encompassed by a fine panorama of hills and mountains. From the botanic gardens,
                    for example, the eastward view comprises the Savoy Alps with the summit of Mount
                    Blanc, and the westward the mountains of St Nizier, while more to the north the
                    hills rise directly above the town, and are crowned by the fort of the Bastille.
                    The beauty of the Isère itself is enhanced by fine bridges <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n196/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0196-0185"/> and quays. With the exception of its more modern
                    portions, the town of Grenoble is characterized by the tortuous and crowded
                    streets usual in places that have long been confined within strong
                    fortifications. The cathedral of Notre Dame, a vast brick building of various
                    periods from the 10th to the 17th century, the foundation of which is
                    traditionally ascribed to Charles the Great; the church of St Laurence, with a
                    remarkable crypt of the 11th century, long believed to be an old temple of
                    Aesculapius: and the church of St André, founded by the dauphin Guigues André
                    about 1220, and frequently visited for the sake of the tomb of Bayard removed
                    thither in 1822, are the most noteworthy of the ecclesiastical edifices. The
                    palais de justice is a striking erection of the 15th and 16th centuries
                    occupying the site of the old castle of the dauphins, and in front is a statue
                    of Bayard dating from 1823. The old town-hall hae nothing remarkable about it;
                    but the new prefecture, built at a cost of 1,404,000 francs about 1867, is a
                    handsome structure. Besides its university or academy, with the three faculties
                    of law, science, and literature,</p>
                <p>Grenoble possesses a lyceum, an episcopal seminary, a school of artillery of the
                    first class, two normal schools, and a great variety of special educational
                    institutions. The library, which since 1868 has been located along with the
                    museum in a building which cost more than 1,500,000 francs, is a noble
                    collection of upwards of 178,875 volumes, on which the town has expended
                    2,000,000 francs.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See
                    Gariel, <hi rend="italic">La Bibliothèque</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Grenoble,</hi> 1772-1878, Paris, 1878.</p></note> Among the numerous societies
                    of Grenoble it is enough to mention the <hi rend="italic">Academie</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">delphinale</hi> (1772), the statistical society, the society of
                    the friends of the arts, the society of agriculture, and the zoological society
                    of the Alps, which maintains zoological gardens. At the head of the benevolent
                    institutions is the general hospital, originally founded by Aimon Chissay in
                    1424, and now comprising civil and military departments, an orphanage, and an
                    asylum for the aged and infirm. It was in Grenoble that the first mutual benefit
                    society was founded in 1803, and the number of such associations in the town was
                    upwards of 40 about 1870. In 1836 M. Berriat Saint Prix established a society
                    for the extinction of mendicity, and in 1851 M. Frédéric originated an <hi
                    rend="italic">association</hi><hi rend="italic">alimentaire</hi> for the purpose
                    of providing the poorer classes with good food at the cheapest possible rate.
                    The staple industry of Grenoble is the making of gloves; 115 establishments,
                    employing 2000 workmen and 20,000 needlewomen in the town and neighbourhood,
                    turn out annually 850,000 dozen pairs. Liqueurs, leather, straw hats, paper,
                    lime, and cement hold a principal place among the miscellaneous products. The
                    population of Grenoble was 26,852 in 1851, 35,280 in 1872, and 43,054 in
                    1876.</p>
                <p>Grenoble occupies the site of Cularo, a village of the Allobroges which first
                    became of importance when it was fortified by Diocletian and Maximian. Its
                    present name is a corruption of Gratianopolis, a title assumed in honour of
                    Gratian, who had strengthened the walls. From the Burgundians who gained
                    possession in 467 the little town passed under the Franks, and on the
                    dismemberment of the empire of Charles the Great it was included in the limits
                    of Cisjuran Burgundy. After the 10th century its bishops grew into power, but
                    they were finally supplanted in the 13th century by the counts of Λlbon,
                    afterwards known as the Dauphins. Though it was ceded in 1349 to France along
                    with Dauphiné, the city continued to enjoy special privileges. In 1563 it was
                    sacked by the Baron des Adrets, but in 1572 the energy of its governor De Gorde
                    saved it from sh≡ ’ ing in tħe massacre of St Bartholomew. Lesdiguières (Roi des
                    Montagnes) took the town by siege in 1590 in name of Henry IV., and he
                    afterwards made his governorship memorable by his fortifications, quays, and
                    other serviceable enterprises. In the close of the 18th century the name of
                    Grenoble appears in the van of the revolutionary movement; the attempt of the
                    Government to substitute a new judicial régime for that of the too independent
                    provincial parliament roused the people to arms and the ‘ ‘ day of the tilee”
                    (7th June 1788) is memorable for the defeat of the royal forces. Grenoble was
                    the first town to open its gates to Napoleon on his return from Elba in 1815,
                    but a few months afterwards it was obliged to surrender to the Austrians. Owing
                    to its situation Grenoble is subject to inundations; in 1219 it was almost swept
                    away, and from that date to 1856 no fewer than 15 similar disasters are
                    enumerated. The great flood of 1778 is known as the “Déluge de la Saint Crépin.”
                    In 1859 the water was 3 feet deep throughout the town. Among the celebrated
                    natives of Grenoble are Vaucanson, Mably, Condillac, Beyle (Stendhal), Barnave,
                    and Casimir Perier.</p>
                <p>See Champoilion Figeac, <hi rend="italic">Antiquités</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Grenoble,</hi> (Grenoble, 1807); Pitot, <hi rend="italic">Hist, de
                    Grenoble</hi><hi rend="italic">et de ses</hi><hi rend="italic">environs</hi>
                    (Grenoble, 1829).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
