<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0085-0076-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GRAY, John Edward</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 76</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:946934">Gray</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:999835">Lists</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1115719">Shells</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:926361">Fishes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:926650">Fishing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq4d">Fishing</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mw0m">Fish</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4sb3x268">Fishes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4bt5f">Shells</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n85/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GRAY, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Edward</hi></label>
                    (1800-1875), a distinguished English naturalist, born at Walsall, Staffordshire,
                    in 1800, was the eldest of the three sons of Mr S. F. Gray, of that town,
                    druggist and writer on botany, author of the <hi rend="italic">Supplement to the
                    Pharmacopoeia,</hi> &lt;fcc., and grandson of Mr S. Gray, who translated for Lee
                    the <hi rend="italic">Philosophia Botanica</hi> of Linnaeus, and assisted in the
                    composition of the <hi rend="italic">Introduction to Botany.</hi> Gray studied
                    at St Bartholomew’s and other hospitals for the medical profession, but was
                    attracted to the more enlivening pursuit of botany, on which he wrote and
                    lectured. At an early age he assisted his father by collecting notes on botany
                    and comparative anatomy and zoology in Sir Joseph Banks’s library at the British
                    Museum, aided by Dr W. E. Leach, assistant-keeper. The systematic synopsis of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Natural Arrangement of British Plants,</hi> 2 vols., 1821,
                    was prepared by him, his father writing the preface and introduction only. This
                    work, which introduced the natural system of plants on Jussieu’s plan to the
                    student of English botany, gave offence to the Linnean Society, who rejected
                    Gray’s application for a fellowship in 1822. Chafed at this unmerited rebuff, he
                    turned to the study of zoology, writing on zoophytes, shells, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mollusca,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Papilionidoe,</hi> still aided by Dr Leach
                    at the British Museum. In December 1824 Gray obtained the post of assistant in
                    that institution; and from that date to December 1839, when Mr J. G. Children
                    retired from the keepership, he had so zealously applied himself to the study,
                    classification, and improvement of the national collection of zoology that he
                    was selected as the fittest person to be entrusted with its charge. Immediately
                    on his appointment as keeper, Gray took in hand the revision of the systematic
                    arrangement of the collections; scientific catalogues followed in rapid
                    succession; the department was raised in importance; its poverty as well as its
                    wealth became known, and whilst increased grants, donations, and exchanges made
                    good many deficiencies, great numbers of students, foreign as well as English,
                    availed themselves of its resources to enlarge the knowledge of zoology in all
                    its branches. Gray found the representatives of the animal kingdom confusedly
                    huddled together in old Montagu House; and the science of zoology was just then
                    emerging from infancy, with little public support to foster it. But, in spite of
                    numerous obstacles, he worked up the department, within a few years of his
                    appointment as keeper, to such a state of excellence as to make it the rival of
                    the cabinets of Leyden, Paris, and Berlin; and later on it was raised under his
                    management to the dignity of the largest and most complete zoological collection
                    in the world. The extensive acquaintance which he had obtained with practical
                    zoology, his love of the subject, close application, and original views, his
                    skill and accuracy of observation, his readiness to impart the information he
                    had acquired to any one who sought it, and above all his marvellous industry,
                    place Gray in the foremost rank of naturalists. It has been said that he tried
                    to accomplish too much, that he wrote hurriedly and paid little attention to
                    anatomy; but it must be remembered that he laboured for the past generation, not
                    among the one-subject men of the present age. He did his work nobly, though
                    somewhat roughly; and it will ever be appreciated by generous men of science.
                    His eagerness for controversy, and the outspoken plainness with which he
                    asserted his views, sometimes brought him into unpleasant relations with those
                    he had to do with. Of this the catalogue dispute with Panizzi, and the gorilla
                    dispute with Du Chaillu, Owen, and others, are well-known instances. Although
                    seized with paralysis in 1870, Gray continued to discharge the functions of
                    keeper of zoology, and to contribute papers to the <hi rend="italic">Annals of
                    Natural History,</hi> his favourite journal, and to the transactions of a few of
                    the learned societies. At Christmas 1874, having completed half a century of
                    official work, he resigned office; and on the 7th of March 1875 this
                    indefatigable naturalist expired.</p>
                <p>Gray was elected a fellow of the Royal Society in 1832; in 1852 the honorary
                    degree of doctor of philosophy of the university of Munich was conferred upon
                    him, in recognition of his formation of the largest zoological collection in
                    Europe; and in 1860 the king of Wiirtemberg, desiring to mark the estimation in
                    which he held Gray, who had declined an offer of knighthood, bestowed upon him
                    the gold medal of merit. He was a president of the Entomological Society,
                    vice-president of the Zoological and Microscopical Societies, fellow of the
                    Geographical and Palaeontological Society, in the formation of which he took
                    part; he was president of the Botanical Society, and also a fellow of the
                    Linnean and Geological Societies; he founded the Greenwich Society of Useful
                    Knowledge; and he was an honorary or corresponding member of numerous foreign
                    societies and academies. He was deputy-chairman of the section of the animal and
                    vegetable substances of the Exhibition of 1851, and a juror of the educational
                    section of the Exhibition of 1862. He took an active part in questions of public
                    importance of his day, sueh as slave emancipation, prison discipline, abolition
                    of imprisonment for debt, sanitary and municipal organizations, the decimal
                    system, public education, extension of the opening of public institutions,
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Works.—ι)τ</hi> Gray commenced to publish in 1820, and
                    continued till the year of his death. He began with an <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historical Sketch of thi Improvements in Comparative Anatomy and Zoology
                    in</hi> 1819, and ended with a paper “On the Madagascar River-Hog <hi
                    rend="italic">{Ρotamochoerus</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi> and on the skulls of
                    the three species of the genus,” <hi rend="italic">Ann. N. H.,</hi> xv., 1875.
                    The titles of the books, memoirs, and miscellaneous <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n86/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0086-0077"/> papers written by him, accompanied by a few
                    notes, fill a privately printed list of 56 octavo pages. The more important of
                    the books, besides those already mentioned, are :— <hi rend="italic">Synopsis of
                    the species of the class Mammalia,</hi> 1827 (Griffith’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cuvier,</hi> vol. v.); <hi rend="italic">Illustrations of Indian Zoology,</hi>
                    2 vols., 1830-35; <hi rend="italic">A Synopsis of the species of the
                    class</hi><hi rend="italic">Reptilia,</hi> 1830 <hi rend="italic">(Cuvier,</hi>
                    ix.); <hi rend="italic">Zoological Miscellany,</hi> 1831-45; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Synopsis</hi><hi rend="italic">Reptilium,</hi> 1831; <hi rend="italic">A
                    Descriptive Catalogue of Recent and Fossil Shells,</hi> 1832; Turton’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Manual of the Land and Freshwater Shells of the British
                    Islands</hi> (new ed.), 1840; <hi rend="italic">List of the Specimens of
                    Mammalia in the British Museum,</hi> 1843; <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of
                    Tortoises,</hi> &amp;c., 1844; <hi rend="italic">Systematic Catalogue of British
                    Land and Freshwater Shells,</hi> 1844; <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Specimens
                    of Lizards,</hi> 1845; <hi rend="italic">Gleanings from the Menagerie and Aviary
                    at Knowsley Hall</hi> (superintended at the request of the late earl of Derby),
                    1846-50; Zis·i <hi rend="italic">of the genera of recent</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Mollusca,</hi> 1847; <hi rend="italic">List of Csteological Specimens,</hi>
                    1847, <hi rend="italic">of British Sponges, Radiated An imals (Centronics), of
                    British</hi><hi rend="italic">Radiata,</hi> separate, 1848; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Catalogue of</hi><hi rend="italic">Mollusca,</hi> 1849-50; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Catalogue of Reptiles (Snakes),</hi> 1849; <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Fish
                    (Chondropterygia),</hi> 1850; <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Mammalia (Cetacea,
                    Seals, Hoofed Quadrupeds),</hi> 1850- 1852; <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of
                    Amphibia,</hi> 1850; <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Bivalve</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Mollusca,</hi> 1850-53; <hi rend="italic">List of Fish
                    (Cartilaginous), of British Fish,</hi> separate, 1851; <hi rend="italic">List of
                    British</hi><hi rend="italic">Mollusca</hi><hi rend="italic">and Shells,</hi>
                    1851; <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Echi-nidce or Sea-Eggs,</hi> 1851; <hi
                    rend="italic">Catalogue of Phaueropneumona</hi> (with L. Pfeiffer), 1852; <hi
                    rend="italic">Catalogue of Fish collected and described by L. T. Gronov,</hi>
                    1854; <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Shield Rep&gt;tiles,</hi> 1855-72; <hi
                    rend="italic">Catalogue of the recent Echinida,</hi> 1855; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Catalogue of Pulmonata</hi> (with L. Pfeiffer), 1855; <hi rend="italic">Guide
                    to the collection of</hi><hi rend="italic">Mollusca,</hi> 1856; <hi
                    rend="italic">Catalogue of Apodal Fish, by Dr J. J. Kaup,</hi> translated and
                    edited by Gray, 1856; <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Auriculidce,</hi> 1857; <hi
                    rend="italic">Systematic arrangement of figures of Conchifera and
                    Brachiopoda,</hi> 1857; <hi rend="italic">List of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Mollusca,</hi> 1858; <hi rend="italic">Handbook of British Waterweeds,
                    or</hi><hi rend="italic">Algae</hi> (with W. Carruthers), 1864; Salisbury’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Genera of Plants,</hi> edited by Gray, 1866; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Catalogue of Seals and Whales,</hi> 1866-71; <hi rend="italic">Synopsis of
                    Species of Starfish,</hi> 1866; <hi rend="italic">Synopsis of species of Whales
                    ancl Dolphins,</hi> 1868; <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Carnivorous,
                    Pachydermatous, and Edentate Mammalia,</hi> 1869; <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of
                    Monkeys, Lemurs, and Fruit-eating Bats,</hi> 1870; <hi rend="italic">Tortoises,
                    Terrapins, and Turtles,</hi> 1872 (re-edited); <hi rend="italic">Handlist of
                    Seals, Morses, Sea-Lions, and Sea-Bears,</hi> 1874.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
