<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0260-0247-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUERNSEY (9th edition, volume 11, page 247)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j39364">Monuments</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025892">Monuments</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884667">Crystals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n260/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUERNSEY</label>, the second in size of the Channel Islands,
                    is situated between 49° 25' and 49° 31' N. lat. and between 2° 30' and 2° 41' W.
                    long., 30 miles W. of Normandy, and 81 miles S. of Portsmouth. The total area at
                    low water is estimated at 15,560 acres, or rather more than 24 square miles, and
                    of this about 10,000 acres are under cultivation. Gradually rising from the
                    north to the south, the island attains its maximum elevation of 349 feet above
                    mean tide at Haut Nez, above Point Icart. According to J. A. Bird’s “Geology of
                    the Channel Islands” in <hi rend="italic">The Geological Magazine,</hi> London,
                    1878, it consists geologically of three very unequal portions, one characterized
                    by a very felspathic syenite and gneiss, another by a hornblendic “granital,”
                    and a third by a micaceous syenite. The felspathic portion yields magnificent
                    crystals of felspar, surpassing those of the porphyritic granites of Cornwall or
                    Cumberland; and the hornblendic portion occasionally affords crystals of black
                    hornblende in similar perfection. No Secondary or Tertiary rocks are found in
                    position, but postTertiary clays containing flints are found all round the
                    island and even on its summit, and Mr Bird is disposed to assign them to the
                    interglacial period of submergence. The soil of Guernsey is generally a light
                    sandy loam, and the subsoil consists for the most part of angular gravel, except
                    in certain places occupied by a curious clay, chiefly composed of a silicate of
                    alumina, which proves destructive to vegetable life. While the island does not
                    grow sufficient grain for its own consumption, it has a large export of fruits
                    and other garden produce. Parsnips were formerly one of the principal items, but
                    they are now less extensively cultivated, having been supplanted by potatoes and
                    turnips. Grapes, which were exported to the amount of 50 tons in 1873, are the
                    source of an increasing trade. Granite is largely shipped at St Sampson.</p>
                <p>For administrative purposes Guernsey is united with Alderney, Sark, Herrn, and
                    the adjacent islands in the bailiwick of Guernsey. The island proper is divided
                    into the ten parishes of St Peter Port, St Sampson, Vale, Câtel, St Saviour, St
                    Andrew, St Martin, Forest, St Peter du Bois, and Torteval. The administration is
                    under the supervision of a lieutenant-governor appointed by the crown; and the
                    parliamentary assembly consists of a bailiff, twelve jurats, a procureur or
                    attorney-general, the beneficed clergy, and twelve delegates elected by the
                    people. Taxation is very light, and the annual revenue amounts to about £10,000.
                    Ecclesiastically the island is a deanery of the Winchester diocese of the Church
                    of England.</p>
                <p>The only town of any great importance is St Peter Port on the eastern coast. In
                    1861 it had a population of 16,388 (6968 males and 9420 females), and in 1871,
                    16,166 (6731 males and 9435 females). The sea frontage of the town extends for
                    about a mile, and is protected in nearly all its length by a wall with an
                    esplanade. On the improvement of the harbour, which was begun in the 13th
                    century by order of King Edward I., a sum of £285,000 has been expended since
                    1854. It is formed by two piers, which enclose an area of 73 acres, the
                    southernmost of the two running out to Castle Cornet and then sending out a
                    breakwater for about 3000 yards. The whole of the works are of the most massive
                    description. Among the principal buildings of the town, which has been greatly
                    improved by the formation of a new street from the harbour up to the hill, are
                    the Government house, the court-house, Elizabeth college, the town hospital, St
                    Stephen’s church built in 1866, the Roman Catholic church designed by Pugin, and
                    the new vegetable market constructed at a cost of £16,000. On the higher ground
                    above the town is a monument in memory of the Queen’s visit to the island in
                    1846, and on the pier there was erected in 1863 a monument to the Prince Consort
                    by Mr Durham, a copy of the monument in the gardens of the Horticultural Society
                    at South Kensington. St Sampson, which is the only port besides St Peter Port,
                    is situated at the eastern end of the Braye du Vai, a depression which at no
                    distant date used to form an arm of the sea at high tides, cutting the island
                    into two unequal parts. The harbour accommodation has been improved at St
                    Sampson contemporaneously with that of St Peter Port. To the south of the latter
                    is the strong fort of St George’s with barracks for 5000 men, and smaller forts,
                    batteries, and martello towers are to be found on suitable points all round the
                    coast.</p>
                <p>By the old Guernsey laws, all the male population from sixteen to sixty are
                    obliged to serve in the militia; but the custom of paying exemption fines has
                    gradually become so common that the real force is very far below its nominal
                    limit. Guernsey is both populous and wealthy, and the wealth is very evenly
                    distributed among the people. In 1873 the assessment value of the town parish
                    was <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n261/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0261-0248"/> £3,564,750, or £2262 per head, and that of
                    the rural parishes £1,831,620, or £1233 per head. Like the neighbouring part of
                    France, Guernsey still possesses numerous traces of its early inhabitants, in
                    the form of sepulchral caves, dolmens, and maenhirs. The most remarkable group
                    of the second class is in the north at Ancresse. Details will be found in Mr
                    Lukis’s paper in vol. i. of the <hi rend="italic">Archaeological Journal,</hi>
                    and in vols. i. and viii. of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Archoeological</hi><hi rend="italic">Association,</hi> as well
                    as in the special chapter in Dr Ansted’s <hi rend="italic">Channel Islands.</hi>
                    The island is usually identified with the Sarnia of the latter Roman writers.
                    Its present name would appear to be a corruption of the Norse for Green Isle.
                    For details on its history see <hi rend="smallcaps">Channel Islands.</hi> An
                    account of a number of its more eminent natives, many of whom have served with
                    high distinction in the British army, will be found in <hi rend="italic">Sarnia,
                        or brief Memorials of many of her Sons,</hi> Guernsey, 1862. Among the
                    better known families are the Sau-marezes, the Tuppers, and the Careys.</p>
                <p>Besides the works referred to under <hi rend="smallcaps">Channel Islands,</hi>
                    see <hi rend="italic">Documents</hi><hi rend="italic">relatifs à</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">file de Guernsey,</hi> Guernsey, 1814; <hi rend="italic">Views
                        of Guernsey,</hi> with descriptive letterpress, Edinburgh, 1867; John Jacob,
                        <hi rend="italic">Annals of the Bailiwick of Guernsey,</hi> London, 1830; Le
                    Marchant, <hi rend="italic">Laws and Customs of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Normando</hi><hi rend="italic">as used in Royal Court of Guernsey.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
