<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0911-0257-0244-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUELFS and (9th edition, volume 11, page 244)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41g0hz7v">Ghibellines</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26h3v">Lombards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m1s">Liberty</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gh4j">Names</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211813">Luxembourg</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1068346">Polenta</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085176">Quarreling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1032344">Names</term>
                    <term ref="fast:960068">Hope</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n257/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUELFS <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi></label> GHIBELLINES. The
                    names Guelfo and Ghibellino, as applied to parties in Italy, are Italianized
                    forms of names which at an earlier period designated parties in Germany. Guelfo
                    is the Italian form of Welf, and Ghibellino the Italian form of Waiblingen, a
                    castle of the emperor Conrad. In Germany these names, which are said to have
                    been first used as battle-cries at the battle of Weinsberg in 1140, designated
                    the struggle between the Welfs of Altdorf and the imperial line of the
                    Hohenstaufen. In Italy the names acquired a different meaning, being generally
                    applied respectively to the party of the pope and the party of the emperor. The
                    conflict between the authority of the emperor and the independence of the
                    Italian towns began before the names were used in Germany. These parties first
                    came into prominence in the Lombard league of 1167. In the war which followed we
                    find the following distribution of parties: on the Ghibellin side were Cremona,
                    Pavia, Genoa, Tortona, Asti, Alba, Acqui, Turin, Ivrea, Ventimiglia, Savona,
                    Albenga, Imola, Faenza, Ravenna, Forli, Cesena, Rimini, the marquis of
                    Montferrat, the counts of Lomello, Guasto, Bosio, &lt;fcc.; on the side of the
                    Guelfs were Venice, Treviso, Padua, Vicenza, Verona, Brescia, Ferrara, Mantua,
                    Bergamo, Lodi, Milan, Novara, Vercelli, Alessandria, Piacenza, Parma, Reggio,
                    Modena, Bologna. These names spread further in consequence of the bitter rivalry
                    which existed between several pairs of Italian towns, for instance, between Rome
                    and Tusculum, Pisa and Genoa, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n258/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0911-0258-0245"/> Ferrara and Mantua, Bergamo and Brescia. A
                    further step in this direction was the division of the towns themselves into
                    Guelf and Ghibellin parties. The struggle for the imperial throne between Philip
                    of Swabia and Otto of Brunswick (1198-1208) enlisted the sympathies of Italy.
                    The Guelfic towns Milan, Piacenza, Brescia, Reggio, Modena, took the part of the
                    Welf Otto. The 13th century witnessed a great increase of the jealousies between
                    rival towns, and more serious divisions of the leading families in the towns
                    themselves. Examples of this were the quarrels between the Montecchi and
                    Capelletti at Verona, the Lambertazzi and Geremei at Bologna, the Rossi and
                    Coreggi at Parma, the Doria and Spinola, the Grimaldi and Fieschi at Genoa, the
                    Buondelmonti and Amedei, the Donati and Liberti at Florence, the Colonna and
                    Orsini at Rome, the Bagnacavalli and Polenta at Ravenna, the Delle Torre and
                    Visconti at Milan, the Cancellieri and Panciatichi at Pistoia, the Salimbeni and
                    Tolomei at Siena.</p>
                <p>Of the principal towns in North and Central Italy, Arezzo was generally
                    Ghibellin. Bergamo was torn in sunder by party quarrels: the Suardi fought
                    against the Coleoni, and afterwards both these against the Rivoli and Bonghi; it
                    was generally more Guelf than Ghibellin. Bologna was generally Guelf. Brescia
                    was much divided. It was generally Guelt, but was conquered by the Ghibellins in
                    1322. It came under the power of the Visconti of Milan in 1337. Cremona was
                    generally Guelf, but occasionally Ghibellin. Always unhappy, it was wasted by
                    the most violent party conflicts. The family of Cavalcabô led the Guelf party in
                    this town in the 14th century. Ferrara was Ghibellin under the Torelli; it
                    became Guelf under the Este. Florence, after 1158, was the chief support of the
                    Guelfs. The struggles which desolated it were between different branches of the
                    Guelf—the Bianchi, and Neri, and others. Forli was Guelf till 1315, afterwards
                    Ghibellin under the Ordelaffi. Genoa was divided between the two parties. Lucca
                    was generally Ghibellin, but had hard work to maintain its position against the
                    attacks of Florence. Mantua was Guelf up to 1220, afterwards mainly Ghibellin.
                    Padua was the enemy of Venice; in 1227 it was Guelf, fighting against the
                    Ghibellin Vicenza; about 1318 it became Ghibellin under the house of Carrara.
                    Parma was divided in its sympathies. It was generally more Guelf than Ghibellin.
                    Pavia was Ghibellin unless compelled to be otherwise. Perugia became Guelf in
                    1198. It was much torn by party quarrels. Piacenza was generally Guelf. Pisa was
                    chiefly Ghibellin during a great part of its history. Pistoia was divided up to
                    1267, after which time it became mainly Guelf. Ravenna was chiefly Guelf under
                    the family of Polenta. Rimini belonged to the family of Malatesta, which was
                    divided between Guelf and Ghibellin. Siena was at first Ghibellin; in 1270 it
                    became Guelf. Venice was scarcely touched by these party quarrels. Verona was
                    much divided. Up to 1259 it was mainly Guelf; under the Della Scala it was
                    Ghibellin. Vicenza was Ghibellin after 1227; at a later period it followed the
                    fortunes of Padua. Viterbo was Ghibellin after 1328.</p>
                <p>It would be generally true to assert the principle that the Guelfs were more
                    attached to liberty than the Ghibellins. The town of Alessandria was the
                    creation of the Lombard league, a protest against the reduction of Italy under a
                    German sovereign. Yet Dante, the keenest patriot, the most ardent aspirant
                    towards the unity of Italy, was a Ghibellin. With him Ghibellinism meant (I)
                    unity under a strong head, and (2) the abolition of the temporal power of the
                    popes. No one, he thought, but an emperor could sit firmly in the saddle or
                    guide the reins of so fierce a steed. The best hope of obtaining this object lay
                    in Henry VII. of Luxembourg. But the object itself was probably impossible of
                    realization. The death of Henry at Buonconvento extinguished the last hope of
                    uniting Italy under the supremacy of Caesar.</p>
                <p>To give a full account of the party quarrels of Guelf and Ghibellin would be to
                    write the history of mediaeval Italy. The names began to die out gradually at
                    the beginning of the 15th century. Twenty years before the two parties had
                    united in opposing John of Bohemia. The expedition of Charles ΓV. into Italy
                    destroyed what shreds still remained of respect for the authority of the empire,
                    and with the extinction of Ghibellinism Guelfism perished also; yet we find the
                    name of Guelf appearing in Milan in 1404, after the death of Gian Galeazzo
                    Visconti, and also in 1447, in the struggle between Ludovico Sforza and the
                    Duchess Bona of Savoy. In the conquest of Milan by Louis XII., in the beginning
                    of the 16 th century, we find the suitporters of the emperor and Sforza called
                    Ghibellins by Roman writers, and the French party called Guelf.</p>
                <p>Of the literary supporters of either cause we can only mention a few. Brunetto
                    Latini, the master of Dante, was a Guelf. Dante himself, as we have seen above,
                    was a Ghibellin; so was his friend Guido Cavalcanti. Petrarch was a Guelf; the
                    three historians Villaniare singularly impartial. For further information, see
                    Wachsmuth, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Politischen Parteiungen,</hi> vol.
                    ii. (ο. B. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
