<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0247-0236-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUARINI, Giovanni Battista</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 11, page 236</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:922595">Felting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:897468">Drama</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:922586">Felt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4nv99f02">Felt</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m89f">Rime</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n247/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUARINI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Giovanni Battista</hi></label>
                    (1537-1612), the author of the <hi rend="italic">Pastor Fido,</hi> was born at
                    Ferrara on the 10th of December 1537, just seven years before the birth of
                    Tasso. He was descended from Guarino of Verona (see next article). The young
                    Battista studied both at Pisa and Padua, whence he was called, when not yet
                    twenty, to profess moral philosophy in the schools of his native city. He
                    inherited considerable wealth, and was able early in life to marry Taddea de’
                    Bendedei, a lady of good birth. In 1567 he entered the service of Alpl-onso II.,
                    duke of Ferrara, thus beginning the court career which was destined to prove a
                    constant source of disappointment and annoyance to him. Though he cultivated
                    poetry for pastime, Guarini aimed at state employment as the serious business of
                    his life, and managed to be sent on various embassies and missions by his ducal
                    master. There was, however, at the end of the 16th century no opportunity for a
                    man of energy and intellectual ability to distinguish himself in the petty
                    sphere of Italian diplomacy. The time too had passed when the profession of a
                    courtier, painted in such glowing terms by Castiglione, could confer either
                    profit or honour. It is true that the court of Alphonso presented a brilliant
                    spectacle to Europe, with Tasso for titular poet, and an attractive circle of
                    accomplished ladies. But the last duke of Ferrara was an illiberal patron,
                    feeding his servants with promises, and ever ready to treat them with the
                    brutality that condemned the author of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gerusalemrne</hi><hi rend="italic">Liberata</hi> to a madhouse. Guarini spent
                    his time and money <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n248/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0248-0237"/> to little purpose, suffered from the spite and
                    ill-will of two successive secretaries,—Pigna and Montecatini,—quarrelled with
                    his old friend Tasso, and at the end of fourteen years of service found himself
                    half-ruined, with a large family and no prospects. When Tasso was condemned to
                    S. Anna, the duke promoted Guarini to the vacant post of court poet. There is an
                    interesting letter extant from the latter to his friend Cornelio Bentivoglio,
                    describing the efforts he made to fill this place appropriately. “I strove to
                    transform myself into another person, and, like a player, reassumel the
                    character, costume, and feelings of my youth. Advanced in manhood, I forced
                    myself to look young; I turned my natural melancholy into artificial gaiety,
                    affected loves I did not feel, exchanged wisdom for folly, and, in a word,
                    passed from a philosopher into a poet.” How ill-adapted lie felt himself to this
                    masquerade life may be gathered from the following sentence: “I am already in my
                    forty-fourth year, the father of eight children, two of whom are old enough to
                    be my censors, while my daughters are of an age to marry.” Abandoning so
                    uncongenial a strain upon his faculties, Guarini retired in 1582 to his
                    ancestral farm, the Vdla Guarina, in the lovely country that lies between the
                    Adige and Po, where he gave himself up to the cares of his family, the nursing
                    of his dilapidated fortunes, and the composition of the <hi rend="italic">Pastor
                    Fido.</hi> He was not happy in his domestic lot; for he had lost his wife young,
                    and quarrelled with his elder sons about the division of his estate. Litigation
                    seems to have been an inveterate vice with Guarini; nor was he ever free from
                    legal troubles. After studying his biography, the conclusion is forced upon our
                    minds that he was originally a man of robust and virile intellect, ambitious of
                    greatness, confident in his own powers, and well qualified for serious affairs,
                    whose energies found no proper scope for their exercise. Literary work offered
                    but a poor sphere for such a character, while the enforced inactivity of court
                    life soured a naturally capricious and choleric temper. Of poetry he spoke with
                    a certain tone of condescension, professing to practise it only in his leisure
                    moments; nor are his miscellaneous verses of a quality to secure for their
                    author a very lasting reputation. It is therefore not a little remarkable that
                    the fruit of his retirement—a disappointed courtier past the prime of early
                    manhood—should have been a dramatic masterpiece worthy to be ranked with the
                    classics of Italian literature. Deferring a further account of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Pastor Fido</hi> for the present, the remaining incidents of
                    Guarini’s restless life maybe briefly told. In 1585 he was at Turin
                    superintending the first public performance of his drama, whence Alphonso
                    recalled him to Ferrara, and gave him the office of secretary of state. This
                    reconciliation between the poet and his patron did not last long. Guarini moved
                    to Florence, then to Rome, and back again to Florence, where he established
                    himself as the courtier of Ferdinand de’ Medici. A dishonourable marriage,
                    pressed upon his son Guarino by the grand-duke, roused the natural resentment of
                    Guarini, always scrupulous upon the point of honour. He abandoned the Medicean
                    court, and took refuge with Francesco Maria of Urbino, the last scion of the
                    Montefeltro-della-Rovere house. Yet he found no satisfaction at Urbino. “The old
                    court is a dead institution,” he writes to a friend; “one may see a shadow of
                    it, but not the substance in Italy of to-day. Ours is an age of appearances, and
                    one goes a-masquerading all the year.” This was true enough. Those dwindling
                    deadly-lively little residence towns of Italian ducal families, whose day of
                    glory was over, and who were waiting to be slowly absorbed by the capacious
                    appetite of Austria, were no fit places for a man of energy and independence.
                    Guarini finally took refuge in his native Ferrara, which, since the death of
                    Alphonso, had now devolved to the papal see. Here, and at the Villa Guarina, his
                    last years were passed in study, lawsuits, and polemical disputes with his
                    contemporary critics, until 1612, when he died at Venice in his seventyfifth
                    year.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Pastor Fido</hi> is a pastoral drama composed not without
                    reminiscences of Tasso’s <hi rend="italic">Aminta.</hi> The scene is laid in
                    Arcadia, where Guarini supposes it to have been the custom to sacrifice a maiden
                    yearly to Diana. But an oracle has declared that when two scions of divine
                    lineage are united in marriage, and a faithful shepherd has atoned for the
                    ancient error of a faithless woman, this inhuman rite shall cease. The plot
                    turns upon the unexpected fulfilment of this prophecy, contrary to all the
                    schemes which had been devised for bringing it to accomplishment, and in despite
                    of apparent improbabilities of divers kinds. It is extremely elaborate, and,
                    regarded as a piece of cunning mechanism, leaves nothing to be desired. Each
                    motive I1a3 been carefully prepared, each situation amply developed. Yet,
                    considered as a play, the <hi rend="italic">Pastor Fido</hi> disappoints a
                    reader trained in the school of Sophocles or Shakespeare. The action itself
                    seems to take place off the stage, and only the results of action, stationary
                    tableaux representing the movement of the drama, are put before us in the
                    scenes. The art is lyrical, not merely in form but in spirit, and in adaptation
                    to the requirements of music which demands stationary expressions of emotion for
                    development. The characters have been well considered, and are exhibited with
                    great truth and vividness; the cold and eager hunter Silvio contrasting with the
                    tender and romantic Mirtillo, and Corisca’s meretricious arts enhancing the pure
                    affection of Amarilli. Dorinda presents another type of love so impulsive that
                    it prevails over a maiden’s sense of shame, while the courtier Carino brings the
                    corruption of towns into comparison with the innocence of the country. In Carino
                    the poet painted his own experience, and here his satire upon the court of
                    Ferrara is none the less biting because it is gravely measured. In Corisca he
                    delineated a woman vitiated by the same town life, and a very hideous portrait
                    has he drawn. Though a satirical element was thus introduced into the <hi
                    rend="italic">Pastor Fido</hi> in order to relieve its ideal picture of Arcadia,
                    the whole play is but a study of contemporary feeling in Italian society. There
                    is no true rusticity whatever in the drama. This correspondence with the spirit
                    of the age secured its success during Guarini’s lifetime; this made it so
                    dangerously seductive that Cardinal Bellarmine told the poet he had done more
                    harm to Christendom by his blandishments than Luther by his heresy. Without
                    anywhere transgressing the limits of decorum, the <hi rend="italic">Pastor
                    Fido</hi> is steeped in sensuousness; and the immodesty of its pictures is
                    enhanced by rhetorical concealments more provocative than nudity. Moreover, the
                    love described is effeminate and wanton, felt less as passion than as lust
                    enveloped in a veil of sentiment. We divine the coming age of <hi rend="italic"
                    >cicisbei</hi> and <hi rend="italic">castrati.</hi> Of Guarini’s style it would
                    be difficult to speak in teτms of too high praise. The thought and experience of
                    a lifetime have been condensed in these five acts, and have found expression in
                    language brilliant, classical, chiselled to perfection. Here and there the taste
                    of the 17th century makes itself felt in frigid conceits and forced antitheses;
                    nor does Guarini abstain from sententious maxims which reveal the moralist
                    rather than the poet. Yet these are but minor blemishes in a masterpiece of
                    diction, glittering and faultless like a polished bas-relief of hard Corinthian
                    bronze. That a single pastoral should occupy so prominent a place in the history
                    of literature seems astonishing, until we reflect that Italy, upon the close of
                    the 16th century, expressed itself in the <hi rend="italic">Pastor Fido,</hi>
                    and that the influence of this drama was felt through all the art of Europe till
                    the epoch of the Revolution. It is not a mere play. The sensual refinement
                    proper to an age of social decadence found in it the most exact embodiment, and
                    made it the code of gallantry for the next two centuries.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n249/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0249-0238"/>
                <p>The best edition of the <hi rend="italic">Pastor Fido</hi> is that of Venice
                    (Ciotti), 1602. The most convenient is that of Barbéra, Florence, 1866. For
                    Guarini’s miscellaneous <hi rend="italic">Rime,</hi> the Ferrara edition, in 4
                    vols., 1737, may be consulted. His polemical writings, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Verato</hi><hi rend="italic">Primo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Secondo,</hi> and
                    his prose comedy called <hi rend="italic">Idropica,</hi> were published at
                    Venice, Florence, and Rome, between 1588 and 1614. (J. A. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
