<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0708-1767-0664-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ELEUSINIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 8, page 664</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942527">Gibbons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:827603">Barley</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1152736">Torches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:946112">Graining</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:945891">Grain</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47659j0m">Descent</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p69w">Barley</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vd7z">Graining</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tp2r">Grain</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193331767" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ELEUSINIA</label>, in Grecian antiquity, a festival observed
                    in honour of Ceres, by some states every fourth, hut by others every fifth year.
                    The Athenians celebrated it at Eleusis, a town of Attica; and hence arose the
                    name.</p>
                <p>Ceres, saysIsoerates, wandering in quest ofher daughter Proserpine, arrived in
                    Attica, where some good officeswere rendered her, which it is unlawful for those
                    who are not initiated to hear. In return she conferred two unparalleled
                    benefits, namely, the knowledge of agriculture, by which the human race is
                    raised above the brute creation; and the mysteries, from which the partakers
                    derive sweeter hopes than other men enjoy, both as to the present life and a
                    future state of existence. It was the popular opinion that the Eleusinian
                    goddesses suggested prudent counsel to their votaries, and influenced their
                    conduct; and that the latter were respected in the infernal regions, and had
                    precedence in the assemblies of the blessed, whilst the unhallowed were left in
                    utter darkness, wallowing in mire, or labouring to fill a leaky vessel. The
                    Athenians were solicitous to secure these advantages to their children, by
                    having them initiated as soon as possible in the Eleusinian mysteries.</p>
                <p>Ceres was supposed to be particularly partial to Eleusis and its vicinity. There
                    were the memorials ofher presence and ofher bounty; the well named <hi
                    rend="italic">Callichorus,</hi> by which she had rested, in the reign of
                    Ereetheus; the stone on which she sat, named the <hi rend="italic"
                    >sorrowful</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the Rharian plain, where barley was
                    first sown; and the thrashing floor and altar of Triptolemus, a herdsman whom
                    she instructed in the culture of that grain, the use of which succeeded to
                    aeorns. Her mysteries continued to possess a pre-cmi-nence in holiness, and to
                    be accounted as much superior to all other religious festivals as the gods were
                    to the deified heroes. Even the garments worn at the solemnity were supposed to
                    partake ôf the efficacy of the mysteries, and to be possessed of signal virtues.
                    It was customary to retain them until they began to decay, and then to dedicate
                    them in the temple, or to use them as swaddling clothes.</p>
                <p>The mystic temple, as it was called, provided by Pericles for the solemnity,
                    created by its sanetity an awe only equalled by the astonishment which its
                    beauty and magnitude excited in every beholder. The profane or uninitiated were
                    forbidden to enter it upon any pretence. Two young Aearnanians happening
                    inadvertently to mix with the crowd at the season of the mysteries, and to go
                    in, were discovered and put to death. The chief priest, hierophant, or
                    mystagogue, was taken from the Eumolpidae, a holy family which flourished at
                    Athens, and derived its descent from Eumolpus, a shepherd and favourite of
                    Ceres. He was enjoined to observe celibacy, and he wore a stole or long garment,
                    and in his hair a wreath of myrtle. The grand requisites in his character were
                    strength and melody of voice, solemnity of deportment, magnificence, and strict
                    decorum. Under him, besides many of inferior station, was the daduchus or
                    torch-bearer, who likewise wore his hair with a fillet; the priest, who
                    officiated at the altar; and the hieroeeryx, or sacred herald; all very
                    important personages. The latter was of a <pb break="no" facs="nls:193331780"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0708-1780-0665"/>family which claimed the god Mercury, and
                    Aglauros, the ∣ daughter of Cecrops, for its ancestors.</p>
                <p>The secrecy in which the mysteries were enveloped 1 served to enhance the idea of
                    their consequence, and to increase the desire of participation. It was so strict
                    that ∣ no person was allowed even to name the hierophant by whom he had been
                    initiated; whilst public abhorrence and detestation awaited the babbler, and the
                    law decreed that he should die the death.</p>
                <p>The Athenians suffered none to be initiated into these mysteries excepting such
                    as were members of their city. This regulation, which compelled Hercules,
                    Castor, and Pollux, to become citizens of Athens, was strictly observed in the
                    first ages of the institution; but after a time all persons, barbarians
                    excepted, were freely admitted.</p>
                <p>The festivals were divided into greater and lesser mysteries. The institution of
                    the latter arose out of the following circumstance. Hercules having passed near
                    Eleusis while the Athenians were celebrating the mysteries, desired to be
                    initiated. As this request could not be complied with, he being a stranger, and
                    as Eumolpus was unwilling to displease him on account of his great power, and
                    the services which he had rendered to the Athenians, another festival was
                    instituted without violating the laws; it was denominated <hi rend="italic"
                    >μmoa,</hi> and Hercules was solemnly admitted to the celebration, and
                    initiated. These lesser mysteries were observed at Agrae, near the Ilissus. The
                    greater were celebrated at Eleusis, from which place Ceres has been called <hi
                    rend="italic">Eleusinia.</hi> In later times the lesser festivals were
                    preparatory to the greater, and no person could be initiated at Eleusis without
                    a previous purification at z∖grae. This purification they performed by keeping
                    themselves pure, chaste, and unpolluted during nine days; after which they came
                    and offered sacrifices and prayers, wearing garlands of flowers called <hi
                    rend="italic">iμt^α,</hi> and having under their feet Δ/o¢ κωδ/ον, <hi
                    rend="italic">Jupiter’s shin,</hi> which was the skin of a victim offered to
                    that god. The person who assisted was called <hi rend="italic">υδgavoς,</hi>
                    from υδωg, <hi rend="italic">water,</hi> which was used at the purification; and
                    those purified were called <hi rend="italic">μυδτaι, the initiated.</hi> A year
                    after the initiation into the lesser mysteries they sacrificed a sow to Ceres,
                    and Avere admitted into the greater, and the secrets of the festivals were
                    solemnly revealed to them.</p>
                <p>This festival was observed in the month Boedromion or September, and continued
                    nine days, from the 15th till the 23d. During that time it was unlawful to
                    arrest any man, or present any petition, on pain of forfeiting a thousand
                    drachmas, or, according to others, on pain of death. It was also unlawful for
                    those who were initiated to sit upon the cover of a well, and to eat beans,
                    mullets, or weazels. If any woman rode to Elcusis in a chariot she was obliged
                    by an edict of Lycurgus to pay six thousand drachmas. The design of this law was
                    to destroy all distinction between the richer and poorer citizens. When the
                    season approached, the mystae, or persons who had been initiated only in the
                    lesser mysteries, repaired to Eleusis to be instructed in the ceremonial. The
                    service for the opening of the temple, with morning sacrifice, was performed,
                    and the ritual was then produced from the sanctuary. It was enveloped in
                    symbolical figures of animals, which suggested words compendiously, in letters
                    with ligatures, the tops being buddled together, or disposed circularly like a
                    wheel, and the whole utterly inexplicable to the profane. The case, which was
                    called <hi rend="italic">pe-troma,</hi> consisted of two stones exactly fitted;
                    and the mysterious record, after being read, was closed up and replaced until a
                    future festival. The principal rite was nocturnal, and confined to the temple
                    and its environs. The mystae waited without with impatience and apprehension.
                    Lamentations and strange sounds were heard. Thunder pealed above these noises,
                    and flashes of light and fire irradiated the gloom, rendering the darkness which
                    followed more awful and sublime. The candidates for initiation were beaten by
                    some invisible hand, whilst frightful apparitions, and monsters of a canine
                    form, were presented to them, which filled them with apprehension and terror,
                    and paralysed their energies. The scene then suddenly changed to one of a
                    brilliant and agreeable character. The propylaea or vestibules of the temple
                    were opened, the curtains withdrawn, and the hidden things displayed. They were
                    introduced by the hierophant and daduchus, the former of whom revealed to them
                    the mysteries. The splendour of illumination, the glory of the temple and of the
                    images, and the singing and dancing which accompanied the exhibition, all
                    contributed to soothe the mind after its recent agitation, and to render the
                    wondering devotee tranquil and satisfied. After this inspection, or. as it was
                    called, the <hi rend="italic">autopsia,</hi> they retired, and others advanced.
                    The succeeding days were employed in purification, in sacrifice, in pompous
                    processions, and in spectacles, at which they assisted, wearing myrtle crowns.
                    The second day was called αλαδs <hi rend="italic">μυδτaι, to the sea, ye
                    initiated</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> because they were commanded to purify
                    themselves by ablution in the sea. On the third.day sacrifices were offered, as
                    also a mullet, and barley from a field of Eleusis. These oblations were called
                    Šua, and were held so sacred that the priests themselves dared not, as in other
                    sacrifices, partake of them. On the fourth day they made a solemn procession, in
                    which the zαλαMov, or <hi rend="italic">holy basket of Ceres,</hi> was paraded
                    in a consecrated cart, while on every ţside the people shouted ∆ij∕znrεi, <hi
                    rend="italic">Hail, Ceres.</hi> After these followed women, called <hi
                    rend="italic">xιδτο&lt;ροξοι,</hi> who <hi rend="italic">carried baskets,</hi>
                    in which was sesamin, carded wool, grains of salt, a serpent, pomegranates,
                    reeds, ivy boughs, and so on. The fifth was called ⅛ <hi rend="italic"
                    >τωv</hi><hi rend="italic">λαμπάδων</hi><hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∣</hi><hi rend="italic">μεξα, the torch day,</hi> because on the
                    following night the people ran about with torches in their hands. It was usual
                    to dedicate torches to Ceres, and contend who should offer the largest, in
                    commemoration of the travels of the goddess, and of her lighting a torch in the
                    flames of Mount Aetna. The sixth day was called Ιακχος, from Iacchus, the son of
                    Jupiter and Ceres, who accompanied his mother in her search after Proserpine,
                    with a torch in his hand. From this circumstance the hand of his statue was
                    furnished with a torch, and carried in solemn procession from the Ccramicus to
                    Eleusis. The statue, with those who accompanied it, called Iα%χα- <hi
                    rend="italic">γωγov,</hi> was crowned with myrtle. In the way nothing was heard
                    but singing and the noise of brazen kettles as the votaries danced along. The
                    way through which they issued from the city was called <hi rend="italic">iιeα
                    oooς,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">the sacred way</hi> the resting place ∕sga <hi
                    rend="italic">δ</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">rxr</hi><hi
                    rend="italic                     subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> from
                    a <hi rend="italic">jig-tree</hi> which grew ir the neighbourhood. They also
                    stopped on a bridge over the Cephisus, where they derided those who passed by
                    After they had crossed this bridge, they entered Eleusis by a place called <hi
                    rend="italic">μυδτMr</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">sιδoδoς,</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">the mystical entrance</hi> The seventh day was devoted to
                    sports, in which the victors were rewarded with a measure of barley, that grain
                    having been first sown in Eleusis. The eighth day was called Eff∕δαu^∕ωv ⅛wga,
                    because Aesculapius on his returr from Epidaurus to Athens was initiated by the
                    repetition of the lesser mysteries. It became customary therefore to celebrate
                    them a second time upon this occasion, ir order that those who had not hitherto
                    obtained the privilege might be lawfully initiated. The ninth and 1as1 day of
                    the festival was called <hi rend="italic">πλημο-χοαι,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >earthen vessels</hi> because it was customary to fill two such vessels wit!
                    wine, one placed towards the east, and the other towards the west; which, after
                    the repetition of some mystica, words, were both thrown down, and the wine spilt
                    on the ground was offered as a libation.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193331793" xml:id="kp-eb0708-1793-0666"/>
                <p>The story of Ceres and Proserpine, the foundation of the Eleusinian mysteries,
                    was both verbally narrated and represented in allegorical show. Proserpine was
                    gathering flowers when she was stolen by Pluto; and hence the procession of the
                    holy basket, which was placed on a car dragged along by oxen and followed by a
                    train of females, some carrying the mystic chests, shouting <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hail, Ceres.</hi> At night a procession was made with lighted torches, in order
                    to commemorate the goddess searching for her daughter. A measure of barley, the
                    grain which, it was believed, she had bestowed, was the reward of the victors in
                    the gym-nic exercises; and the proceedings at the temple had a reference to the
                    legend. A knowledge of these things, from which the profane were excluded,
                    formed the amount of what was communicated to the initiated; and the mode in
                    which it was performed was skilfully adapted to the reigning superstitions. The
                    operation was forcible, and the effect in proportion. The priesthood flourished
                    as piety increased; and although the dispensation was corrupt, its tendency was
                    not malignant. It produced sanctity of manners, an attention to the social
                    duties, and a desire to be distinguished for what was then deemed virtue. (See
                    <hi rend="italic">Divine Legation of Moses demonstrated</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> Gibbon, in his <hi rend="italic">Miscellaneous Works,</hi> on Virgil’s
                    account of Aeneas’s Descent into the Shades; and Heyne’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Excursus,</hi> in reference to the same subject.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
