<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0708-1832-0669-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ELIS, or Elea</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 8, page 669</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193331832" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ELIS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Elea</hi></label>, a province
                    in the north-west of the Peloponnesus, which was comprehended in its greatest
                    extent between the promontory Araxus, where it touched on Achaia, and the river
                    Neda, which separated it from Messenia. In the interior it was separated from
                    Arcadia by the ridges of Mount Phołoë, and farther south by a continuation of
                    the mountains from Arcadia.</p>
                <p>In earlier times this tract of country was divided into three distinct
                    principalities independent of each other. The most northern was surrounded by
                    the lofty mountain Pholoë, which, sending out two ridges towards the coast, the
                    one towards the promontory Araxus, the other towards the promontory Chelnatas,
                    inclosed a large extent of champaign country, called from this circumstance the
                    Hollow Elis (⅛ xo∕λ&gt;; Hλ∕ς). The second principality was named Pisatis, and
                    through its territories flowed the river Alpheus; whilst the district to the
                    south was called Triphylia.</p>
                <p>Elis was by far the most fertile and populous district of the Peloponnesus,
                    chiefly because its extensive plains enjoyed an almost uninterrupted state of
                    peace. Towards the coast the soil becomes sandy; a broad belt of sand stretches
                    along the sea nearly as tar as the Triphylian Pylos, so often called by Homer
                    “the sandy.” This tract of country is but little raised above the level of the
                    sea, and from that reason a number of small lakes or lagoons have been formed,
                    which extend along the greater part of the coast. It was the only district in
                    Greece which produced flax; but this, though equal in fineness, was far inferior
                    in colour, to that of Palestine. Another extraordinary circumstance<pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193331845" xml:id="kp-eb0708-1845-0670"/> was, that no
                    mules could be here engendered, though they abounded in the adjacent
                    district.</p>
                <p>At a very early period we find it under the government of Endymion, and called
                    the kingdom of the Epci. Homer was acquainted with the divine Elis, where the
                    Epei ruled. His son Aetolus having accidentally committed a murder, was obliged
                    to fly, and proceeded to found a kingdom on the opposite coast, called from him
                    Aetolia. He was succeeded by Eleus, the grandson of Endymion, who gave name to
                    the country, and after him came Augeas, who was put to death by Hercules because
                    he refused him the reward he had promised for clearing out his stables. We now
                    lose sight of Elis till the irruption of the Heraclidae into Greece, eighty
                    years after the destruction of Troy, when Oxylus, a descendant of Aetolus,
                    offered to become their guide, on condition of receiving the province of Elis,
                    which he considered as the inheritance of bis family. A numerous body of
                    Aetolians attended him, and uniting cordially with the native inhabitants of
                    Elis, they conquered a great part of Pisatis, and took possession of Olympia
                    about 1190 before Christ. Then it was that the Olympic games were first
                    established on the banks of the river Alpheus, though they were not regularly
                    celebrated till the year 776 before Christ, when Coroebus obtained the prize of
                    victory. In the wars between Messenia and Sparta, they were faithful allies of
                    the latter; and with their assistance they took possession of the whole country
                    belonging to the Caucones and Minyae, to which the name of Triphylia was then
                    given. During the Peloponnesian war, we still find them staunch supporters of
                    Spartan politics; and they continued so till the conclusion of the treaty after
                    the battle of Amphipolis, when the countenance afforded by the Spartans to the
                    independent movements of the people of Lepreum produced a rupture between the
                    two nations. Elis endeavoured to take vengeance on the Spartans, by excluding
                    them from all participation in the Olympic games; but the marauding invasions of
                    the Spartans were soon so severely felt, that the inhabitants of Elis were glad
                    to sue for peace, and to renew their ancient alliance with Sparta. In the year
                    365 before Christ, a few years after the battle of Leuctra, they were engaged in
                    war with the Arcadians, and were so unsuccessful that they were compelled to
                    cede the greater portion of their southern possessions. During the Social War,
                    the Eleans were staunch allies of the Aetolians, and no reverses could detach
                    them from the cause which they had joined, or induce them to unite with the
                    Achaean League. These seem to have been the last events in which the Eleans took
                    part as an independent people; and we find them finally included in the general
                    decree which annexed the whole of Greece to the Roman empire.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Elis,</hi> the chief city of the district of Elis, in the
                    Peloponnesus, situated on the banks of the river Peneus, 120 stadia from the
                    sea, and first formed into a district corporation by the union of several
                    detached villages after the Persian war, about 490 years before Christ. The
                    people of this portion of Greece had for ages been devoted to the pleasures of a
                    country life, and they had been able to indulge this natural desire by the
                    sacred character which had been long attached to their territory. At the time
                    when Oxylus got possession of this fertile province, and became master of the
                    temple of Olympia, he had such influence with the Heraclidae as to obtain from
                    them the sanction of an oath that this district should be considered as under
                    the immediate protection of the god whose festival was there solemnized. This
                    seems to have been so strictly attended to that those who founded the city did
                    not think it necessary to surround it with walls, or to take any steps to ward
                    off the attack of an enemy. In the unsettled times which followed the death of
                    Alexander, Elis was occupied, and probably fortified, by Telesphorus, who
                    commanded the fleet of Antigonus. (Diodor. xix. 87; Strab. viii. 357; Xen. Hall.
                    iii. 2, 20.) It appears, in the time of Pausanias, to have still retained much
                    of its former beauty and magnificence, if we may be allowed to judge from the
                    account he has left us of the public buildings. “Its ruins,” says he, “are found
                    now at a spot called <hi rend="italic">Paleopoli,</hi> consisting of several
                    masses of Roman tile and mortar, with many wrought blocks of stone and fragments
                    of sculpture scattered over a space of two or three miles in circumference. The
                    most remarkable of the ruins is that of a square building of about twenty feet
                    on the outside, which is in the form of an octagon with niches. Like most of the
                    other remains, it is built of alternate strata of Roman tile and stone rubble.”
                    (Leake’s <hi rend="italic">j</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >[orea,</hi> vol. i. p. 6.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
