<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0708-2144-0693-11" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ENAMELLING</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 8, page 693</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:925173">Fire</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:878331">Copper</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j1r">Copper</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193332144" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ENAMELLING</label>, the art of laying enamel upon metals, as
                    gold, silver, or copper, and of melting it on the fire, or of making divers
                    curious works in it by means of a lamp. It signifies also to paint in
                    enamel.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The method of painting in</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">
                    Εnαmεl.</hi> This is performed on plates of gold or silver, and most commonly of
                    copper, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193332157" xml:id="kp-eb0708-2157-0694"
                    />enamelled with the white enamel, on which painting is executed with colours
                    which are melted in the fire, where they take a brightness and lustre like that
                    of glass. This painting is the most prized of all for its peculiar brightness
                    and vivacity, which is permanent, the force of its colours not being liable to
                    be effaced or sullied with time, as in other painting, and continuing always as
                    fresh as when it came out of the workmen’s hands. This method of painting is
                    usual in miniature; but it is the more difficult the larger it is, by reason of
                    certain accidents to which it is liable in the operation. Enamelling should only
                    be practised on plates of gold, the other metals being less pure; copper, for
                    instance, scales with the application, and yields fumes, and silver turns the
                    yellow white. Nor must the plate be made flat; for in such case the enamel
                    cracks; to avoid which accident the plates are usually forged a little round or
                    oval, and not too thick. The plate being well and evenly forged, the operation
                    is usually commenced by laying on a couch of white enamel (as we observed above)
                    on both sides, which prevents the metal from swelling and blistering; and this
                    first layer serves for the ground of all the other colours. The plate being thus
                    prepared, the next step is to draw out exactly the subject to be painted with
                    red vitriol, mixed with oil of spike, marking all parts of the design very
                    lightly with a small pencil. After this, the colours (which must be previously
                    ground with water in a mortar of agate extremely fine, and mixed with oil of
                    spike somewhat thick) are to be laid on, observing the mixtures and colours
                    which agree to the different parts of the subject; for which purpose it is
                    necessary to understand painting in miniature. But here the workmen must be very
                    cautious as to the quality of the oil of spike he employs to mix his colours
                    with, for it is very subject to adulteration.</p>
                <p>Great care must likewise be taken that the least dust imaginable mix not with the
                    colours while the artist is either painting or grinding them; for the smallest
                    speck worked up with the colour, when the work comes to be put into the
                    reverberatory to be made red hot, will leave a hole, and so deface the
                    performance.</p>
                <p>When the colours are all laid, the painting must be gently dried over a slow fire
                    to evaporate the oil, and the colours afterwards melted to incorporate them with
                    the enamel, making the plate red hot in a fire like that which the enamellers
                    use. Afterwards that part of the painting must be gone over again which the fire
                    has in any degree effaced, <sic>strenghening</sic> the shade and colours, and
                    committing it a second time to the fire, observing the same method as before,
                    which is to be repeated till the work be finished.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Method of</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Enamelling</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">by the lamp.</hi> Most enamelled works are wrought at the fire of
                    a lamp, in which, instead of oil, is put melted horse-grease, which they called
                    <hi rend="italic">caballine oil.</hi> The lamp, which is of copper, or white
                    iron, consists of two pieces; in one of which is a kind of oval plate, six
                    inches long and two inches high, in which are put the oil and the cotton; whilst
                    the other part, called the <hi rend="italic">box,</hi> in which the lamp is
                    inclosed, serves only to receive the oil which boils over by the force of the
                    fire. This lamp, or, where several artists work together, two or more lamps, are
                    placed on a table of proper height, under which, about the middle of its height,
                    is a double pair of organ-bellows, which one of the workmen moves up and down
                    with his foot to quicken the flame of the lamps, which by this means is excited
                    to an incredible degree of vehemence. Grooves made with a gauge in the upper
                    part of the table, and covered with parchment, convey the wind of the bellows to
                    a pipe of glass before each lamp; and in order that the enamellers may not be
                    incommoded with the heat of the lamp, every pipe is covered at six inches
                    instance with a little tin plate, fixed into the table by a wooden .handle. When
                    the works do not require a long blast, the workmen only use a glass pipe, into
                    which they blow with their mouth.</p>
                <p>It is incredible to what a degree of fineness and delicacy the threads of enamel
                    may be drawn at the lamp. Those which are used in making false tufts of feathers
                    are so fine that they may be wound on a reel like silk or thread. The fictitious
                    jets of all colours used in embroideries are also made of enamel, and that with
                    so much art, that every small piece has its hole to pass the thread through with
                    which it is sewed. These holes are made by blowing them into long pieces, which
                    are afterwards cut with a proper tool.</p>
                <p>It is seldom that the Venetian or Dutch enamels are used alone; they are commonly
                    melted in an iron ladle, with an equal part of glass or crystal; and when the
                    two matters are in perfect fusion, the mass is drawn out into threads of
                    different sizes, according to the nature of the work. The workmen take it out of
                    the ladle while liquid with two pieces of broken tobacco-pipes, which they
                    extend from each other at arm’s length. If the thread is required still longer,
                    then another workman holds one end, and continues to draw it out, while the
                    first holds the enamel to the flame. Those threads, when cold, are cut into
                    whatever lengths the workman thinks fit, but commonly from ten to twelve inches;
                    and as they are all round, if they are required to be flat, they must, while
                    hot, be drawn through a pair of pincers. They have also another iron instrument
                    in the form of pincers for drawing out the enamel by the lamp when it is to be
                    worked and disposed in figures. Lastly, they have glass tubes of various sizes,
                    which serve to blow the enamel into various figures, and preserve the necessary
                    vacancies therein, as also to spare the stuff, and form the contours. When the
                    enameller is at work, he sits before the lamp with his foot on the step which
                    moves the bellows; and holding in his left hand the work to be enamelled, or the
                    brass or iron wires on which the figures are to be formed, he directs with his
                    right the enamel thread, which he holds to the flame with a management and
                    patience equally surprising. There are few things which cannot be made or
                    represented with enamel; and some figures are as well finished as if done by the
                    most skilful carvers.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
