<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0708-1845-0670-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ELIZABETH</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 8, page 670</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4br3k">Ambassadors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bt4s">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43r0ps53">Mirrors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kn24">Glass</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193331845" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ELIZABETH</label>, queen of England, daughter of Henry VIII.
                    and Anne Boleyn, was born at Greenwich, on the 7th of September 1533. According
                    to the custom of the times, she was early instructed in the learned languages,
                    first by Grindal, who died when she was about seventeen, and afterwards by the
                    celebrated Roger Aschara. She likewise acquired considerable knowledge of the
                    Italian, Spanish, and French languages. Dr Grindal was also her preceptor in
                    divinity, which she is said to have studied with uncommon application and
                    industry. That Elizabeth became a Protestant and her sister Mary a Catholic, was
                    the effect of that cause which determines the religion of the greater part of
                    mankind, namely, the opinion of those by whom they were educated; and this
                    difference of opinion in their tutors is not at all surprising, when we
                    recollect that their father Harry was of both religions, or of neither.</p>
                <p>But the studies of Elizabeth were not confined merely to languages and theology;
                    she was also instructed in the political history of the ancients; and was so
                    well skilled in music as to sing and play “artfully and sweetly.”</p>
                <p>After the short reign of her brother Edward, her sister Mary succeeding to the
                    crown, Elizabeth experienced a considerable degree of persecution, so as to be
                    not a little apprehensive of a violent death. She was accused, imprisoned, and,
                    we are told, inhumanly treated. At last, by the intercession of King Philip of
                    Spain, she was set at liberty; which she continued to enjoy, till, on the death
                    of her sister, she, on the 17th of November 1558, ascended the throne of
                    England. Her history as a queen is detailed in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >England.</hi> The cares of government did not wholly suspend her pursuit of
                    learning. Ascham, in his <hi rend="italic">Schoolmaster,</hi> tell us that about
                    the year 1563, five years after her accession, she read more Greek in θ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ne</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:193331858"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0708-1858-0671"/>day than some prebendaries of that church did read
                    Latin in a whole week. That the Latin language was familiar to her, is evident
                    from her speech to the university of Oxford, when she was nearly sixty, and also
                    from her spirited answer to the Popish ambassador in the year 1598. And that she
                    was also skilled in the art of poetry, appears not only from the several scraps
                    which have been preserved, but likewise from the testimony of a contemporary
                    writer, Puttenham, in his <hi rend="italic">Art of English Poetry.</hi> These
                    are his words: “But last in recital and first indegree is the queen, whose
                    learned, delicate, noble muse, easily sur-mountcth all the rest, for sense,
                    sweetness, or subtility, be it in ode, elegy, epigram, or any other kind of
                    poem.” In this author are to be found only a specimen of sixteen verses of her
                    English poetry. “But,” says Mr Walpole, “a greater instance of her genius, and
                    that too in Latin; was her extempore reply to an insolent prohibition delivered
                    to her from Philip II. by his ambassador, in this te-trastic.</p>
                <p>Te veto ne pergas bello defendere Belgas:</p>
                <p>Quae Dracus cripuit, nunc restituantur oportet;</p>
                <p>Quas pater evertit, jubeo to condere cellas: Religio papae fac restituatur ad
                    unguem.</p>
                <p>She instantly answered him, with as much spirit as she used to return his
                    invasions,</p>
                <p>Ad Graecas, bone rex, fient mandata kalendas.”</p>
                <p>She died in her palace at Richmond, the 24th of March 1603, aged seventy, having
                    reigned forty-four years; and was interred in the chapel of Henry VII. in
                    Westminster Abbey. She was the author of the following works: 1. The Mirror, or
                    Glass of the Sinful Soul, which she translated from French verse into English
                    prose when she was eleven years old. The translation was dedicated to Queen
                    Catharine Parr. Probably it was never printed; but the dedication and preface
                    are preserved in the <hi rend="italic">Sylloge</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Epistolarum,</hi> in Hearne’s edition of <hi rend="italic">Livii</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Eoro-Juliensis,</hi> p. 161. 2. Prayers and Meditations, dedicated
                    to her father, and dated at Hatfield, 1545. Manuscript in the Royal Library. 3.
                    A Dialogue from Xenophon, between Hiero a king yet some time a private person,
                    and Simonides a poet, touching the life of the prince and the private man. This
                    was first printed from a manuscript in her majesty’s own handwriting, in the
                    Gentleman’s Magazine for 1743. 4. Two Orations of Isocrates, translated into
                    Latin. 5. Latin Oration at Cambridge, preserved in the king’s library; also in
                    Hollinshed’s Chronicle, and in Fuller’s History of Cambridge. 6. Latin Oration
                    at Oxford. 7. Comment on Plato. 8. Boethius <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Consolatione</hi><hi rend="italic">Pliiloscphiae,</hi> translated
                    into English anno 1593. 9. Sallust <hi rend="italic">DeJBelloJugur-thino,</hi>
                    translated into English anno 1590. 10. A Play of Euripides, translated into
                    Latin. 11. A Prayer for the use of her fleet in the great expedition in 1596.
                    12. Part of Horace’s Art of Poetry, translated into English anno 1598. 13.
                    Plutarch <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Curiositate,</hi> translated
                    into English. 14. Letters on various occasions to different persons. 15. Several
                    Speeches to her Parliament; and a number of other pieces. (See Wood’s <hi
                    rend="italic">History and Antiquities of Oxford</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and
                    Walpole’s <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Royal and Noble Authors.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
