<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-9491-0202-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NICERON, John Francis</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950030">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:803903">Aix</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn85">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194559491?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">NICERON, <hi rend="smallcaps">John
                        Francis</hi></label>, a French mathematician, was born at Paris in the year
                    1613. Having finished his academical studies, he entered into the order of the
                    Minims, and took the habit in 1632; and, as is usual, he changed the name given
                    him at his baptism for that of Francis, the name of his paternal uncle, who was
                    also a Minim, or Franciscan. His inclination and taste for the mathematics
                    ap∙</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:194559504?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0716-9504-0203"/>
                <p part="N">peared early during the course of his philosophical studies; and to that
                    science he devoted what time he could spare from his other employments, after he
                    had completed his studies in theology. All the branches of the mathematics,
                    however, did not equally engage his attention; he confined himself particularly
                    to optics, and only learned as much of the rest as was necessary for rendering
                    him perfect in this branch. He has himself informed us, in the preface to his
                        <hi rend="italic">Thaumaturgus Opticus,</hi> that he travelled twice to
                    Rome, and that, on his return home, he was appointed teacher of theology. He was
                    afterwards chosen to accompany Father Francis de la Noue, vicar-general of the
                    order, in his visitation of the convents throughout France. The eagerness of his
                    passion for study, however, induced him to make the best use of all the moments
                    he had to spare, and that wise economy of time furnished him with as much
                    leisure as satisfied his love of knowledge. Being taken sick at Aix, in
                    Provence, he died there on the 22d of September 1646, at the early age of
                    thirty-three. He was an intimate acquaintance of Descartes, who had a high
                    esteem for him. The principal works of Niceron arc, 1. L’Inter-pretatioh des
                    Chiffres, ou Règles pour bien entendre et expliquer facilement toutes sortes des
                    Chiffres simples, Paris, 1641, in 8vo; 2. La Perspective Curieuse, ou Magie
                    Artificielle des effets merveilleux de l’Optique, Catoptrique, et Dioptrique; 3.
                    Thaumaturgus Opticus, sive admiranda Optices, Catoptrices, et Dioptrices, pars
                    prima, 1646, in folio, a work to which the preceding essay was intended to serve
                    as an introduction.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Niceron,</hi><hi rend="italic">John Peter,</hi>
                    justly celebrated on account of his Biographical Memoirs, was born at Paris on
                    the 11th of March 1685. He was descended of an ancient and noble family, which
                    was in very high repute about 1540. He studied with success in the Mazarin
                    College at Paris, and afterwards at the college of Duplessis. Having resolved to
                    forsake the world, he consulted one of his uncles, who belonged to the order of
                    Barnabite Jesuits. This uncle examined him, and not doubting his election,
                    introduced him as a probationer to that society at Paris. He was received in
                    1702, took the habit in 1703, and made his vows in 1704, at the age of nineteen.
                    After he had professed himself, he wassent to Montargis, in order tostudy
                    philosophy and theology; and his superiors, being satisfied with his
                    proficiency, sent him to Loches, in Touraine, to teach the classics and
                    rhetoric. Here his devout behaviour and excellent conduct as a teacher made him
                    be thought worthy of the priesthood, which he received at Poitiers in 1708; and
                    as he had not arrived at the age to assume this order, a dispensation was
                    obtained in his favour. The college of Montargis having recalled him, he there
                    professed rhetoric for two years, and philosophy during four. Notwithstanding
                    all these avocations, he was humanely attentive to every call of charity, and to
                    the instruction of his fellowcreatures, many of whom heard his excellent
                    discourses, not only in the pulpits of the churches within the province, but
                    even in those of Paris. In 1716, his superiors invited him to the city, that he
                    might have an opportunity of prosecuting with more convenience those studies for
                    which he had always expressed the greatest inclination. He understood not only
                    the ancient, but also the modern languages; a circumstance of infinite advantage
                    in the composition of those works which he has given to the public, and which he
                    carried on with great assiduity till the time oí his death, which happened on
                    the 8th of July 1738, at the age of fifty-three. His works are, 1. Le Grand
                    Febrifuge, or, a Dissertation to prove that common water is the best remedy in
                    fevers, and even in the plague (translated from the English of John Hancock,
                    minister of St Margaret’s, London), in 12mo. This little treatise made its
                    appearance, amongst other pieces relating to this subject, in 1770, and was
                    attended with such success that it pass ed through three editions, the last of
                    which appeared in 1730, in two vols. 12mo. 2. The Voyages of John Ouv-ington to
                    Surat, and divers parts of Asia and Africa, containing the history of the
                    revolution in the kingdom of Golconda, and some observations upon silk worms,
                    Paris, 1725, in two vols. 12mo. 3. The Conversion of England to Christianity,
                    compared with its pretended Reformation, a work translated from the English,
                    Paris, 1729, in 8vo. 4. The Natural History of the Earth, translated from the
                    English of Mr Woodward, by Μ. Nogues, doctor in physic, with an answer to the
                    objections of Dr Camerarius, and containing also several letters written on the
                    same subject, with a methodical distribution of fossils, translated from the
                    English by Niceron, Paris, 1735, in 4to. 5. Memoirs of Men illustrious in the
                    Republic of Letters, with a critical account of their works, Paris, in 12mo. The
                    first volume of this great work appeared in 1727; and the others were given to
                    the public in succession, as far as the thirty-ninth, which appeared in 1738.
                    The fortieth volume was published after the death of the author, in 1739. Since
                    that period three others have been added; but in these there are many articles
                    of which Niceron was not the author. To a work of this kind many objections may
                    be made, according to the particular taste or views of each individual objector;
                    and, in fact, the French critics have expatiated with much severity upon the
                    mistakes unavoidable in an undertaking of such magnitude and difficulty. But it
                    is much more easy to censure than to execute. Since the time of Niceron the
                    French have produced no such collection as his, which, with all its faults, has
                    been the foundation, as far as it goes, of all the subsequent accounts given of
                    the same authors. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
