<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-0128-0251-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NORTHCOTE, James</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194560128?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">NORTHCOTE, <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi></label>,
                    a distinguished English painter, was born at Plymouth in the year 1746. He
                    evinced a predilection for the arts at a very early period, but received no
                    encouragement from his father, who was an eminent <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:194560141?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0716-0141-0252"/>watchmaker,
                    and apprenticed him to his own trade. When the period of his indenture had
                    expired, the strong bent of young Northcote’s genius prevailed; and being
                    fortunate enough to obtain a recommendation to Sir Joshua Reynolds, that eminent
                    artist received him as a pupil. Northcote had nearly reached his twenty-fifth
                    year when he arrived in London; and having had comparatively little experience
                    in painting previously to this period, his attainments were greatly inferior to
                    those of other beginners much younger than himself. It was therefore with no
                    great reliance on his talents that Sir Joshua gave him a trial; but diligence
                    and native genius soon made amends for all deficiencies, and, much to the
                    satisfaction of his master, with whom he became a favourite pupil, his
                    improvement was rapid. He was also of an age to be a pleasant companion to Sir
                    Joshua; and from his great natural talents, and extraordinary powers of
                    conversation, he was enabled to avail himself of all the advantages of that
                    polished society which assembled in the house of his master. Northcote remained
                    domesticated for five years, on the most agreeable terms, in Sir Joshua’s
                    family; and in 1776 he reluctantly quitted an abode which had in every way been
                    rendered delightful to him. He commenced portrait painter, in which he would
                    doubtless have attained great eminence; but his powerful intellect was scarcely
                    satisfied with this limited branch of art, and he resolved to prosecute the more
                    independent and pleasing, although much less lucrative, study of historical
                    painting. In furtherance of this object, he, in 1777, repaired to Italy, where
                    he remained three years, devoting his time alternately to the study of the great
                    masters, and to original compositions. During his sojourn on the Continent, he
                    was elected a member of the Imperial Academy at Florence, of the ancient
                    Etruscan Academy at Cortona, and of the Accademia delle Arti at Rome. He was
                    also requested to execute a portrait of himself, to be placed amongst those of
                    distinguished artists which grace the gallery at Florence; and the picture which
                    he presented is at once a faithful resemblance and an exquisite specimen of his
                    professional skill.</p>
                <p part="N">On his return to England, Northcote pursued the study of design with all
                    the ardour of an artist; and it was soon apparent that he had not mistaken his
                    forte or miscalculated his powers. About this period Mr Boydell was engaged in
                    procuring engravings from pictures by the old masters, whose works he had either
                    obtained the use of, or had caused tobe copied by skilful hands. His next
                    experiment was to commission native artists of distinction to paint original
                    composition from history and other subjects, and to cause these also to be
                    engraved by Englishmen. Northcote being one of the most promising painters of
                    the British school, was employed by Mr Boydell, and also by other printsellers;
                    and prints from his designs were to be seen, framed and glazed, upon the walls
                    of the higher order of dwellings in every part of the kingdom. One of the most
                    admired, entitled the Village Doctress, had for several years a considerable
                    sale. It was not, however, until the Shakspeare Gallery was opened, that the
                    world was made fully aware of the powers of Northcote. Amongst the many-splendid
                    efforts of British art which were thus collected together, none proved more
                    attractive than his compositions. The scene of the smothering of the young
                    princes in the Tower of London; that of removing their bodies secretly by
                    torch-light for interment at the foot of the stone steps; the subject of Arthur
                    and Hubert; the entrance into London of Richard II. and Bolingbroke, and others
                    from his pencil, are undoubtedly to be reckoned amongst the best specimens of
                    British art at this flourishing period of its history. These productions clearly
                    proved how well he had studied the works of his illustrious master, and imbibed
                    his feelings as a colourist. Northcote had now attained the zenith of his fame;
                    and he received the reward of his abilities by being elected an associate of the
                    Royal Academy on the 6th of November 1786, and a royal academician on the 13th
                    of February 1787.</p>
                <p part="N">From this period Northcote divided his professional labours between
                    historical compositions, fancy subjects, and portraiture. The dramatic style,
                    however, attracted his attention for a time, and he painted a series of moral
                    subjects, illustrative of virtue and vice, in the progress of two young women.
                    This was trenching upon the ground' of Hogarth, and the attempt proved a
                    failure; for although the main points of this graphic drama bore directly upon
                    the subject, the characters were deficient in expression and individuality. In
                    painting, Northcote kept the colouring of Sir Joshua Reynolds steadily in his
                    eye; and&gt; so little change in his style had his contemplation of the great
                    masters in Italy wrought, that no one could discover the least approach to that
                    severity of manner which is peculiar to the Roman and other Italian masters. His
                    pictures are distinguished for their breadth of light and’ shade; and most of
                    his historical works display a comprehensive and accurate knowledge of the
                    subject, much study, and considerable force of conception. For a period of above
                    thirty years his productions may be said to have borne a conspicuous part in the
                    exhibitions at Somerset House; and, to the last year of his life, a season
                    seldom elapsed without his presenting one or more efforts of his pencil at the
                    British Institution or the Gallery of the British Artists.</p>
                <p part="N">That Northcote was an enthusiast in his art may be gathered from many
                    anecdotes related of him whilst expatiating upon the merits of the great
                    masters. A favourite pursuit of his was the painting of wild animals; and one
                    day, whilst making a study from nature of a vulture, he laid down his palette,
                    and clasping his hands, exclaimed, “I lately beheld an eagle painted by Titian,
                    and if heaven would give me the power to achieve such a work, I would then be
                    content to die.’' His conversational powers have been extolled by all who had an
                    opportunity of knowing him; but he never allowed the fascinations of society to
                    interfere with his professional avocations. It was his custom for many years to
                    take an early morning walk, on his return from which he breakfasted, and then
                    went to his studio. About eleven in the forenoon, unless he had an engagement
                    with a sitter, his levee commenced. It seldom happened that he remained alone;
                    one visitor succeeding another, and occasionally three or four at a time,
                    holding him in conversation until the hour for dinner. Al) the while he was
                    proceeding with whatever picture he had on hand, working and talking at the same
                    time. His conversation was distinguished by sagacity, acuteness, and great
                    extent of information, as may be seen from a volume published by Mr Hazlitt,
                    entitled Conversations with the late James Northcote, R. A. He had, however,
                    much of that cynical spirit too prevalent amongst artists, of depreciating the
                    works and characters of their rivals; but he was benevolent withal, and whatever
                    he might say in disparagement of those who crossed his path, he was ever ready
                    to befriend those who applied to him for assistance or advice. To young artists
                    he was kind and condescending, and always easily accessible. Such traits in the
                    pictures or drawings which they submitted to him as happened to display
                    originality and talent, gave him delight; for he felt a patriotic pride in the
                    arts of his country, and a personal interest in their advancement. In whatever
                    company Northcote might be, he always maintained his opinions, which were often
                    singular, with a manly independence, which secured him general respect. One day
                    a royal duke, whilst attending at a sitting of Master Betty, the young Roscius,
                    whom Northcote, with his usual sagacity, thoroughly despised, used some
                    liberties with the ar <pb break="no" facs="nls:194560154?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0716-0154-0253"/>tist’s gray locks, observing, “You do not
                    devote much time to the toilet, I perceive ?” Northcote instantly replied, “Sir,
                    I never allow any one to take personal liberties with me; you are the first who
                    ever presumed to do so, and I beg your royal highness to recollect that I am in
                    my own house.” He then resumed his painting, and the royal personage, feeling
                    the rebuke, shortly afterwards took his departure. Next day, however, the artist
                    was surprised by a visit from his royal highness, who, in returning something of
                    which he had obtained the loan, handsomely apologised to him for the liberty
                    which had been thoughtlessly taken.</p>
                <p part="N">Northcote was naturally just, temperate, careful, and in the strictest
                    sense of the word a philosopher. The system of life which he early prescribed
                    for himself was founded on wisdom, and maintained with constancy. The frugal
                    manner in which his table was served from principle might lead to the idea that
                    he was parsimonious; but this is rendered nugatory by the facts, that he lent
                    money freely without asking for interest, and sometimes not even for the
                    principal, by which means he frequently lost it; that he was the most patient
                    and long-suffering of creditors, not only feeling a horror at asking for what
                    was justly due him for his works, but often having whole-lengths, halflengths,
                    and bust portraits thrown upon his hands without his ever attempting to enforce
                    payment. His prudence and foresight, however, enabled him to secure an
                    independence for the evening of life, which so often overtakes artists in
                    destitution and misery. The last years of Northcote’s life were spent in
                    preparing for the press a volume of fables and a Life of Titian. He died on the
                    13th of July 1831, and his remains were deposited in the church of St
                    Mary-le-Bone on the 20th of the same month.</p>
                <p part="N">Northcote was an author as well as a painter. His earliest productions
                    were some papers inserted in a periodical work called The Artist. The subjects
                    of these papers were, Originality in Painting, Imitators and Collectors,
                    Disappointed Genius, a Character of John Opie, Letter from a Disappointed
                    Genius, and the Imitation of the Stage in Painting. In the second volume of the
                    same work, the History of the Slighted Beauty, an allegory, was also by him. He
                    further contributed to the fine arts of the English school the biography of Sir
                    Joshua Reynolds, which he afterwards expanded into a quarto volume, entitled
                    Memoirs of Sir Joshua Reynolds, comprising anecdotes of many distinguished
                    persons, his contemporaries, and a brief ana-ysis of his Discourses; to which
                    are added, Varieties on Art, 1813. A supplement to the work appeared in 1815;
                    and an octavo edition, with considerable additions, came aut in 1819. In 1828 he
                    published^ in octavo, One Hun-lred Fables, original and selected, embellished
                    with two aundred and eighty engravings on wood from his own designs. He likewise
                    left materials for a second series, which )y directions given in his will was to
                    be published after the leath of his sister. His last work, which appeared at the
                    dose of the year 1830, in two volumes octavo, is the Life )f Titian, with
                    anecdotes of the distinguished persons of ιis time; a work containing a vast
                    mass of useful informa- .ion and reflection on the art of painting. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">(r. r. r.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
