<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-7775-0070-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NECKER, James</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942527">Gibbons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194557775?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">NECKER, <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi></label>, a
                    well-known statesman and financier of France. He was born on the 30th of
                    September 1732, at Geneva, being descended of a respectable family, originally
                    from the north of Germany. At the age of fifteen be quitted Geneva, and
                    proceeded to Paris with a view to push his fortune in that city. He entered
                    first into the banking-house of Vernet, and afterwards into that of Thelluson,
                    of which he became the cashier, and at length a partner. On the death of
                    Thelluson, he established a bank on his own account, by which he accumulated a
                    very large fortune. After twenty years of unremitting attention to business, he
                    married a Protestant lady of respectable family, but in reduced circumstances,
                    the patrimonial estate having been lost in consequence of the revocation of the
                    edict of Nantes. With this lady he appears to have enjoyed the highest degree of
                    domestic happiness. A short time after his marriage, he was named minister of
                    the republic of Geneva at Paris. In accepting of this employment he refused the
                    emoluments which were attached to it, a degree of forbearance not very usual in
                    public men, but in which he resolutely persisted during the whole course of his
                    political life. Two works which he published, namely, an Eulogium on Colbert,
                    and a treatise on the Legislation and Trade of Corn, greatly extended the
                    reputation of his political talents; and he had fortunately succeeded in
                    adjusting some differences between the East India Company and the crown, in such
                    a manner as to receive the approbation of both parties, a circumstance which
                    added to the weight of his character.</p>
                <p part="N">About this time the disorder in the state of the French finances had
                    become so alarming, that it was found necessary to break through the routine of
                    official promotion, and to choose able men for the public service wherever they
                    could be found. These inducements so far outweighed the objections to Μ. Necker,
                    as a foreigner and a Protestant, that, after some conversations with Μ.
                    Maurepas, he was, in the year 1776, appointed director of the royal treasury,
                    and, in the following year, director-general of the finances. The great object
                    of Μ. Necker was to introduce order and economy in the public management. With
                    this view he found himself compelled cither to suppress useless offices, or to
                    diminish emoluments; and his retrenchments drew upon him the enmity of all those
                    who suffered by his economical reforms. A party was formed against him, chiefly
                    composed of rapacious courtiers; and though the repeal of several most
                    oppressive imposts had conciliated the general good will of the people, he was
                    daily the object of malicious libels. His severe measures of economy had also
                    excited the dislike of the minister Μ. Maurepas, although others ascribe his
                    hostility to a different cause, namely, to his disappointment at not finding in
                    Necker that subserviency which he expected from a person of his comparatively
                    obscure origin, and a Protestant. Whatever was the reason, the minister was
                    amongst the number of his enemies; and he is charged by Madame de Staël with
                    secretly instigating those libellous attacks of which Μ. Necker now became the
                    object. To enable him, according to Madame de Staël, the better to struggle with
                    his opponents, he requested some signal mark of royal favour, such as a seat in
                    the council, which was granted. This demand on the part of Necker gave rise to
                    new and acrimonious discussions, in the course of which he tendered his
                    resignation, after having been five years in office. Others give a different
                    account of this transaction. Under the influence, it is said, of that passion
                    for popular applause, which proved the torment of his life, he published, in
                    1781, the well-known piece on the state of the finances, entitled <hi
                        rend="italic">Le Compte</hi><hi rend="italic">Rendu</hi><hi rend="italic">au
                        Roi,</hi> of which an immense number of copies were sold. Elated by this
                    success, he made a demand for a seat in the council, but was objected to on the
                    ground of his religion. Being persuaded that this scruple would be abandoned, he
                    persisted, and offered his resignation, which was accepted; and in this manner,
                    as is alleged, he became the dupe of his own presumption.</p>
                <p part="N">The enemies of Necker reproached him with indulging, during his short
                    administration, his passion for popularity at the expense of the public
                    interest. The great point which he laboured to establish in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Compte</hi><hi rend="italic">Rendu</hi> was, that there was no
                    deficit in the public revenue, and that there was no necessity for additional
                    taxes. In lieu of new impositions, he is charged with supplying the public
                    necessities by the expedient of large loans; postponing, in this manner, the
                    evil day, but accumulating on posterity an increasing load of debt, which,
                    sooner or later, must be provided for by adequate taxes, and all this to procure
                    a temporary popularity at the expense of his rivals. Notwithstanding these
                    objections, he had numerous partisans, especially amongst the men of letters,
                    who regarded his elevation to power as the triumph of philosophy and liberal
                    principles over aristocratical prejudice.</p>
                <p part="N">After his resignation, he retired to Switzerland, where he purchased the
                    barony of Coppet. In 1784 he published an able work, further illustrating his
                    financial policy, entitled <hi rend="italic">De ΓAdministration des
                        Finances.</hi> This work, of which 80,000 copies were speedily sold, served
                    to support the reputation of his plans, and also to keep together his adherents,
                    whose numbers formed a counterpoise to the influence of his enemies at
                    court.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1787 Μ. de Calonne convoked the Assembly of the Notables, and, in his
                    opening speech to that body, impeached the accuracy of the statements contained
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Compte</hi><hi rend="italic">Rendu.</hi> It was not to
                    be supposed that Μ. Necker would quietly submit to this charge. He sent a
                    memorial upon the subject to the king, with various other papers, for the
                    purpose of proving the correctness of his calculations. His majesty having read
                    these documents, requested that they might not be published, a proposition which
                    by no means suited the views of Μ. Necker. His statements were accordingly
                    printed, and for this offence he was exiled, by a <hi rend="italic"
                        >lettre</hi><hi rend="italic">de cachet,</hi> forty leagues from Paris.</p>
                <p part="N">Μ. de Calonne did not, however, remain long in power; and the Archbishop
                    of Toulouse, by whom he was succeeded, was also obliged to resign, and to make
                    way for Μ. Necker, the favourite of the people, who was reinstated in his former
                    post in August 1788. A new and remarkable era was now about to open in the
                    history both of France and of the world. The writings of the French philosophers
                    and men of letters had gradually given currency to notions of constitutional
                    freedom. The people could no longer endure, like their forefathers, the bondage
                    of feudal privileges, by which the few acquired the power of oppressing the
                    many. They had become jealous and discontented, and were deeply irritated at the
                    insolence and oppression of the aristocratical body; and with those indignant
                    feelings were mingled, in the minds of the popular leaders, the brilliant
                    visions of speculative reform. But as long as the people wanted a legitimate
                    organ through which their voice could be heard, it was clear that whatever<pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:194557788?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0716-7788-0071"/>
                    might be their feelings, they could make little impression on the measures of
                    the state. What was wanting in this respect was now about to be supplied; and
                    the popular voice, hitherto so little considered, was, through the
                    representative body, to become the pre-eminent influence in the government. At
                    this period the French government was assailed by a complication of
                    difficulties, the chief of which was the impracticability of raising the
                    necessary supplies, and the danger of an immediate bankruptcy. A great scarcity
                    also prevailed at Paris, which rendered the populace unusually discontented and
                    tumultuous. In this emergency various expedients were suggested; and the
                    convocation of the states-general, which had long been talked of, was advised by
                    Μ. Necker, as likely to give general satisfaction to the people. In assenting to
                    this proposition, it was the plan of the court that the different orders of the
                    clergy, nobility, and commons, should vote in separate chambers, in order that
                    the deputies of the commons might be controlled by the other two bodies. But the
                    popular leaders were by far too penetrating to allow their influence to be
                    annihilated by this device. They determined, from the beginning, that the three
                    orders should sit and vote together; and it is well known that, after various
                    fruitless efforts to bring about this union, the commons resolved to form
                    themselves into an assembly for the despatch of business, without regard to the
                    other two chambers. This decisive step proved effectual, and the three chambers
                    at length all met and voted in one house, by which the whole power was thrown
                    into the hands of the commons.</p>
                <p part="N">During these transactions, the king and his advisers pursued a weak and
                    vacillating policy. They perceived, when it was too late, the error they had
                    committed, or supposed themselves to have committed, in putting into the hands
                    of the people the powerful weapon of a representative body. But instead of
                    yielding to the necessity of circumstances, and conciliating this new power,
                    which could no longer be resisted, by conceding with a good grace every just
                    demand of constitutional right, they endeavoured to recover the ground which
                    they had for ever lost, vainly struggling against the power of the commons, and
                    meditating even the most violent measures for the recovery of their authority.
                    It was in pursuance of these views that troops were drawn from the most distant
                    parts, and encamped around Paris; a measure, the only construction that could be
                    put upon which was, that it was intended to overawe the deliberations of the
                    assembly, or, perhaps, to dissolve it at once at the point of the bayonet. These
                    violent courses Μ. Necker opposed, and he was accordingly dismissed on the 11th
                    of July 1789, and ordered to quit the kingdom in twenty-four hours. This order
                    he obeyed with equal secrecy and despatch, and had arrived at Brussels before it
                    was generally known in Paris that he was out of office.</p>
                <p part="N">It is impossible to describe the consternation which prevailed in the
                    capital when the dismission and exile of this favourite minister was made known.
                    The person who first communicated the intelligence was considered as a madman,
                    and with difficulty escaped some harsh treatment; and the event was no sooner
                    confirmed, than all the shops and places of amusement were shut up, and his
                    bust, along with that of the Duke of Orleans, was paraded through the streets,
                    dressed in mourning. These proceedings were interrupted by a German regiment;
                    the busts were broken in pieces; and in the course of the tumult one man lost
                    his life, whilst others were wounded. Fresh troops arriving, a serious conflict
                    now ensued; and an old man being cut down in the Tuilleries by an officer of
                    distinction, the populace were enraged to the highest pitch, and being joined by
                    the French guards, who deserted their officers, they at last succeeded in
                    overpowering the Germans. New outrages and tumults succeeded; the Bastille was
                    stormed; and the capital became the scene of bloody massacres, whilst the
                    people’s minds were at the same time filled with dismay at the near approach of
                    foreign troops, from whom they apprehended nothing less than the sack of the
                    city. In the midst of these alarms, they beseeched the assembly to intercede
                    with the king for the recall of their favourite minister. The necessity of
                    complying with this demand was at length perceived by the king, and a letter was
                    written to Μ. Necker, requesting him to return.</p>
                <p part="N">Μ. Necker was at Basle when he received this letter, with the request
                    contained in which he resolved immediately to comply. His progress to Paris was
                    one continued triumph. He was cheered as he passed through the different towns
                    by the acclamations of multitudes, who hailed him as their deliverer. This
                    popularity, however, was not of long duration. Being alarmed by the·excesses
                    which had already taken place, Μ. Necker became desirous to support the
                    authority of the sovereign; and, without conciliating the confidence of the
                    king’s friends, he lost that of the popular party. By the royalists he was
                    always hated; he now became an object of suspicion to the more violent patriots,
                    and was reproached as an aristocrat. Seeing his popularity on the decline, he
                    resolved to retire; and he accordingly wrote a letter to the assembly, pleading
                    the necessity of repose for the restoration of his health. No notice was taken
                    of this letter; and his personal safety being now in danger from the violence of
                    the people, he quitted Paris in the month of December 1790, having withdrawn in
                    the most private manner possible.</p>
                <p part="N">i After the loss of his power and popularity, Μ. Necker seems to have
                    sunk into the greatest dejection. “I could have wished,” says Mr Gibbon, who
                    passed some days with him about this period, “to have exhibited him as a warning
                    to any aspiring youth possessed with the demon of ambition. With all the means
                    of private happiness in his power, he is the most miserable of human beings; the
                    past, the present, and the future, are equally odious to him. When I suggested
                    some domestic amusements, he answered with a deep tone of despair, ‘ In the
                    state in which I am, I can feel nothing but the blast which has overthrown
                    me.’”</p>
                <p part="N">But his mind was soon diverted from the disappointments of ambition by
                    domestic griefs of a more poignant nature; his wife, to whom he was deeply
                    attached, dying after a long illness, in which he attended her with great
                    affection. He had now recourse to writing to divert his melancholy; and several
                    works, which he published, were the fruits of his labours. He died at Coppet, on
                    the 9th of April 1804, after a short but painful illness. His public character
                    is, of course, differently estimated, according to the political views of
                    parties. In his private and domestic relations he was amiable and affectionate,
                    and appears to have been greatly beloved.</p>
                <p part="N">His writings, besides those already mentioned, are the following: An
                    Answer to the Memorial of the Abbé Morellet, on the East India Company, 1769;
                    Memorials on the Provincial Administrations, 1781; Answer to the Speech
                    pronounced by Μ. de Calonne to the Assembly of Notables, 1787; New Explanations
                    on the Compte Rendu, 1788; Of the Importance of Religious Opinions, 1788;
                    Observations on the Introduction to the Red Book, 1790; On the Administration of
                    Μ. Necker, by Himself, 1791; On the Executive Power in Great States, 1791; On
                    the French Revolution, 1796; Course of Religious Morality, 1800; Last Views of
                    Politics and Finance. (See <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire Universelle,</hi>
                    article <hi rend="smallcaps">Necker</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">;</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Biographie Universelle,</hi> article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Necker</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">;</hi><hi rend="italic">Mémoires sur
                        la</hi><hi rend="italic">Vie</hi><hi rend="italic">Privée de mon Pere,</hi>
                    par Madame la Baronne de Staël-Holstein, suivis des <hi rend="italic">Mélanges
                        de M.</hi><hi rend="italic">Necker.)</hi><pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:194557801?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0716-7801-0072"/><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Necker Isles,</hi> a group of small islands in the South
                    Pacific Ocean, nine in number. They were discovered and so denominated by
                    Perouse. The principal island is about 500 toises in length, and sixty in
                    elevation. Long. 162. 32. W. Lat. 23. 31. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
