<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-9556-0207-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NICOLE, Peter</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:981348">Jansenists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085761">Quietism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bv7p">Jansenists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194559556?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">NICOLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Peter</hi></label>, a
                    celebrated French moralist and theologian, the nephew of Claude Nicole, a French
                    poet, and one of the most illustrious writers of the Port-Royal, was born at
                    Chartres in October 1625. His father, John Nicole, having a perfect knowledge of
                    the ancient languages, instructed him in the elements of grammar, and initiated
                    him so thoroughly in the classics, that at the age of fourteen he had completed
                    his preliminary studies, and read the best works in Greek and in Latin. He then
                    proceeded to Paris, where he commenced a course of philosophy and theology, and
                    at the same time applied to the study of Hebrew; but the weakness of his sight,
                    occasioned by excessive application, obliged him to abandon this pursuit, in
                    which he had already made great progress. Having completed his course of
                    theology, and received the degree of bachelor, he was preparing to take his
                    license, when the troubles which broke out in the university, on the subject of
                    the famous propositions of Jansenius, forced him to defer the accomplishment of
                    this object. Being attached by gratitude and esteem to the inmates of the
                    Port-Royal, he passed several years in that house, occupied in teaching the
                    belles-lettres. But, in 1655, he returned to Paris to labour under the direction
                    of Dr Arnauld, with whom he was united by the ties of the most intimate
                    friendship; and, desiring to live altogether unknown amidst the bustle of the
                    capital, he took the name of Rosny. The advancement of Jansenism appears to have
                    furnished the motive that induced him to undertake a journey which he made into
                    Germany, in the course of the year 1658; and whilst there, he not only
                    translated into Latin the <hi rend="italic">Lettres Provinciales,</hi> in the
                    composition of which he had participated, but published them, accompanied with
                    very virulent notes. He soon returned, however, to join Arnauld; and they
                    retired together to Chàtillon, where they applied themselves to the preparation
                    of different writings. Nicole, although he did not entirely adopt the opinions
                    of the Jansenists, made frequent excursions to Port-Royal, Paris, and the
                    neighbouring provinces, in the interest of that party; but in these he acted
                    with extreme circumspection, not choosing, as he himself observed, to play any
                    part in,civil wars. Being warmly solicited by his friends to enter into holy
                    orders, he at length resolved to demand ordination of the Bishop of Chartres, in
                    whose diocese he resided. But that prelate refused to ordain him, no doubt by
                    reason of his connections with the Port-Royal. He continued undisturbed at Paris
                    until the year 1677, when a <hi rend="italic">Lettre,</hi> which he wrote in the
                    names of the Bishops of St Pons and Arras, on the laxity of the casuists, raised
                    such a storm against him, that he was obliged to withdraw from the capital. For
                    some time he remained concealed in the environs of Chartres and of Beauvais; but
                    the death of the Duchess of Longueville, the most ardent protectress of
                    Jansenism, having decided him to quit France, where he did not consider himself
                    as any longer safe, he left the kingdom, and took refuge successively at
                    Brussels, the Abbey of Orval, and Liège, frequently changing his name and the
                    place of his retreat, and believing himself incessantly exposed to the
                    machinations of his enemies. At length, by the intercession of Μ. de Harlay, the
                    archbishop of Paris, he obtained permission to return secretly to Chartres, and
                    soon afterwards to fix his residence at Paris, where he resumed his ordinary
                    occupations; and it was then that he completed his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Essais</hi><hi rend="italic">de Morale,</hi> a work which is less read than
                    esteemed, and which stamped his reputation as a writer. In the last years of his
                    life he mingled in the dispute about Quietism, and took the part of Bossuet
                    against Fénélon, but with wisdom and moderation. Having for some time been
                    deprived of the use of his hands, he was meditating alone in his cabinet when he
                    was suddenly struck with apoplexy. The tidings soon spread in the capital, and
                    the crowd of persons who hurried to visit the pious cenobite proved the high
                    consideration which he enjoyed. Racine, being reconciled to his master, came in
                    a diligence, bringing a medicine <hi rend="italic">(gouttes</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Angleterre)</hi> which for a moment
                    revived him; but the resuscitation was soon succeeded by a relapse, and he died
                    two days afterwards, on the 16th of November 1695, at the age of seventy. He had
                    given orders that he should be interred without any ceremony; but his will, in
                    this particular, was not respected, and his remains were accompanied to the
                    grave by the most distinguished men of the time.</p>
                <p part="N">Nicole, being of a simple and ingenuous character, evinced during his
                    whole life the timidity of an infant. Nothing was more easy than to embarrass
                    him in discussion; an objection which he had not foreseen entirely disconcerted
                    him. Speaking of Tréville, onc of his friends, he said, “Tréville beats me in
                    the chamber; but before he reaches the foot of the stair I confute him.” In the
                    last year of his life he seldom went abroad, being afraid that, in passing along
                    the streets, a tile would fall upon his head. He had also a great dread of
                    travelling, and particularly of aquatic excursions. During a long period he had
                    relegated himself to the faubourg Saint-Marcel; and when asked the reason of
                    this, he replied, “It is because the enemies who menace Paris will probably
                    enter by the gate of Saint Martin, and consequently will be obliged to traverse
                    the whole city before reaching the place where I live.” But, with all this
                    simplicity and timidity, Nicole had a reach and an accuracy of thought which
                    were altogether admirable. He equalled the best dialecticians, in the order, the
                    method, the sequence, and the depth of his ideas; but as his object in all his
                    works was rather to prove than to please, his style, although remarkable for its
                    purity and clearness, often fatigues by its dryness and monotony. “On quitte ses
                        <hi rend="italic">Essais</hi> sans peine,” says Palissot; “on y revient sans
                    plaisir, parce que les lecteurs ont besoin d’être flattés.” Nicole attempted
                    panegyric, but soon found that he had no talent for a species of composition
                    which requires invention and warmth of style.</p>
                <p part="N">A list of the works of Nicole will be found in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mémoires</hi> of Niceron (tome xxix.), at the end of his Life by the Abbé
                    Goujet, and also in the Dictionary of Moreri. The following are the principal,
                    viz. 1. Epigrammatum Delectus ex omnibus tum veteribus tum recentioribus Poëtis,
                    cum Dissertatione de vera Pulchritudine, Paris, 1659, in 12mo; 2. La Perpétuité
                    de la Foi de l’Eglise Catholique, touchant l’Eucharistie, Paris, 1664, in 12mo,
                    called <hi rend="italic">la Petite Perpétuité,</hi> to distinguish it from the
                    great work which bears the same title; 3. Traité de la Foi Humaine, Paris, 1664,
                    in 4to, a work in which Arnauld had some share; 4. Les Imaginaires et les
                    Visionaires, ou Lettres sur l’Hérésie Imaginaire, Liège, 1667, in two vols.
                    12mo; 5. La Perpétuité de la Foi de l’Eglise Catholique, touchant l’Eucharistie,
                    Paris, 1669-1676, in three vols. 4to, a masterpiece of reasoning, which appeared
                    under the name of his friend Arnauld; 6. Essais de Morale, et Instructions
                    Théologiques, Paris, 1671-1672, in twenty-five vols. 12mo; 7. De l’Unité de
                    l’Eglise, ou Réfutation du Nouveau Système de Jurieu, Paris, 1687, in 12mo. The
                    last writings of Nicole turn upon the system of general grace, which he
                    supported, to the no small displeasure of most of his friends. The consequence
                    was a controversy, which appears to have produced some coldness on both sides.
                    Arnauld, in his Letters (tome vii.), expresses himself with much force on the
                    subject; and Quesnel complained warmly to Nicole of this species of defection on
                    his part. The various pieces produced in this dispute will be found in a
                    collection of writings on general grace, published by Fouillon in 1715, with a
                    long preface; and a curious analysis of the <hi rend="italic">Traité</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de la Grace</hi><hi rend="italic">Générale</hi> will be found
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque</hi> of the Dictionary of Richelet.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:194559569?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0716-9569-0208"/>
                <p part="N">Nicole had a large share in the <hi rend="italic">Méthodes Grecques
                        et</hi><hi rend="italic">Latines,</hi> and also in the excellent treatise on
                    Logic, known under the name of the Port-Royal. The life of this able and
                    laborious writer has been written by the Abbé Goujet, who is, however, more of a
                    panegyrist than a biographer; by Besoigne, in his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de Port-Royal</hi> (tome iv.); and also by
                    Saverien, in his <hi rend="italic">Vies</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                        Philosophes</hi><hi rend="italic">Modernes</hi> (tome i.). <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
