<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-7160-0123-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANDROÏDES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 3, page 123</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:802066">Air</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:928208">Flute</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:999431">Lips</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1174522">Wheels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8td7c">Flute</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4z31nv0r">Lips</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193097160" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ANDROÏDES</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Mechanics,</hi> a
                    human figure, which, by certain springs or other movements, is capable of
                    performing some of the natural motions of a living man. The motions of the human
                    body are more complicated, and consequently more difficult to be imitated, than
                    those of any other creature; whence the construction of an <hi rend="italic"
                    >androides,</hi> in such a manner as to imitate any of these actions with
                    tolerable exactness, is justly supposed to indicate a greater skill in mechanics
                    than any other piece of workmanship whatever.</p>
                <p>A very remarkable figure of this kind appeared in Paris in the year 1738. It
                    represented a flute-player, and was capable of performing different pieces of
                    music on the German flute; which, considering the difficulty of blowing that
                    instrument, the different contractions of the lips necessary to produce the
                    distinctions between the high and low notes, and the complicated motions of the
                    fingers, must appear truly wonderful.</p>
                <p>This machine was the invention of Μ. Vaucanson, member of the Royal Academy of
                    Sciences; and a particular description of it was published in the Memoirs of the
                    Academy for that year.</p>
                <p>The figure itself was about 5ļ feet in height, situated at the end of an
                    artificial rock, and placed upon a square pedestal 4⅜ feet high and 3⅜ broad.
                    The air entered the body by three pipes separated one from the other. It was
                    conveyed to them by nine pairs of bellows, three of which were placed above and
                    six below. These were made to expand and contract regularly in succession by
                    means of an axis of steel turned round by some clockwork. On this axis were
                    different protuberances at proper distances, to which were fixed cords thrown
                    over pulleys, and terminating in the upper boards of the bellows, so that, as
                    the axis turned, these boards were alternately raised and let down. A
                    contrivance was also used to prevent the disagreeable hissing fluttering noise
                    usually attending the motion of bellows. This was by making the cord by which
                    the bellows was moved press, in its descent, upon one end of a smaller lever,
                    the other end of which ascending, forced open the small leathern valve that
                    admitted the air, and kept it so till, the cord being relaxed by the descent of
                    the upper board, the lever fell, and the air was forced out. Thus the bellows
                    performed their functions constantly without the least hissing, or other noise
                    by which it could be judged in what manner the air was conveyed to the machine.
                    The upper boards of three of the pairs of bellows were pressed down by a weight
                    of 41bs∙, those of three others by a weight of 21bs∙, and those of the three
                    remaining ones by nothing but their own weight.</p>
                <p>The three tubes by which the air entered terminated in three small reservoirs in
                    the trunk of the figure. There they united, and, ascending towards the throat,
                    formed the cavity of the mouth, which terminated in two small lips adapted in
                    some measure to perform their proper functions. Within this cavity also was a
                    small movable tongue, which, by its play, at proper periods admitted the air, or
                    intercepted its passage to the flute.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193097173" xml:id="kp-eb0703-7173-0124"/>
                <p>The fingers, lips, and tongue, received their proper directions by means of a
                    steel cylinder turned by clockwork. It was divided into 15 equal parts, which,
                    by means of pegs pressing upon the ends of 15 different levers, caused the other
                    extremities to ascend. Seven of these levers directed the fingers, having wires
                    and chains affixed to their ascending extremities, which being attached to the
                    fingers, caused them to ascend in proportion as the other extremity was pressed
                    down by the motion of the cylinder, and <hi rend="italic">vice versa.</hi> Thus
                    the ascent or descent of one end of a lever produced a similar ascent or descent
                    in the corresponding finger, by which one of the holes of the flute was
                    occasionally opened or stopped, as by a living performer. Three of the levers
                    served to regulate the ingress of the air, being contrived so as to open and
                    shut, by means of valves, the three reservoirs of air above mentioned, so that
                    more or less strength might be given, and a higher or lower note produced, as
                    occasion required. The lips were, by a similar mechanism, directed by four
                    levers, one of which opened them, to give the air a freer passage; the other
                    contracted them; the third drew them backward; and the fourth pushed them
                    forward. The lips were projected upon that part of the flute which receives the
                    air; and, by the different motions already mentioned, modified the tone in a
                    proper manner. The remaining lever was employed in the direction of the tongue,
                    which it easily moved so as to shut or open the mouth of the flute.</p>
                <p>Thus we see how all the motions necessary for a fluteplayer could be performed by
                    this machine; but a considerable difficulty still remains, namely, how to
                    regulate these motions properly, and make each of them follow in just
                    succession. This, however, was effected by the following simple method: the
                    extremity of the axis of the cylinder was terminated on the right side by an
                    endless screw, consisting of twelve threads, each placed at the distance of a
                    line and a half from the other. Above this screw was fixed a piece of copper,
                    and in it a steel pivot, which, falling in between the threads of the screw,
                    obliged the cylinder to follow the threads, and instead of turning directly
                    round, it was continually pushed to one side. Hence, if a lever was moved by a
                    peg placed on the cylinder in any one revolution, it could not be moved by the
                    same peg in the succeeding revolution, because the peg would be moved a line and
                    a half beyond it by the lateral motion of the cylinder. Thus, by an artificial
                    disposition of those pegs in different parts of the cylinder, the statue was
                    made, by the successive elevation of the proper levers, to exhibit all the
                    different motions of a flute-player, to the admiration of every one who saw
                    it.</p>
                <p>The construction of machines capable of imitating even the mechanical actions of
                    the human body shows exquisite skill; but what shall we say of one capable, not
                    only of imitating actions of this kind, but of acting as external circumstances
                    require, as though it were endued with life and reason? This, nevertheless, has
                    been done. Μ. de Kempelen, a gentleman of Presburg in Hungary, excited by the
                    performances of Μ. de Vaucanson, at first endeavoured to imitate them, and at
                    last far excelled them. This gentleman constructed an androides capable of
                    playing at chess! Every one who is in the least acquainted with this game must
                    know that it is so far from being mechanically performed, as to require a
                    greater exertion of the judgment and rational faculties than is sufficient to
                    accomplish many matters of greater importance. That this machine really was
                    made, however, the public have had ocular demonstration. The inventor came over
                    to Britain in 1783, where he remained above a year with his automaton.</p>
                <p>It is a figure as large as life, in a Turkish dress, sitting behind a table, with
                    doors of three feet and a half in length, two in depth, and two and a half in
                    height. The chair on which it sits is fixed to the table, which runs on four
                    wheels. The automaton leans its right arm on the table, and in its. left hand
                    holds a pipe: with this <hi rend="superscript"> k</hi> hand it plays after the
                    pipe is removed. A chess-board of 18 inches is fixed before it. This table, or
                    rather cup. board, contains wheels, levers, cylinders, and other pieces of
                    mechanism, all which are publicly displayed. The vestments of the automaton are
                    then lifted over its head, and the body is seen full of similar wheels and
                    levers. There is a little door in its thigh, which is likewise opened; and with
                    this, and the table also open, and the automaton uncovered, the whole is wheeled
                    about the room. The doors are then shut, and the automaton is ready to play; and
                    it always takes the first move.</p>
                <p>At every motion the wheels are heard; the image moves its head, and looks over
                    every part of the chessboard. When it checks the queen it shakes its head twice,
                    and thrice in giving check to the king. It likewise shakes its head when a false
                    move is made, replaces the piece, and makes its own move; by which means the
                    adversary loses one.</p>
                <p>Μ. de Kempełen remarks as the most surprising circumstance attending his
                    automaton, that it had been exhibited at Presburg, Vienna, Paris, and London, to
                    thousands, many of whom were mathematicians and chessplayers, and yet the secret
                    by which he governed the motion of its arm was never discovered. He prided
                    himself solely in the construction of the mechanical powers, by which the arm
                    could perform ten or twelve moves. It then required to be wound up like a watch,
                    after which it was capable of continuing the same number of motions.</p>
                <p>The automaton could not play unless Μ. de Kempelen or his substitute was near it
                    to direct its moves. A small square box, during the game, was frequently
                    consulted by the exhibiter; and herein consisted the secret, which he said he
                    could in a moment communicate. He who could beat Μ. de Kempelen was, of course,
                    certain of conquering the automaton. It was made in 1769. His own account of it
                    was, “C’est une bagatelle qui n’est pas sans mérite du côté du mechanisme; mais
                    les effets n’en pa-roissent si merveilleux que par la hardiesse de l’idée, et
                    par Theureux choix des moyens employés pour faire illusion.” See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Automaton.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
