<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-1905-0488-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARISTIDES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 3, page 488</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b40p0wq2m">Temperance</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jr84">Tempering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1147289">Temper</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1147375">Tempering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1147309">Temperance</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193101905" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARISTIDES</label>, surnamed the <hi rend="italic">Just,</hi>
                    one of the most celebrated characters of his age for purity and integrity, and
                    contemporary with Themistocles, was the son of Lysimachus, a man of middle rank,
                    and born at Athens. His dispositions and temper from his youth all conjoined in
                    anticipating that greatness to which he afterwards rose. To a firm, resolute,
                    and placid temper, he likewise added a great contempt of dissimulation, and an
                    utter abhorrence of every thing dishonourable. He began very early to meditate
                    on subjects of government, and applied to his studies with the greatest
                    assiduity. He imbibed a strong predilection for oligarchy upon becoming
                    acquainted with the laws of Lycurgus, which excited his admiration, and gave him
                    a distaste of the unlimited democracy then established in his native city. On
                    the other hand, Themistocles favoured democracy; and even when at school he is
                    said to have been his constant antagonist on that point. A perpetual opposition
                    to one another in all political points was the consequence of this difference of
                    opinion, when their abilities raised them to several important stations in the
                    state. It is related, that one day having firmly opposed a proposal of
                    Themistocles in the assembly, which in his own conscience he knew to be right,
                    on coming out he exclaimed, “The affairs of the Athenians will never prosper
                    till they throw both of us into the <hi rend="italic">barathrum</hi>” (the
                    dungeon for condemned criminals).</p>
                <p>Aristides was present at the battle of Marathon, fought B. c. 490, and was next
                    in command among the Athenians to Miltiades; and there, upon that general’s
                    proposing to come to battle as soon as possible, he seconded his motion with the
                    utmost vigour. In the field he distinguished himself by his intrepidity, valour,
                    and generosity; and being left after the battle to secure the spoils, he
                    executed his trust with honour and fidelity, bringing all to the public account,
                    reserving nothing for himself. He was elected to the important office of chief
                    magistrate the year following; but, by the art of Themistocles, the high
                    authority he had attained by his merits was at length converted into an
                    accusation against him, and he was accordingly banished by the ostracism,—a mild
                    but often unjust measure in the policy of the Athenian state, for getting a
                    temporary relief from the presence of any political influence by which they
                    thought their independence might be injured. As the Persians were meditating a
                    new invasion of Greece, he employed himself in his exile in encouraging the
                    Greeks to defend their liberties against the invaders. The Athenians
                    immediately, upon the approach of Xerxes, recalled Aristides, whose absence they
                    began sincerely to regret, along with their other exiles. At this critical
                    moment, upon his return, he suspended all political animosities; and upon
                    understanding that it was the design of Themistocles to fight the Persian navy
                    in the Straits of Salamis, he waited on him in private, proposed an oblivion of
                    all past circumstances, extolled his intentions, and gave him his sincere
                    promise to do the utmost in his power towards effecting his designs.
                    Themistocles, some time after the battle of Salamis, acquainted the Athenians
                    that he had formed a scheme which, although it was of such a nature as forbade
                    his public avowal of it to them, was of inestimable advantage to the state. They
                    immediately ordered that he should communicate it to Aristides. It was a project
                    for consuming the whole confederate fleet of Greece by fire, except their own
                    ships; and thus the entire sway of the sea would be left to the Athenian navy.
                    Aristides reported that nothing could be more unjust, and at the same time
                    nothing more advantageous, than the scheme of Themistocles. Upon this report the
                    people immediately determined to drop any further thought of it. Aristides,
                    before the battle of Plataea, was of considerable service in persuading his
                    countrymen, who were elated with their former successes, to submit to the
                    superior power of the Spartans, and in preserving peace and amity between the
                    confederate forces. He acquitted himself with great valour and resolution in the
                    engagement, and was appointed after the victory to determine a very dangerous
                    dispute concerning the honour of the day, which he conferred upon the Plataeans,
                    giving up the claim of the Athenians, the Lacedemonians following his example.
                    Upon the rebuilding of Athens, he was the first person to promote a law which
                    divided the administration among the citizens at large, and enjoined that the
                    archons or chief magistrates should be elected out of the whole body of the
                    people, who had so deservedly merited the favour of the state.</p>
                <p>Aristides, upon the continuation of the war with the Persians, was sent, along
                    with Cimon the son of Miltiades, to take the command of the Athenian forces in
                    the confederate army. Their humility and meekness, compared with the haughty
                    domineering temper of Pausanias, so engaged the rest of the allies, that the
                    superiority of rank was conferred upon Athens, with the joint concurrence of the
                    other states. The nomination of Aristides to lay an equal assessment upon all
                    the states for the purposed defraying the expense of the war, was a signal proof
                    of the high idea all Greece had of his integrity and justice. The wisdom and
                    impartiality with which he performed this commission gave universal
                    satisfaction. He obliged all the confederates, after this affair was terminated,
                    solemnly to swear to all the articles of association. Γh advice which he
                    afterwards gave the Athenians to extend their own territories beyond their
                    proper limits, must certainly have proceeded from some very pressing necessity,
                    when he thus drew down the consequences of the perjury upon his own head.
                    Aristides, on Themistocles’s falling under the displeasure of the ruling party,
                    would not con<pb break="no" facs="nls:193101918" xml:id="kp-eb0703-1918-0489"
                    />cur in a capital prosecution of him; and instead of triumphing over an old
                    enemy, he always spoke of him after his banishment with the highest respect.</p>
                <p>This great man died about 407 years <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.,</hi> according to
                    some at Athens, at an advanced age; others say at Pontus, where he was
                    transacting public business. He was buried at the public expense, his daughters
                    received portions out of the public treasury, and an estate in land was bestowed
                    on his son Lysimachus, in gratitude for the signal services Aristides had done
                    his country.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Aristides,</hi><hi rend="italic">Aelius,</hi> a celebrated
                    orator, born in Mysia about 129 years before the Christian era. The best edition
                    of his works is that of Oxford, printed in Greek and Latin, in two volumes
                    quarto.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Aristides,</hi> a painter contemporary with Apelles,
                    flourished at Thebes about the 122d Olympiad. He was the first, according to
                    Pliny, who expressed character and passion, but he was not remarkable for
                    softness of colouring.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
