<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0703-9565-0308-04" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">APPELLATION</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 3, page 308</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz36">Inns</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40k26h3v">Lombards</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1002186">Lombards</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1028427">Mouth</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:938950">Gates</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1134794">Streets</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:841533">Bulls</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193099565" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">APPELLATION</label>, the name by which any thing is known or
                    distinguished when spoken of. Nothing can be more foreign to the original
                    meaning of many words and proper names than their present or vulgar
                    appellations; frequently owing to the history of those things being forgotten,
                    or an ignorance of the language in which they were expressed. Who, for example,
                    would dream that the legal proclamation called “0 yes,” was a proclamation
                    commanding the talkers to become hearers, being the French word <hi rend="italic">Oyez,</hi> listen, retained in our courts ever since the law
                    pleadings were held in French? Or would any person suppose that the headland on
                    the French coast near Calais, called by our seamen Blackness, would be so titled
                    from its French name of <hi rend="italic">Blanc Nez,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">White Head-land?</hi></p><p>King Henry the Eighth having taken the town of Boulogne in France, the gates of
                    which he brought to Hardes in Kent, where they are still remaining, the
                    flatterers of that reign highly magnified this action, which, Porto Bello like,
                    became a popular subject for signs; and the port or harbour of Boulogne, called
                    <hi rend="italic">Boulogne Mouth,</hi> was accordingly set up at a noted inn in
                    Holborn. The name of the inn long outliving the sign and fame of the conquest,
                    an ignorant painter, employed by a no less ignorant landlord to paint a new one,
                    represented it by a bull and a large gaping human mouth; answering to the vulgar
                    pronunciation of <hi rend="italic">bull and mouth.</hi> The same piece of
                    history gave being to the <hi rend="italic">bull and gate,</hi> originally meant
                    for Boulogne gate, and represented by an embattled gate or entrance into a
                    fortified town.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">barbed s pole</hi> has been the subject of many
                    conjectures; some conceiving it to have originated from the word <hi rend="italic">poll</hi> or head, with several other conceits as farfetched and
                    as unmeaning; but the true intention of that party-coloured staff was to show
                    that the master of the shop practised surgery, and could breathe a vein as well
                    as mow a beard. The white band which encompasses the staff was meant to
                    represent the fillet thus elegantly twined about it.</p><p>Nor were the <hi rend="italic">chequers,</hi> at this time a common sign of a
                    public house, less expressive,—being the representation of a kind of
                    draught-board called <hi rend="italic">tables,</hi> and showing that there that
                    game might be played. From their colour, which was red, and the similarity to a
                    lattice, it was corruptly called the <hi rend="italic">red lettuce,</hi> which
                    word is frequently used by ancient writers to signify an ale-house.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> has explained the sign of the <hi rend="italic">bellsavage inn</hi> plausibly enough, in supposing it to have been
                    originally the figure of a beautiful female found in the woods, called in French
                    <hi rend="italic">la belle</hi><hi rend="italic">sauvage.</hi> But another
                    reason has since been assigned for that appellation, namely, that the inn was
                    once the property of Lady Arabella Savage, and familiarly called <hi rend="italic">Bell Savages Inn,</hi> probably represented as at present, by a
                    bell and a savage or wild man, which was a rcbus for her name; rebuses being
                    much in fashion in the 16th century.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">three blue balls</hi> prefixed to the doors and windows of
                    pawnbrokers’ shops, by the vulgar humorously enough said to indicate that it is
                    two to one that the things pledged are never redeemed, were in reality the arms
                    of a set of merchants from Lombardy, who were the first that publicly lent money
                    on pledges. They dwelt together in a street, from them named Lombard Street, in
                    London, and also gave their name to another at Paris. The appellation of Lombard
                    was formerly all over Europe considered as synonymous with that of usurer.</p><p>At the institution of yeomen of the guards, they used to wait at table on all
                    great solemnities, and were ranged near the buffets. This procured them the name
                    of <hi rend="italic">lnffe∙ tiers,</hi> not very unlike in sound to the jocular
                    appellation of <hi rend="italic">beef-eaters,</hi> now given them; though
                    probably it was rather the voluntary misnomer of some wit, than an accidental
                    corruption arising from ignorance of the French language.</p><p>The opprobrious title of <hi rend="italic">bum bayliffe,</hi> so constantly
                    bestowed on the sheriff’s officers, is, according to Judge Blackstone, only the
                    corruption of <hi rend="italic">bound bayliffe,</hi> every sheriff’s officer
                    being obliged to enter into bonds and to give security for his good behaviour,
                    previous to his appointment. 1</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">cordwainer</hi> seems to have no relation to the occupation
                    it is meant to express, which is that of a shoemaker. But <hi rend="italic">cordonier,</hi> originally spelt <hi rend="italic">cordaunier,</hi> is the
                    French word for that trade; the best leather used for shoes coming originally
                    from Cordova in Spain.</p></div></body></text></TEI>