<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-0410-0373-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARAGON, or Arragon</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 3, page 373</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61762">Leveling</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:996970">Levellers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:996964">Leveling</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193100410" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARAGON, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Arragon</hi></label>, a
                    province, or, as it is usually denominated by the inhabitants of the peninsula,
                    a kingdom, of Spain, and one of the component parts of that monarchy, situated
                    between 40. 17. and 42. 51. N. lat. It is almost surrounded by Old and New
                    Castile, but to the south the province of Valencia adjoins it and a small part
                    of Catalonia. It is the most thinly peopled and the most extensive of all the
                    European dominions of the Spanish crown. Its superficies is 1232 square leagues;
                    and its population, according to the census of 1803, was 657,376 souls. It is
                    indeed contended that the numeration of that period was incorrect; but the
                    highest calculation, made by the Economical Society of Saragossa, makes it
                    amount to but a few hundreds more than the census on which we rely. The province
                    is nearly divided into two equal parts by the river Ebro, which are
                    distinguished by the appellations of <hi rend="italic">trans-ibero</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">cis-ibero.</hi> Its surface is very irregular: the north-east part
                    towards Old Castile begins with the Sierra de Moncayo, but from the foot of
                    these mountains to the Ebro the country is a continued level and fertile plain
                    hi the centre. To the south the ground rises gradually till it attains
                    considerable elevation in the mountains near Cuença, in which are the sources of
                    the most considerable rivers of Spain, some of which direct their courses to the
                    Mediterranean, while others force their way to the A tian tic.</p>
                <p>The agricultural productions of the province necessarily vary with the variations
                    in the elevation and aspect of the land. The greater part is appropriated to
                    feeding flocks of Merino sheep. The number of those belonging to the inhabitants
                    of Aragon amounted to 2,050,000, and their wool forms the most important of the
                    productions of the province. Wheat is grown more than sufficient for its own
                    consumption, and it contributes to feed the neighbouring province of Navarre.
                    Its wine and oil are generally more than itsown demands require, and they are
                    both of the best quality which Spain produces; but having none but difficult
                    communication with any other country where these valuable articles are wanted,
                    the cultivation of them languishes. Near the banks of the Ebro flax and hemp are
                    grown in more than sufficient quantities for the domestic manufactures; and a
                    supply of the latter is furnished to some of the maritime towns of Biscay, where
                    it is preferred for cables to any other. The whole annual quantity of its growth
                    is 1000 tons. The supply of horses and cows is not equal to the demands of the
                    inhabitants, and the deficiency is made up from the breed of the adjoining
                    provinces. The mountainous parts abound with excellent ship-timber, but the
                    badness of the roads prevents this branch of commerce irom being carried to any
                    great extent.</p>
                <p>The manufactures of the province are inconsiderable; that of silk, which was
                    formerly extensive, has been gradually on the decline for some years.
                    Manufactories for coarse cloths occupy the inhabitants of the town, or, as they
                    call it, the city, of Albarracin, and the large village of Tarazona; and some
                    cloths of fine wool are made &lt;lt Jaca, and some baize in its vicinity. Some
                    linen and sail-cloth are also made, but the quantity of each is small. There are
                    iron manufactories on the mountains, where the abundance ol trees calculated for
                    making charcoal have introduced forges; but the badness of the roads checks
                    their extension.</p>
                <p>Aragon is not deficient in mineral riches, though the labour applied to them, as
                    to most other objects in Spain, ' is in a very languid state. Near the Pyrenees,
                    besides mines of iron, there are three mines of lead and one of copper, and,
                    what is unique in Spain, a mine of cobalt. Besides these there is a mine of alum
                    near Alcaniz, which is very productive.</p>
                <p>Though the soil is generally very dry, and the greater part of the province
                    suffers from the want of water, yet the largest rivers of Spain, the Tagus, the
                    Guadiana, and the Xucar, have their sources within it, and by their early
                    streams water the valleys, whilst, as before noticed, the Ebro runs through its
                    centre. At two leagues N. N. E. of Albarracin is the extraordinary fountain
                    called Celia, at an elevation of 3700 feet above the level of the sea. From this
                    fountain the river Xiloca issues, and running through a beautiful country of 30
                    miles in extent, filled with inclosures, orchards, gardens, and vineyards, joins
                    its waters, near Calatayud, to the more copious stream of the Xalon, which
                    descends from Old Castile; and these united, lose their names by being emptied
                    into the Ebro. Between the stream of the Xiloca and the mountains which separate
                    Aragon from Molina, is a very extensive lake called Gallo-canta, which covers
                    about 6000 acres of land; and at a little distance from the lake are the ruins
                    of the ancient city Bilbilis, which has derived celebrity from being the native
                    place of the Roman poet Martial. The Ebro receives the tributary streams of the
                    Gallego and the Guervajustas it reaches the walls of Saragossa; and soon after
                    the Martin joins it near the populous town of Caspe. In this vicinity are
                    abundant coal-mines, which supply the inhabitants and the manufactories with
                    that valuable fuel. In Aragon trans-ibero the river Cinca, issuing from the
                    Pyrenees, passes the town of Ainsa, the former residence of the ancient kings of
                    Aragon; and, increased by the streams of the Esera, the Vero, and the Alcanadre,
                    in its passage to the Ebro, fertilizes the lands near the city of Huesea. In
                    this place is a university and two colleges, the former of which is a building
                    of great antiquity and considerable magnificence; and it is surrounded by the
                    ruins of very ancient fortifications. After receiving, besides the streams
                    noticed, several copious rivulets, whose short courses have scarcely received
                    any names, the Ebro enters the province of Catalonia, and at length falls into
                    the Mediterranean Sea near Tolosa.</p>
                <p>The capital of Aragon is Saragossa, or, as the Spaniards spell it, Zaragosa, a
                    city of more than 50,000 inhabitants; the description of which, with its
                    memorable resistance to the French invaders, will be treated of under the
                    article <hi rend="smallcaps">Saragossa.</hi> The other considerable cities and
                    towns are Teruel, Daroca, Calatayud, Borja, Tarazona, Alcaniz, Caspe, Barbastro,
                    Monzon, Huesea, and Jaca. At the most southern part of the province a district
                    called Cinco-villas is remarkably fruitful. The whole extent of 17,000 acres
                    derives its fertility principally from an artificial canal, cut for the purpose
                    of irrigation, called the royal canal of Tauste, by means of which the whole of
                    the land may be flooded at pleasure.</p>
                <p>The name of this kingdom was derived from the small but precipitous torrent
                    Aragon, which rises in the Pyrenean Mountains, and, running from north to south,
                    forms part of the waters of the Ebro.</p>
                <p>A great portion of the Pyrenees is in the province of Aragon. They run from east
                    to west, presenting towards Spain the convex part of a kind of spherical
                    segment, losing their height gradually towards each extremity. The highest point
                    of this range of mountains, called by the French Mont Perdu, and by the
                    Spaniards Las Tres Sorores, is visible from the city of Saragossa. According to
                    the actual measurement of the naturalist Ramond, who <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193100423" xml:id="kp-eb0703-0423-0374"/>reached its summit in 1802,
                    it is 11,430 feet above the level of the sea. Its top is constantly covered with
                    snow, the permanent limits of which, on the same authority, are stated at 7750
                    feet of elevation. Before the measurement of Ramond, the point called Canigu was
                    supposed to be the highest peak of this range, but it was thereby ascertained to
                    be but 10,050 feet high.</p>
                <p>The regular passages from Spain into France are none of them through any of the
                    ridges within the province of Aragon. One of them is in Biscay, one in Navarre,
                    and one in Catalonia; but on an accurate survey by the French engineers, it
                    appeared there were upwards of eighty practicable passages, of which
                    twenty-eight would allow of cavalry, and seven of artillery and wheel-carriages.
                    None of these had been ever examined by the Spanish government, though it was
                    more than suspected that a very considerable contraband traffic had been
                    conducted through these passes, in spite of the vigilance of the officers of
                    revenue in both kingdoms.</p>
                <p>The history of Aragon before its union with Castile by the marriage of Ferdinand
                    and Isabella, when it was merged in the kingdom of Spain, will be found in the
                    general history of that country. <hi rend="italic">Viage de</hi> Ponz; <hi
                    rend="italic">Geografia de</hi> Don Isidoro de Antillon; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Economia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Politica</hi><hi rend="italic">de Aragon,</hi> por Don Ignacio de Asso. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(g.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
