<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0703-7121-0120-08" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">ANDREWS, St</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 3, page 120</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19s90">Students</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1136041">Students</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:923951">Fife</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:829042">Bays</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1154418">Trails</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193097121" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">ANDREWS, <hi rend="smallcaps">St</hi></label>, a city of
                    Scotland, in the county of Fife, pleasantly situated in a spacious bay of the
                    German Ocean, into which flow the river Eden, the small rivulet of Kinness, and
                    several other streams. It was formerly a place of much greater extent and
                    importance. At present it is only about a mile and a half in circuit, and
                    consists of three leading streets, intersected by a few considerable lanes. The
                    principal street is well built, and is straight and broad, and of late years its
                    appearance has been much improved. The town contains many interesting memorials
                    of antiquity. Of the splendid cathedral, which was founded by Bishop Arnold in
                    1159, and attained to its highest magnificence in 1318, part of the east and
                    west ends, and of the south side, are all that now remain. The length of this
                    edifice from east to west was 350 feet within the walls; that of the transept
                    180 feet. This whole pile of building, which it took 150 years to complete, was
                    in June 1559 demolished in a single day by John Knox and his infuriated
                    followers. About 40 yards to the south-east is the chapel of St Regulus, the
                    tower of which is a lofty square prism, the side of the base being 20 feet, and
                    the height 108. The chapel to the east of the tower, which was the principal
                    one, remains; but of a small chapel to the west, which formerly existed, there
                    is now no trace. The arches of the windows and doors are round, and the figure
                    of some of them is more than half of the circle, which is an undoubted proof of
                    their antiquity. The priory, which was founded by Robert, bishop of St Andrews,
                    during the reign of Alexander I. in 1120, was of great extent, and richly
                    endowed. The prior had precedence of all abbots and priors, and on festival days
                    had a right to wear a mit <hi rend="superscript"> re</hi> and all episcopal
                    ornaments. The walls of the pre-cìnct<pb break="no" facs="nls:193097134" xml:id="kp-eb0703-7134-0121"/> are all that
                    now remain to mark the vast extent of this edifice. Part of the top of the great
                    altar towards ʹ the east end of the cathedral was discovered between 30 and 40
                    years ago, in consequence of an excavation made in the hope of finding concealed
                    treasure. At a much more recent period, the soil, which had for ages been
                    permitted to accumulate, having been removed, part of the pavement was laid
                    open, and several shafts of two rows of pillars parallel to each other, by which
                    it is supposed that galleries in the inside of the walls had been supported. The
                    other religious houses were, that of the Dominicans, founded in 1274 by Bishop
                    Wishart; another of Observantines, founded by Bishop Kennedy, and finished by
                    his successor Patrick Graham in 1478; and, according to some, the Carmelites had
                    a fourth. Immediately above the harbour stood the collegiate church of
                    Kirk-heugh, originally founded by Constantine III., who, retiring from the
                    world, became here a Culdee. From its having been first built on a rock, it was
                    styled <hi rend="italic">Proepositura Sanctae</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">
                    Mariae</hi><hi rend="italic">de Rupe.</hi></p><p>On the east side of the city are the remains of the castle, on a rock overlooking
                    the sea. This fortress was founded about the year 1200, by Roger, one of the
                    bishops of St Andrews, and was repaired towards the end of the 14th century by
                    Bishop Trail, who died in it in 1401. He was buried near the high altar of the
                    cathedral, with this singular epitaph:</p><p>Hic fuit ecclesiae directa columna, fenestra Lucida, thuribulum redolens, campana
                    sonora.</p><p>The castle was the residence of Cardinal Beaton, who, after the cruel execution
                    of the celebrated reformer George Wishart in front of it, was afraid of the fury
                    of the people; and his knowledge of this, joined to his apprehension of an
                    invasion from England, induced him to strengthen the fortifications, with a view
                    of rendering the castle impregnable. In this fortress he was surprised and
                    assassinated by Norman Lesley, aided by fifteen others. Early in the morning of
                    May 29, 1546, they seized on the gate of the castle, which had been left open
                    for the workmen who were finishing the fortifications; and having placed
                    sentinels at the door of the cardinal’s apartment, they awakened his numerous
                    domestics one by one, and, turning them out of the castle, without violence,
                    tumult, or injury to any other person, inflicted on Beaton the death he justly
                    merited. The conspirators were immediately besieged in this castle by the
                    regent, earl of Arran; and although their strength consisted of only 150 men,
                    they resisted his efforts for five months, owing more to the unskilfulness of
                    the attack than the strength of the place, for in 1547 the castle was reduced
                    and demolished, and its picturesque ruins serve as a land-mark to mariners. The
                    entrance to the castle, and the window out of which it is said Cardinal Beaton
                    leaned to witness the cruel martyrdom of George Wishart, are still pointed
                    out.</p><p>The parish church is a spacious structure, 162 feet in length by 63 in breadth,
                    and is large enough to accommodate 2500 persons. It contains a lofty monument of
                    white marble, erected in honour of Archbishop Sharpe, who, in revenge for his
                    oppressive conduct, was murdered by some of the exasperated reformers of that
                    day. On this monument is a rude piece of sculpture representing the tragical
                    scene of the murder. To the north is situated the college church, which belongs
                    to the united college of St Salvator and St Leonard. It was founded in 1458 by
                    Bishop Kennedy, and contains a beautiful tomb of its rounder, who died in 1466;
                    which is a fine specimen of leftθ <hi rend="superscript"> 0t</hi> ^ <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> * <hi rend="superscript"> c</hi> architecture of that
                    period. About the year 683, on opening this tomb, six highly ornamented silver
                    maces Were discovered, which had been concealed there in times of trouble, three
                    of which are still preserved in the university, and three were sent to the other
                    universities of Scotland. On the top is represented our Saviour; around are
                    angels with the instruments of his passion. With these are shown some silver
                    arrows, with large silver plates affixed to them, on which are inscribed the
                    arms and names of those who were victors in the annual competitions of archery,
                    which were regularly held until within these few years. Golf is now the reigning
                    game. That sport, and foot-ball, were formerly prohibited by an act of
                    parliament passed in the reign of James II. in 1457, as interfering too much
                    with the acquisition of dexterity in archery, an accomplishment in those days of
                    much consequence to the safety of the state. The statute has been long obsolete,
                    and the inhabitants, and the students who attend the university, have full
                    permission to enjoy this elegant amusement.</p><p>The celebrated university of this city was founded in 1411 by Bishop Wardlaw. It
                    consisted formerly of three colleges. 1. St Salvator’s was founded in 1458 by
                    Bishop Kennedy. This was a handsome building, with a court or quadrangle, which
                    is 230 feet long by 150 wide, and a gateway surmounted by a spire 156 feet high.
                    On one side is the church; on another what was the library of St Salvator’s; the
                    third contains apartments for students; the fourth is unfinished. The buildings
                    connected with the college being in a state of great decay, a grant has been
                    made by government for erecting a new structure. Part of this building will soon
                    be finished, and the remainder, it is expected, will be immediately after
                    commenced. When it is completed it will be in a high degree elegant and
                    commodious. 2. St Leonard’s College was founded by Prior Hepburn in 1522. This
                    is now united with the last, and the buildings sold, and converted into private
                    houses. 3. New or St Mary’s College was established by Archbishop Hamilton in
                    1552; but the house was completed by Archbishop Beaton. This is said to have
                    been the site of a celebrated school long before the establishment even of the
                    university, where several eminent clergymen taught gratis the sciences and
                    languages; but it was called the <hi rend="italic">New College,</hi> because of
                    its late erection into a divinity college by the archbishop. The buildings of
                    this college have been substantially repaired, and with great taste.</p><p>The university is governed by a chancellor,—an office which it was originally
                    intended should be permanently exercised by the archbishop of St Andrews.
                    Subsequent to the Reformation, the chancellor has been elected by the two
                    principals and the professors of both colleges.</p><p>The rector is the next great officer, to whose care are committed the privileges,
                    discipline, and statutes of the university. The colleges have their principals,
                    and professors of different sciences, who are indefatigable in their attention
                    to the instruction and the morals of the students. The place possesses, in its
                    pure and salubrious air, and in its extensive grounds for exercise, very great
                    advantages for the education of youth. In St Salvator’s College are taught the
                    languages, philosophy, and the sciences. St Mary’s, which stands in a different
                    part of the town, is reserved exclusively for theology. The classes and
                    discipline of the two colleges are quite distinct, each having its respective
                    principal and professors. They have a common library, which is entitled to a
                    copy of every work entered in Stationers Hall, and which now (1830) contains
                    upwards of 40,000 volumes. An addition has been in the course of last season
                    made to the library, which was much required, in consequence of the great
                    increase of the number of books.</p><p>Seventy-five bursaries or endowments belong to the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193097147" xml:id="kp-eb0703-7147-0122"/>university, and
                    are conferred on the students. Of these, 58 belong to the United, and 17 to the
                    New College. The number of students at St Andrews never exceeded 300 at any
                    period. During the present year (1830) they amount to 190 at both colleges—149
                    at the United College, 41 at St Mary’s.</p><p>The trade of St Andrews was once very considerable. So late as the reign of
                    Charles I. it had thirty or forty trading vessels, and carried on a considerable
                    herring and white fishery, by means of busses, in deep water, which had for ages
                    been a most profitable branch of commerce, and a source of wealth. During the
                    troubles which followed the death of this monarch, this whole coast, and St
                    Andrews in particular, became a scene of murder and rapine; and every town
                    suffered in proportion to its magnitude and opulence. St Andrews was required to
                    pay a contribution of L.1000, which the inhabitants, after being plundered, were
                    not able to raise: a composition of L.500 was accepted, which was raised by a
                    loan at interest, and has remained a burden upon the corporation, it is
                    believed, ever since.</p><p>The harbour of St Andrews is artificial: it is guarded by piers, and is safe and
                    commodious; but it is difficult of access, having a narrow entrance, and being
                    exposed to the east winds, which raise a heavy sea on the coast. The shore of
                    the bay is low; and, in the storms of winter, vessels are frequently driven on
                    it and lost.</p><p>St Andrews had a manufactory of sail-cloth to some extent, but it is now
                    discontinued. The game of golf being much practised here, there is a manufactory
                    of golf balls, which, after supplying the home consumption, sends about 9000
                    annually to other parts. The shipping of the port consists of about eleven
                    vessels, which are employed in the coasting trade. St Andrews is a royal
                    borough, uniting with Cupar, Perth, Dundee, and Forfar, in returning a member to
                    parliament.</p><p>According to early traditions, St Andrews owes its origin to a Greek monk,
                    Regulus, who having been warned in a vision to visit Albion, was shipwrecked in
                    the bay about the end of the fourth century. He was hospitably received,
                    according to these ancient accounts, by the king, who presented him with his own
                    palace, and built near it the church of St Regulus, the remains of which are
                    still to be seen. At this time the place was styled <hi rend="italic">Mucross,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">land of boars.</hi> All around was
                    forest, and the lands bestowed on the saint were called <hi rend="italic">Byrehid.</hi> The boars equalled in size the ancient Erymanthian; as a proof of
                    which, two tusks, each sixteen inches long and four thick, were chained to the
                    altar of St Andrew. The king changed the name to <hi rend="italic">Kilrymont,</hi> and established here the first Christian priests of the
                    country, called <hi rend="italic">Culdees.</hi> The church was supreme in the
                    kingdom of the Picts, Hungus having granted to God and St Andrew that it should
                    be the head and mother of all the churches in his dominion. He also directed
                    that the cross of St Andrew should become the badge of the country. In 818,
                    after the conquest of the Picts, he removed the episcopal see to St Andrews, and
                    the bishop was styled <hi rend="italic">maximus Scotorum episcopus.</hi> In 1471
                    it was erected into an archbishopric by Sextus IV. at the intercession of James
                    III. In 1606 the priory was suppressed; and in 1617 the power of election was
                    transferred to eight bishops, the principal of St Leonard’s College, the
                    archdeacon, the vicars of St Andrews, Leuchars, and Cupar. This see contained
                    the greater part of the shire of Fife, with a part of the counties of Perth,
                    Forfar, and Kincardine, and a great number of parishes, churches, and chapels in
                    other dioceses.</p><p>The town of St Andrews was erected into a royal borough by David I. in the year
                    1140, and its privileges afterwards confirmed. The charter of Malcolm II.,
                    written on a small bit of parchment, is preserved in the tolbooth.' Here also
                    are kept the silver keys of the city, which, f <hi rend="subscript"> 0r</hi>
                    form’s sake, are delivered to the king if he should visit the place, or to a
                    victorious enemy in token of submission. In this place, likewise, is to be seen
                    the enormous axe with which, in 1646, Sir Robert Spotswood and other
                    distinguished loyalists were beheaded. The town underwent a siege in 1337, at
                    which time it was possessed by the English and other partisans of Baliol; but
                    the loyalists, under the earls of March and Fife, made themselves masters of it
                    in three weeks, by the help of their battering machines. It is 9 miles E. of
                    Cupar, and 39 N. N. E. of Edinburgh. The population, according to the last
                    census, was 4899. Long. 2. 50. W. Lat. 56. 19. 33. N. <hi rend="smallcaps">(f.)</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>