<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-8629-0236-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANQUETIL DU PERRON (Abraham Hyacinth)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 3, page 236</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bt4s">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p86d">Avesta</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4125q97k">Upas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z61d">Hyacinth</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1008230">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1162064">Upas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:964459">Hyacinths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1155691">Travelers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193098629" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ANQUETIL DU PERRON <hi rend="smallcaps">(Abraham
                    Hyacinth)</hi></label>, brother of the subject of the preceding article, was
                    horn at Paris on the 7th of December 1731. Having distinguished himself as a
                    student at the university of that city, and acquired a considerable knowledge of
                    the Hebrew language, he was invited to Auxerre by Μ. de Caylus, then the bishop
                    of that diocese. This prelate made him study theology, first at the academy of
                    his diocese, and afterwards at that of Amersfort, near Utrecht; but Anquetil had
                    no desire to embrace the ecclesiastical vocation, and devoted himself with
                    ardour to the study of the different dialects of the Hebrew, and of the Arabic
                    and Persian. Neither the solicitations of Μ. de Caylus, nor the hopes of rapid
                    preferment, bad the power to detain him at Amersfort after he thought he had
                    acquired every thing that was to be learnt there. He returned to Paris, where
                    his diligent attendance at the Royal Library; and his ardour in the prosecution
                    of his favourite studies, attracted the attention of the Abbé Sallier, keeper of
                    the manuscripts, who introduced him to the acquaintance of his associates and
                    friends, whose united exertions procured for him a small salary, as student of
                    the oriental languages. He had scarcely received this appointment, when, having
                    accidentally laid his hands on some manuscripts in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Zend,</hi> he formed the project of a voyage to India, with the view of
                    discovering the works of Zoroaster. At this period an expedition was preparing
                    at the port of L’Orient, which was destined for India. Μ. du Perron, however,
                    applied in vain, through his protectors, for a passage; and seeing no other
                    means of accomplishing his plan, he enlisted as a common soldier, and set out
                    from Paris, with a knapsack on his back, on the 7th of November 1754. His
                    friends procured his discharge; and the minister, affected by this romantic zeal
                    for science, granted him a free passage, a seat at the captain’s table, and a
                    salary, the amount of which was to be fixed by the governor of the French
                    settlements in India. After a passage of nine months, Anquetil landed, on the
                    10th of August 1755, at Pondicherry. Here he remained no longer than was
                    necessary to make himself master of the modern Persian, and then hastened to
                    Chandernagore, where he thought to acquire the Sanserit. But in this he was
                    deceived; and he was on the point of returning, when a serious complaint
                    threatened his life. He had scarcely escaped from this danger, when war was
                    declared between France and England; Chandernagore was taken; and Anquetil
                    resolved to return to Pondicherry by land. After a journey of one hundred days,
                    in the course of which he encountered many adventures, and suffered many
                    hardships, he arrived at Pondicherry. Here he found one of his brothers who had
                    arrived from France, and embarked with him for Surat; but, with the view of
                    exploring the country, he landed at Mahe, and proceeded on foot. It was at Surat
                    that he succeeded, by perseverance and address in his intercourse with the
                    native priests, in acquiring a sufficient knowledge of the languages to enable
                    him to translate the Ðietibnary called the <hi rend="italic">Vedidad-Sade,</hi>
                    and some other works. From thence he proposed going to Benares, to study the
                    languages, 'antiquities, and sacred laws of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193098642"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0703-8642-0237"/>Į the Hindoos; but the capture of Pondicherry
                    obliged him ∣∙to return to France. He accordingly embarked on board ʹ an English
                    vessel, and landed at Portsmouth in the month of November 1761. After spending
                    some time in London, and visiting Oxford, he set out for Paris, where he arrived
                    on the 4th of May 1762, without fortune or the desire of acquiring any, but
                    esteeming himself rich in the possession of one hundred and eighty oriental
                    manuscripts, besides other curiosities. The Abbé Barthelemy, and his other
                    friends, procured for him a pension, with the title and appointments of
                    Interpreter for the oriental languages at the royal library. In 1763 the Academy
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Belles</hi><hi rend="italic">Lettres</hi> received him
                    among the number of its associates; and from that period he devoted himself to
                    the arrangement and publication of the materials he had collected during his
                    eastern travels. In 1771 he published a work in three volumes 4to, under the
                    title of <hi rend="italic">Zend-Avesta,</hi> containing collections from the
                    sacred writings of the Persians, among which are fragments of works ascribed to
                    Zoroaster; and he accompanied this work with an account of the life of that
                    sage. This publication must be considered as constituting a very important
                    accession to our stores of oriental literature. A recent historian, and very
                    competent judge, refers to the <hi rend="italic">Zend-Avesta,</hi> as certainly
                    the most authentic source from which we can derive information regarding the
                    religion and institutions of the great Persian legislator. (Sir John Malcolm’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Hist, of Persia,</hi> vol. i. p. 193, note.) To the <hi
                    rend="italic">Zend-Avesta</hi> Μ. du Perron prefixed a discourse, in which he
                    treated the university of Oxford, and some of its learned members, with ridicule
                    and disrespect. Mr (afterwards Sir William) Jones replied to these invectives in
                    an anonymous letter, addressed to the author, written in French, with uncommon
                    force and correctness of style, but at the same time with a degree of asperity
                    which could only be justified by the petulance of Μ. du Perron. In 1778 he
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Législation Orientale,</hi> in 4to, a work in
                    which he controverts the system of Montesquieu, and endeavours to prove that the
                    nature of oriental despotism has been misrepresented by most authors; that in
                    the empires of Turkey, Persia, and Hindostan, there are codes of written law
                    which equally bind the prince and subject; and that in these three empires the
                    inhabitants possess both movable and immovable property, which they enjoy with
                    perfect security. His <hi rend="italic">Recherches Historiques</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ct</hi><hi rend="italic">Géographiques sur</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >l’lnde</hi> appeared in 1786, and formed part of Thieffenthaler’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Geography of India.</hi> They were followed in 1789 by his
                    treatise <hi rend="italic">De la Dignité</hi><hi rend="italic">du
                    Commerce</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">de l’Etat du</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Commercant.</hi> The Revolution seems to have greatly affected
                    him. During that period he abandoned society, shut himself up in his study, and
                    devoted himself entirely to literary seclusion. In 1798 he published <hi
                    rend="italic">L’</hi><hi rend="italic">Inde en</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Rapport</hi><hi rend="italic">avec l’Europe,</hi> &amp;c. in 2 vols. 8vo; a
                    work which is more remarkable for its virulent invectives against the English,
                    and for its numerous misrepresentations, than for the information which it
                    contains, or the soundness of the reflections which it conveys. The spirit of
                    the work, indeed, may be ascertained from the summary of its contents stated in
                    the title-page, in which the author professes to give a detailed, accurate, and
                    terrific picture of the English Machiavelism in India; and he addresses his work
                    in a ranting bombastic dedication to the <hi rend="italic">Manes</hi> of Dupleix
                    and Labonrdonnais. In 1804 he published a Latin translation from the Persian of
                    the <hi rend="italic">OupneKhat</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Upa-ηιsehadα, i.
                    e.</hi> Secrets which must not be revealed, in 2 vols. 4to. On the
                    re-organization of the Institute, Μ. Anquetil was elected a member, but soon
                    afterwards gave in his resignation. He died at Paris on the 17th of January
                    1805. <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, <hi rend="subscript"> t</hi>. ... . √. . . .
                    , <hi rend="subscript"> u 7</hi>..,</p>
                <p>Besides the works we have already enumerated,] Μ.</p>
                <p>Anquetil read to the academy several memoirs on subjects connected with the
                    history and antiquities of the East, At the time of his death he was engaged in
                    revising a translation of the <hi rend="italic">Travels of Father Paulin de
                    St</hi><hi rend="italic">Barthelemy</hi><hi rend="italic">in India,</hi> which
                    work was continued by Μ. Silvestre de Sacy, and published in 1808,'in 3 vols.
                    8vo. He also left behind him a great number of manuscripts, among which his
                    biographers particularly notice the translation of a Latin treatise <hi
                    rend="italic">on the Church,</hi> by Doctor Legros, in 4 vols. 4to.</p>
                <p>From the preceding narrative our readers will be enabled to form some notion of
                    the character of Anquetil du Perron. Among his countrymen he is regarded as one
                    of the most learned men of the 18th century. He certainly distinguished himself
                    by a very ardent and disinterested zeal in the prosecution of those studies to
                    which he dedicated the labours of a long life; but the lustre of his literary
                    character was obscured by a very‘absurd vanity, and the most inveterate
                    prejudices. In a Discourse addressed to the Asiatic Society at Calcutta, in
                    1789, Sir William Jones speaks of him as “having had the merit of undertaking a
                    voyage to India, in his earliest youth, with no other view than to recover the
                    writings of Zeratust (Zoroaster), and who would have acquired a brilliant
                    reputation in France, if he had not sullied it by his immoderate vanity and
                    virulence of temper, which alienated the goodwill even of his own countrymen.”
                    In the same Discourse he affirms that Μ. Anquetil most certainly had no
                    knowledge of the Sanscrit.—See <hi rend="italic">Biographie Universelle;</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Monthly Review,</hi> vol. lxi.; Lord Teignmouth’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of Sir William Jones.</hi> (κ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
