<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-0371-0370-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARAEOMETER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 3, page 370</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="19" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r13x">Cupping</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55q5x">Liquids</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39307">Equality</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn8c">Mark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="19" ref="fasttopic:1131392">Stalking</term>
                    <term n="19" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:885243">Cupping</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:999671">Liquidation</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:999687">Liquids</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193100371" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARAEOMETER</label> (composed of <hi rend="italic"
                    >agaιος,</hi><hi rend="italic">levis,</hi><hi rend="italic">tenuis,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">μtτξον, measure),</hi> a measure of the comparative density and
                    rarity of bodies. The name does not occur in ancient authors; hydroscopium and
                    baryllium being the ancient names of the instrument. This instrument was known
                    in the civilized part of the Roman empire about the year 400, as appears from
                    the fifteenth epistle of Synesius, addressed to Hypatia, daughter of Theon; and
                    to Hypatia some modern writers have erroneously ascribed its invention. The
                    instrument is also described in some verses annexed to Priscian; and the
                    principles on which its operation is founded are to be seen in the treatise of
                    Archimedes on floating bodies <hi rend="italic">(De Hurnido</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Insidentibus).</hi> The term, as used by writers on natural
                    philosophy, is chiefly applied to instruments which are made to float, so as to
                    indicate the specific gravity of the liquids in which they are placed: the <hi
                    rend="italic">pese liqueur</hi> and hydrometer, in common use for measuring the
                    specific gravity of vinous spirits, are instruments of this kind.</p>
                <p>A floating body displaces a portion of the liquid, the weight of which is equal
                    to its own weight: the liquid acting upwards with a force equal to this weight,
                    and the weight of the body acting downwards with the same force, equilibrium
                    takes place. If the body be afterwards placed in a liquid of less density, the
                    part of the body immersed will be greater than when the body was in the more
                    dense liquid, because it requires a greater volume of this less dense liquid to
                    equal the weight of the floating body. The absolute weights of two bodies being
                    the same, their specific gravities are in the inverse ratio of their volumes — =
                    ^ <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi>, when <hi rend="italic">G</hi> is put for the
                    specific <hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic">V</hi> gravity of the first
                    body, <hi rend="italic">g</hi> for that of the second; <hi rend="italic">V</hi>
                    for the volume of the first, and <hi rend="italic">ν</hi> for the volume of the
                    second. On this principle the common hydrometer is constructed;, the instrument
                    described by Synesius is also of this kind. In order that a small difference in
                    the volume immersed may be sensible, the part which is intersected by the
                    surface of the fluid is in the form of a very slender cylinder, the great bulk
                    of the instrument being always immersed in the liquid. At the inferior part is a
                    small ball, containing mercury or small lead shot, which serves as ballast,
                    bringing the centre of gravity low, so that the instrument may float erect, and
                    without much lateral oscillation. The common hydrometers are made of glass, and
                    sometimes of brass, or tin or pewter, and some have been made of amber as
                    objects of curiosity. When made of glass, a scale, inscribed upon paper, is
                    inserted in the cylindrical stalk: the division of the scale at which the
                    surface of any liquid intersects the stalk, denotes the specific gravity of that
                    liquid. The divisions of the sea e should be formed by immersing the instrument
                    in liquids of known specific gravity, and marking a number corresponding to that
                    specific gravity opposite to each division· The specific gravities of water and
                    alcohol mixed in various proportions have been accurately ascertained by Mr <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193100384" xml:id="kp-eb0703-0384-0371"/>Gilpin. (See his
                    Tables, and Dr Blagden’s paper in the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical
                    Transactions.)</hi> On immersing the instrument in a mixture of known
                    proportions of these two liquids, the point at which the surface intersects the
                    stalk is to be marked with the number expressing the specific gravity of the
                    mixture taken from the table. Some hydrometers, such as that constructed by the
                    French chemist Beaumé, and which is much used in France under the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">Aréomètre</hi><hi rend="italic">de Beaumé,</hi> have the scale
                    divided into equal parts, so that the divisions do not correspond as they ought
                    to do with the numbers which express specific gravities.</p>
                <p>In the araeometer of Fahrenheit, the uncertainty arising from the erroneous
                    division of the scale is obviated, no division being required. The form of the
                    instrument is the same as that just described, only at the top there is a small
                    cup, into which weights are put, so as to bring the surface of the denser liquid
                    to a fixed mark on the stalk: when the instrument is placed in a liquid of less
                    density, some of the weights are taken out till the mark again comes to the
                    surface. Suppose the weight of the instrument and of the weights in the cup
                    together equal to 1000, when sunk to the mark in distilled water at a certain
                    temperature; the instrument is now taken out of the water and immersed in a
                    liquid, where 10 must be taken out of the cup in order to bring the mark to the
                    surface; the immersion in water indicates that a volume of water weighs 1000;
                    the immersion in the second liquid shows that an equal volume of this liquid
                    weighs 990; when the volumes of bodies are equal, the specific gravities are
                    directly as the absolute weights <hi rend="italic">GW . .</hi></p>
                <p>— = —, consequently the specific gravity of the second liquid is 990, that of
                    water being 1000. To save computation, it is convenient· that the whole weight
                    of the apparatus, when in distilled water at a certain temperature, should be
                    represented by 1000; for this purpose the instrument-maker divides the weight of
                    the apparatus into 100u parts, and forms small weights consisting of one, two,
                    three, &amp;c. of these 1000th parts, the relation of which to the ounce or
                    pound does not require to be known; the weights thus formed are to be used with
                    the instrument.</p>
                <p>The araeometer of Nicholson is like that of Fahrenheit, with the addition of an
                    immersed cup, whereby it is rendered proper for ascertaining the specific
                    gravity of solids. Suppose that it requires 400 grains m the exterior cup to
                    sink the instrument to the mark in distilled water, at 60 degrees of
                    Fahrenheit’s thermometer; hi, The body under examination is put into the
                    exterior cup, and weights (say grains) are taken out till the mark again stands
                    at the surface; this gives the absolute weight of the body 300 grains. 2<hi
                    rend="italic">dly,</hi> The body is then put into the immersed cup S, taking
                    carc to brush off any air-bubbles with a hair pencil, and in order to bring the
                    mark to the surface, a weight (say 100 grains) must be put into the exterior
                    cup, that is, the. weight of a volume of water equal to the body is 100 granu.
                    Ιhe first part of the process gave the absolute weight of the body 300 grams;
                    and the volumes being equal, the specific gravities are as the absolute weights;
                    conse quently the specific gravity of the body is 300, that of watereing 100.
                    This araeometer may be used to find the specific gravity of liquids: the
                    process, in that case, is the same as that described above in speaking of the
                    araeometer of Fahrenheit. The araeometer of Nicholson is useful to the
                    mineralogist for ascertaining the specific gravity of minerals, the specific
                    gravity being a convenient character for distinguishing one kind of mineral from
                    another. It is sometimes made of tinned iron, but where more accuracy is
                    required, copper is the material employed. When put together, it does not exceed
                    a foot in length, and therefore is suited to form a part of the travelling
                    mineralogist’s apparatus.</p>
                <p>Some araeometers have been constructed with the exterior cup C placed underneath,
                    and supported by a stirrup, whose upper part is fixed to the stalk of the
                    araeometer, as represented on the margin. This is done in order to place the
                    centre of giavity low, that the araeometer may thereby float more steadily. The
                    araeometer floats in a cylindrical vessel fitted to the size of the stirrup, and
                    this vessel is supported on a stand so formed as not to interfere with the free
                    motion of the stirrup.</p>
                <p>The araeometer ofDeparcieux is like the common hydrometer, only the ball is much
                    more voluminous. This renders it capable of indicating the small difference
                    which exists in the specific gravity of the water of different springs, for
                    which purpose Deparcieux proposed it. The dilatation of the large glass bulb by
                    heat has a considerable effect on the operation of this instrument, and this
                    dilatation being different in different instruments, renders the results
                    inaccurate. The different araeometers above mentioned have the advantages of
                    being easily made and easily carried about; but where the specific gravity of a
                    body is required with the greatest accuracy recourse must be had to the
                    hydrostatic balance, which ought to be constructed with the utmost care by the
                    most skilful artist.</p>
                <p>The following algebraic expressions may serve to elucidate some of the properties
                    of the araeometers hitherto spoken of:</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">g</hi> is the specific gravity of water, whi ch is 1000 ounces
                    when the ounce and foot are taken as unities, 1000 ounces avoirdupois being the
                    weight of a cubic foot of water.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">z</hi> is the diameter of the wire-stalk of the araeometer.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">&lt;κ</hi> is 3∙14&lt;15, &amp;c. the number expressing the
                    periphery of a circle whose diameter is 1.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">⅜πz</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> is the surface of
                    a transverse section of the wirestalk.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">v</hi> is the volume of the bulb or body of the araeometer. w
                    is the whole weight of the araeometer.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">x</hi> is the length of the stalk that is plunged in the
                    water.</p>
                <p>’ rws <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> is the volume of the immersed portion of the
                    stalk.</p>
                <p>When the araeometer floats in equilibrio, it displaces a volume of water equal to
                    its own weight; therefore, ∕ . i <hi rend="subscript"> θ</hi> ∖ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> w</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >⅛(</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> w</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">&lt;l</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ν</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >)</hi><hi rend="italic">w</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">gυ</hi>
                    is the difference between the quantity of water displaced by the whole
                    araeometer, and the quantity displaced by the bulb alone; <hi rend="italic"
                    >w</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">gv,</hi> therefore, is the
                    volume of water displaced by the immersed portion of the stalk. As the diameter
                    of the stalk <hi rend="italic">z</hi> is very small, the cylinder of water <hi
                    rend="italic">w</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">gv,</hi> which has
                    <hi rend="italic">z</hi> for its diameter, is likewise very small, and does not
                    exceed a few grains in weight; therefore a small variation in w (the weight of
                    the araeometer), or in <hi rend="italic">g</hi> (the density of the liquid),
                    occasions a great variation in <hi rend="italic">x</hi> (the length of the
                    immersed part of the stalk). The value of <hi rend="italic">x</hi> changes
                    rapidly, when <hi rend="italic">z</hi> (the diameter of the stalk) is
                    changed.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193100397" xml:id="kp-eb0703-0397-0372"/>
                <p>because the value of a? is divided by z <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, which is
                    the square of a very small quantity. ∙</p>
                <p>When the araeometer is immersed in a liquid of another specific gravity <hi
                    rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >,</hi> then the equation is x <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> = • l’ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi>. (Lĩ ’. subtract the value of <hi rend="italic"
                    >x</hi><hi rend="italic                superscript"> x</hi> from that of <hi
                    rend="italic">x,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Q CP ) ∙ . .</hi> there results <hi
                    rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi
                    rend="italic           superscript"> χ</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi>-,—÷-^∙ This
                    is the diminution <hi rend="italic">g g</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    l</hi><hi rend="italic">πz</hi> ’ in the length of the immersed part of the
                    stalk, which takes place when the araeometer is transferred to a liquid of a
                    greater density. By this formula it is seen, that the sensibility of the
                    araeometer, that is, the length of the portion of the stalk which emerges upon
                    transferring the araeometer to a denser liquid, is augmented, in the first place
                    by increasing <hi rend="italic">w</hi> (the weight of water displaced by the
                    araeometer), that is, by increasing the volume of the body of the araeometer;
                    secondly, by diminishing <hi rend="italic">z</hi> (the diameter of the stalk),
                    which is in the denominator of the value of <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> consequently, the faculty of the
                    araeometer to show the different densities of liquids is in w general expressed
                    by the fraction</p>
                <p>With regard to the vertical mobility of the araeometer, when put in motion by
                    placing a small weight 5 in its cx-</p>
                <p>-, . , „ <hi rend="subscript"> 1 1</hi> 4(w + s— <hi rend="italic">gv)</hi> tenor
                    cup, substitute <hi rend="italic">w</hi> + s for <hi rend="italic">w;</hi> then,
                    <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >=</hi> 7, 5 ∙</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">2gνz</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">∙</hi></p>
                <p>4fw —- <hi rend="italic">OV)</hi> Take the difference between this and <hi
                    rend="italic">x = -~</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 5</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >2,g</hi><hi rend="italic           superscript"> c</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >sz</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> t</hi></p>
                <p>4s this difference is <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    1</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">x =</hi> 5; which shows that the
                    length of the portion of the stalk that a small weight <hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi> s .</p>
                <p>causes to immerge is proportional to or in the direct ratio of the small weight,
                    and in the inverse ratio of the square of the diameter of the stalk.</p>
                <p>When the small weight, the density of the liquid, and the length of that part of
                    the stalk which is submerged on adding the small weight, are known, then this
                    equation will give the diameter of the stalk in known quantities ⅛= <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 8</hi> √ <hi rend="underline">*</hi> z.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">gπ{x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">x)</hi></p>
                <p>When the weight of the whole araeometer is known in ounces, &amp;c., and the
                    specific gravity of one of two liquids (water, for instance) is known, the
                    difference of specific gravity between that liquid and another liquid may be had
                    in known quantities.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">g</hi> is the specific gravity of water.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> χ</hi> is the specific
                    gravity of the second liquid, which is here supposed more dense.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">w</hi> is the weight of the volume of water displaced by the
                    araeometer.</p>
                <p>í is a small additional weight placed on the exterior cup to keep the araeometer,
                    when placed in the denser liquid, at the same point of immersion as when it
                    floated in water.</p>
                <p>w + s is the whole weight of the apparatus when floating in the denser
                    liquid.</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> rι x∙ 1 <hi rend="italic">wA-s . . . , , ,
                    .</hi></p>
                <p>The equation <hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> λ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">=</hi><hi rend="italic">——</hi> is obtamed by substι-</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">v + -</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> χ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">xπz</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i j</hi> tuting <hi
                    rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> χ</hi> for <hi rend="italic"
                    >g,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">w</hi>-ļ- .9 for <hi rend="italic">w,</hi> in the
                    equation <hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic">= w .</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> ν</hi> + ± <hi rend="subscript"> χi</hi>- <hi rend="subscript"
                    > z</hi> ~ <hi rend="superscript"> W nc 1 WaS</hi> 8 <hi rend="superscript"> wen
                    a</hi> b° <hi rend="superscript"> ve</hi> ∙ Divide by <hi rend="italic"
                    >g</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi><hi rend="superscript"> w</hi> 1,1 <hi
                    rend="italic                     subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi
                    rend="italic                     superscript"> λ</hi><hi rend="italic">w</hi> +
                    s , . ,</p>
                <p>—, —ļ——¾, and there results — = , which gives the <hi rend="italic">v +
                    -įx¶z</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ĩo</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> b</hi> proportion of the
                    density of the second liquid to the den-</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">•</hi><hi rend="italic">cp^</hi><hi rend="italic">∩ s</hi> sity
                    of water. By subtraction there results — = —</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">9 τo</hi><hi rend="italic">SCI</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >g</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> t</hi><hi rend="italic">— g</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">= '~</hi>; that is, the difference between the density of the
                    second liquid and the density of water is found by multiplying the small weight
                    by 1000 ounces and dividing this product by the number of ounces, &lt;⅛. which
                    denote the weight of the araeometer uncharged.</p>
                <p>Small bodies, whose specific gravities are known, serve] to indicate the specific
                    gravity of a liquid in which theye just remain suspended. In this way beads of
                    glass three or four tenths of an inch in diameter are employed, each of which
                    remains suspended in spirit of a certain specific gravity. The density of each
                    of these beads, or rather bubbles, is regulated by the proportion between the
                    quantity of glass and the cavity which the glass incloses. A piece of bees-wax,
                    whose specific gravity, by the addition of lead, is such that the body is just
                    suspended in brine of a known density, is used as an araeometer in some salt
                    works. The fresh egg of a common fowl is just sustained by brine of a certain
                    specific gravity, and is employed as an araeometer.</p>
                <p>The araeometer of Homberg consists of a phial withal slender neck and glass
                    stopper, so made that it may be filled ♭ with the same volume of different
                    liquids. It is employed in finding the specific gravity of liquids in the
                    following way: 1st, The phial is filled with distilled water, and then weighed
                    in a balance; <hi rend="italic">⅝fly,</hi> the phial is emptied, and again
                    filled with the liquid whose specific gravity is sought, and weighed in a
                    balance: the proportion of the weight of the contents of the phial in the second
                    process to the weight of its contents in the first, is the specific gravity
                    required. The inconveniences which have prevented this method from being
                    generally used are, the difficulty of completely cleaning the phial from the
                    liquid which it previously contained; the difficulty of filling the phial
                    exactly with the same volume of each liquid; and the variation of the volume of
                    the phial from changes of temperature.</p>
                <p>The pressure of the atmosphere supports columns ofl different fluids, whose
                    height is inversely as the densities of the fluids. An araeometer has been
                    constructed on this principle. It is a curved tube, one leg of which has its
                    extremity immersed in water, and the other in the spirit whose density is to be
                    tried. On rarefying the air in the tube, by means of a pump fixed at the upper
                    part of the tube, the water ascends in one leg, and the spirit in the other; the
                    height of the column of each liquid being measured by a scale of equal parts
                    applied to each branch of the tube. This instrument has never come into use,
                    probably on account of the difficulty of ascertaining with precision the points
                    at which the surfaces of the columns are terminated. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(bb.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
