<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0703-7147-0122-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">ANDREWS, James Pettit</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 3, page 122</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795510">Accounts</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tq5rg4g">Coins</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h10">Sermons</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193097147" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">ANDREWS, <hi rend="smallcaps">James Pettit</hi></label>, a
                    late English historian and miscellaneous writer, was the younger son of Joseph
                    Andrews, Esq. of Shaw-house, near Newbury, Berks, where he was born in the year
                    1737. He was educated privately, and is said to have discovered an early taste
                    for literature and the fine arts. He joined the Berkshire militia when they were
                    first called out, being then about 18 or 19, and held the rank of lieutenant in
                    that regiment until it was disbanded. On the institution of the new system of
                    London police, he was appointed one of the commissioners for the district of
                    Queen’s Square and St Margaret’s, Westminster, and discharged the duties of that
                    office with great industry and integrity until his death, which took place at
                    his house in London, on the 6th of August 1797, in the 60th year of his age. He
                    married Miss Ann Penrose, daughter of the Rev. Mr Penrose, late rector of
                    Newbury, by whom he had two sons and a daughter. He seems to have possessed a
                    cheerful and social disposition, and enjoyed the conversation of a large circle
                    &gt;of literary acquaintance, who frequently met at his house and experienced
                    his hospitality.</p><p>Mr Andrews appears to have devoted a considerable portion of his time to literary
                    pursuits; and he is the author of several works which are not undeserving of
                    notice. The first publication upon which we find him employed is an edition of
                    the poems of his friend and relation Penrose, in 1781; to which he prefixed an
                    introduction, containing a short account of the life and character of the
                    author. His first original production, so far as we have been able to ascertain,
                    was a pamphlet in behalf of the chimneysweepers’ apprentices in 1788, which is
                    said to have led to the act of parliament passed not long afterwards for the
                    purpose of ameliorating the condition of that unfortunate class of beings. In
                    1789 he published <hi rend="italic">Anecdotes, Ancient and Modern,</hi> 8vo, a
                    work of pleasantry, in the composition of which he acknowledged having received
                    assistance from the late lauréat Mr Pye, the facetious antiquary Captain Grose,
                    and others. To this volume he added a Supplement in 1790.</p><p>The most extensive work undertaken by Mr Andrews was his <hi rend="italic">History of Great Britain, connected with the Chronology of Europe; with
                    Notes,</hi> &amp;c. The first volume, which commences with Caesar’s invasion,
                    and ends with the deposition and death of Richard II., was published in 1794 in
                    4to. A second volume, in which the history is continued from the deposition and
                    death of Richard H∙tθ the accession of Edward VI., appeared in 1795. The plan of
                    this work is new, and in some respects singular; a certain portion of the
                    history of England is given on one page, and a corresponding portion of the
                    contemporaneous history of Europe on the one opposite. The notes consist oţ a
                    variety of curious and amusing particulars, not immediately connected with the
                    main story. Appendixes are also added at proper intervals, containing an account
                    of the state of literature, science, religion, government, man <pb break="no" facs="nls:193097160" xml:id="kp-eb0703-7160-0123"/>ners, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> at different periods. The author, however, did not
                    live to complete this curious and extensive work, no more of it having appeared
                    than the two volumes above mentioned. In 1796 he published a continuation of
                    Henry’s <hi rend="italic">History of Britain,</hi> in one volume 4to and two
                    volumes 8vo.</p><p>The other productions of this author are, <hi rend="italic">An Account of Saxon
                    Coins found in Kintbury Churchyard, Berks,</hi> printed in the seventh volume of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Archaeologia</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Account of Shaw,</hi> in Mr Mores’s Berkshire Collections; <hi rend="italic">The Savages of Europe,</hi> a popular French novel, which he
                    translated, and illustrated by prints from his own designs. Mr Andrews was also
                    a frequent contributor to the <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine.</hi> See
                    the <hi rend="italic">Gen. Biog. Diet,</hi> by Chalmers; <hi rend="italic">Introduction to Poems by the Bev. Thomas Penrose,</hi> 1781; <hi rend="italic">Gent. Mag.</hi> for 1797 and 1801; and Lysons’ <hi rend="italic">Supplement to
                    Environs of London,</hi> 1811. (κ.)</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Andrews,</hi><hi rend="italic">Lancelot,</hi> bishop of
                    Winchester, was born at London in 1555, and educated at Cambridge. After several
                    preferments he was made bishop, first of Chichester, then of Ely, and in 1610
                    was raised to the see of Winchester. This very learned prelate, who was
                    distinguished by his piety, charity, and integrity, may be justly ranked with
                    the best preachers and scholars of his age. He appeared, however, to much
                    greater advantage in the pulpit than he does now in his works, which abound with
                    Latin quotations and trivial witticisms. He died at Winchester House in
                    Southwark, September 27, 1626, in the 71st year of his age, and was buried in
                    the parish church of St Saviour’s, where his executors erected to him a very
                    fair monument of marble and alabaster, on which is an elegant inscription in
                    Latin, written by one of his chaplains. His most popular works are, his <hi rend="italic">Sermons,</hi> his <hi rend="italic">Lectures on the Ten
                    Commandments,</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Orphan Lectures,</hi> each forming
                    a folio volume. There is a collection by Felix Kyngston, of some other pieces
                    written by him, which was published in 4to in 1629.</p></div></body></text></TEI>