<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0124-0113-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">OZONE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 113</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="22" ref="fasttopic:1049655">Oxygenators</term>
                    <term n="22" ref="fasttopic:1049616">Oxygen</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1073293">Potassium</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="22" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wr3t">Oxygen</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc8d">Potassium</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vd7z">Graining</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n124/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">OZONE</label> has been defined and to some extent discussed
                    under the heading <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> vol. v. p. 481.</p>
                <p>From the time of Van Marum (1785) at least it was known that the passage of
                    electric sparks through air is accompanied by the production of a peculiar
                    smell; but the cause of this remained unknown until 1840, when Schönbein
                    observed that a similar smell is exhibited by electrolytic oxygen (as obtained
                    in the electrolysis of acidulated water), and also develops in the atmosphere of
                    a vessel in which phosphorus suffers spontaneous oxidation at ordinary
                    temperatures in the presence of water. The three kinds of odoriferous gas, he
                    found, had the power of decomposing iodide of potassium with liberation of
                    iodine, and they agreed also in their behaviour to other reagents, whence he
                    concluded that in all the three cases the smell was owing to the same peculiar
                    substance which he called <hi rend="italic">ozone</hi> (from <hi rend="italic"
                    >oζεw,</hi> to emit an odour). Numerous experiments confirmed his first
                    impression that ozone is chemically similar to, though distinctly different
                    from, chlorine, but he got no further towards establishing its nature. Having
                    found, however, that dry phosphorus produces no ozone, and that ready-made ozone
                    is destroyed by being passed through a heated glass tube, he surmised that ozone
                    was a peroxide of hydrogen. This surmise was seemingly raised to a certainty by
                    an investigation of Baumert’s, who found that electrolytic (ozonized) oxygen,
                    when deozonized by heat, yields water, and ascertained that the weight of water
                    thus produced amounted to H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O = 18 parts for every
                    41 = 4 × 127 parts of iodine which the same quantity of gas would have liberated
                    if it had been deozonized by iodide of potassium. This, if true, would prove
                    that ozone is H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>,—a
                    conclusion which passed current as an established fact, in reference to
                    electrolytic ozone at least, until Andrews showed that Baumert’s result was
                    founded upon incorrect observations. The merit of having discovered the true
                    elementary composition of ozone belongs to Marignac and De la Rive, who proved
                    that it can be produced, as easily and abundantly as in any other way, by the
                    electrification of absolutely pure oxygen gas, whence it at once followed
                    that—unless oxygen be a compound of two or more unknown elements—ozone cannot be
                    anything else than an allotropic modification of oxygen.</p>
                <p>With regard to the relations of the two kinds of oxygen to one another, our
                    present knowledge is derived mainly from the work of Andrews and Prof. Tait. The
                    first important result which they arrived at was that the ozonization of pure
                    oxygen gas involves a contraction, and that consequently ozone is denser than
                    oxygen gas. Presuming (with all their contemporaries) that in the de-ozonization
                    of oxygen by iodide of potassium all the substance of the ozone is taken up by
                    the reagent with elimination of its equivalent of iodine, they sought to
                    determine the density of ozone by comparing the weight of oxygen-matter which
                    goes into the iodide of potassium with the contraction involved in the process.
                    But they obtained variable results. As their methods became more and more
                    perfect, the weight of unit volume of ozone grew greater and greater, and at
                    last stood at ∞. In other words, what they found and established finally was
                    that the removal of ozone from oxygen by means of -iodide of potassium involves
                    no change of volume whatever, although de-ozonization by heat always leads to a
                    (permanent) increase of volume. This result, to them and everybody else,
                    appeared very singular; but Andrews, after a while, found the correct
                    explanation. Supposing at a certain temperature and pressure one volume of
                    ordinary oxygen contains <hi rend="italic">a</hi> grains of matter, then one
                    volume of ozone, being denser, contains a greater quantity of matter, say <hi
                    rend="italic">a+x</hi> grains; when the gas acts on iodide of potassium, the <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> grains come out as one volume of oxygen, while the <hi
                    rend="italic">x</hi> grains of surplus oxygen vanish in the iodide. In the
                    decomposition by heat the <hi rend="italic">x</hi> grains of surplus oxygen of
                    course assume the form of a∙∕α volumes of additional oxygen gas. It is no
                    addition to Andrews’s explanation, but merely a close translation of it into the
                    language of Avogadros law, to say that, if oxygen (proper) consists of molecules
                    O <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, ozone must consist of molecules O <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> ⅛ (perhaps O <hi rend="subscript"> 2+</hi> 1), and tħat
                    in the iodide reaction this molecule breaks up into one molecule of oxygen gas
                    and <hi rend="italic">x</hi> atoms of oxygen which go to the reagent. What did
                    constitute a new discovery w¾s Berthelot’s important observation that the
                    conversion of ozone into ordinary oxygen involves an evolution of heat which
                    amounts to 29,600 units for every 16 parts of oxygen matter available for the
                    liberation of iodine from iodide of potassium. What the real density of ozone is
                    was made out with a high degree of probability by Soret. He took two equal
                    volumes of the same supply of ozonized oxygen, and in one determined the
                    contraction produced by shaking with oil of turpentine (which he assumes to take
                    away the ozone as a whole), while the other served for the (direct or indirect)
                    determination of the expansion involved in the destruction of the ozone by heat.
                    He found this increase to amount to half a volume for every one volume of ozone
                    present; hence one volume of ozone contains the matter of one and a half volumes
                    of ordinary oxygen, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> its density is 1'5 (if that of
                    ordinary oxygen is taken as unity), and its molecular weight is ⅜× O <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> =O <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> ∙ To check this result
                    Soret determined the rate at which ozone diffuses into air, and compared it with
                    the rate, similarly determined, for carbonic acid. From the two rates, on the
                    basis of Graham’s law, he calculated the ratio of the density of ozone to that
                    of carbonic acid, and found it in satisfactory accordance with O <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 3</hi>: CO <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> = 48: 44.</p>
                <p>From the facts that ozone is destroyed (z.e., converted into O <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>) at 270° (Andrews and Tait), and that this reaction is
                    not reversible, it at once follows that it is impossible to convert oxygen
                    completely into ozone by electric sparks. Supposing the ozonization to have gone
                    a certain way, each additional spark, besides producing ozone, will destroy some
                    of that previously produced.</p>
                <p>From Clerk Maxwell’s notion concerning the distribution of temperatures amongst
                    the molecules of a gas, it would follow that ozonized oxygen, even at ordinary
                    temperatures, will gradually relapse into the condition of plain oxygen,
                    because, although the temperature as indicated by the thermometer may be only
                    20° C. (say), there are plenty of molecules at temperatures above the
                    temperature of incipient dissociation (which of course lies below 270 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> c</hi>), and any ozone once destroyed will never come back.
                    But, be this as it may, the lower the temperature of the oxygen treated with
                    sparks the greater the chance of the ozone formed to remain aliVe. This idea
                    forms the basis of an important research by Hautefeuille and Chappuis, who, by
                    operating upon oxygen at very low temperatures, produced unprecedentedly large
                    percentages of ozone. By operating at 0° C. they produced a gas containing 14
                    <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 9 per cent, by weight of ozone (presumably
                    reckoned as O <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>), λvhile at - 23° the percentage rose
                    to 21 ’ 4. They subsequently (1882; <hi rend="italic">Compt. Rend.,</hi> xciv.
                    p. 1249) succeeded in producing even liquid ozone, by applying a pressure of 125
                    atmospheres to richly ozonized oxygen at -100° C. (the boiling point of
                    liquefied ethylene). Liquid ozone is of a dark indigo-blue colour, which, as
                    they tell us, is distinctly visible even in ordinary ozonized oxygen if it is
                    viewed in tubes about one metre long.</p>
                <p>According to Carius the coefficient of absorption of ozone by water of +1° C. is
                    about 0 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 8; that is to say, one volume of water of
                    1°, if shaken with excess of pure ozone at 1° and a pressure of 760 mm., would
                    absorb 0’8 volume of ozone measured dry at 0° and 760 mm. pressure. But it is
                    not certain that Carius’s determinations are correct.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Antozone.—</hi> According to a now obsolete notion of
                    Schönbein’s, ordinary oxygen gas is a compound of two kinds of oxygen of which
                    one is positively and the other negatively electrical. Ordinary ozone would be a
                    mixture of the two in equal parts; but certain peroxides, according to
                    Schönbein, contain the one kind, others the other. He supported his view by many
                    ingenious experimental arguments. Meissner and others, while adopting
                    Schönbein’s idea, somehow drifted into the notion that Schönbein’s two kinds of
                    oxygen correspond to two different substances, of which ordinary ozone is one.
                    They naturally searched for the other, and of course did not fail to discover
                    it; but their “antozone,” when critically looked into, turned out to be peroxide
                    of hydrogen. ’ (W. D.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
