<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0077-0068-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">OTTAWA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 18, page 68</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1202511">Buildering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1204832">Ontario</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205049">Victoria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n77/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">OTTAWA</label>, the capital of the Dominion of Canada, the
                    seat of the supreme court, and the residence of. the governor-general, of the
                    Church of England bishop of Ontario, and of the Roman Catholic bishop of Ottawa,
                    is situated in 45° 25' 59" N. lat. and 75° 42' 4" W. long., in the province of
                    Ontario, on the south bank of the Ottawa (which forms the boundary between
                    Ontario and Quebec), about 90 miles above its junction with the St Lawrence. By
                    the Canadian Pacific Railway, which here crosses from the north to the south
                    side of the Ottawa valley, the city is 120 miles west of Montreal (by the Canada
                    Atlantic Railway the distance is 116 miles), and from Prescott on the Grand
                    Trunk Railway and opposite Ogdensburg in New York it is distant 54 miles. The
                    site of Ottawa is sufficiently remarkable, extending as it does for about 2
                    miles along the Ottawa from the Chaudière Falls (where the river, narrowed to
                    200 feet, rushes down about 40 feet over a broken ledge of rock) to the falls at
                    the mouth of the Rideau (a right-hand tributary), and rising about midway into a
                    cluster of hills—Parliament or Barrack Hill (160 feet), Major’s Hill,
                    &lt;fcc.—which front the river with bold bluffs. The Rideau Canal, which skirts
                    the east side of Parliament Hill, separates what is known as the higher from the
                    lower town. To the south of Parliament Hill is the more commercial part of the
                    city, stretching westward to the suburb of Rochester ville and the lumber
                    district round the Chaudière Falls. Major’s Hill, east of the canal, is laid out
                    as a public park; and</p>
                <p>Sandy Hill, to the south of the lower town, forms a residential quarter. Beyond
                    the Rideau river lies the suburban village of New Edinburgh, with the official
                    residence of the governor-general, Rideau Hall. The city of Hull too, on the
                    opposite side of the Ottawa, in the province of Quebec, may be regarded as a
                    suburb of the capital, with which it is connected by a suspension bridge. The
                    Government buildings, which give the name to Parliament Hill, rank among the
                    finest specimens of architectiιre in North America. The central pile, or
                    Parliament House, is in Italian Gothic, of the 13th century,—the material mainly
                    Potsdam sandstone from Nepean. The main (south) front is 470 feet long and 40
                    feet high, and in the middle over the principal entrance stands Victoria Tower,
                    180 feet high, and surmounted by a great iron crown. In the centre of the north
                    front is a semi-detached polygonal (almost circular) hall, 90 feet in diameter,
                    appropriated to the library. The corner stone of the building was laid by the
                    Prince of Wales in 1860. The total cost was about £1,000,000.</p>
                <p>(For ground plan and elevation see <hi rend="italic">The Builder,</hi> 1859 and
                    1860.) Two extensive blocks of departmental buildings are placed like detached
                    wings forming the sides of the quadrangle in front. Ottawa also contains a Roman
                    Catholic cathedral (Notre Dame) with twin spires 200 feet high, the Gray Nunnery
                    (the mother-house of the province of Ontario), the Black Nunnery, two convents,
                    a Roman Catholic college (Ottawa University), a Roman Catholic hospital, a
                    Protestant hospital, a Protestant ladies’ college, a city-hall, a custom-house,
                    the Government normal school for central Canada, the museum of the geological
                    survey, &amp;c. Besides being a great seat of the lumber trade, with saw-mills
                    and match-works, it manufactures flour, cast-iron wares, leather, and bricks.
                    The exports were valued at $1,683,148 in the fiscal year ending June 1874, and
                    at $2,444,723 in the fiscal year 1883,—the imports at the same dates amounting
                    to $1,495,169 and $1,562,344. The revenue arising from customs duties amounts to
                    about £260,000 annually. The population of the city (about half being Roman
                    Catholics and half Protestants) was 14,669 in 1861, 21,545 in 1871, and 27,412
                    in 1881. A mayor and board of aidermen constitute the municipal government, and
                    the city is divided into five wards—Wellington, Victoria, St George’s, By, and
                    Ottawa.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n78/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0078-0069"/>
                <p>Steamers ply in summer down to Montreal, and for about 200 miles up the river
                    above the falls, as well as through the Rideau Canal to Kingston.</p>
                <p>Philemon Wright of Woburn, in Massachusetts, settled in 1800 at the foot of the
                    portage round the Chaudière Falls on the site of Hull, and some twenty years
                    later he transferred his claim to the hills on the other side of the river to a
                    teamster named Sparks, who would have preferred the $200 due to him. Sparks
                    Street is now the fashionable commercial street of Ottawa. In 1827 the Rideau
                    Canal was constructed at a cost of $2,500,000 to connect lower Canada with
                    Kingston on Lake Ontario, and in that way prevent the necessity of gun-boats,
                    &amp;c., passing up the St Lawrence exposed to the enemy’s fire; and soon
                    afterwards a town sprang up at the Ottawa end, called Bytown after Colonel By,
                    R. E., who had surveyed the canal. At its incorporation as a city in 1854 Bytown
                    received the name of Ottawa. In 1858 the queen, to whom the matter was referred,
                    selected Ottawa as the capital of the Dominion of Canada, partly because of the
                    advantages of its site, and partly to avoid invidious preference among the rival
                    claims of Quebec, Montreal, Kingston, and Toronto. The first session of
                    parliament in Ottawa was opened in 1865.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
