<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0704-1785-0190-03" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">AUDRAN, Claude</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 190</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4280506x">Tents</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x362">Printing</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n76n">Prints</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65g52">Plating</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mn8h">Plate</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1147746">Tents</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1076612">Printing</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1076812">Prints</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:817559">Artists</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1057798">Perfection</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193191785" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">AUDRAN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Claude</hi></label>, a French
                    engraver, the first of the celebrated artists of that name, was the son of Louis
                    Audran, an officer belonging to the wolf-hunters in the reign of Henry IV. of
                    France, and was born at Paris in 1592. He never made any great progress in that
                    art, so that his prints are held in little or no estimation. Yet though he
                    acquired no great reputation by his own works, it was no small honour to him to
                    be the father of three great artists, Germain, Claude, and Girard; the last of
                    whom has immortalized the name of the family. Claude Audran retired from Paris
                    to Lyons, where he died in 1677.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Audran,</hi><hi rend="italic">Carl,</hi> a very eminent
                    engraver, was brother to the preceding, though some assert he was only his
                    cousin-german, and was born at Paris in 1594. In his infancy he discovered a
                    great taste and disposition for the arts; and to perfect himself in engraving,
                    to which he appears to have been chiefly attached, he went to Rome, where he
                    produced several prints which did him great honour. At his return he adopted
                    that species of engraving which is performed with the graver only. He settled at
                    Paris, where he died in 1674. The Abbé Marolles, who always speaks of this
                    artist with great praise, attributes 130 prints to him; amongst which, the
                    Annunciation, a middle-sized plate, upright, from Hannibal Carracci, and the
                    Assumption, in a circle, from Domenichino, are the most esteemed. In the early
                    part of his life he marked his prints with C, or the name of Carl, till his
                    brother Claude published some plates with the initial only of his baptismal
                    name, when, for distinction’s sake, he used the letter K, or wrote his name
                    Karl, with the K instead of the C∙</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Audran,</hi><hi rend="italic">Germain,</hi> the eldest son
                    of Claude, mentioned in the preceding article but one, was born in 1631, at
                    Lyons, where his parents then resided. Not content with the instructions of his
                    father, he went to Paris and perfected himself under his uncle Carl; so that,
                    upon his return to Lyons, he published several prints which did great honour to
                    his burin. His merit was in such estimation that he was made a member of the
                    academy established in that town, and chosen a professor. He died at Lyons in
                    1710, and left behind him four sons, all artists, namely, Claude, Benoit, John,
                    and Louis.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Audran,</hi><hi rend="italic">Claude,</hi> the second of
                    this name, and second son to Claude above mentioned, was born at Lyons in 1639,
                    and went to Rome to study painting, where he succeeded so well that on his
                    return he was employed by Le Brun to assist him in the Battles of Alexander,
                    which he was then painting for the king of France. He was received into the
                    Royal Academy in the year 1675, and died unmarried at Paris in 1684.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Audran,</hi><hi rend="italic">Girard,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Gerard,</hi> the most celebrated artist of the whole family of the
                    Audrans, was the third son of Claude Audran mentioned in a preceding article,
                    and was born at Lyons in 1640. He was taught the first principles of design and
                    engraving by his father; and, following the example of his brother, he went to
                    Paris, where his genius soon began to manifest itself. His reputation there
                    brought him to the knowledge of Le Brun, who employed him to engrave the Battles
                    of Constantine, and the Triumph of that emperor; and for these works he obtained
                    apartments at the Gobelins. At Rome, whither he went for improvement, he is said
                    to have studied under Carlo Maratti, in order to perfect himself in drawing; and
                    in that city, where he resided three years, he engraved several fine plates.
                    That great encourager of the arts, Μ. Colbert, was so struck with the beauty of
                    Audran’s works whilst he resided at Rome, that he persuaded Louis XIV. to recall
                    him. On his return he applied himself assiduously to engraving, and was
                    appointed engraver to the king, from whom he received great encouragement. In
                    the year 1681 he was named counsellor of the Royal Academy. He died at Paris in
                    1703, without male issue.</p><p>“He was,” says the Abbé Fontenai, “the most celebrated engraver that ever existed
                    in the historical line. We have several subjects which he engraved from his own
                    designs, that manifested as much taste as character and facility. But in the
                    Battles of Alexander he surpassed even the expectations of Le Brun himself.”
                    These consist of three very large prints, lengthwise, each consisting of four
                    plates, which join together, from Le Brun; namely, The Passage of the Granicus,
                    The Battle of Arbela, and Porus brought to Alexander after his defeat. To this
                    set are added two more large prints lengthwise, on two plates each, also from Le
                    Brun, namely, Alexander entering the Tent of Darius, and The Triumphal Entry of
                    Alexander into Babylon. The former was engraved by Girard Edelink, and the
                    latter by Girard Audran. It is to be remarked of all these plates, that those
                    impressions are generally most esteemed which have the name of Goyton the
                    printer marked upon them. The Pest, from Peter Mignard, a large plate,
                    lengthwise, also deserves particular notice. In the first impressions, the
                    figure in the clouds is Juno with her peacock behind her; in the latter the
                    peacock is obliterated, and the wings of an angel are added to the figure.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Audran,</hi><hi rend="italic">Benoit,</hi> the second son
                    of Germain Audran, was born at Lyons in 1661, where he learned the first
                    principles of design and engraving under the instruction of his father. But soon
                    after going to Paris, his uncle Girard Audran took him under his tuition; and
                    Benoit so greatly profited by his instructions, that though he never equalled
                    the sublime style of his tutor, yet he deservedly acquired great reputation. He
                    was honoured with the appellation of the king’s engraver, and received the royal
                    pension in 1715. He was made an academician, and admitted into the council. He
                    died unmarried at Louzouer, where he had an estate, in 1721. His manner was
                    founded upon the bold clear style of his uncle. His <pb break="no" facs="nls:193191798" xml:id="kp-eb0704-1798-0191"/>outlines were
                    firm and determined, his drawing correct, the heads of his figures in general
                    very expressive, and the other extremities well marked.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Audran,</hi><hi rend="italic">John,</hi> the third son of
                    Germain Audran, was born at Lyons in 1667, and, after having received
                    instructions from his father, went to Paris to perfect himself in the art of
                    engraving under his uncle Gerard Audran. At the age of twenty years the genius
                    of this great artist began to display itself in a surprising manner; and his
                    subsequent success was such, that in 1707 he obtained the title of engraver to
                    the king, and had a pension allowed him by his majesty, with apartments in the
                    Gobelins; and the following year he was made a member of the Royal Academy. He
                    was eighty years of age before he quitted the graver, and nearly ninety when he
                    died at the apartments assigned him by the king. He left three sons behind, one
                    of whom was also an engraver, as we shall see below. The best and most masterly
                    prints of this artist are those which appear not so pleasing to the eye at first
                    sight. In these the etching constitutes a great part; and he has finished them
                    in a bold rough style.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Audran,</hi><hi rend="italic">Louis,</hi> the last son of
                    Germain Audran, was born at Lyons in 1670, and thence went to Paris, after the
                    example of his brothers, to complete his studies in the school of his uncle
                    Girard. He died suddenly at Paris in 1712, before he had produced any great
                    number of prints by his own hand.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Audran,</hi><hi rend="italic">Benoit,</hi> the second
                    engraver of that name, was the son of John Audran, nephew to the former Benoit,
                    and also established at Paris. He engraved but few plates. It is necessary,
                    however, to be careful not to confound him with his uncle. But a little
                    attention will easily prevent this mistake; for the second Benoit is vastly
                    inferior to the first in point of merit. We have some few portraits by this
                    artist; and, among other plates, the Descent from the Cross, from a picture of
                    Poussin.</p></div></body></text></TEI>