<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0704-1746-0187-06" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">ATWOOD, George</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 187</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1027064">Motion</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:837261">Bowyers</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:813061">Arches</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1046845">Optics</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96091f">Arches</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tq5rk78">Optics</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hm8r">Bread</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193191746" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">ATWOOD, <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi></label>, an author
                    celebrated for the accuracy of his mathematical and mechanical investigations,
                    and considered particularly happy in the clearness of his explanations, and the
                    elegance of his experimental illustrations, was born in the early part of the
                    year 1746. He was educated at Westminster school, where he was admitted in 1759.
                    Six years afterwards he was elected <hi rend="italic">off</hi> to Trinity
                    College, Cambridge. He took his degree of bachelor of arts in 1769, with the
                    rank of third <hi rend="italic">wrangler;</hi> Dr Parkinson of Christ’s College
                    being senior of the year. This distinction was amply sufficient to give him a
                    claim to further advancement in his own college, on the list of which he stood
                    the foremost of his contemporaries; and in due time he obtained a fellowship,
                    and was afterwards one of the tutors of the college. He became master of arts in
                    1772, and in 1776 was elected a fellow of the Royal Society of London.</p><p>The higher branches of the mathematics had, at this period, been making some
                    important advances at Cambridge, under the auspices of Dr Waring, and many of
                    the younger members of the university became diligent labourers in this
                    extensive field. Mr Atwood chose for his peculiar department the illustration of
                    mechanical and experimental philosophy, by elementary investigations and ocular
                    demonstrations of their fundamental truths. He delivered, for several successive
                    years, a course of lectures in the observatory of Trinity College, which were
                    very generally attended and greatly admired. In the year 1784 some circumstances
                    occurred which made it desirable for him to discontinue his residence at
                    Cambridge; and soon afterwards Mr Pitt, who had become acquainted with his
                    merits by attending his lectures, bestowed on him a patent office, which
                    required but little of his attendance, in order to have a claim on the
                    employment of his mathematical abilities in a variety of financial calculations,
                    to which he continued to devote a considerable portion of his time and attention
                    throughout the remainder of his life.</p><p>The following, we believe, is a correct list of Mr Atwood’s publications:—1. A
                    Description of Experiments to illustrate a Course of Lectures; about 1775 or
                    1776, 8vo. 2. This work was reprinted, with additions, under the title of An
                    Analysis of a Course of Lectures on the Principles of Natural Philosophy.
                    Cambridge, 1784, 8vo. 3. A General Theory for the Mensuration of the Angle
                    subtended by two objects, of which one is observed by rays after two reflections
                    from plane surfaces, and the other by rays coming directly to the spectator’s
                    eye. Phil. Trans. 1781, p. 395. 4. A Treatise on the Rectilinear Motion and
                    Rotation of Bodies, with a Description of Original Experiments relative to the
                    subject. Cambridge, 1784, 8vo. 5. Investigations founded on the Theory of Motion
                    for determining the Times of Vibration of Watch Balances. Phil. Trans. 1794, p∙
                    119. 6. The Construction and Analysis of Geometrical Propositions, determining
                    the positions assumed by homogeneal bodies, which float freely, and at rest, on
                    a fluid’s surface; also determining the Stability of Ships, and of other
                    Floating Bodies. Phil. Trans. 1796, p. 46. 7. A Disquisition on the Stability of
                    Ships. Phil. Trans. 1798, p. 201. 8. A Review of the Statutes and Ordinances of
                    Assize which have been established in England from the 4th year of King John,
                    1202, to the 37th of his present Majesty. Lond. 1801, 4to. 9. A Dissertation on
                    the Construction and Properties of Arches. Lond. 1801,4to. 10. A Supplement to a
                    Tract entitled a Treatise on the Construction and Properties of Arclies,
                    published in the year 1801; and containing Propositions for determining the
                    Weights of the several Sections which constitute an Arch, inferred from the
                    Angles. Also containing a Demonstration of the Angles of the several Sections,
                    when they are inferred from the Weights thereof. To which is added, a
                    Description of Original Experiments to verify and illustrate the Principles in
                    this Treatise. With occasional Remarks on the Construction of an Iron Bridge of
                    one Arch, proposed to be erected over the river Thames at London. Part II. By
                    the author of the first part. Lond. 1804,4to. Dated 24th November 1803. 11. A
                    Treatise on Optics is mentioned by Nichols as having been partly printed by
                    Bowyer in 1776, butnever completed.</p><p>It may be very truly asserted that several of these works of Mr Atwood have
                    materially contributed to the progress of science, by multiplying the modes of
                    illustration which experimental exhibitions afford for the assistance of the
                    instructor; at the same time they can scarcely be said to have extended very
                    considerably the bounds of human knowledge, or to have demonstrated that their
                    author was possessed of any extraordinary talent or energy of mind in overcoming
                    great difficulties or in inventing new methods of reasoning. The <hi rend="italic">Analysis of a Course of Lectures</hi> has been little read; and it
                    bears evident marks of having been composed before Mr Atwood had acquired a
                    habit of accurate reasoning on physical subjects. In the first page, for
                    example, the forces of cohesion and gravitation are completely confounded; and
                    in the third we find the idea of perfect spheres touching each other in a
                    greater or less number of points, notwithstanding the appearance of precision
                    which the author attempts to maintain in his language.</p><p>The object of the paper on <hi rend="italic">Pefiectiοη</hi> is, to illustrate
                    and improve the construction of Hadley’s quadrant; and Mr Atwood proposes, for
                    some particular purposes in practical astronomy, two new arrangements of the
                    speculums, by which the rays are caused to move in different planes, and which
                    he considers as affording greater accuracy for the measurement of small angles
                    than the common form of the instrument, although not of general utility, nor
                    very easily adjusted for observation.</p><p>The treatise on <hi rend="italic">Pectilinear Motion and Potation</hi> exhi <pb break="no" facs="nls:193191759" xml:id="kp-eb0704-1759-0188"/>
                    bits a good compendium of the elementary doctrines of mathematical mechanics;
                    but it shows a great deficiency in the knowledge of the higher refinements which
                    had been introduced into that science by Daniel Bernoulli, and Euler, and
                    Lagrange. The properties of simply accelerated and retarded motion are first
                    discussed, and the phenomena of penetration experimentally examined; the laws of
                    varying forces are then investigated, and the properties of the pendulum
                    demonstrated; the vibrations of an elastic chord are calculated, “considering
                    the whole mass to be concentrated in the middle point,” as an approximation; and
                    then, instead of imitating and simplifying the elegant but complicated
                    demonstrations of the continental mathematicians, the author most erroneously
                    repeats, in the words of Dr Smith, the exploded doctrine, that “the string,
                    during any instant of its vibration, will coincide with the harmonic curve.” The
                    subject of a resistance, varying as the square of the velocity, is next
                    examined; and some useful experiments on the descent of bodies in water are
                    stated in confirmation of the theory. On this occasion, the author observes,
                    with regard to the formation of the different strata of the earth, that bodies
                    disposed to break into large masses, though specifically lighter, may easily
                    have descended more rapidly through a fluid, than denser but more brittle
                    bodies, so that the natural order of densities may thus have become inverted. He
                    next examines the theory of rotation, and relates some very interesting
                    experiments on rectilinear and rotatory motions; and he shows that Emerson and
                    Desaguliers were totally mistaken in asserting that “the momentum produced is
                    always equal to the momentum which produces it.” The last section of the work,
                    which is devoted to the subject of free rotation, is the most elaborate of the
                    whole; but it exhibits no material extension of the earlier investigations of
                    the Bernoullis and Professor Vince; nor does it contain the important
                    proposition of Segner, relating to the existence of three axes of permanent
                    rotation, at right angles to each other, in every body, however irregular.</p><p>Notwithstanding these partial objections, the work may still, in many respects,
                    be considered as classical. The paper on <hi rend="italic">Watch-balances</hi>
                    is principally intended to show the advantages which may be obtained, in Mr
                    Mudge’s construction, from the effect of subsidiary springs in rendering the
                    vibrations isochronous, their actions being limited to certain portions of the
                    arc of motion. If the author has here again omitted to follow the continental
                    mathematicians in some of their refinements of calculation, it must be confessed
                    that his view of the subject has, in this instance, not only the advantages of
                    simplicity, but also that of a nearer approach to the true practical state of
                    the question, than is to be found in the more complicated determinations which
                    had been the result of the labours of some of his predecessors.</p><p>. But, whatever may be the merits of these investigations, they appear to be far
                    exceeded in importance by the papers on <hi rend="italic">Ships,</hi> the first
                    of which obtained for its author the honour of a Copleian medal. Its principal
                    object is to show how much the stability of a ship will commonly vary, when her
                    situation with respect to the horizon is materially altered; and how far the
                    assumptions of theoretical writers, respecting many others of the forces
                    concerned in naval architecture, will generally differ from the true state of
                    these forces when they actually occur in seamanship. In the second part of the
                    investigation, some errors of Bouguer and of Clairbois are pointed out; and the
                    theoretical principles of stability are exemplified by a detailed calculation,
                    adapted to the form and dimensions of a particular vessel, built for the service
                    of the East India Company.</p><p>The latter years of our author’s life do not appear to have been productive of
                    any material advantage to science. His application to his accustomed pursuits
                    was unremitting, hut his health was gradually declining. He had no amusement
                    except such as was afforded by the continued exercise of his mind, with a change
                    of the object only; the laborious game of chess occupying, under the name of a
                    recreation, the hours which he could spare from more productive exertions. He
                    became paralytic some time before his death; and although he partially recovered
                    his health, he did not live to complete his 62d year.</p><p>His researches concerning the history of the <hi rend="italic">Assize of
                    Bread</hi> must have required the employment of considerable diligence and some
                    judgment in the discovery and selection of materials, although certainly the
                    subject was not chosen for the purpose of affording a display of talent. His
                    opinion respecting the operation of the assize, as favourable to the community,
                    may by some be thought to be justified by the want of success which has hitherto
                    attended the experiment on its suspension; but the advocates of that measure
                    would certainly not admit the trial of a year to be sufficient for appreciating
                    its utility.</p><p>The title-pages of the works on <hi rend="italic">Arches</hi> explain the
                    occasion on which they were brought forward, and at the same time exhibit a
                    specimen of the want of order and precision which seems to have begun to prevail
                    in the author’s faculties; while the works themselves betray a neglect of the
                    fundamental principles of mechanics, which is inconceivable in a person who had
                    once reasoned with considerable accuracy on mathematical subjects. An anonymous
                    critic, who is supposed to have been the late Professor Robison <hi rend="italic">(British Critic,</hi> vol. xxi. January 1804), very decidedly, and
                    at the same time very respectfully, asserted Mr Atwood’s error in maintaining
                    that there was no manner of necessity for the condition, that the general curve
                    of equilibrium of an arch should pass through some part of every one of the
                    joints by which it is divided; and in fact we may very easily be convinced of
                    the truth of this principle, if we reflect that the curve of equilibrium is the
                    true representative of the direction of all the forces acting upon each of the
                    blocks, and that, if the whole pressure be anywhere directed to a point situated
                    beyond the limit of the joint, there can be nothing whatever to prevent the
                    rotation of the block on the end of the joint as a centre, until some new
                    position of the block shall have altered the direction of the forces, or until
                    the whole fabric be destroyed. The critic has also very truly remarked that the
                    effects of friction have never been sufficiently considered in such
                    arrangements; but a later author, in an anonymous publication, has removed a
                    considerable part of this difficulty by showing that no other condition is
                    required for determining these effects than that every joint should be
                    perpendicular to the direction of the curve of equilibrium, either accurately or
                    within the limit of a certain angle, which is constant for every substance of
                    the same kind, and which he has termed the angle of repose. <hi rend="smallcaps">(l. l.)</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>