<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-1018-0131-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ATMOMETER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 131</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68d53">Tubes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh5s">Columns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tg7r">Rates</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1158581">Tubes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:868845">Columns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:896894">Doors</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193191018" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ATMOMETER</label> (from <hi rend="italic">αrμος, vapour,</hi>
                    and μsrgoι∕, <hi rend="italic">a measure),</hi> an instrument contrived by
                    Professor Leslie, for measuring the quantity of moisture exhaled from any humid
                    surface in a given time. It consists of a very thin ball of porous earthenware,
                    from one to three inches in diameter, having a small neck firmly cemented to a
                    long and rather wide tube of glass, to which is adapted a brass cap, with a
                    narrow collar of leather to fit close. Being filled with distilled or pure
                    water, the waste and descent of this column serves to indicate the quantity of
                    evaporation from the external surface of the ball. The tube is marked downwards,
                    through its whole length, by the point of a diamond, with divisions across it,
                    amounting to from 200 to 500, each of which corresponds to a ring of fluid,
                    that, spread over the whole exhaling surface, would form a film only one
                    thousandth part of an inch in thickness. This graduation is performed by
                    previously sealing one of the ends of the tube with wax, and introducing
                    successive portions of quicksilver, to mark every 20, 50, or 100 of those
                    divisions; being calculated of equal bulk to. disks of water, that have the
                    surface of the ball (exclusive of the neck) for their base, and so many thousand
                    parts of an inch for their altitude.</p>
                <p>The instrument, being thus constructed, has its cavity filled with pure water,
                    and its cap screwed tight, and is then suspended freely out of doors, sheltered
                    indeed from rain, but exposed to the action of the wind. The water transudes
                    through the porous substance of the ball just as fast as it evaporates from the
                    external surface; and <pb break="no" facs="nls:193191031"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0704-1031-0132"/>this waste is measured by the corresponding
                    descent of the liquid in the stem. At the same time, the column is suspended in
                    consequence of the tightness of the cap, and prevented from oozing so freely as
                    to drop from the ball. As the process of evaporation goes on, minute globules of
                    air, separated by the removal of atmospheric pressure from the body of the
                    water, or partly introduced by external absorption, continue to rise in fine
                    streamlets to the top, where they partially occupy the space left by the
                    subsidence of the fluid column. We need scarcely observe, that, after the water
                    has sunk to the bottom of the stem, it will be requisite again to fill the
                    cavity.</p>
                <p>It is a fact of main importance for the accuracy of the atmometer, that the rate
                    of evaporation is nowise affected by the quality of the porous ball, and
                    continues precisely the same whether the exhaling surface appears almost dry or
                    glistens with excess of moisture. This rate must evidently depend on the effect
                    of the dryness of the air combined with its quickness of circulation. In a close
                    room the instrument might therefore serve the purpose of an hygrometer; and,
                    placed out of doors, first screened, perhaps, for an hour, and then exposed
                    during an equal space of time, it would furnish data for calculating the
                    velocity of the wind.</p>
                <p>This instrument is of extensive application and great practical utility. To
                    ascertain readily and accurately the rate of evaporation from any surface, is an
                    important acquisition, not only in meteorology, but in agriculture, and in the
                    various mechanical arts. The quantity of exhalation from the surface of the
                    ground is not of less consequence than the measure of the fall of rain, and a
                    knowledge of it might often direct the farmer advantageously in his operations.
                    On the rapid dispersion of moisture depends the efficacy of drying-houses, which
                    are generally constructed on most erroneous principles.</p>
                <p>The atmometer, in its most compendious form, is admirably fitted for delicate
                    experiments on the evaporation which takes place in close vessels when absorbent
                    substances are introduced. Let the ball of the instrument, for example, be
                    immersed in air variously rarefied or condensed, under a receiver covering a
                    surface of sulphuric acid which has different degrees of strength; and, things
                    being thus disposed, on extracting the common air, and introducing hydrogen gas,
                    the rate of evaporation will then be nearly tripled.</p>
                <p>We shall close this notice with mentioning a striking fact, which shows the
                    necessity of extreme caution in all physical inquiries. Let the ball of an
                    atmometer be cemented to a narrow glass tube of three or four feet in length,
                    and the whole capacity filled with fresh distilled water. Now invert the
                    instrument upright in a basin of quicksilver, and secure it in that situation;
                    the quicksilver, following the column of water, will rise at first quickly, and
                    then by degrees more slowly, till it reaches, perhaps, an elevation of 28
                    inches, where it will remain stationary and afterwards sink down, when the
                    evaporation is nearly spent. Ice-water is raised in this way about 26 inches
                    only, and common water scarcely 24 inches; the air separated from such liquids
                    forming near the top of the ball a thin medium, which, by its elasticity,
                    counteracts in part the pressure of the external atmosphere supporting the
                    mercurial column. But a similar experiment, where the shoot of a vine was
                    cemented to a tube holding quicksilver, has been thought, by Dr Hales and Μ. Du
                    Hamel, quite conclusive in proving the <hi rend="italic">power</hi> of the
                    living principle of vegetation. It is obvious that the force of evaporation
                    alone was sufficient to explain the facts advanced by those ingenious
                    philosophers. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Meteorology. .</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">.
                    .</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
