<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0704-1031-0132-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">ATMOSPHERE</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 132</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="96" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term><term n="31" ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term><term n="23" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wr3t">Oxygen</term><term n="21" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term><term n="15" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s24m">Acids</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:939255">Gays</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1750261">Inch</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term><term n="96" ref="fasttopic:802066">Air</term><term n="23" ref="fasttopic:1049655">Oxygenators</term><term n="23" ref="fasttopic:1049616">Oxygen</term><term n="21" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term><term n="15" ref="fasttopic:795828">Acids</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193191031" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">ATMOSPHERE</label> is the name applied to the invisible
                    elastic medium which surrounds the globe of the earth to an unknown height. The
                    fluid of which it is composed is usually distinguished by the name of <hi rend="italic">air.</hi></p><p>It is well known that the pressure of the atmosphere is the cause of the rise of
                    the mercury in the barometer. Now the mean height of the barometer at the level
                    of the sea is 29∙82 inches. Hence it follows that the whole weight of the
                    atmosphere is equal to that of a sphere of mercury covering the whole surface of
                    the globe, and extending to the height of 29∙82 inches. The specific gravity of
                    mercury is 13∙568, and a cubic inch of water at the temperature of 60° weighs
                    very nearly 252∙5 grains. Hence a cubic inch of mercury will weigh 3425∙92
                    grains, or 0∙48956 lb. avoirdupois; and a column of the atmosphere reaching from
                    the surface of the earth to the utmost height to which that elastic fluid
                    reaches, and whose base is a square inch, weighs about 14*6 lbs. avoirdupois, or
                    exerts a pressure equal to 14*6 lbs. upon the earth or any substance on which it
                    rests.</p><p>The atmosphere consists chiefly of <hi rend="italic">air,</hi> an elastic fluid
                    composed of a mixture of four volumes of azotic with one volume of oxygen gas.
                    Now, from the most exact experiments hitherto made, it follows, that at the
                    temperature of 60°, and under the mean pressure of the atmosphere, a cubic inch
                    of air weighs 0∙311446 grains. If, therefore, the air were everywhere of the
                    same density, the height of the atmosphere above the surface of the earth would
                    be 328,021 inches, or 27,335 feet, or 5∙17 miles.</p><p>But air is an elastic fluid, the particles of which repel; each other with a
                    force varying inversely as the distance 1 of the centres of the particles from
                    each other. It is obvious, from this property of air, that its volume, and
                    consequently its density, will depend upon the pressure. The greater the
                    pressure, the smaller the volume. Those portions of the atmosphere that are in
                    contact with the earth are pressed upon by the whole portion above them. The air
                    at the top of a mountain is pressed upon by all the air above it; while all that
                    portion below it, or lying between the top of the mountain and the surface of
                    the sea, exerts no action on it whatever. This will be better understood by the
                    following diagram. Let ABCD be conceived to be a section of a vessel extending
                    from the surface of the earth at AB to the limit of the atmosphere CD, and
                    filled with air. Let this pillar of air be divided into an infinite number of
                    equal sections, each exceedingly thin, by the planes <hi rend="italic">er, gh,
                    ih, lm, no,</hi> &amp;c. Since the density of air is always as the compressing
                    force, it follows that the density of the stratum ABe∕ ’ is to that of the
                    density of the stratum <hi rend="italic">efgh</hi> as ç/CD to g∙ACD. So that the
                    difference between the pressures on <hi rend="italic">er</hi> and <hi rend="italic">gh</hi> is equal to the quantity of air <hi rend="italic">efgh.</hi> For the same reason, the difference be tween the pressures on <hi rend="italic">gh</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ih</hi> is equal to the quantity of
                    air <hi rend="italic">ghih</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and this ratio holds to
                    the very limit of the atmosphere. Therefore the densities of air in these spaces
                    are proportional to the quantities of which they themselves are the differences.
                    Now, when there is a series of quantities whose terms are proportional to their
                    own differences, both those quantities and their differences are in geometrical
                    progression; therefore the densities of the strata of air ABc∕i <hi rend="italic">efgh&gt; ghih, ihlm,</hi> &amp;c. are in geometrical
                    progression.</p><p>It is equally obvious that the heights of these equal spaces above AB, the
                    surface of the earth, are in arithmetical<pb break="no" facs="nls:193191044" xml:id="kp-eb0704-1044-0133"/> progression.
                    If <hi rend="italic">er</hi> be 1 inch above the earth’s surface, <hi rend="italic">gh</hi> will be 2 inches, <hi rend="italic">ik</hi> will be 3
                    inches, and so on. From all this we derive this remarkable conclusion, that <hi rend="italic">if the altitudes above the surface of the earth be taken in
                    arithmetical progression, the densities of the air at these altitudes will be in
                    geometrical progression decreasing. If</hi> at a certain altitude above the
                    earth’s surface the density of the air be one half what it is at the surface of
                    the earth, then at twice that altitude the density will be reduced to one fourth
                    of the density at the earth’s surface, and so on.</p><p>We can calculate the density of the atmosphere at all heights above the earth’s
                    surface very readily by means of a table of logarithms; for logarithms
                    constitute a set of numbers in arithmetical progression annexed to another set
                    of numbers which are in geometrical progression. If, therefore, we take
                    logarithms to represent the heights, the numbers to which these logarithms are
                    attached will represent the corresponding densities of the air. Suppose the
                    density of the air at one mile above the surface of the earth to be represented
                    by unity; then, from the common tables of logarithms, we easily deduce the
                    following densities at greater heights:</p><p>Height. Density.</p><p>1 mile 1*</p><p>2 0∙7943</p><p>3 0∙6309</p><p>4 0∙5011</p><p>5 0∙3981</p><p>6 0∙3163</p><p>7 0∙2511</p><p>8 0∙1995</p><p>9 0∙1585</p><p>10 0∙1260</p><p>So that at 10 miles the density of the air is only ∣-th of its density at one
                    mile above the surface of the earth.</p><p>These observations are sufficient to show that the height of the atmosphere above
                    the surface of the earth must greatly exceed five miles; but how much, we have
                    no data to enable us to determine.</p><p>Air possesses the property of refracting light; that is, of bending it from a
                    right line, and making it move in a curve. The consequence of this property is,
                    that the sun continues visible for some little time after he sets, and is seen
                    also a short time before he rises. Nor are we deprived of all the benefits of
                    his rays so long as any of them are capable of reaching the utmost limit of the
                    atmosphere. This light, brought to the surface of the earth by the refracting
                    power of the atmosphere, is called <hi rend="italic">twilight;</hi> and
                    mathematicians have endeavoured to determine the height of the atmosphere by
                    observing how many degrees below the horizon the sun must sink before twilight
                    ends. The result of this calculation is, that, at the height of 45 miles, the
                    atmosphere has no sensible power of refracting light. Its rarity therefore at
                    that height must be very great.</p><p>There is another way in which an estimate may be formed of the height of the
                    atmosphere. That height must ultimately depend upon the degree of rarity which
                    air is capable of bearing. The particles of air repel each other with forces
                    varying inversely as the distances of the centres of these particles from each
                    other. Now there is no great difficulty in rarefying air by means of a good
                    air-pump, till it is capable of supporting a column of mercury only γθth of an
                    inch in height. In such a case air is rarefied about 300 times, and the distance
                    between the centres of its particles is increased seven times; consequently the
                    force of repulsion between these particles is reduced to ^th of what it is when
                    air is of its mean density. If we suppose that this is the utmost limit to the
                    rarefaction of air (a supposition not at all likely to be strictly true), we are
                    entitled to infer that the atmosphere extends to the height of 40 miles, with
                    properties yet unimpaired by extreme rarefaction.</p><p>If matter be infinitely divisible, the extent of the atmosphere must be equally
                    infinite. But if air consists of ultimate atoms no longer divisible, then must
                    the expansion of the medium composed of them cease at that distance where the
                    force of gravity downwards upon a single particle is equal to the resisting
                    force arising from the repulsive force of the particles. If the air be composed
                    of indivisible atoms, our atmosphere may be conceived to be a medium of finite
                    extent, and may be peculiar to our planet; but if we adopt the hypothesis of the
                    infinite divisibility of matter, we must suppose the same medium to pervade all
                    space, where it would not be in equilibrio, unless the sun, the moon, and all
                    the planets, possess their respective shares of it condensed around them, in
                    degrees depending on the force of their respective attractions.</p><p>It is obvious that the atmosphere of the moon (supposing it to have any) could
                    not be perceived by us; for, since the density of an atmosphere of infinite
                    divisibility at her surface would depend upon the force of her gravitation at
                    that point, it would not be greater than that of our atmosphere when the earth’s
                    attraction is equal to that of the moon at her surface. Now this takes place at
                    about 5000 miles from the earth’s surface,—a height at which our atmosphere,
                    supposing it to extend so far, would be quite insensible.</p><p>But since Jupiter is fully 309 times greater than the earth, the distance at
                    which his action is equal to gravity must be as V ’ 309, or about 17∙6 times the
                    earth’s radius; and since his diameter is nearly 11 times greater than</p><p>17∙6 . . . .</p><p>that of the earth, 11 = 1∙6 times his own radius will be the distance from his
                    centre at which an atmosphere equal to our own should occasion a refraction
                    exceeding 1°. To the fourth satellite this distance would subtend an angle of
                    about 3° 37'; so that an increase of density to 3½ times our common atmosphere
                    would be more than sufficient to render the fourth satellite visible to us when
                    behind the centre of the planet, and consequently to make it appear on both
                    sides at the same time. It is needless to say that this does not happen, and
                    that the approach of the satellites, instead of being retarded by refraction, is
                    regular till they appear in actual contact; showing that there is not that
                    extent of atmosphere which Jupiter should attract to himself from an infinitely
                    divisible medium filling space.</p><p>If the mass of the sun be considered as 330,000 times that of the earth, the
                    distance at which his force is equal to gravitation will be √330,000, or about
                    575 times the earth’s radius; and if his radius be 111*5 times that of 575</p><p>the earth, then this distance will be —— = 5∙15 times lll∙o the sun’s radius. But
                    Dr Wollaston has shown, by the phenomena attending the passage of Venus very
                    near the sun on the 23d May 1821, that the sun has no sensible atmosphere. For
                    the apparent and calculated place of that planet were the same when the planet
                    was only 53' 15" from the sun’s centre. Μ. Vidal of Montpellier observed Venus
                    on the 30th May 1805, when her distance from the centre of the sun was only 46'
                    of space; and the apparent and calculated positions of that planet corresponded.
                    These observations leave no doubt that the sun has no sensible atmosphere, and
                    of course are inconsistent with the notion of the infinite divisibility of the
                    matter of our atmosphere.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193191057" xml:id="kp-eb0704-1057-0134"/><p>But if air consist of atoms incapable of further division, it is obvious that the
                    height of the atmosphere has a limit, and that limit is the place where the
                    gravitation of the atoms of air just balance the force of their repulsion. The
                    exact situation of this limit we cannot assign; but it cannot far exceed the
                    height of 45 miles above the earth’s • surface. Nor are the objections to this
                    determination drawn from meteors of sufficient weight to overturn the force of
                    the arguments just adduced. Dr Halley observed a meteor in the month of May
                    1719, whose altitude he computed to be between 69 and 73∣ English miles, its
                    diameter 2800 yards, and its velocity about 350 miles in a minute. The
                    celebrated meteor which appeared on the 18th August 1783 was not less than 90
                    miles above the surface of the earth. Its diameter must have been at least equal
                    to that of Dr Halley’s meteor, and its velocity certainly not less than 1000
                    miles in a minute. We know too little about the nature of these meteors to
                    connect them with the earth’s atmosphere. Indeed their velocity would lead to
                    the conclusion that they were revolving round the earth like satellites. The
                    light which they emitted, or the state of combustion which they exhibited, we
                    cannot explain. But the same difficulty occurs to account for the volcanoes
                    which have been seen in the moon, though we are quite certain that her
                    atmosphere is far too rare to support combustion.</p><p>The ancients thought that air constituted one of the four <hi rend="italic">elements,</hi> from which, in their opinion, all things originated; and this
                    doctrine continued prevalent till after the year 1774. It was during that year
                    that Dr Priestley first discovered oxygen gas, and showed it to be a constituent
                    of air. He determined several of its most remarkable properties, and called it
                    <hi rend="italic">dephlogisticated air,</hi> from a notion he entertained that
                    it was air deprived of <hi rend="italic">phlogiston.</hi> When <hi rend="italic">azotic</hi> gas, the other constituent of air, was discovered soon after, the
                    difference between its properties and those of oxygen gas could not fail to
                    strike the most careless observer. Bodies burn more rapidly, with much greater
                    splendour, and with the evolution of much greater heat, in oxygen gas than they
                    do in common air; while in azotic gas they cannot be made to burn at all.
                    Animals breathe oxygen gas without inconvenience, and they live much longer when
                    confined in a given bulk of it, than when in the same volume of common air; but
                    in azotic gas animals cannot live at all. When plunged into it they die of
                    suffocation, precisely as they would do if plunged under water. Dr Priestley
                    considered <hi rend="italic">oxygen</hi> gas as the pure elementary principle of
                    the ancients: common air was oxygen united to a certain quantity of phlogiston,
                    while azotic gas was oxygen saturated with phlogiston.</p><p>Scheele discovered both oxygen and azotic gas, without any knowledge of what had
                    been done in Britain; and he first drew the proper consequences from his
                    experiments. Air, in his opinion, consists essentially of a mixture of two
                    distinct elastic fluids, namely, oxygen and azote. He determined the properties
                    of each, and made a set of experiments to ascertain the relative volumes of each
                    contained in the atmosphere. The result of these experiments led him to the
                    conclusion that air is a mixture of</p><table cols="2"><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 27</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">volumes oxygen gas,</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"> 73</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">volumes azotic gas.</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">100.</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row></table><p>Lavoisier drew the same conclusions as Scheele had done; and he assures us that
                    he did so before he knew any thing of the researches and discoveries of the
                    Swedish chemist; and, what is very remarkable, he deduced the same volumes of
                    each gas, as constituents of the atmosphere, as Scheele had done. His
                    experiments were made in the same way as Scheele’s, and no doubt the mistakes of
                    both had the same origin.</p><p>It was in 1782 that Mr Cavendish, by a careful analysis of the air in the
                    neighbourhood of London, repeated frequently, and continued for a whole year,
                    determined that the volume of oxygen gas in atmospherical air is a good deal
                    smaller than Scheele and Lavoisier had made it. He found the constituents of air
                    to be—</p><table cols="2"><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">79∙18</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">volumes of azote,</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">20.82</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">volumes of oxygen.</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">100∙00.</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row></table><p>He found that these proportions never varied, though he analyzed air at different
                    periods of the day, and during all the different seasons of the year. Hence it
                    followed that the conclusions drawn by Dr Ingenhousz and others, that air
                    differs in the proportion of oxygen gas which it contains in different parts of
                    the earth, and that the salubrity of different places is connected with this
                    difference, were erroneous.</p><p>These experiments of Mr Cavendish were published in the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions</hi> for 1783; but they continued for many years
                    unattended to. The determination of Scheele and Lavoisier was universally
                    adopted; and the notion of Dr Ingenhousz, that the proportions between the
                    oxygen and the azote vary in different places, was also adopted. At last, in
                    1802, Berthollet announced that he had frequently analyzed the air in Egypt, by
                    absorbing its oxygen by means of a stick of phosphorus, and that he had always
                    found it a compound of</p><table cols="2"><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">79</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">volumes azote,</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">21</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">volumes oxygen.</cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">100.</cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row></table><p>Davy about the same time announced that he had tried air from the coast of
                    Africa, from Cornwall, and from the neighbourhood of Bristol, and had uniformly
                    found it composed of 79 volumes of azotic gas and 21 volumes of oxygen gas. It
                    was soon after analyzed in Edinburgh, in North America, and in France, with the
                    very same results. Gay-Lussac and Humboldt made a set of careful experiments to
                    determine the exact proportions of the two constituents, and confirmed the ratio
                    of 21 volumes of oxygen gas and 79 volumes of azotic gas. This ratio has been
                    generally adopted by chemists.</p><p>But there is a circumstance which cannot avoid striking an attentive observer;
                    namely, the very near approach of these numbers to 80 volumes azotic and 20
                    volumes oxygen gas, or four volumes azotic and one volume oxygen gas. It has
                    been deduced from a great variety of unexceptionable experiments, that a volume
                    of azotic gas is equivalent to an atom, while half a volume of oxygen gas is
                    equivalent to an atom. Hence four volumes azotic and one volume oxygen gases are
                    equivalent tô four atoms azote and two atoms oxygen, or to two atoms azote and
                    one atom oxygen. If, therefore, we were to admit that air consists of 80 volumes
                    azotic and 20 volumes of oxygen gases, it would follow that it is a compound of
                    two atoms azote and one atom oxygen. There is no evidence, indeed, that in air
                    the oxygen and azotic gases are chemically combined; the phenomena of air rather
                    lead to the conclusion that the two elastic fluids are merely mixed. And the
                    hypothesis of Dalton, that the particles of elastic fluids only repel particles
                    of their own kind, but that two elastic fluids are not mutually elastic to each
                    other, will enable us to account for their remaining intimately mixed, though
                    not chemically united.</p><p>It may seem immaterial, then, whether air be a mixture of azotic and oxygen gases
                    in the proportion of two atoms of the former to one atom of the latter, or in
                    the pro <pb break="no" facs="nls:193191070" xml:id="kp-eb0704-1070-0135"/>portion ( as c∏emists at present think) of 1∙975
                    atom azote and 1∙05 atom oxygen; or, as fractions of atoms can hardly be
                    admitted, of 79 atoms of azote and 42 atoms of oxygen. But certainly the
                    constitution of air must appear much simpler, and therefore much more agreeable
                    to contemplate, when viewed as consisting of the simple ratio of two to one,
                    than in the much more complex ratio of 79 to 42. The writer of this article was
                    induced in consequence to make a set of experiments with all possible attention
                    to accuracy, in order to deduce the volume of oxygen gas which it contains. The
                    air was collected in a grass field at some distance from houses and trees; and
                    this spot was selected as likely to furnish air containing as great a proportion
                    of oxygen as it ever contains, because grass and vegetables in general are
                    supposed to make up the waste of oxygen which the air sustains by the processes
                    of combustion and respiration,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>It is easy to show, that whether the oxygen thus withdrawn
                    from the air be supplied or not, no alteration in the proportions of the
                    constituents amounting to one millionth part can possibly have taken place. It
                    would therefore be quite insensible as far as our means of estimating it can
                    go.</p></note> and because the quantity of carbonic acid which it was likely to
                    contain would be too small to make any sensible alteration in the
                    experiments.</p><p>Ten measured volumes of this air were placed successively in a small glass jar,
                    over mercury, together with a stick of phosphorus. After the oxygen gas had been
                    removed by the phosphorus, the air was washed, and then measured. The following
                    table exhibits the result of these ten trials. 100 volumes of air consist of</p><p>Volumes of Volumes of</p><p>Azotic Gas. Oxygen Gas.</p><p>1 80∙927 19∙073</p><p>2 79∙246 20∙754</p><p>3 80∙504 19∙496</p><p>4 79∙532 20∙468</p><p>5 79∙85I 20∙149</p><p>6 79∙652 20∙348</p><p>7 79∙374 20∙626</p><p>8 80∙770 19∙230</p><p>9 79∙843 20∙157</p><p>10 80∙028 19∙972</p><p>Mean, 79∙9735, ............. ...20∙0265</p><p>The mean of these ten trials gives us air, a mixture of 79∙9735 volumes of azotic
                    and 20∙0265 volumes of oxygen gas. Now, this approaches as near 80 volumes of
                    azotic and 20 volumes of oxygen gas as the mode of experimenting permitted, for
                    the measure employed to determine the volume of the gases was about half an inch
                    in diameter. .</p><p>It was found, also, that when 100 volumes of air were mixed with 42 volumes of
                    hydrogen gas, and an electric spark passed through the mixture, the diminution
                    of bulk by the explosion was precisely 60 volumes; and this in three successive
                    experiments. Now, this diminution is owing to the oxygen of the air uniting with
                    the hydrogen gas and forming water, and water is a compound of two volumes
                    hydrogen and one volume oxygen gas. The third part of the diminution, therefore,
                    gives us the quantity of oxygen gas consumed. Now, the third of 60 is 20, which
                    constitutes therefore the volumes of oxygen gas in 100 volumes of air.</p><p>If we employ less than 42 volumes of hydrogen gas, the whole oxygen of the air is
                    not consumed. Thus, when we employ a mixture of 100 volumes of air and 40
                    volumes of hydrogen gas, the diminution of volume after combustion is only 57
                    volumes, which would indicate 19 volumes of oxygen instead of 20 in the air; so
                    that one volume of oxygen in this case has escaped combustion. When we mix more
                    hydrogen than 42 volumes with 100 volumes of common air, the diminution of
                    volume is somewhat greater than 60, and it goes on increasing slowly till the
                    volume of hydrogen gas is equal to that of the air. 100 volumes of air being
                    mixed with 100 volumes of hydrogen gas, and fired, the diminution amounted to 64
                    volumes. This would raise the amount of the oxygen in 100 volumes of air to 21∣^
                    volumes.</p><p>It is obvious from these experiments that absolute certainty cannot be obtained
                    by firing mixtures of air and hydrogen gas. The reason, doubtless, is, that when
                    the surplus of hydrogen is considerable, a little of it unites with the azotic
                    gas of the air, and forms ammonia, which, being absorbed by the water over which
                    the explosion is made, occasions a greater diminution of bulk than would have
                    proceeded from the simple union of all the oxygen of the air with hydrogen
                    gas.</p><p>Knowing the composition of air to be 80 volumes azotic and 20 volumes oxygen gas,
                    and knowing the atemic weight of these bodies to be azote 1∙75 and oxygen 1, we
                    can easily deduce the specific gravity of azotic and’ oxygen gases, reckoning
                    that of air unity, in the following manner :—</p><p>100 parts of air by weight must be a compound of oxygen 22∙22= <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> azote 77∙77=δ.</p><p>Let zr=specific gravity of oxygen gas, 2∕=specific gravity of azotic gas, a? +
                    4?y _ <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi> „ .</p><p>—— 1 and <hi rend="italic">x =</hi> 5 — 4?/ 5 <hi rend="superscript"> j</hi></p><p>. <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi>. 4α?/</p><p><hi rend="italic">X</hi>: 4?/:: <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">χ = —A-,</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> j</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi></p><p>Hence 5 — 4∕∕=^v^, from which we deduce <hi rend="italic superscript"> j</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic">5b</hi> 5×77∙77 .</p><p><hi rend="italic">y∑∑l</hi> “ ∩∙Q729</p><p><hi rend="superscript"> j</hi> 4«+46 4 × 22∙22 + 4 × 77∙77 ~~</p><p>and <hi rend="italic">χ</hi><hi rend="italic">=5</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi>
                    4?/=5 — 3∙8888= 1∙I 11İ.</p><p>Thus, the specific gravity of these two gases is as follows :—</p><p>oxygen gas 1∙1111, azotic gas 0∙9722.</p><p>That the specific gravity of these two gases hitherto determined by the most
                    careful experimenters is inaccurate, is obvious from this, that when we
                    calculate the specific gravity of air from them, it never comes out unity, but
                    usually higher than unity.</p><p>Besides oxygen and azotic gases, air contains likewise a little carbonic acid
                    gas. Who first made that remark we do not know; but n could not avoid being
                    inferred as soon as the cause of the difference between caustic and mild alkali
                    came to be known. Chemists at first stated the volume of carbonic acid gas in
                    the atmosphere at 1 per cent., but this determination was not founded on any
                    accurate experiments. Mr Dalton found the quantity much smaller than had been
                    stated by preceding experimenters. He observed, that if a glass vessel, filled
                    with 102,400 grains of rain water, be emptied in the open air, and 125 grains of
                    lime water poured in, and the mouth then closed, by sufficient time and
                    agitation the whole of the lime water is just saturated with the carbonic acid
                    which it finds in the inclosed volume of air; but 125 measures<pb break="no" facs="nls:193191083" xml:id="kp-eb0704-1083-0136"/> of lime water
                    require 70 measures of carbonic acid gas to saturate them. Hence it follows that
                    10,000 volumes of air contain 6 ’ 8 volumes of carbonic acid.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Phd.
                    Mag.</hi> (1st senes), xxiii, 354.</p></note> Thenard ascertained by means of
                    barytes water that 10,000 volumes of air which he examined contained 3∙91
                    volumes of carbonic acid.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Traite</hi><hi rend="italic">Eiern,</hi><hi rend="italic">de Chirn.</hi> i. 303.</p></note> This is little more than half
                    the quantity found by Mr Dalton. But by far the most complete set of experiments
                    on the volume of carbonic acid gas in the atmosphere was made by M. Saussure. He
                    abstracted the carbonic acid from given volumes of air by means of barytes
                    water. The carbonic acid was estimated by dissolving the precipitated carbonate
                    of barytes in muriatic acid, and throwing down the barytes in the state of
                    sulphate from the solution. The sulphate of barytes, ignited and weighed, easily
                    furnished the weight of carbonic acid; and this weight, together with the known
                    specific gravity of carbonic acid gas, furnished the data for determining its
                    volume. The experiments were continued for two years. Sometimes (indeed most
                    commonly) the air examined was collected at Chambeisy, a meadow about three
                    fourths of a league from Geneva, elevated about 52 <hi rend="superscript">
                    1</hi>- feet above the lake, and distant from it 820 feet. Its elevation above
                    the level of the sea is 1272 feet. It is dry, open, and consists of a clay soil,
                    a little inclined. The mean quantity of carbonic acid gas found in 10,000
                    volumes of air deduced from 104 observations made during both day and night, and
                    at all seasons, was 4∙15 volumes. The greatest quantity was 5∙74 volumes, and
                    the smallest 3∙13 volumes. The quantity of this gas is affected by rainy
                    weather; for when the soil is soaked with water, it has the property of imbibing
                    this gas. Hence in rainy seasons the quantity of carbonic acid gas in the
                    atmosphere is usually rather less than in dry seasons. On the contrary, it would
                    seem, from the observations of Saussure, that a continued frost has a tendency
                    to augment the quantity of carbonic acid in the atmosphere, doubtless because
                    the frozen and dry soil does not possess the property of absorbing it.</p><p>Air taken from the surface of the lake of Geneva, at an elevation of four feet,
                    was found in general to contain less carbonic acid than the air of Chambeisy;
                    but the same kind of variation, depending on the season of the year, was
                    observable in both. Air from the streets of Geneva, on the contrary, was found
                    rather more loaded with carbonic acyl than the air above Chambeisy; but the
                    difference was not great. The volume of carbonic acid in air from the tops of
                    mountains was found to be rather greater than that of carbonic acid in air from
                    the low country; and this difference is more remarkable in rainy than in dry
                    weather.</p><p>Wind has rather a tendency to augment the quantity of carbonic acid in the air in
                    low situations, doubtless by mixing together the air on the mountains and in the
                    valleys; but the difference is so small that it only becomes perceptible by a
                    long series of observations.</p><p>In general, the air over plains contains a greater proportion of carbonic acid
                    during the night than during the day; but this difference is not nearly so great
                    in winter as in summer. Indeed during that season of the year the quantity is
                    often as great or even greater during the day than during the night.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Ann.</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Chirn.</hi><hi rend="italic">et de
                    Phyt.</hi> xliv. 5.</p></note></p><p>The reason why the quantity of carbonic acid gas in the atmosphere is greater in
                    the superior strata than at the surface of the earth, is, probably, that
                    vegetables have the property of absorbing it and applying it to the purposes of
                    vegetation. Hence, doubtless, the reason why it does not increase,
                    notwithstanding the prodigious quantity of it constantly thrown into the
                    atmosphere by the breathing of animals and the combustion of fuel.</p><p>If we admit the mean volume of carbonic acid gas in air to be 0*000415, then the
                    true component parts of lθθ; volumes of air will be</p><p>Azotic gas 79∙9668</p><p>Oxygen gas 19 ’ 9917</p><p>Carbonic acid gas 0 ’ 0415</p><p>100.</p><p>This, doubtless, will somewhat modify the specific gravity of oxygen and azotic
                    gases; but the alteration is too insignificant to claim any attention.</p><p>Besides these three constituents, there is a fourth, name-, ly, the vapour of
                    water, from which air is never altogether ∣ free, and the proportion of which,
                    owing to causes which! cannot at present be fully explained, is continually
                    altering. The consequence of this is, that if we weigh air in its natural state
                    ever so often, we shall hardly ever find its weight in any two consecutive
                    experiments altogether the same. It is sufficiently known that water evaporates
                    spontaneously at all temperatures, and mixes with air in the state of an
                    invisible elastic fluid known by the name of <hi rend="italic">vapour</hi> or of
                    <hi rend="italic">steam</hi> when its elasticity is so great as to balance that
                    of the atmosphere. The elasticity of vapour varies with the temperature. At 32°
                    it is capable of supporting a column of mercury 0∙2 inch high. At 80° it
                    supports a column of 1 inch, at 163° of about 10 inches, at 180° of about 15
                    inches, and at 212° of about 30 inches. Now, the quantity of it which can exist
                    in the atmosphere at the same time is proportional to this elasticity.</p><p>Mr Dalton has shown, that if <hi rend="italic">p</hi> = pressure of the
                    atmosphere in inches of mercury, y = elasticity of vapour contained in the
                    atmosphere, <hi rend="italic">x</hi> = volume of dry air in 100 volumes of the
                    given atmospherical air; then <hi rend="underline">100</hi></p><p>— 100; consequently <hi rend="italic">χ</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">p .</hi><hi rend="italic superscript smallcaps"> p</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> ~</hi><hi rend="italic superscript smallcaps"> p</hi><hi rend="italic                     smallcaps"> p</hi><hi rend="italic">-f</hi></p><p>Let air be saturated with moisture at 32°. In that case we have <hi rend="subscript"> p</hi> ¾ = ⅛⅛ = <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> * <hi rend="superscript"> 00δ71</hi> 2</p><p>* = Fδ≡ = "∙ <hi rend="superscript"> 333ι</hi> so that the volume of vapour
                    (supposing its specific gravity 0∙625) in 100 volumes of such air will amount to
                    0∙666, which is just <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ^-θth part of the volume of
                    the air.</p><p>At the temperature of 60° <hi rend="italic">f</hi> = 0∙52, we have therefore <hi rend="italic">px</hi> 30 <hi rend="italic">x</hi></p><p>? <hi rend="superscript"> =</hi> ōri <hi rend="strikethrough">4</hi> 77 <hi rend="superscript"> =</hi> lθθ, and <hi rend="italic">x</hi> = 98*267; so that
                    the vo- <hi rend="italic">p—f</hi> 29∙48</p><p>lume of vapour capable of existing in the atmosphere at 17∙33</p><p>θ0° is <hi rend="strikethrough">1θθ,θθθ</hi> of* the atmosphere.</p><p>The highest temperature that the writer of this article has had an opportunity of
                    witnessing in Great Britain was 93°. At that temperature <hi rend="italic">f
                    =</hi> 1∙5</p><p><hi rend="italic">px</hi> 30ae</p><p>~~ <hi rend="subscript"> f</hi> = -5√l’ = 10θ&gt; and <hi rend="italic">x</hi> =
                    95; <hi rend="italic">p—f</hi> 28∙5</p><p>so that the volume of vapour capable of existing in the</p><p>5 1</p><p>atmosphere at such a temperature is ¶— or —.</p><p>JL W 4u</p><p>To determine the volume of vapour in the atmosphere <pb break="no" facs="nls:193191096" xml:id="kp-eb0704-1096-0137"/>at any
                    particular time, various instruments have been contrived, called <hi rend="italic">hygrometers,</hi> some more and some less exact; but the simplest
                    and most accurate method of all is that employed by Leroi, and afterwards by Mr
                    Dalton. Take a glass tumbler, as thin as possible, and fill it with water
                    somewhat colder than the temperature of the air at the time. Observe if vapour
                    be condensed on the outside of the tumbler; if not, the water employed is not
                    cold enough for our purpose. Its temperature must be lowered either by putting
                    pieces of ice into it or by dissolving in it some carbonate of soda or sulphate
                    of soda, retaining their water of crystallization, but in powder. If vapour
                    condense on the outside of the tumbler, pour out the water into another glass
                    and wipe the outside of the tumbler dry. When the temperature of the water has
                    had time to be a little elevated, pour it into the tumbler again, and observe
                    whether moisture condense on the outside of the glass. If it do, pour out the
                    water, wipe the outside of the tumbler again, and repeat the process when the
                    water has become a little warmer. This method of proceeding is to be persevered
                    in till you find the temperature at which the moisture just ceases to be
                    condensed on the glass. That temperature, by means of the following table, will
                    enable you to determine the volume of vapour (of the specific gravity 0'625)
                    existing in the atmosphere at the time that your observation is made.</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Temperature.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Force of Vapour in Inches of Mercury.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Temperature.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Force of Vapour in Inches of Mercury.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Temperature.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Force of Vapour in Inches of Mercury.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Temperature.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Force of Vapour in Inβhes of Mercury.</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>32°</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2000</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>47°</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙3264</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>62°</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙5560</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>77°</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙9175</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>33</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2066</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>48</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙3372</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>63</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙5749</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>78</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙9487</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>34</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2134</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>49</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙3483</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>64</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙5944</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>79</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙9809</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>35</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2204</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>50</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙3600</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>65</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙6146</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>80</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>]∙0120</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>36</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2277</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>51</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙3735</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>66</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙6355</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>81</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙04</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>37</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2352</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>52</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙3875</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>67</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙6571</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>82</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙07</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>38</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2429</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>53</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙4020</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>68</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙6794</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>83</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>l∙10</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>39</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2509</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>54</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙4171</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>69</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙7025</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>84</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙14</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>40</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2600</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>55</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙4327</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>70</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙7260</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>85</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙17</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>41</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2686</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>56</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙4489</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>71</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙7507</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>86</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙21</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>42</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2775</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>57</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙4657</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>72</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙7762</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>87</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙24</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>43</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2866</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>58</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙4832</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>73</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙8026</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>88</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙28</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>44</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙2961</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>59</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0-5012</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>74</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙8299</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>89</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>l∙32</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>45</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙3059</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>60</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙5200</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>75</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙8581</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>90</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙36</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>46</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙3l60</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>61</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙5377</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>76</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙8873</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row></table><p>Suppose we find that the temperature of the water when moisture ceases to be
                    condensed on the outside of the tumbler is 40°, we look into the above table,
                    and opposite to 40° in it, we find 0∙26 inch of mercury. This denotes the force
                    of the vapour contained in the atmosphere at the time our experiment was made.
                    Suppose the barometer to be standing at 30 inches, then the volume of vapour in
                    the atmosphere is 3⅜⅞7y, or nearly <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ∣ <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>- of the volume of the atmosphere.</p><p>The absolute quantity of vapour in the atmosphere is usually greatest in summer
                    on account of the temperature being so much higher; but the moisture or dryness
                    of the air does not depend so much upon the absolute quantity of vapour which it
                    contains, as on its approach to saturation. Suppose the temperature of the air
                    to be 60°, and that a tumbler filled with water of 60° condenses water on its
                    outside. This would indicate a force of vapour equal to 0∙52 inch of mercury.
                    Now, as this is the force of vapour at 60°, it is clear that as much vapour
                    exists in the air as is possible at that temperature. The air is saturated with
                    moisture, evaporation cannot go on in it, and moisture will be deposited upon
                    all bodies the least colder than the air itself. Such a state of things takes
                    place pretty frequently in this country during winter, though rarely during
                    summer. Hence the atmosphere is moister during winter than during summer, though
                    the absolute quantity of vapour which it contains may be much le is.</p><p>With respect to the quantity of vapour in the atmosphere we have still very few
                    data. Mr Daniel, in his book on Meteorology, has given a table of the force of
                    vapour in the atmosphere at London for three years. The following table gives
                    the mean force of vapour in Glasgow during every fortnight, from May 1823 to
                    February 1824:</p><p>Force of Vapour in Inches of Mercury.</p><p>1823. May, 1st fortnight 0∙2707</p><p>2d 0∙3494</p><p>June, 1st 0∙3052</p><p>2d 0∙2822</p><p>July, 1st 0∙3526</p><p>2d 0∙3819</p><p>August, 1st 0∙4000</p><p>2d 0∙3546</p><p>September, 1st 0.3790</p><p>2d 0∙3404</p><p>October, 1st 0∙3233</p><p>2d 0∙3026</p><p>November, 1st 0∙2808</p><p>2d 0∙3230</p><p>December, 1st 0∙2449</p><p>2d 0∙2453</p><p>1824. January, 1st 0∙2481</p><p>2d 0∙2578</p><p>February, 1st 0∙-2468</p><p>2d 0*2170</p><p>The mean force of vapour in the atmosphere in Glasgow is nearly 0∙3 inch, which
                    indicates the quantity of vapour capable of existing in the atmosphere at 45°.
                    Now the mean temperature of Glasgow is 47° ∙75. It is obvious from this that the
                    atmosphere in that part of Scotland is moist.</p><p>It would be very interesting if we knew the force of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193191109" xml:id="kp-eb0704-1109-0138"/>vapour at all
                    the different seasons in the torrid zone. The regularity of the weather in these
                    climates, and the little alteration in height of the barometer, would make a set
                    of such observations particularly valuable. They would probably throw more light
                    on the theory of rain than has yet been done. The only set of observations which
                    we have seen on the quantity of vapour in countries approaching the torrid zone,
                    are the following by Dr Heinecker, in which he gives the maximum and minimum dew
                    points at Funchal in Madeira (lat. 32⅛ N.), during the year 1828. which in that
                    part of the world was remarkably dry.</p><p>Maximum. Minimum. Rain in Inches.</p><p>January 65° 50° 4 ’ 08</p><p>February 56 50 1 ’ 64</p><p>March 65 48 1'68</p><p>April 63 45 3∙35</p><p>May 69 51 2∙14</p><p>June 70 54 0 ’ 21</p><p>July 72 61 0∙10</p><p>August 73 63 0</p><p>September...75 69 1 ’ 39</p><p>October 74 56 0</p><p>November....72 ’ 5 54 2 ’ 56</p><p>December....67 50 0∙52</p><p>17∙67<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Brewster’s <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> (new series), i. 34.</p></note></p><p>These observations are not sufficient to give us an accurate notion of the state
                    of the atmosphere at Funchal. The highest dew point is 75°, indicating a force
                    of vapour amounting to 0 ’ 8581 inch, so that the vapour at that time in the
                    atmosphere was nearly 3⅛-th of its volume. The lowest dew point is 45°,
                    indicating a force of vapour amounting to 0∙3059 inch, so that the vapour at
                    that time in the atmosphere was nearly <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi>-Lθ of its
                    volume. The mean dew point deduced from the maxima and minima is 61°, indicating
                    a force of vapour of 0∙5377 inch, or a quantity of vapour amounting to nearly
                    ⅛th of the volume of the atmosphere. The mean temperature of Madeira is 66° ∙3.
                    Now since the mean dew point is 61°, it is obvious that the atmosphere over
                    Madeira is much drier than at Glasgow, though the absolute quantity of vapour
                    which it contains is much greater.</p><p>Thus the atmosphere is a mixture of at least four different elastic fluids,
                    namely, azotic gas, oxygen gas, carbonic acid ĝas, and the vapour of water.
                    Doubtless all other gaseous bodies and many vapours exist in it also, but in too
                    small quantities to be discovered by the most delicate tests that we have it in
                    our power to apply. These different elastic fluids are mixed equably together;
                    and though there be a considerable difference in their specific gravities, that
                    difference has no tendency to cause them to separate. The reason of this equable
                    mixture was first pointed out by Dalton. It depends upon a principle not yet
                    generally recognised, but of the existence of which recent observations leave
                    little doubt. This principle is, that the particles of elastic fluids are not
                    mutually elastic to each other. The particles of oxygen repel the particles of
                    oxygen, the particles of azotic gas repel those of azotic gas; but a particle of
                    oxygen does not repel a particle of azotic gas. Hence, wheΛ a gas issues from an
                    orifice into a space filled by another gas, it rushes precisely as if it were
                    flowing into a vacuum. But the full development of this important principle
                    belongs to the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Pneumatics.</hi></p><p>A great deal has been written about the salubrity of the atmosphere in different
                    countries. It has been supposed, and is still believed, that the average length
                    of life in different places depends chiefly upon the state of the atmosphere. It
                    has been generally admitted that the atmosphere is frequently a vehicle by which
                    diseases are communicated; and the prevalence of certain epidemic diseases, as
                    the plague and the yellow fever, in particular places, at particular seasons,
                    has been accounted for in this way. But no satisfactory evidence has ever been
                    adduced to satisfy us of the accuracy of these opinions. The constituents of the
                    atmosphere, azotic and oxygen gases, never undergo any sensible change in their
                    proportions. Carbonic acid varies somewhat, but its proportion is always so
                    small that it cannot be considered as a source of disease. The proportion of
                    aqueous vapour is much more variable, and there can be no doubt that it may have
                    an effect upon individuals predisposed to certain diseases. Consumptive patients
                    suffer much more when they breathe a very moist than when they breathe a dry
                    atmosphere. There are few places in the habitable globe, if there be any, where
                    the atmosphere is constantly saturated with moisture; and it cannot prove very
                    injurious, even to consumptive patients, except when in this state. Besides,
                    that a very dry atmosphere is not the best adapted for the continuance of
                    health, is obvious from the sufferings to which those who inhabit the west coast
                    of Africa are liable during the prevalence of the sirocco, a wind So excessively
                    dry that even the wood of the floors shrinks in consequence of its action.</p><p>Nothing has been more completely ascertained than that marshy countries are
                    subject to intermittent fevers, and that the malignancy of these intermittent
                    fevers increases with the heat of the climate. These diseases disappear when the
                    marshes are drained, and therefore are connected with moisture; but that they
                    are not owing to mere moisture, is obvious from this, that they do not appear at
                    the sea-shore or on the banks of rivers, though the moisture be as great as in
                    marshy countries. It is the general opinion that these diseases owe their origin
                    to certain vapours which are given out during the putrefaction of vegetable
                    substances; but of the nature of these <hi rend="italic">miasmata</hi> nothing
                    is known. In the West Indies marshes are most fatal to the inhabitants just when
                    they are almost (but not quite) dried up by the heat of the weather. It is then
                    that the exhalations are most abundant and most deadly. It is known that
                    smallpox, &amp;c. may be communicated by the mixture of a particular matter with
                    the blood. It is possible, though not very probable, that this matter may at
                    times exist in the atmosphere in the state of vapour, or in combination with one
                    or other of the constituents of air, most probably the aqueous vapour, and the
                    disease may be communicated by breathing such air. It is a conceivable thing
                    that the matter, which, like a ferment, is capable of inducing certain diseases
                    when it enters into the blood, may exist occasionally united to the aqueous
                    vapour in the atmosphere.</p><p>It has been ascertained, by experiments that seem conclusive, that these noxious
                    states of the atmosphere, however they originate, may be destroyed, and the air
                    rendered healthy, by mixing it with chlorine. This is most easily accomplished
                    by introducing into the chamber to be so purified a quantity of chloride of lime
                    in an open dish and pouring on it sulphuric acid. The chlorine is disengaged and
                    speedily fills the apartment. Then the mixture is withdrawn and the room
                    ventilated. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Climate, Meteorology, Pneumatics.
                    (l.)</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>