<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0704-2162-0219-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">AUSTRIA</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 4, page 219</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="50" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term><term n="13" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term><term n="10" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1210278">Belgium</term><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="24" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="14" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term><term n="14" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term><term n="14" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term><term n="15" ref="fasttopic:821579">Austrians</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term><term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term><term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193192162" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">AUSTRIA</label>.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">This</hi> great empire is situated nearly in the centre of
                    Europe, extending from the 44th to the 51st degree of north latitude, and from
                    the 8th to the 26th degree of east longitude. Its configuration is irregular,
                    but its extent corresponds to that of an oblong of fully 600 miles in length
                    from east to west, and above 400 miles in breadth from north to south. Compared
                    with France, the Austrian dominions have a form nearly as compact, but their
                    frontiers are by no means so strongly defined, nor so well guarded by physical
                    barriers. France resembles a fivesided figure, having on three sides the sea,
                    and on the other sides the Pyrenees, the Alps, and the Vosges; while in Austria
                    the chief ranges of mountains are in the interior. In extent of surface, the
                    Austrian dominions considerably exceed those of France, for they cover a space
                    of no less than 260,000 square miles. They comprise a remarkable diversity of
                    tribes, and even nations, differing from each other in language, habits,
                    religion, and comparative civilization.</p><p>The component parts of this great empire consist of six countries bearing each
                    the name of kingdom, viz. Hungary, Bohemia, Galicia, Lombardy and Venice,
                    Illyria, and Dalmatia; one archduchy, Austria; one principality, Transylvania;
                    one duchy, Styria; one margraviate, Moravia; and one county, Tyrol. We shall
                    begin with an historical notice of this empire, that our readers may have a
                    distinct view of two important subjects; first, of the means by which Austria,
                    at first a small state, progressively rose into importance; and, next, of those
                    resources by which she withstood the reverses sustained in her long contest with
                    revolutionary France.</p><p>The cradle of Austrian power was the fertile tract lying along the southern bank
                    of the Danube to the eastward of the river Ens. It is said to have been overrun
                    and partly colonized by Germans under Charlemagne; but be that as it may, after
                    the empire of Germany was constituted in the ninth century, the district in
                    question, afterwards called Lower Austria, was declared a military frontier for
                    repelling the incursions of the Huns and other barbarous tribes to the eastward.
                    It was called <hi rend="italic">Ost-reich,</hi> the east country, from its
                    position relatively to the rest of Germany; and its governor received from the
                    head of the empire the title of margrave (in German <hi rend="italic">mark∙graf,</hi> or lord of the marches), which his descendants bore for
                    centuries without anticipating the future greatness of their house. Towards the
                    middle of the twelfth century their territory received an important accession in
                    the province west of the Ens, which, from its vicinity to the Alps, and the
                    greater elevation of its surface, was called Upper Austria. The governors of
                    this augmented domain were now raised by the emperors of Germany from the humble
                    rank of margrave to that of duke; and it was one of their number, Duke Leopold,
                    who, towards the end of the twelfth century, ungenerously detained our Richard
                    I. in confinement on his return from the Holy Land. It was at this time also
                    that the important province of Styria came to the dukes of Austria by bequest.
                    Hitherto the ducal residence had been in a castle on the mgh ground of
                    Kahlenberg, near Vienna; but it was now removed to that city. In 1246 the male
                    branch of the ducal line, originally from Bamberg in Franconia, became extinct,
                    and Austria underwent a long interregnum, he reigning emperor of Germany
                    declared both that uchy and Styria to have lapsed to the imperial crown, and
                    appointed a lieutenant <hi rend="italic">(Statthalter)</hi> to govern them on
                    the part of the empire. But claims to the succession were brought forward by
                    descendants of the female branch of the Bamberg line; and after various
                    contests, Ottocar, son of the king of Bohemia, was, in 1262, duly invested with
                    the government of Austria and Styria. Carinthia, Istria, with part of Friuli,
                    soon after devolved on Ottocar by succession; but he forfeited all these
                    advantages by his imprudence in refusing to acknowledge as emperor Rodolph of
                    Hapsburg, who had been regularly elected to that high station. Hostilities
                    ensued; the talents of Rodolph prevailed; and, in 1276, Ottocar was obliged to
                    renounce his title to Austria and its appendant states. Notwithstanding this
                    renunciation, Ottocar re-entered Austria with an army, but soon after fell in
                    battle. The ducal throne being then vacant, Rodolph vested the succession to it
                    in his sons; and having obtained the sanction of the electors of the empire to
                    that important act, the reign of the Hapsburg dynasty over Austria commenced in
                    1282.</p><p>In the beginning of the following century the dukes of Austria lost a part of
                    their Swiss territory by the insurrection of the cantons. This they never
                    recovered; but in 1364 they acquired Tyrol; and Austria, hitherto known only as
                    a remote province, little connected with the improved part of Germany, was soon
                    after brought into contact with the general politics of the empire. The rank of
                    emperor of Germany had been held successively by Saxon, Franconian, Suabian, and
                    Bohemian princes, Austria having as yet supplied only one of the number (Albert
                    I.); but, in 1438, another Albert, duke of Austria, was raised to that dignity,
                    and, from close connection with Bohemia and Hungary, the power of Austria became
                    so much greater than that of any other state in the empire, that from 1438 the
                    imperial crown was regularly vested in the chief of the Austrian family. In the
                    latter part of the century of which we are treating (the fifteenth), Maximilian
                    I., an emperor of the Austrian line, made great additions to the power of his
                    house by matrimonial connections, having himself espoused the heiress of the
                    Netherlands, and afterwards married his son to the heiress of the crown of
                    Spain. Of the latter marriage the issue was the well-known Charles V., who held
                    the crown of Spain by inheritance, and the empire of Germany by election.
                    Several years after his election, viz. in 1527, on the death of the king of
                    Hungary and Bohemia, these extensive countries, formerly held by the house of
                    Austria, reverted to it, along with Moravia, Silesia, and Lusatia, and were all
                    governed by Ferdinand, a younger brother of Charles. Such were the countries
                    directly or indirectly subject to the sovereign who carried on such obstinate
                    conflicts with France, and was accused, like Louis XIV., of aiming at the
                    sovereignty of Europe.</p><p>But the dominions of Charles V. did not long remain under one ruler. Spain was
                    made over to his son Philip, along with the Netherlands; whilst Austria,
                    Hungary, and his German states, were vested in his brother Ferdinand. These
                    formed a splendid possession, but their efficiency in a political sense was not
                    at all proportioned to their extent. A long time elapsed before Hungary and the
                    eastern provinces became cordially attached to the imperial family. The
                    treatment they in general experienced from their sovereigns was far from
                    conciliatory, and the vicinity of the Turks afforded a ready support to
                    insurgents.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193192175" xml:id="kp-eb0704-2175-0220"/><p>Meanwhile, in the north of Germany, the religious antipathy of Catholics and
                    Protestants led first to repeated dissensions, and eventually to the obstinate
                    and sanguinary contest known from its duration (from 1618 to 1648) as the Thirty
                    Years’ War. On the one side were the Catholic princes of the empire, with
                    Austria at their head; on the other, Saxony and the Protestant states, assisted
                    at one time by Sweden, and subsequently by France. The most distinguished
                    commanders were Gustavus Adolphus on the part of the Protestants, and, on that
                    of the Catholics, Wallenstein the Austrian. Both were greatly superior to the
                    age in which they lived, and evinced, at the battle of Lutzen, fought in 1632,
                    talents not inferior to those displayed on the same fields in 1813. Wallenstein
                    survived his illustrious opponent, but his end was tragical: he met a violent
                    death by order of his imperial master, against whom he had ventured to conspire.
                    The war was at last ended by the peace of Westphalia, by which Austria was
                    obliged to relinquish Lusatia to Saxony and Alsace to France.</p><p>The peace of Westphalia, like that of Utrecht in a subsequent age, restored
                    tranquillity throughout Europe. It continued many years, and might have lasted
                    much longer, had not the ambition of Louis XIV. alarmed the neighbouring states,
                    and obliged them to look for safety in arms. Belgium, held at that time with a
                    feeble hand by Spain, was the prize at stake; and the dread of that fertile and
                    populous country falling into the power of France called forth the greatest
                    efforts on the part of both Austria and Holland, which, from the extent of its
                    financial means, was at that time a power of great influence. Louis was
                    surrounded by able generals and well-disciplined armies. Flattered with the
                    prospect of success, he attempted the conquest of the Netherlands in no less
                    than three wars, in two of which (those begun in 1672 and 1689) Austria bore a
                    principal part. In the last she received the co-operation of England, which
                    then, for the first time, came forward as a principal in continental coalitions,
                    contributing largely both in troops and subsidies. The chief scenes of conflict
                    were the Netherlands and the banks of the Rhine. The French, acting with all the
                    advantage of unity, had frequently the superiority in action; but the allies,
                    numerous and resolute, were never discouraged by defeat. At last, in 1697, came
                    the peace of Ryswick, which <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> left, as peace often
                    does, the contending parties in nearly the same relative positions as at the
                    outset of the contest. They had the satisfaction, however, of having compelled
                    the aspiring Louis to stop short in his encroachments and schemes of
                    aggrandizement.</p><p>But with so restless a prince at the head of a population of 20,000,000, peace
                    could not be of long continuance; and, on the death of the king of Spain,
                    Austria, England, and Holland, found it again necessary to take the field. The
                    question now related not merely to the Netherlands, but whether a French or an
                    Austrian prince should succeed to the crown of Spain. Hence the name of War of
                    the Succession, given to this long contest, which, beginning in 1701, lasted no
                    less than twelve years. The superiority in military skill was now for the first
                    time on the side of the allies. The Austrians and other Germans, subsidized by
                    Holland and England, were led to repeated victories by Eugene and Marlborough.
                    France sent forth numerous armies, and showed, in Villars and Vendome, generals
                    worthy of the better days of Louis; but in Italy and the Low Countries the
                    allies were completely successful; and it was in Spain only that they failed.
                    Such was the state of circumstances in 1711, when the death of the reigning
                    emperor took place unexpectedly, and the election to that dignity fell on his
                    brother, who had been destined by the allies to the throne of Spain. The
                    prospect of the junction on one head of the crowns of Spain and Austria brought
                    to recollection the ambitious projects of the emperor Charles V., and inclined
                    many who had supported the war from a dread of France, to consider the transfer
                    of Spain to a grandson of Louis XIV. the less dangerous alternative of the two.
                    This, joined to the change of ministry in England, the removal of Marlborough
                    from the command, and the impatience of the Dutch under so long and burdensome a
                    war, led to the peace of Utrecht, to which Austria, after urgent remonstrances
                    with her allies, and fruitless efforts in the field, acceded, by a treaty
                    concluded the year after (1714) at Baden. Well might she give her assent to a
                    treaty which transferred to ’ her not only the Low Countries, but extensive
                    possessions in both the north and south of Italy.</p><p>The emperor, anxious to confirm his authority in Hungary and Transylvania, now
                    directed his troops against the Turks. The latter had, during more than a
                    century, been ready to take part with the insurgents in Hungary against the
                    Austrians, and had at one time, in 1683, advanced to the walls of Vienna, whence
                    they were driven by a Polish army under Sobieski. This was the first serious
                    check given to these confident barbarians. At a subsequent date Prince Eugene
                    defeated them in several actions, and the peace concluded with them at
                    Carlowitz, in 1699, secured to Austria a considerable accession of territory on
                    the side of Hungary. Still that country continued divided and of doubtful
                    allegiance to Austria. Eugene led thither, in 1716, a part of the armies with
                    which he had conquered in Italy and the Netherlands, and applied European
                    tactics against the Turks with distinguished success. The result was a series of
                    splendid successes, and a treaty of peace highly favourable to Austria.</p><p>Such, however, was not the case in the last scene of the military career of
                    Eugene, when, nearly twenty years after (in 1735), he headed the Austrian armies
                    on the Rhine. The French had taken the field in support of the claims of Spain
                    on the south of Italy. Austria was evidently overmatched in force; and England,
                    guided by the pacific counsels of Walpole, declining to interfere, the result
                    was a treaty, by which the emperor relinquished to Spain the contested territory
                    in Italy.</p><p>In 1740 the death of the reigning emperor, Charles VI., brought to a close the
                    male line of the house of Hapsburg, the succession devolving on Charles’s
                    daughter, Maria Theresa. The death of Charles became the signal for attack on
                    his dominions by almost all the neighbouring powers; by Prussia, Bavaria,
                    Saxony, and even by France. But England came forward to support the cause of
                    Austria with a liberal subsidy, while the Hungarians, now united and loyal,
                    recruited her armies. The aspect of affairs was soon altered; the Bavarians were
                    driven back; and the French, who had ventured to advance as far as Bohemia, were
                    obliged to retire to the Rhine. Frederick II. of Prussia proved a more obstinate
                    opponent; and, as the interest of England and Holland called the Austrian forces
                    to the Low Countries to maintain the great contest carrying on in that quarter
                    against France, Maria Theresa was induced to subscribe, first in 1742, and
                    afterwards in 1745, a separate treaty with Frederick, by which she ceded to him
                    the chief part of Silesia. But the unprovoked attack of Frederick sunk deep in
                    her mind; she watched an opportunity of revenge; and, in 1756, formed that
                    coalition of powers against Prussia, which gave rise to a war of seven years,
                    and to an extent of devastation such as Germany had not witnessed for more than
                    a century. On one side was the whole Austrian force, aided by 80,000 French,
                    and, at particular periods of the war, by the Russians and Swedes; on the other
                    stood Pn <hi rend="superscript"> ιs</hi> '</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193192188" xml:id="kp-eb0704-2188-0221"/><p>sia and England, inferior numerically to their antagonists, but managing their
                    resources, and directing their military efforts, with all the ability belonging
                    to the character of Frederick and Lord Chatham. On the side of the French there
                    appeared no commander of eminence; but on that of the Austrians, Marshals Daun
                    and Laudohn were generals worthy of being opposed to Frederick. After a number
                    of battles and great alternations of success, both sides became tired of the
                    waste of blood; and a contest, waged for a time with a rapidity of movement and
                    an eagerness for conflict almost equal to those displayed in the French
                    revolution, was marked towards its close by the cautious tactics of Turenne. At
                    last, in 1763, a general peace was concluded, and the rival powers were left
                    very nearly in the same position as at the beginning of the war.</p><p>From this time Germany enjoyed peace during thirty years. In 1778 the death of
                    the elector of Bavaria gave rise to pretensions on the part of Austria, which
                    drew once more into the field Frederick II., now grown grey in command. Austria
                    opposed to him forces fully equal in number and scarcely inferior in discipline,
                    but happily the campaign proved bloodless, each side anticipating a close of the
                    dispute by negociation. In that manner, accordingly, it ended; Austria being
                    content with the cession by Bavaria of the frontier district, called the quarter
                    of the Inn.</p><p>Maria Theresa had married Francis duke of Lorraine, who was afterwards elected
                    emperor of Germany, but died in 1765. Their son, Joseph IL, was then joined in
                    the sovereign power with his mother; and, on her death in 1780, he became sole
                    ruler. The princes of the house of Austria, disposed rather to follow than to
                    lead, have seldom been the authors of political change; but the emperor Joseph
                    was imbued with all the ardour of a sanguine innovator. He gave a loose to this
                    disposition after 1780, issuing a number of edicts, of which several were
                    praiseworthy in their objects, but abrupt and premature in their operations. He
                    established general toleration in religion, abolished a number of monasteries
                    and convents, dismantled various fortresses, and took steps for new-modelling
                    the existing systems both of law and of national education. Had the public in
                    his dominions been ripe, as in France, for a general political change, Joseph
                    would have been hailed as a subverter of abuses, and as the author of general
                    improvement; but the Austrians, attached to old usages, understood little of his
                    plans, and merely received them with passive acquiescence. The actual effect was
                    thus very limited, notwithstanding the example of new institutions in the United
                    States of America, and soon after in France. But in Belgium the case was
                    different: the contagion of the French revolution spread over the country, and
                    produced a sudden rising against the Austrians. This unexpected revolt, and the
                    chequered success of the war then carrying on against Turkey, are understood to
                    have preyed on the sensitive mind of the emperor, and to have caused his death
                    in 1790.</p><p>Leopold, the brother and successor of Joseph, had a very short reign, the crown
                    devolving in 1792 on his son Francis IL, the present emperor. Francis had hardly
                    succeeded to it when he found himself involved in a contest with France, the
                    length and vicissitudes of which proved such as to castjnto the shade all former
                    wars between that country and Austria. The first important blow was struck in
                    November 1792 at Jemappes, where the numbers and audacity of the French obtained
                    a signal success. Next year the superior efficiency of the Austrian armies
                    secured to them a temporary superiori- y; but, i∏ 1794, the multitudes of
                    Frenchmen brought orward by the energetic measures of the terrorists, and <hi rend="superscript"> le</hi> talents of commanders such as Pichegru, Moreau,
                    Kleber, young in years, but full of enterprise and activity, led to the conquest
                    of the Netherlands, and to the retreat of the Austrians beyond the Rhine. France
                    now offered to Austria a separate peace; but England engaging to furnish large
                    subsidies, the emperor declined a treaty that would have involved the cession of
                    Belgium. The French, determined to obtain this cession by force of arms, crossed
                    the Rhine, in the autumn of 1795, with two formidable armies. Prussia had
                    withdrawn from the contest, and allowed the whole weight of it to fall upon the
                    emperor. It was then that the talents of Marshal Clairfayt, as yet known only to
                    military men, became apparent to Europe at large. With numbers inferior to the
                    two French armies collectively, he found means, by rapid movements, to
                    concentrate a force superior to either singly, and drove them across the Rhine
                    with great loss. Next year, however, the French, undismayed by failure, resumed
                    the offensive, and crossed the Rhine again with two armies; one of which
                    penetrated into the heart of Franconia, whilst the other overran Suabia and part
                    of Bavaria. But these armies had not the means of affording each other ready
                    support; they were separated by the Danube, while the Austrians were in
                    possession of the bridges on that river, and could move within a smaller circle.
                    They were thus enabled to repeat their manoeuvre of the preceding year, by
                    detaching a superior force against the French army in Franconia, and thus
                    obliging it not only to evacuate the country it had overrun, but to seek safety
                    beyond the Rhine. Such was also the case with the southern army of the French,
                    although the retreat conducted by Moreau was the subject of general
                    commendation.</p><p> But whilst in Germany success inclined to the side of Austria, the case was very
                    different in Piedmont and Lombardy. In Piedmont indeed the war had long been
                    carried on between the French and the allies without decisive success on either
                    side. The opposing forces were nearly equal, and the mountainous nature of the
                    country afforded so many strong positions, that there seemed no means of
                    bringing the contest to a speedy termination. But all this was suddenly changed
                    by the genius of one man. Buonaparte appeared on the scene, and in less than a
                    month after receiving the command, defeated the allies in three engagements;
                    obliged the court of Turin to make a separate peace; and, pouring his forces
                    into Lombardy, drove the Austrians from every position in that country except
                    Mantua. The strength of the latter place, however, bade defiance to the attacks
                    of the French, and enabled the emperor to make repeated attempts for the
                    recovery of Lombardy. No part of the war is more deserving of attention than
                    this campaign; for none displayed in a more striking light the extensive
                    resources of Austria, or the inventive mind of Buonaparte. Threatened in the end
                    of July by an Austrian army of great strength, but which was imprudently
                    advancing in two bodies, he hesitated not a moment in sacrificing his artillery,
                    that by sudden marches he might assail his opponents before they effected a
                    junction. In this he succeeded; but his loss was heavy, and the Austrians were
                    rather repulsed than defeated. Six weeks after, a repetition by Buonaparte of
                    these daring movements was attended with decisive success. When apparently
                    marching against the Austrian troops in Trent, he turned suddenly to the right,
                    and advancing by a valley, reached the head-quarters of their army before they
                    were prepared. The result was a series of actions, which cut off the retreat of
                    their main body, and obliged it to fly for refuge to Mantua. But ere two months
                    had passed the Austrians prepared another army, which, advancing towards Verona,
                    Buonaparte marched to encounter, using in his dispatch to Paris these remarkable
                    words: <hi rend="italic">Il</hi><hi rend="italic">faut</hi><hi rend="italic">frap-</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:193192201" xml:id="kp-eb0704-2201-0222"/><hi rend="italic">per l’</hi><hi rend="italic">ennemi comme la foudre, et le balayer des son premier pas.</hi> On this
                    occasion, however, fortune was not favourable to him. He was worsted twice in
                    action (on the 6th and 12th November); yet, far from being discouraged, he
                    conceived the extraordinary plan of quitting his camp, at night, and gaining the
                    rear of that army which had twice repulsed him. He reckoned on the effect of a
                    surprise; but his hopes were disappointed by the time unavoidably lost in
                    attacks on the village of Arcole, which stood in his way. The main body of the
                    Austrians had time to advance, and the result was a series of conflicts,
                    attended with great loss on both sides.</p><p>Thus ended the campaign of 1796, sanguinary beyond example even in those days of
                    waste of life, and not altogether conclusive in its results. Next year, however,
                    the chances of war were no longer doubtful. The Austrians having reinforced
                    their army, made a final effort to relieve Mantua; but Buonaparte having
                    intercepted a dispatch with their intended plan of operations, was enabled to
                    make such a disposition of his troops as to insure success; and the results
                    were, the victory of Rivoli, the surrender of the force destined to relieve
                    Mantua, and the complete expulsion of the Austrians from Italy. The French now
                    crossed the mountain barrier, and advanced toward the heart of Austria. This,
                    joined to the approach of their armies from the Rhine, obliged the emperor to
                    conclude preliminaries of peace at Leoben, and afterwards a treaty proceeding on
                    these as a basis at Campo Formio. This treaty involved the cession by Austria of
                    Belgium and Lombardy, but gave her, in return, Venice and its dependent
                    provinces, making an absolute loss in population of 1,500,000 souls.</p><p>This peace, however, proved only a truce. The absence of a portion of the French
                    armies in Egypt, and the evident misgovernment of the directory, induced England
                    to form a new coalition, and renew the continental contest early in 1799. The
                    Austrian troops took the field, powerful equally in numbers and discipline; and
                    the French, commanded for the first time by inferior leaders, were driven back
                    both in Germany and Italy. The arrival of Russian auxiliaries, and the talents
                    of Suwaroff, bore forward the tide of success, until the autumn of the year,
                    when increased levies on the part of the French, and a better choice of
                    generals, began to turn the scale in their favour. The capricious Paul now
                    withdrew from the coalition, and the Austrians entered on the campaign of 1800
                    with their own forces only. These proved, as formerly, insufficient to withstand
                    the French, especially when the latter were commanded in Germany by Moreau, in
                    Italy by Buonaparte. Battles, unfortunately too decisive, took place; the
                    victories of Hohenlinden and Marengo led to the treaty of Luneville, and to the
                    cession by Austria of almost all her Venetian acquisitions.</p><p>This peace, though not so short as the preceding, lasted only four years. In 1805
                    Austria and Russia, provoked by Buonaparte’s aggressions, and stimulated by
                    English subsidies, took the field with numerous armies; but the successive
                    overthrows at Ulm and Austerlitz rendered peace again indispensable to Austria.
                    It was obtained (6th August 1806) by the surrender of the remainder of the
                    Venetian territory, of the Tyrol, and of various districts, comprising a
                    sacrifice in all of three millions of subjects. Soon after these reverses,
                    Francis II. renounced the title and authority of emperor of Germany, and assumed
                    the title of emperor of Austria. Taught by repeated disasters, he remained
                    passive in the great contest in 1806 and 1807 between France, Prussia, and
                    Russia; but in 1809 the war in Spain having withdrawn a very large portion of
                    the French force, he ventured once more to try his fortune in the field. The
                    Austrian armies were numerous; but Buonaparte had still a powerful French force
                    at command, and was aided by all the troops of the confederation of the Rhine.
                    The' Austrians, worsted in Bavaria, retreated to Vienna; and although temporary
                    hopes were excited by their success at Aspern (21st and 22d May), they were
                    blasted by the disastrous day of Wagram, and peace was again purchased by a
                    sacrifice of territory containing more than three millions of inhabitants.
                    Austria, now reduced to a population of twenty millions, remained in peace
                    during the years 1810, 1811, and 1812; but when the disasters of the French in
                    Russia once more raised the hopes of Germany, and brought friendly standards
                    into Saxony, Austria took part with the grand alliance, and her troops bore a
                    conspicuous part in the battle of Leipsic and the invasion of France. The
                    definitive treaties of 1814 and 1815 reinstated her in all her former
                    territories, except Belgium, and gave her substantial additions on the side of
                    Italy. Satisfied with these, the Austrian government has ever since wisely
                    abstained from war, directing its attention to the reinstatement of its
                    finances, and the promotion of its productive industry.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Population of the Austrian Empire in</hi> 1831 <hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">the provinces classed by the comparative
                    density of the inhabitants.</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 1</hi></p><p>Population of the 1 nhabitants per</p><p>Province. Square Mile.</p><p>Tyrol 780,000 50</p><p>Dalmatia 340,000 ..58</p><p>Military frontier adjoining (<hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> θθθ θθθ <hi rend="subscript"> 73</hi></p><p>Turkey J ’ ’</p><p>Sclavonia 370,000 85</p><p>Transylvania 2,000,000 88</p><p>Hungary 9,000,000 100</p><p>Styria 850,000 102</p><p>Governments of Laybachì</p><p>and Trieste (Carinthia?- 1,160,000 105</p><p>and Istria).... J</p><p>Croatia 600,000 110</p><p>Upper Austria and Salzburg... 900,000 130</p><p>Galicia of the Buckowine 4,400,000 135</p><p>Lower Austria, including! <hi rend="subscript"> 1 30</hi> θ θθθ <hi rend="subscript"> 16</hi> 5</p><p>Vienna í</p><p>Moravia and Austrian Sile-Ì g θθθ θθθ ∣g-</p><p>sia J ’ ’</p><p>Bohemia 3,900,000 190</p><p>Lombardy and the Venetiani ^θθ θθθ g∣5</p><p>provinces J ’ ’</p><p>Population of the empire 33,000,000</p><p>Yearly increase, computed! 400 000</p><p>from the last 10 years....) ’</p><p>Average of the whole empire per square mile,! ∣ <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> θ
                    nearly J</p><p>Such are the constituent portions of this great empire. Differing as they do in
                    climate, soil, language, and customs, no general description can possibly apply
                    to the whole. We shall therefore recapitulate the chief characteristics of each
                    in succession, classing them in the following order: The archduchy of Austria;
                    Hungary and the adjacent provinces; Bohemia, Moravia, Galicia; the Alpine
                    Provinces; Lombardy and Venice.</p></div></body></text></TEI>