<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0073-0060-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LUGANSK (9th edition, volume 15, page 60)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41g0hw2j">Capuchins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wm7s">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9h942">Coaling</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865087">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865671">Coaling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:846074">Cantabrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n73/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LUGANSK</label>, a town of Russia, in the government of
                    Ekaterinoslaff, district of Slavianoserbsk, 300 miles to the eastward of the
                    capital of the province, is connected by a branch with the railway between
                    Kharkoff and Azoff, as well as with other towns and iron-works of the Donetz
                    coal-mines district. It stands on the small river Lugan, 10 miles from its
                    junction with the northern Donetz, in the Lugan mine district, of which it is
                    the chief town. This district, which comprises the important coal-mines of
                    Lisi-tchansk and the anthracite mines of Gorodische, occupies an area of about
                    110,000 acres on the banks of the Donetz river, and has a population of more
                    than 15,000. Although it is mentioned in Russian history as early as the 16th
                    century, and coal was discovered in it at the time of Peter I., it was not until
                    1795 that an Englishman, Gascoyne or Gaskoin, established its first iron-work
                    for supplying the Black Sea fleet and the southern fortresses with guns and
                    shot. This proved a failure, owing to the great distance from the sea, and the
                    manufacture of supplies for the navy was suspended; but during the Crimean war
                    the iron-works of Lugan again largely produced shot, shell, and gun-carriages.
                    Since 1864 agricultural implements, steam-engines, and the various machinery
                    required for beetroot sugar-works, distilleries, &lt;fcc., have been the chief
                    manufactures. The Lugan works, which employ about 1200 men, are the chief centre
                    for smelting the ores of the neighbouring iron-mines. The town is the seat of
                    the mining authorities for the district, and has a first-class meteorological
                    and magnetic observatory. The 11,000 inhabitants of Lugansk also carry on a very
                    active trade in cattle, tallow, wools, skins, linseed, wine, corn, and
                    manufactured wares. The weekly fairs are much frequented. There are also in the
                    town many tallowmelting works, and the smith trade is largely carried on.</p>
                <p>‘ LUGO, a maritime province of Spain, one of the four into which Galicia has
                    since 1833 been divided, is bounded on the E. by Oviedo and Leon, on the S. by
                    Orense, on the W. by Pontevedra and Coruna, and on the N. by the Atlantic. Its
                    extreme length from north to south is about 98 miles, its breadth 58, and the
                    area 3787 square miles. The coast, which extends for about 40 miles from the
                    estuary of Rivadeo to Cape Vares, is extremely rugged and inaccessible, and few
                    of the inlets that exist, except those of Rivadeo and Vivero, admit vessels of
                    any size. The province, especially in the north and east, is mountainous in its
                    character, being traversed by the great Cantabrian chain and its offshoots; the
                    sierra by which it is separated from Leon attains in some places a height of
                    6000 feet. A large part of the area is drained by the Mino, which rises on the
                    western slope of the Sierra de Meira, and follows a southerly direction until it
                    is joined by the Sil; the latt·er for a considerable distance forms the southern
                    boundary of the province. Of the rivers of the northern versant the most
                    important are the Navia (which has its lower course through Oviedo), the Eo (for
                    some distance the boundary between the two provinces), the Masma, the Oro, and
                    the Landrobe. The Eume, one of the rivers of Coruna, and the Ulla, which
                    separates that province from Pontevedra, both have their rise on the western
                    slopes of Lugo. Some of the northern valleys even, in their lower portions, are
                    fertile, and yield not only corn but fruit and wine, but the principal
                    agricultural wealth is on the Mino and Sil, where rye, maize, wheat, legumes of
                    various kinds, flax, hemp, and a little silk are produced. The hills are
                    comparatively well wooded. Iron is found at Cancel and Incio, antimony at
                    Castroverde and Cervantes, argentiferous lead at Riotorto; and there a:e
                    quarries of granite, marble, and various kinds of slate and building stone.
                    Linen and woollen cloths are manufactured, but to an insignificant extent, and
                    the trade of the province is unimportant. The internal communications are still
                    very imperfect. There is only one railway, that connecting Lugo with Coruna; but
                    connexions with Leon (Branuelas) <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n74/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0915-0074-0061"/> and with Orense are in contemplation. The
                    total population in 1877 was 410,387, being a decrease of 22,129 since 1860.
                    There are ten towns with a population over 10,000 —Chantada, Fonsagrada, Lugo,
                    Mondonedo, Monforte, Panton, Sarria, Savinao, Villalba, and Vivero.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Lugo,</hi> the capital of the above province, stands on a
                    small hill near the northern bank of the river Mino, at a height of 1930 feet
                    above the level of the sea, 60 miles south-west from Coruna, and 353 north-west
                    from Madrid, on the highway between these two cities. With the former it is
                    continuously connected by rail. The form of the town, which is nearly
                    quadrangular, is defined by a massive Roman wall, from 30 to 40 feet in height
                    and 20 feet thick, with projecting semicircular towers which, prior to the civil
                    war in 1809, were eighty-five in number; it now serves as a promenade,
                    commanding an extensive and delightful prospect. The principal public places are
                    the Plaza de la Constitucion, a spacious arcaded square, the Plaza de San
                    Domingo, the Plaza del Hospital, and the busy Plaza del Campo, where fairs and
                    markets are held. The most important of the public buildings is the Gothic
                    cathedral on the south side of the town; it dates from the 12th century, but was
                    modernized in the 18th, and possesses no special architectural merit. Other
                    churches are those of the Capuchins and that of San Domingo; the only other
                    buildings of note are the episcopal palace, the secondary school, the hospital,
                    and the prison. The principal industries are tanning, and the manufacture of
                    linen cloth and of cream of tartar; there is some trade in silk wares. About a
                    mile to the south of the town, on the left bank of the Mino, are the famous hot
                    sulphur baths of Lugo; the bathing house dates from 1847. The population of the
                    ayuntamiento in 1877 was 18,909.</p>
                <p>Lugo <hi rend="italic">{Lucus</hi><hi rend="italic">Augusti)</hi> was made by
                    Augustus the seat of a <hi rend="italic">conventus juridicus.</hi> Its sulphur
                    baths were even then well known. It suffered greatly in the 5th century, during
                    the Moorish wars, and, more recently, during the war of independence. The
                    bishopric dates from a very early period, and it is said to have acquired
                    metropolitan rank in the middle of the 6th century; it is now suffragan to
                    Santiago.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
