<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0136-0121-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LYTTON, Edward George Earle Lytton Bulwer Lytton, Baron
                    (9th edition, volume 15, page 121)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41834b98">Wards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pt4b">Novels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039784">Novelle</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1037627">Night</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086604">Racing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n136/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LYTTON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward George Earle Lytton
                            Bulwer Lytton, Baron</hi></label> (1805-1873), novelist, dramatist,
                    poet, politician, miscellaneous essayist, the most versatile writer and one of
                    the most active and widely discursive theorizers of his generation, was born in
                    May 1805, the youngest of the three sons of General Bulwer, of Heydon Hall and
                    Wood Dalling, Norfolk. He was a few months younger than Benjamin Disraeli; the
                    two lives acted not a little one on the other, and offer many curious points of
                    likeness and contrast. Bulwer’s father died when he was two years old; the care
                    of the boy devolved on his mother, one of the Lyttons of Knebworth,
                    Hertfordshire, whose name he afterwards assumed. To this devoted and
                    accomplished mother he always expressed the warmest gratitude for his early
                    training. He was not sent to a public school; he was educated privately.</p>
                <p>In his novels and essays he often discusses the advantages and disadvantages of
                    public schools. One thing is tolerably certain—that if he had been sent to a
                    public school he would not have published at the age of fifteen a volume of
                    poems <hi rend="italic">{Ismael, an Oriental Tale, with other Poems,</hi> 1820).
                    Generous sentiment and eager love of fame are more conspicuous in these juvenile
                    productions, than metrical faculty. One of the poems dwells warmly on the
                    ancient glories of the house of Lytton; the volume as a whole is dedicated to
                    “the British public—that generous public who have always been the fosterers of
                    industry or genius, who have always looked forward from the imperfections of
                    youth to the fruits of maturity.” The youthful poet criticizes Byron from the
                    point of view of a respectable household; but, though he seems to have been
                    taught to make Pope,'Gray, and Collins his models, the Byronic influence is very
                    apparent both in phrase and in sentiment. In the local colouring of the
                    “Oriental Tale <hi rend="superscript"> ,r</hi> he gives promise, afterwards
                    amply fulfilled, of painstaking study of his materials; and “Geraldine, or the
                    Fatal Boon,” gives a good foretaste of his fertility in the invention of
                    romantic incident.</p>
                <p>At Cambridge, in 1825, Bulwer won the chancellor’s medal with a poem on
                    “Sculpture.” In 1826 he printed for private circulation <hi rend="italic">Weeds
                        and Wild Flowers.</hi> In 1827 he published <hi rend="italic">O'Neill, or
                        the Rebel,</hi> a romance, in heroic couplets, of patriotic struggle in
                    Ireland, dedicated to Lady Blessington. These juvenilia, and also a metrical
                    satire,. <hi rend="italic">The Siamese Twins,</hi> issued in 1831, he afterwards
                    ignored, describing <hi rend="italic">The New</hi><hi rend="italic">Timon</hi>
                    as his first publication in verse, with the exception of his dramas and
                    translations from Schiller.</p>
                <p>Bulwer’s first romance, <hi rend="italic">Falkland,</hi> published anonymously in
                    1827, was in the vein of fantastic German romance popular at the beginning of
                    the century, and did not bring him the fame that he coveted so ardently. It was
                    otherwise with <hi rend="italic">Pelham,</hi> published in the following year.
                    In this he went with the native stream of fiction, and at once made himself felt
                    as a power. For two or three years before he wrote <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pelham,</hi> the books of the season had been novels of remarkable
                    freshness and brilliancy dealing with fashionable life—Plumer Ward’s now
                    forgotten but then much-talked-of <hi rend="italic">Tremaine,</hi> Theodore
                    Hook’s <hi rend="italic">Sayings and Doings,</hi> Lister’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Granby,</hi> Disraeli’s <hi rend="italic">Vivian Grey.</hi> With· these
                    brilliant celebrities Bulwer, always a chivalrous emulator of whatever was
                    famous, entered into direct competition, and at once became at least their equal
                    in popular favour. If we compare this his first novel with any of his last
                    productions, he strikes us as having attained at a bound to the full measure of
                    his powers. That he wrote <hi rend="italic">Pelham</hi> at twenty-two is a much
                    more remarkable fact than that he w r0te ballads at five. The plot is not
                    perhaps so closely woven together as in <hi rend="italic">The Parisians,</hi>
                    but the variety of character introduced from high life, low life, and middle
                    life is quite as great. He had evidently been fascinated by <hi rend="italic"
                        >Wilhelm Meister,</hi> and the central purpose of his story is to run the
                    hero through an apprenticeship like Wilhelm’s.. All kinds of human beings and
                    all their works are interesting to Pelham, the man of fashion, the bustling
                    statesman,.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n137/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0137-0122"/>
                <p>the selfish epicure, the retiring scholar, the reckless rogue and vagabond, the
                    melodramatic Byronic man of mystery; and his adventures are so contrived as to
                    bring him in contact with many different types. The novel might have been called
                        <hi rend="italic">The Londoners;</hi> most of the criticisms of life and
                    books in <hi rend="italic">England and the English,</hi> published in 1833, may
                    be found in <hi rend="italic">Pelham,</hi> delivered through the mouths of
                    various characters. These characters are great talkers; no subject, from a rare
                    dish or a nicety of costume to a painting or a philosophical treatise, is
                    strange to them. And," curiously enough, the judgments of the youth of
                    twenty-two are as mature, as large, catholic, generous, widely sympathetic, as
                    those of the sage of sixty-six, and his knowledge of men and books hardly less
                    extensive. <hi rend="italic">Pelham</hi> displayed—in the literal sense of the
                    word— extraordinary vivacity of intellect and range of interest. The author was
                    yet to prove that with his wonderful powers of reading, observing, and
                    reflecting was combined a faculty rarely found in union with such gifts,
                    untiring rapidity of production. In the preface to his juvenile “Ismael,” he
                    speaks of a habit of his never to leave anything unfinished, and during his long
                    life he began and finished many works in many different veins. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pelham</hi> was followed in quick succession by <hi rend="italic">The
                        Disowned</hi> (1828), <hi rend="italic">Devereux</hi> (1829), <hi
                        rend="italic">Paul Clifford</hi> (1830), <hi rend="italic">Eugene Aram</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Godolphin</hi> (1833). Bulwer was deeply impressed with
                    German theories of art; all these novels were novels with a purpose, moral
                    purpose, psychological purpose, historical purpose. To embody the leading
                    features of a period, of a phase of civilization, to trace the influence of
                    circumstance on character, to show how the criminal may be reformed by the
                    development of his better nature, and how men of fine nature may be led stage by
                    stage into crime, to explain the secrets of success and failure in life—these,
                    apart from the purely dramatic object of exhibiting inward struggles between the
                    first conceptions of desires and their fulfilment, and between triumph and
                    retribution, were his avowed aims as a novelist. He did not leave his purposes
                    to the interpreter; he was a critic as well as a creator, and he criticized his
                    own works frankly, and laboured to admit other critics to a fair point of view.
                    It was perhaps a tribute to the intrinsic interest of his plots, characters, and
                    descriptions that he was under the necessity of begging attention to these
                    higher aims. In <hi rend="italic">The Pilgrims of the Rhine</hi> (1834), a work
                    of graceful fantasy, in which some of his most acute observations on human life
                    are incorporated with the sayings and doings of elves and fairies, an ambitious
                    author is made to complain that “the subtle aims that had inspired him were not
                    perceived,” and that he was often approved for what he condemned himself. The
                        <hi rend="italic">Pilgrims,</hi> charmingly written in many passages, was
                    too German in its combination of serious thought and mundane personages with
                    fairies to be heartily welcomed by the English public. Bulwer was more
                    successful in another attempt to break new ground in <hi rend="italic">The Last
                        Days of Pompeii</hi> (1834) and <hi rend="italic">Rienzi</hi> (1835). No
                    historical romances dealing with times and scenes so remote were ever more
                    widely popular in England, and in aiming at popularity the author laboured hard
                    to secure historical accuracy. In <hi rend="italic">Athens, its Rise and
                        Fall</hi> (1836), we received in the form of historical essays what had
                    probably been acquired industriously as materials for romance. Two romances from
                    Spanish history, <hi rend="italic">Leila</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Calderon,</hi> published in 1838, aimed at a less realistic treatment, and,
                    with all their purely literary excellences, were not so popular. In <hi
                        rend="italic">Ernest Maltravers</hi> (1837) and its sequel <hi rend="italic"
                        >Alice, or The Mysteries</hi> (1838), the novelist returned to English
                    ground and psychological and social problems—“the affliction of the good, the
                    triumph of the unprincipled.” Critics to whom he failed to make the full purpose
                    of these works apparent in the execution complained of the low tone of their
                    morality, a fair complaint concerning most exhibitions of vice as a warning.</p>
                <p>To his other literary labours Bulwer superadded for some time the editorship of a
                    magazine. He succeeded Campbell as editor of <hi rend="italic">The New
                        Monthly</hi> in 1833. In 1838 he projected a magazine called <hi
                        rend="italic">The Monthly Chronicle,</hi> and contributed to it as a serial
                    story the fantastic romance “ZiccL” The magazine expired before the story was
                    completed, and it was afterwards developed into <hi rend="italic">Zaηoηi,</hi> a
                    romance of which he was himself especially proud, and which suffered in public
                    estimation from being tried by realistic standards.</p>
                <p>During the most productive period of his literary life Bulwer was an eminent
                    member of parliament. He was returned for St Ives in 1831, and sat for Lincoln
                    from 1832 to 1841. He spoke in favour of the Reform Bill, and took the leading
                    part in obtaining the reduction, after vainly trying to procure the repeal, of
                    the newspaper stamp duties. His support of the Whigs in parliament, and by a
                    pamphlet on “the crisis” when they were dismissed from office in 1834, was
                    considered so valuable that Lord Melbourne offered him a place in the
                    administration. His intimacy with Radical leaders at this period exposed him to
                    an undeserved charge of tergiversation when later in life he was a member of a
                    Conservative Government. Charles Buller and Charles Villiers were among his
                    friends at Cambridge; he was an admiring student of Bentham; Mill’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Essay on Government</hi> was the text-book on which was
                    founded “Pelham’s” instruction by his uncle in the principles of politics; J. S.
                    Mill contributed the substance of the appendices to <hi rend="italic">England
                        and the English,</hi> on Bentham and Mill; Godwin suggested to him the
                    subject and some part of the plot of <hi rend="italic">Eugene Aram</hi>; he even
                    succeeded in winning the good opinion of Miss Martineau; but we have only to
                    read his speech in favour of the Reform Bill to see that it was the situation
                    that had changed and not the man when he assailed the repeal of the corn laws,
                    and took office under Lord Derby. Bulwer’s leading political aim, like his
                    leading artistic aims, was early formulated, and the formula governed all his
                    political reasoning: it was to “aristocratize the community,” “to elevate the
                    masses in character and feeling to the standard which conservatism works in
                    aristocracy,” a standard not of wealth or pedigree but of “superior education,
                    courteous manners, and high honour.” Hence it was “social reforms” from first to
                    last that enlisted his interest, and he sought the motive power for these
                    reforms in the public spirit of the classes enfranchised by the Reform Act of
                    1832.</p>
                <p>There was a slight break in Bulwer’s career as a novelist between 1838 and 1847.
                    During this interval he applied himself enthusiastically to play
                    writing,—Macready’s management of Covent Garden having inspired men of letters
                    with the hope of reconciling poetry with the stage. In 1836 he had produced <hi
                        rend="italic">The Duchess of</hi><hi rend="italic">La Vallière.</hi> It was
                    a failure. But in 1838 and the two following years he produced three plays which
                    have kept the stage ever since— <hi rend="italic">The Lady of Lyons,
                        Richelieu,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Money.</hi> In his plays as in his
                    novels definite theory preceded execution. The principles on which he wrote his
                    plays were laid down in his chapter on the drama in <hi rend="italic">England
                        and the English.</hi> For many of the details of stagecraft, all-important
                    to success under any principles, he is said to have been indebted to Macready.
                    No Englishman not himself an actor has written so many permanently successful
                    plays as Bulwer Lytton, and this is another instance of his extraordinary
                    plasticity of mind and practical insight. Thirty years afterwards, in 1869, he
                    turned his thoughts again to writing for the stage, recast an old failure with a
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n138/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0915-0138-0123"/> new title <hi rend="italic">The Rightful
                        Heir,</hi> and produced a new comedy, <hi rend="italic">Walpole.</hi>
                    Neither was a success.</p>
                <p>From 1841 to 1852 Bulwer (he assumed his mother’s name of Lytton on succeeding to
                    her estates in 1843) had no seat in parliament. But the issue of novels and
                    romances was not so rapid as it had been in the full energy of his youth. Before
                    1849, when he opened a new vein with <hi rend="italic">The Caxtons,</hi> he
                    produced five works in his familiar vein :— <hi rend="italic">Night and
                        Morning</hi> (1841, in which the influence of Dickens is traceable), <hi
                        rend="italic">Zaηοni</hi> (1842), <hi rend="italic">The Last of the
                        Barons</hi> (1843, the most historically solid, and perhaps the most
                    effective of his romances), <hi rend="italic">Lucretia, or the Children of the
                        Night</hi> (1847; moral purpose—to exhibit the horrors caused by the worship
                    of money; popular effect—disgust at these horrors, and indignation at the
                    author’s sentiment as morbid), <hi rend="italic">Harold, The Last of the Saxon
                        Kings</hi> (1848).</p>
                <p>The cause of the comparative infertility of this period in prose fiction probably
                    was that Lytton was now making a determined effort to win high rank as a poet.
                    He published a volume of poems in 1842, a volume of translations from Schiller
                    in 1844, <hi rend="italic">The New</hi><hi rend="italic">Timon,</hi> a satire,
                    in 1845.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A feeble attack
                            in the last on Mr Tennyson’s poetry provoked a brusque but powerful
                            reply from the enraged laureate, aimed at his assailant’s
                        person.</p></note> Then came the work on which mainly Lytton rested his
                    pretensions, <hi rend="italic">King Arthur,</hi> a romantic epic. “I am
                    unalterably convinced,” he said, “that on this foundation I rest the least
                    perishable monument of those thoughts and those labours which’ have made the
                    life of my life.” But <hi rend="italic">King Arthur</hi> fell flat. The verse,
                    the six-lined stave of elegiac quatrain and couplet, lacks charm and variety;
                    the incidents are monotonous, the personages uninteresting, the plot unexciting,
                    and the allegory obscure. <hi rend="italic">St Stephen’s,</hi> a gallery of
                    parliamentary portraits from the time of Queen Anne, was a kind of metrical
                    composition that lay more within his powers. In this the satire is keen-edged,
                    the admiration just and generous. It was published in 1860. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Lost Tales of Miletus</hi> (1866) and a translation of
                    Horace’s <hi rend="italic">Odes</hi> (1869) were Lytton’s last essays in
                    verse.</p>
                <p>In the skill with which he sustained a new style in <hi rend="italic">The
                        Caxtons</hi> (1848) Lytton gave a more convincing proof of his versatility.
                    This imitation of Sterne (by no means a servile imitation, rather an adaptation
                    of Sterne’s style and characters to the circumstances of the 19th century)
                    appeared anonymously in <hi rend="italic">Blackwood’s Magazine,</hi> and made a
                    reputation before the authorship was suspected. <hi rend="italic">My Novel</hi>
                    (1853) and <hi rend="italic">What will He Do with Itl</hi> (1858) continued in
                    the same strain. The sub-title of <hi rend="italic">My Novel,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> u</hi> Varieties of English life,” shows still
                    operative the same purpose that we find in <hi rend="italic">Pelham,</hi> but
                    the criticism of the “Varieties” is more polemical in spirit. There is more than
                    a shade of defiance in his praise of the virtues of a territorial aristocracy,
                    and a strong spice of hostility to the vulgarities of the manufacturers who
                    threatened to push them from their stools. There is a blindness to defects in
                    the one case and to merits in the other quite foreign to the broad sympathies of
                    the dandy Pelham; Caxton paints the ideal best of the one class and the ideal
                    worst of the other. In these, as in all Lytton’s novels, the characters are
                    placed on the stage and described; they are not left to reveal themselves
                    gradually in action.</p>
                <p>Lytton returned to parliament in 1852 as member for Hertfordshire, and sat on the
                    Conservative side. Early in life he had decided in his mind against the
                    reduction of the corn duties, and, unchanged in 1851, he addressed a “Letter to
                    John Bull,” enlarging on the dangers of their repeal. Incapable of failure in
                    any intellectual exercise that he set his mind to, he was an effective speaker;
                    but the effort was against nature: he could speak only under extreme excitement
                    or after laborious preparation, and he never took a high place among
                    parliamentary orators. He was colonial secretary in Lord Derby’s Government from
                    1858 to 1859, and threw himself industriously into the duties of his office. He
                    was raised to the peerage as Baron Lytton in 1866.</p>
                <p>That he had not forgotten his power of moving the sense of melodramatic and
                    romantic mystery when he adopted the more subdued style of <hi rend="italic">The
                        Caxtons,</hi> Lytton proved by <hi rend="italic">A Strange Story,</hi>
                    contributed to <hi rend="italic">All the Year Round</hi> in 1862. A serial story
                    of the kind made a new call on his resources, but he was equal to it, and fairly
                    rivalled the school of Dickens in the art of sustaining thrilling interest to
                    the close.</p>
                <p>When he died, in January 1873, after a short painful illness, two works of high
                    repute, <hi rend="italic">The Coming Race</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The
                        Parisians,</hi> were not acknowledged, and were only vaguely suspected to be
                    his. They had freshness enough to be the work of youth, and power enough to
                    shame no veteran. These two books, the fable and the novel, are classed by
                    Lytton’s son and successor in the the title with the romance of <hi
                        rend="italic">Kenelm Chillingly,</hi> left completed at his death, as
                    forming a trilogy, animated by a common purpose, to exhibit the influence of
                    “modern ideas” upon character and conduct. The moulding force whose operation is
                    traced in <hi rend="italic">The Parisians</hi> is the society of imperial and
                    democratic France, in <hi rend="italic">Chillingly</hi> the society of England
                    in relation to its representative institûtions. The leading purpose is kept well
                    in view throughout both works, and the tendencies to corruption analysed and
                    presented with admirable skill; but the theorist has omitted from his problem
                    certain important regenerating and safeguarding factors in the large world
                    outside the pale of society. Problems and theories apart, these last works show
                    no falling off' of power; he is as vivid as ever in description, as fertile as
                    ever in the invention of humorous and melodramatic situation. If he had been
                    content to abandon his purpose in <hi rend="italic">Chillingly,</hi> and end
                    with the first volume by some such commonplace contrivance as giving “motive
                    power” to his hero in the love of Cecilia Travers, it would have been the most
                    perfect of his works in unity of humorous sentiment. The veteran author died in
                    harness,—two novels all but completed; another, an historical romance, <hi
                        rend="italic">Pausanias</hi><hi rend="italic">the Spartan,</hi> outlined and
                    partly written.</p>
                <p>The fact that in the fiftieth year of his authorship, after publishing at least
                    fifty separate works, most of them popular, Lord Lytton had still vigour and
                    freshness enough to make a new anonymous reputation with <hi rend="italic">The
                        Coming Race</hi> would seem to indicate that critics had not fairly gauged
                    his versatility, and also that an erroneous fixed idea had been formed of his
                    style. The explanation probably is that even after the publication of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Caxtons</hi> he was thought of in connexion with that
                    school of melodramatic romance of which he was indisputably the leader, if not
                    the founder, and that heavily loaded rhetorical style which was made ridiculous
                    by his imitators. “Every great genius,” one of his characters is made to say,
                    “must deem himself alone in bis conceptions. It is not enough for him that these
                    conceptions should be approved as good, unless they are admitted as inventive.”
                    Invention and originality are matters of degree, and, though no one can deny
                    that Lytton possessed great inventive powers, he did not put that individual
                    stamp on his work without which no writer is entitled to a place in the foremost
                    rank. He was not self-centred ençugh; he was too generally emulous to win the
                    highest individual distinction. But his freshness of thought, brilliancy of
                    invention, breadth and variety of portraiture, gave him a just title to his
                    popularity, and, with all allowance for superficial affectations, his generous
                    nobility of sentiment made his influence as wholesome as it was widespread. (w.
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">μ.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
