<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0080-0067-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LURAY CAVERN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 67</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m3m">Caves</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh5s">Columns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s42j">Crystallization</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b56d58r">Floors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j6857x">Railroads</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bm5h">Toys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40c4st3m">Shopping</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204597">Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1088711">Railroads</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:868845">Columns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1153487">Toys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1116884">Shopping</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1174597">White</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1174816">Whites</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:849907">Caves</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:849926">Caving</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n80/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LURAY CAVERN</label>, in Page county, Virginia, United
                    States, 39° 35' N. lat. and 78° 17' W. long., is 1 mile west of the village of
                    Luray, on the Shenandoah Valley Railroad. The valley, here 10 miles wide,
                    extends from the Blue Ridge to the Massanutton mountain, and displays remarkably
                    fine scenery. These ridges lie in vast folds and wrinkles; and elevations in the
                    valley are often found to be pierced by erosion. Cave Hill, 300 feet above the
                    water-level, had long been an object of local interest on account of its pits
                    and oval hollows, or sink-holes, through one of which, August 13, 1878, Mr
                    Andrew J. Campbell and others entered, thus discovering the extensive and
                    beautiful cavern now described.</p>
                <p>Geologically considered, the Luray cavern does not date beyond the Tertiary
                    period, though carved from the Silurian limestone. At some period long
                    subsequent to its original excavation, and after many large stalactites had
                    grown, it was completely filled with glacial mud charged with acid, whereby the
                    dripstone was eroded into singularly grotesque shapes. After the mud had been
                    mostly removed by flowing water, these eroded forms remained amid the new
                    growths. To this contrast may be ascribed some of the most striking scenes in
                    the cave. The many and extraordinary monuments of aqueous energy include massive
                    columns wrenched from their place in the ceiling and prostrate on the floor; the
                    hollow column 40 feet high and 30 feet in diameter, standing erect, but pierced
                    by a tubular passage from top to bottom; the leaning column, nearly as large,
                    undermined and tilting like the campanile of Pisa; the organ, a cluster of
                    stalactites dropped points downward and standing thus in the room known as the
                    cathedral; besides a vast bed of disintegrated carbonates left by the whirling
                    flood in its retreat through the great space called the Elfin Ramble.</p>
                <p>The stalactitic display exceeds that of any other cavern known, and there is
                    hardly a square yard on the walls or ceiling that is not thus ornamented. The
                    old material is yellow, brown, or red; and its wavy surface often shows layers
                    like the gnarled grain of costly woods. The new stalactites growing from the
                    old, and made of hard carbonates that had already once been used, are usually
                    white as snow, though often pink, blue, or amber-coloured. The size attained by
                    single specimens is surprising. The Empress Column is a stalagmite 35 feet high,
                    rose-coloured, and elaborately draped. The double column, named from Professors
                    Henry and Baird, is made of two fluted pillars side by side,the one 25 and the
                    other 60 feethigh, a mass of snowy alabaster. Several stalactites in the Giant
                    Hall exceed 50 feet in length. The smaller pendents are innumerable; in the
                    canopy above the Imperial Spring it is estimated that 40,000 are visible at
                    once.</p>
                <p>The “cascades” pointed out are wonderful formations like foaming cataracts caught
                    in mid-air and transformed into milk-white or amber alabaster. The Chalcedony
                    Cascade displays a variety of colours. Brand’s Cascade, which is the finest of
                    all, being 40 feet high and 30 feet wide, is unsullied and wax-like white, each
                    ripple and braided rill seeming to have been polished.</p>
                <p>The Swords of the Titans are monstrous blades, eight in number, 50 feet long, 3
                    to 8 feet wide, hollow, 1 to 2 feet thick, but drawn down to an extremely thin
                    edge, and filling the cavern with tones like tolling bells when struck heavily
                    by the hand. Their origin and also that of certain so-called scarfs and blankets
                    exhibited is from carbonates deposited by water trickling down a sloping and
                    corrugated surface. Sixteen of these alabaster scarfs hang side by side in
                    Hovey’s Balcony, three white and fine as crape shawls, thirteen striated like
                    agate with every shade of brown, and all perfectly translucent. Down the edge of
                    each a tiny rill glistens like silver, and this is the ever-plying shuttle that
                    weaves the fairy fabric.</p>
                <p>Streams and true springs are absent, but there are hundreds of basins, varying
                    from 1 to 50 feet in diameter, and from 6 inches to 15 feet in depth. The water
                    in them is exquisitely pure, except as it is impregnated by the carbonate of
                    lime, which often forms concretions, called, according to their size, pearls,
                    eggs, and snowballs. A large one is known as the cannon ball. On fracture these
                    spherical growths are found to be radiated in structure.</p>
                <p>Calcite crystals, drusy, feathery, or fern-like, line the sides and bottom of
                    every water-filled cavity, and indeed constitute the substance of which they are
                    made. Variations of level at different periods are marked by rings, ridges, and
                    ruffled margins. These are strongly marked about Broaddus Lake, and the curved
                    ramparts of the Castles on the Rhine. Here also are polished stalagmites, a rich
                    buff slashed with white, and others, like <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n81/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0081-0068"/> huge mushrooms, with a velvety coat of red,
                    purple, or olive-tinted crystals. In some of the smaller basins it sometimes
                    happens that when the excess of carbonic acid escapes rapidly there is formed,
                    besides the crystal bed below, a film above, shot like a sheet of ice across the
                    surface. One pool 12 feet wide is thus covered so as to show but a third of its
                    surface. The quantity of water in the cavern varies greatly at different
                    seasons. Hence some stalactites have their tips under water long enough to allow
                    tassels of crystals to grow on them, which, in a drier season, are again coated
                    over with stalactitic matter; and thus singular distortions are occasioned.
                    Contiguous stalactites are often inwrapped thus till they assume an almost
                    globular form, through which, by making a section, the primary tubes appear.
                    Twig-like projections, lateral outgrowths, to which the term helictite has been
                    applied, are met with in certain portions of the cave, and are interesting by
                    their strange and uncouth contortions. Their presence is partly due to the
                    existence of a diminutive fungus peculiar to the locality, and designated from
                    its habitat <hi rend="italic">Mucor</hi><hi rend="italic">stalactitis.</hi> The
                    Toy-Shop is an amusing collection of these freaks of nature.</p>
                <p>The dimensions of the various chambers included in Luray Cavern cannot easily be
                    stated, on account of the great irregularity of their outlines. Their size may
                    be seen from the diagram on p. 67. But it should be understood that there are
                    several tiers of galleries, and the vertical depth from the highest to the
                    lowest is 260 feet. The tract of 100 acres owned by the Luray Cave Company
                    covers all possible modes of entrance; and the explored area is much less than
                    that.</p>
                <p>The waters of this cavern appear to be entirely destitute of life; and the
                    existing fauna is quite meagre, comprising only a few bats, rats, mice, spiders,
                    flies, and small centipedes. When the cave was first entered, the floor was
                    covered with thousands of tracks of raccoons, wolves, and bears,—most of them
                    probably made long ago, as impressions made in the tenacious clay that composes
                    most of the cavern floor would remain unchanged for centuries. Layers of
                    excrementitious matter appear, and also many small bones, along with a few large
                    ones, all of existing species. The traces of human occupation as yet discovered
                    are pieces of charcoal, flints, moccasin tracks, and a single skeleton imbedded
                    in stalagmite in one of the chasms, estimated to have lain where found fornot
                    morethanfivehundred years, judging from the present rate of stalagmitic
                    growth.</p>
                <p>The temperature is uniformly 54° Fahr., coinciding with that of the Mammoth Cave,
                    Kentucky. The air is very pure, and the avenues are not uncomfortably damp.</p>
                <p>The portions open to the public are now lighted by electric lamps. The registered
                    number of visiters in 1881 was 12,000. <hi rend="smallcaps">(h. c. h.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
