<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0074-0061-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LUINI, Bernardino (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    61)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1150229">Thorns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1002186">Lombards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1063919">Pietà</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f05t">Thorns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26h3v">Lombards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93k3f">Madonna</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n74/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LUINI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Bernardino</hi></label>, the most
                    celebrated master of the Lombard school of painting founded upon the style of
                    Leonardo da Vinci, was born at Luino, a village on the Lago Maggiore, towards
                    1465. He himself wrote his name as “Bernardin Lovino,” but the spelling “Luini”
                    is now very generally adopted. Few facts are known regarding the life of this
                    illustrious and delightful painter, and it is only since a comparatively recent
                    date that he has even been credited with the production of his own works, and
                    with the fame thereto appertaining, as many of them had, in the lapse of years
                    and laxity of attribution, got assigned to Leonardo. It appears that Luini
                    studied painting at Vercelli under Giovenone, or perhaps under Lo Scotto. He
                    reached Milan either after the departure of Da Vinci in 1500, or shortly before
                    that event; it is thus left uncertain whether or not the two artists had any
                    personal acquaintance, but Luini was at any rate in the painting-school
                    established in Milan by the great Florentine. In the latter works of Luini a
                    certain influence from the style of Raphael is superadded to that, far more
                    prominent and fundamental, from the style of Leonardo; but there is nothing to
                    show that he ever visited Rome. His two sons are the only pupils who have with
                    confidence been assigned to him; and even this can scarcely be true of the
                    younger, who was born in 1530, when Bernardino was well advanced in years, and
                    was not far from the close of his career. Gaudenzio Ferrari has also been termed
                    his disciple. One of the sons, Evangelista, has left little which can now be
                    identified; the other, Aurelio, was accomplished in perspective and landscape
                    work. There was likewise a brother of Bernardino, named Ambrogio, a competent
                    painter. Bernardino, who hardly ever left Lombardy, had some merit as a poet,
                    and is said to have composed a treatise on painting. The precise date of his
                    death is unknown; he may perhaps have survived till about 1540. A serene,
                    contented, and happy mind, naturally expressing itself in forms of grace and
                    beauty, seems stamped upon all the works of Luini. The same character is
                    traceable in his portrait, painted in an upper group in his fresco of Christ
                    Crowned with Thorns in the Ambrosian library in Milan,—a venerable bearded
                    personage. The only anecdote which has been preserved of him tells a similar
                    tale. It is said that for the single figures of saints in the church at Saronno
                    he received a sum of money equal to 22 francs per day, along with wine, bread,
                    and lodging; and he was so well satisfied with this remuneration that, in
                    completing the commission, he painted a Nativity for nothing.</p>
                <p>Along with this natural sweetness of character, a dignified suavity is the most
                    marked characteristic of Luini’s works. They are constantly beautiful, with a
                    beauty which depends at least as much upon the loving self-withdrawn expression
                    as upon the mere refinement and attractiveness of form. This quality of
                    expression appears in all Luini’s productions, whether secular or sacred, and
                    imbues the latter with a peculiarly religious grace—not ecclesiastical unction,
                    but the devoutness of the heart. His heads, while extremely like those painted
                    by Leonardo, have less subtlety and involution and less variety of expression,
                    but fully as much amenity. He began indeed with a somewhat dry style, as in the
                    Pietà in the church of the Passione; but this soon developed into the quality
                    which distinguishes all his most renowned works; although his execution,
                    especially as regards modelling, was never absolutely on a par with that of
                    Leonardo. Luini’s paintings do not exhibit an impetuous style of execution, and
                    certainly not a negligent one; yet it appears that he was in fact a very rapid
                    worker, as his picture of the Crowning with Thorns, painted for the College del
                    S. Sepolcro, and containing a large number of figures, is recorded to have
                    occupied him only thirty-eight days, to which an assistant added eleven. His
                    method was simple and expeditious, the shadows being painted with the pure
                    colour laid on thick, while the lights are of the same colour thinly used, and
                    mixed with a little white. The frescos <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n75/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0915-0075-0062"/> exhibit more freedom of hand than the oil
                    pictures; and they are on the whole less like the work of Da Vinci, having at an
                    early date a certain resemblance to the style of Mantegna, as later on to that
                    of Raphael. Luini’s colouring is mostly rich, and his light and shade
                    forcible.</p>
                <p>Among his principal works the following are to he mentioned. At Saronno are
                    frescos painted towards 1525, representing the life of the Madonna—her Marriage,
                    the Presentation of the Infant Saviour in the Temple, the Adoration of the Magi,
                    and other incidents. His own portrait appears in the subject of the youthful
                    Jesus with the Doctors in the Temple. This series—in which some comparatively
                    archaic details occur, such as gilded nimbuses—was partly repeated from one
                    which Luini had executed towards 1520 in S. Croce. In the Brera Gallery, Milan,
                    are frescos from the suppressed church of La Pace and the Convent della
                    Felucca,—the former treating subjects from the life of the Virgin, the latter,
                    of a classic kind, more decorative in manner. The subject of girls playing at
                    the game of “hot-cockles,” and that of three angels depositing St Catherine in
                    her sepulchre, are particularly memorable, each of them a work of perfect charm
                    and grace in its way. In the Casa Silva, Milan, are frescos from Ovid’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Metamorphoses.</hi> The Monastero Maggiore of Milan (or church
                    of S. Maurizio) is a noble treasure-house of Luini’s art,—including a large
                    Crucifixion, with about one hundred and forty figures; Christ Bound to the
                    Column, between figures of Saints Catherine and Stephen, and the founder of the
                    chapel kneeling before Catherine; the Martyrdom of this Saint; the Entombment of
                    Christ; and a large number of other subjects. In the Ambrosian library is the
                    fresco (already mentioned), covering one entire wall of the Sala della S.
                    Corona, of Christ Crowned with Thorns, with two executioners, and on each side
                    six members of a confraternity; in the same building the Infant Baptist Playing
                    with a Lamb; in the Brera, the Virgin Enthroned, with Saints, dated 1521; in the
                    Louvre, the Daughter of Herodias receiving the Head of the Baptist; in the
                    Esterhazy Gallery, Vienna, the Virgin between Saints Catherine and Barbara; in
                    the National Gallery, London, Christ Disputing with the Doctors. Many or most of
                    these gallery pictures used to pass for the handiwork of Da Vinci. The same is
                    the case with the highly celebrated Vanity and Modesty in the Sciarra Palace,
                    Rome, which also may nevertheless in all probability be assigned to Luini.
                    Another singularly beautiful picture by him, which seems to pass almost entirely
                    unobserved by tourists and by writers, is in the Royal Palace in Milan—a large
                    composition of Women Bathing. That Luini was also pre-eminent as a decorative
                    artist is shown by his works in the Certosa of Pavia.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
