<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0035-0022-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LOUISVILLE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 22</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1205075">Ohio</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204604">Indiana</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1432109">Tobacco</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n35/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LOUISVILLE</label>, the sixteenth city of the United States
                    in population, and the most important place in the State of Kentucky, is
                    situated on the south bank of the Ohio river, in 38° 3' N. lat. and 85° 30' W.
                    long. The river is here interrupted by a series of rapids which, except at high
                    water, oblige the steamboat traffic to make use of the Louisville and Portland
                    Canal (2J miles long, constructed in 1833). The city, which has an area of 13
                    square miles, and a water front of 8 miles, occupies an almost level site about
                    70 feet above low-water mark. Its plan is regular and spacious, and, in the
                    residential portions the houses, for the most part, have lawns and gardens in
                    front. Among the public buildings of importance may be mentioned the city-hall,
                    the court-house, the public library, the female high school, the industrial
                    exhibition building, the Roman Catholic cathedral, and the State school for the
                    blind.</p>
                <p>From the time of the introduction of steam navigation upon the Ohio by Fulton in
                    1812, Louisville rapidly gained in importance as a centre of river trade. Owing
                    to its <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n36/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0036-0023"/> position at the “falls of the Ohio, which
                    obstruction long made necessary the transfer of goods at this point, the city
                    became an important depot of supplies for the cotton-growing States lying
                    immediately to the south. The owners of plantations in those States devoted
                    themselves wholly to the culture of cotton, and relied upon Kentucky for
                    supplies of wheat, Indian corn, oats, and the like cereals, for the hempen
                    bagging and rope used in baling the cotton, and for mules and horses, large
                    droves of which were annually driven south from Louisville. The city was also
                    for many years one of the principal points in the United States for
                    pork-packing.</p>
                <p>After the close of the civil war, the development of Kentucky, as of the South
                    generally, entered new channels. Largely increased facilities of railway
                    transportation, while bringing Louisville into more direct competition with
                    Cincinnati, St Louis, and Chicago, resulted in a marked increase of both its
                    commercial and manufacturing interests, notwithstanding the decline of the river
                    trade. The extensive tobacco crop of Kentucky, with much of that grown in
                    neighbouring States, now finds a market at Louisville, instead of at New Orleans
                    as formerly; and it has become probably the largest market in the world for leaf
                    tobacco, 68,300 hogsheads of which, of an aggregate value exceeding $5,000,000,
                    were sold here during 1881. The manufacture of whisky is also important, this,
                    with that of tobacco, paying to the Federal Government nearly $3,000,000
                    annually in revenue taxes, in the Louisville district. Pork-packing employs a
                    capital of $2,520,000, and the tanning of leather $1,704,000, this industry
                    being twenty times larger than before the war, and the product, especially of
                    sole-leather, being in high demand. The manufacture of agricultural and
                    mechanical implements employs $1,915,000 capital, the plough factories, which
                    produce 125,000 ploughs annually, being among the largest in the United States.
                    Steam-power is chiefly employed, the available water-power of the rapids having
                    been neglected. The greater part of the coal consumed by the factories is
                    brought down the Ohio from Pittsburg. The mountainous eastern portion of the
                    State, rich in vast deposits of both coal and iron, is now penetrated by several
                    railroads, and others are being constructed, whose influence in developing this
                    mineral wealth will add largely to the prosperity of the city.</p>
                <p>The reports of the United States census of 1880 give the following summary of the
                    industries of the city :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>I860..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1870.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>18S0.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Number of establishments</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>j 436</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>801</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,191</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Number of hands employed</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>j 7,396</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11,589</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>21,937</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Capital invested</p><p>Wages
                            paid</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>$5,023,491</p><p>2,120,179</p><p>7,896,891</p><p>14,135,517</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>$11,129,291</p><p>4,464,040</p><p>10,369,556</p><p>20,364,650</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>$20,864,449</p><p>5,765,387</p><p>22,362,704</p><p>35,908,338</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Value of material....</p><p>Value of
                            product ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The Louisville and Nashville Railway, opened in 1859, controls, under one
                    management, nearly 4000 miles of connected lines, reaching New Orleans,
                    Pensacola, and Savannah. Various other lines contribute to make Louisville an
                    important railway centre.</p>
                <p>A bridge across the river, 5218-j feet long between abutments, with twenty-seven
                    spans, and admitting the free passage of steamboats at high water, affords
                    continuous railway transit, and connects the city with the thriving towns of New
                    Albany (population 16,423) and Jeffersonville (population 9357), situated on the
                    opposite bank of the Ohio, in the State of Indiana. A second railway bridge,
                    having waggon-ways and foot-ways in addition, is now (1882) building.</p>
                <p>Louisville is provided with adequate water-works, gasworks, Ac. The famous Dupont
                    artesian well, 2066 feet deep, has a flow of 330,000 gallons per day, with a
                    force of ten horse-power, its water resembling slightly that of the Kissengen
                    and Blue Lick (Ky.) springs. Although once regarded as unhealthy, the city has
                    now an effective system of sewerage, and is in good sanitary condition.</p>
                <p>The public school system is sustained at an annual expense of over $300,000,
                    abundant separate provision being made for coloured children. There are four
                    medical colleges, having a large attendance and reputation, and numerous private
                    seminaries and schools. Among the newspapers published at Louisville the <hi
                    rend="italic">Courier Journal</hi> deserves mention both for its early connexion
                    with George D. Prentice, and as a leading representative of the best order of
                    American journalism. There are four other dailies (two English and two German),
                    besides thirteen weekly sheets.</p>
                <p>Louisville is a port of entry for foreign imports, which aggregate annually about
                    $125,000. The city is governed by a mayor, elected every third year, with a
                    board of aldermen and a common council, the former containing one, and the
                    latter two representatives of each of the twelve wards. The population in 1830
                    was 10,341; in 1840, 21,210; in 1850, 43,196; in 1860, 68,033; in 1870, 100,753;
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n37/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0037-0024"/> and in 1880 it was 123,758. This last total
                    includes 20,905 persons of colour and 23,156 foreigners, the larger proportion
                    of the latter being Germans.</p>
                <p>It was in 1778 that Colonel George Rogers Clarke, on his way down the Ohio, left
                    a company of settlers who took possession of Corn Island (no longer existing),
                    near the Kentucky shore above the falls; and in the following year the first
                    rude cluster of cabins appeared on the site of the present city. An Act of the
                    Virginian legislature in 1780 gave the little settlement the rank of a town, and
                    called it Louisville in honour of Louis XVI. of France, then assisting the
                    American colonies in their struggle for independence. The rank of city was
                    conferred by the Kentucky legislature in 1828.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
