<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0099-0086-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LUXEMBOURG, François (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    86)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1211813">Luxembourg</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07518">Face</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02z952">Cannon</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899352">Dues</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004133">Luxembourgers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010769">Marshals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025853">Months</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n99/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LUXEMBOURG, <hi rend="smallcaps">François</hi></label><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Henri de Montmorency-Boutteville, Dug de</hi> (1628-1695),
                    marshal of France, the comrade and successor of the great Condé, was born at
                    Paris on January 8, 1628. His father, the Comte de Montmorency-Boutteville, had
                    been executed six months before his birth for killing the Marquis de Beuvron in
                    a duel, but his aunt, the Princesse de Condé, recognizing in him the last male
                    heir of her great family De Montmorency, took charge of him, and educated him
                    with her son, the Due d’Enghien. The young Montmorency attached himself
                    enthusiastically to his cousin, and shared his successes and reverses throughout
                    the troubles of the Fronde. He returned to France in 1659 and was pardoned, and
                    Condé, who was then much attached to the Duchesse de Châtillon, Montmorency’s
                    sister, contrived the marriage of his adherent and cousin to the greatest
                    heiress in France, the Princesse de Tingry, after which he was created Due de
                    Luxembourg and peer of France. At the opening· of the war of the devolution,
                    1667-68, Condé, and consequently Luxembourg, had no command, but in the second
                    campaign he served as one of Condé’s lieutenants in the conquest of Franche
                    Comté. During the four years of peace which followed the peace of
                    Aix-la-Chapelle, Luxembourg diligently cultivated the favour of Louvois, and in
                    1672 received orders to commence hostilities with the Dutch. He defeated the
                    prince of Orange, whom he was to beat again and again, at Woerden, and ravaged
                    Holland, and in 1673 made his famous retreat from Utrecht with only 20,000 men
                    in face of 70,000, an exploit which placed him in the first rank of generals. In
                    1674 he was made captain of the gardes du corps, and in 1675 was made marshal of
                    France. In 1676 he was placed at the head of the army of the Rhine, but failed
                    to keep the duke of Lorraine out of Philipsburg; in 1677 he stormed
                    Valenciennes; and in 1678 he defeated the prince of Orange, who attacked him at
                    St Denis after the signature of the peace of Nimeguen. His reputation was now at
                    a great height, and it is commonly reputed that he quarrelled with Louvois, who
                    managed to mix him up in the confessions of the poisoners, and get him sent to
                    the Bastille. Rousset in his <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                        Louvois</hi> has, however, shown that this quarrel is probably apocryphal.
                    There is no doubt that Luxembourg spent some months of 1680 in the Bastille, but
                    on his release took up his post at court as <hi rend="italic">capitaine</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">des gardes,</hi> and was in no way disgraced. When the war of
                    1690 broke out, the king and Louvois also recognized that Luxembourg was the
                    only general they had fit to cope with the prince of Orange, and accordingly he
                    was put in command of the army of Flanders. On July 1, 1690, he defeated the
                    prince of Waldeck at Fleurus with the loss of 14,000 men and 49 pieces of
                    cannon. In the following year he commanded the army which covered the king, who
                    was besieging Mons, and defeated William III. of England at Leuze on September
                    18, 1691. Again in the next campaign he covered the king’s siege of Namur, and
                    utterly defeated William at Steenkerk on June 5, 1692; and on July 29, 1693, he
                    won his greatest victory over his old adversary at Neerwinden, in which he took
                    76 pieces of cannon and 80 flags. No wonder he was received with enthusiasm at
                    Paris by all but the king, who looked coldly on a relative and adherent of the
                    Condés. He conceived himself strong enough to undertake an enterprise which St
                    Simon describes at length in the first , volume of his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Memoirs</hi>: instead of ranking as eighteenth peer of France according to
                    his patent of 1661, he claimed through his wife to be Due de Piney of an old
                    creation of 1571, which would place him second on the roll. The whole affair is
                    described with St Simon’s usual keen interest in all that concerned the peerage,
                    and was chiefly checked through his assiduity. In the campaign of 1694, possibly
                    owing to this check, Luxembourg did but little in Flanders, except his
                    well-known march from Vignamont to Tournay in face of the enemy. On his return
                    to Versailles for the winter he fell ill, and died on January 4, 1695. In his
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n100/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0915-0100-0087"/> last moments he was attended by the famous
                    Jesuit priest Bourdaloue, who said on his death, “I have not lived his life, but
                    I would wish to die his death.” The holy father certainly had not lived like
                    Luxembourg, whose morals were conspicuously bad even in those times, and whose
                    life had shown very slight signs of religious conviction. But as a general he
                    was Condé’s grandest pupil. Utterly slothful, like Condé, in the management of a
                    campaign, and therein differing from Turenne, at the moment of battle he seemed
                    seized with happy inspirations, against which no ardour of William’s and no
                    steadiness of Dutch or English soldiers could stand. His death and Catinat’s
                    disgrace close the second period of the military history of the reign of Louis
                    XIV., and Catinat and Luxembourg, though inferior to Condé and Turenne, were
                    very far superior to Tailard and Villeroi. He was distinguished for a pungent
                    wit. One of his best retorts referred to his deformity. “I never can beat
                    that'cursed humpback,” William· was reputed to have said of him. “How does he
                    know I have a hump 1” retorted Luxembourg, “he has never seen my back.” He left
                    four sons, the youngest of whom was a marshal of France as Maréchal de
                    Montmorency.</p>
                <p>See the various memoirs and histories of the time. There are some interesting
                    facts in Desormeaux’s <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de la
                        Maison de Montmorency.</hi> Camille Rousset’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lou,υois</hi> should also be studied.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
