<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0710-8816-0373-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GAY, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 10, page 373</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:939255">Gays</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1046191">Operas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1046145">Opera</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90251t">Opera</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93g2m">Friendship</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wr06">Hares</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rv0d79g">Riches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p635">Swifts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193518816" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GAY, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>, a celebrated
                    English poet, descended from an ancient family in Devonshire, was born at
                    Exeter, and received his education at the free school of Barnstaple in that
                    county, under the care of Mr William Rayner. He was bred as a mercer in the
                    Strand; but having a small fortune, independently of business, and considering
                    the attendance on a shop as a degradation of those talents which he knew himself
                    to be possessed of, he quitted that occupation, and applied himself to other
                    pursuits, including the indulgence of his inclination for poetry. In 1712 we
                    find him secretary, or rather domestic steward, to the Duchess of Monmouth, a
                    station in which he continued until the beginning of the year 1714, when he
                    accompanied the Earl of Clarendon to Hanover, whither that nobleman was
                    dispatched by Queen Anne. At the close of the same year, the queen’s death
                    recalled him to England, where he lived in the highest estimation and intimacy
                    of friendship with many persons of the first distinction in point both of rank
                    and abilities. He was even particularly noticed by Queen Caroline, then princess
                    of Wales, to whom he had the honour of reading in manuscript his tragedy of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Captives</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and in 1726 he dedicated
                    his <hi rend="italic">Fables,</hi> by permission, to the Duke of Cumberland.
                    From the countenance thus shown to him, and numberless promises made him of
                    preferment, it was reasonable to suppose, that he would have been provided for
                    in some office suited to his inclination and abilities. But instead of this, in
                    1727, he was offered the place of gentleman usher to one of the young
                    princesses; an office which, looking on it as an indignity to a man whose
                    talents might have been so much better employed, he thought proper to refuse;
                    and some pretty warm remonstrances were made on the occasion by the Duke and
                    Duchess of Queensberry, his sincere friends and zealous patrons, which
                    terminated in these two noble personages withdrawing from court in disgust. Mr
                    Gay’s dependence on the promises of the great, and the disappointments he met
                    with, he has figuratively described in his fable of the <hi rend="italic">Hare
                    with many Friends.</hi> However, the extraordinary success which he met with
                    from the public made ample amends both in respect to satisfaction and emolument;
                    for in the season of 1727-28 appeared his <hi rend="italic">Beggars Opera,</hi>
                    the success of which was not only unprecedented, but almost incredible. It had
                    an uninterrupted run in London of sixty-three nights in the first season, and
                    was renewed in the ensuing one with equal approbation. It spread into all the
                    great towns of England; it was played in many places to the thirtieth and
                    fortieth, and at Bath and Bristol to the fiftieth time; it made its progress
                    into Wales, Scotland, and Ireland, in which last country it was acted for
                    twenty-four successive nights; and it was even performed at the island of
                    Minorca. Nor was the fame of this opera confined to the reading and
                    representation alone, for the card-table and drawing-room shared with the
                    theatre and closet in this respect; the ladies carried about the favourite songs
                    of the piece engraven upon their fans; and screens and other pieces of furniture
                    were decorated with designs from it. In short, the satire of this production was
                    so striking, so apparent, and so perfectly adapted to the taste of all degrees
                    of people, that it overthrew the Italian opera, that dagon of the nobility and
                    gentry, which had so long seduced them to idolatry, and which Dennis by the
                    labours and outcries of a whole life, and many other writers by the force of
                    reason and reflection, had in vain endeavoured to drive from the throne of
                    public taste. The profits of this piece were so very great, both to the author
                    and the manager Mr Rich, that it gave rise to a quibble, which became frequent
                    in the mouths of many, namely, that it had made Rich gay, and Gay rich. It has
                    been asserted, indeed, that the author’s own emoluments from it were not less
                    than L.2000. This success induced Mr Gay to write a second part, which he
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Polly.</hi> But the disgust subsisting between him
                    and the court, together with the misrepresentations made of him as having been
                    the author of some disaffected libels and seditious pamphlets, occasioned a
                    prohibition and suppression of it to be sent from the lord chamberlain, at the
                    very time when every thing was in readiness for the rehearsal of the piece. A
                    very considerable sum, however, accrued to the author from the publication of it
                    afterwards in quarto. Mr Gay wrote several other pieces in the dramatic line,
                    and many valuable compositions in verse. Amongst the latter, his <hi
                    rend="italic">Trivia, or the art of Walking the Streets of London,</hi> though
                    his first poetical attempt, is tar from being the least considerable, and is
                    what recommended him to the esteem and friendship of Mr Pope. But as, among his
                    dramatic works, his Beggar’s Opera did at first, and perhaps ever will, stand as
                    an unrivalled masterpiece, so, among his poetical works, his Fables hold the
                    same degree of estimation; the latter having been almost as universally read as
                    the former was represented, and both equally admired. Mr Gay’s disposition was
                    sweet and affable, his temper generous, and his conversation agreeable and
                    entertaining. But he had one foible, too frequently incident to men of literary
                    abilities, and which subjected him at times to inconveniences which otherwise he
                    might have avoided, namely, an excess of indolence, without any knowledge of
                    economy. Hence, although his emoluments were, at some periods of bis life, very
                    considerable, he was at others greatly straitened in his circumstances; nor
                    could he prevail on himself to follow the advice of his friend Dean Swift, whom
                    we find in many of his letters endeavouring to persuade him to purchase an
                    annuity as a reserve for the exigencies of old age. Mr Gay chose rather to throw
                    himself on patronage, than secure to himself an independent competency by the
                    means pointed out to him; and hence, after having undergone many vicissitudes of
                    fortune, and being for some time chiefly supported by the liberality of the Duke
                    and Duchess of Queensberry, he died at their house in Burlington Gardens, in
                    December 1732. He was interred in Westminster Abbey, and a monument erected to
                    his memory, at the expense <pb break="no" facs="nls:193518829"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0710-8829-0374"/>of his noble benefactors, with an inscription
                    expressive of their regards and his own deserts, and an epitaph in verse by Mr
                    Pope.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
