<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0710-7841-0298-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GALLAND, Antony</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 10, page 298</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:845944">Canonization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:847566">Caring</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xd69">Canonization</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mp4vm9b">Alcoran</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193517841" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GALLAND, <hi rend="smallcaps">Antony</hi></label>, a
                    celebrated orientalist and numismatist, was born, in 1646, at Rollat, near
                    Montdidier, in Picardy. His life shows what may be effected by the love of
                    study, firm resolution, and irreproachable morals. By a rare perseverance in his
                    pursuits, Galland triumphed over the caprices of fortune; by the rectitude and
                    nobleness of his character he was enabled to overcome all the disadvantages of
                    his humble lot. Born of poor parents, he lost his father at the age of four,
                    being the youngest of seven children. But his mother, though reduced to live by
                    the labour of her hands, contrived to place him in the college of Noyon, where
                    the principal and a canon of the cathedral charitably undertook the care and
                    expense of educating young Galland. At the age of fourteen he lost both his
                    benefactors at the same time, and returned to his mother with no other wealth
                    than the knowledge of a little Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, a decided taste for
                    letters, and a firm resolution to apply himself to learning. But as his mother
                    could not of course furnish the means necessary for the completion of his
                    studies, it became necessary to learn a trade and renounce literature. This
                    cruel distraction Galland supported for a year, when, finding it intolerable, he
                    one day set out for Paris, with no other resource than the address of an old
                    relation who was in good circumstances, and that of an ecclesiastic whom he had
                    sometimes seen at the house of the canon of Noyon. The hardihood of this
                    resolution created an interest in his favour į the sub-principal of the college
                    of Plessis made him continue his studies at that seminary, and then confided him
                    to the care of Μ. Petitpied, doctoι of the Sorbonne. Anything more fortunate
                    could not have happened to Galland than this last act of kindness, which may be
                    said to have prepared, and indeed ensured the success of his literary career. He
                    now extended his knowledge of Hebrew and the other oriental languages, attended
                    the courses of instruction in the Royal College, and even undertook to make a
                    catalogue of the oriental manuscripts of the Sorbonne. Doctor Petitpied had jusl
                    placed him in the house of Μ. Godouin, professor in Mazarin College, when Μ. de
                    Nointel set out, in 1670, on hit embassy to Constantinople, and took along with
                    him young Gatland, whose labours and acquirements had already attracted notice.
                    The intention of this minister was to employ Galland in procuring from the Greek
                    churches formal attestations of the articles of their faith, which ther <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193517854" xml:id="kp-eb0710-7854-0299"/> formed the
                    subject of a grand controversy between Arnauld and Claude. Galland soon acquired
                    at Constantinople a knowledge of the vulgar Greek, from his long conferences
                    with the Greek prelates, and obtained from them attestations, along with much
                    information on the subjects discussed in France. De La Croix, secretary of the
                    embassy, makes no mention of these researches in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mémoires;</hi> but it may be supposed that he found them useful in the
                    composition of <hi rend="italic">Etat</hi><hi rend="italic">present de
                    l’</hi><hi rend="italic">Eglise Grecque et</hi><hi rend="italic">Maronite,</hi>
                    published in 1695, 12mo, and reprinted without any alteration under the title of
                    <hi rend="italic">Turquie-Chrétienne.</hi> Galland accompanied Μ. de Nointel in
                    his journey to Jerusalem, and availed himself of the opportunity to copy a great
                    number of inscriptions, and even to remove them, as often as he found it
                    practicable to do so. Of these, Montfaucon has published some fragments in his
                    <hi rend="italic">Palcεo∙</hi><hi rend="italic">graphie.</hi> From Syria Galland
                    returned directly to France, whence he immediately set out again for the Levant
                    with the intention of collecting more medals. In 1679 he undertook a third
                    voyage, being charged by the India company to collect every thing calculated to
                    enrich the cabinet of Colbert; but this commission having ceased in consequence
                    of changes which took place in the company, Colbert, and, after his death,
                    Louvois, instructed Galíand to continue his researches, and caused the title of
                    antiquary to the king to be conferred on him. At the moment when he was about to
                    embark at Smyrna to return to his native country, he was on the point of
                    perishing in an earthquake. The house which he occupied fell, and buried him in
                    the ruins, under which he remained until next day, breathing with difficulty
                    through accidental openings in therubbish. On his return to Paris, Thevenot,
                    keeper of the king’s library, and D’Herbelot, the celebrated oriental scholar,
                    availed themselves of his labours. But death having soon deprived him of both
                    these learned men, he attached himself to Bignon, a zealous protector of men of
                    letters, whom he also lost the following year. It appears to have been the
                    fortune of Galland continually to lose those useful protections which
                    acknowledged merit is sometimes long in obtaining; but such was the esteem
                    inspired by his attainments and his character, that death no sooner deprived him
                    of one support than he found another. Foucault, intendant of Lower Normandy,
                    supplied the place of Bignon, and received Galland into his house, where, in the
                    midst of a fine library, and a numerous collection of medals, he applied himself
                    to the composition of different works, in which he turned to account his
                    knowledge of the Arabic, Persian, and Turkish languages, with which he had
                    rendered himself familiar during his residence in the East. In 1701, he was
                    admitted into the Academy of Inscriptions, although he resided at Caen; in 1706
                    he returned to take up his habitation in Paris; and, three yeprs afterwards, he
                    obtained the chair of Arabic in the Royal College of France. This learned man
                    terminated his laborious, useful, and irreproachable life, on the 17th of
                    February 1715, at the age of sixty-nine. The following is a list of his printed
                    works: 1. Trois Lettres touchant la critique Μ. de Guillet, sur le Voyage de
                    Grèce de Spon, printed in the reply of Spon, Lyons, 1679, in 12mo; 2. Paroles
                    remarquables, bons mots, et maximes des Orientaux, traduits de leurs ouvrages
                    Arabes, Persans, et Tures, avec des remarques, Pąris, 1694, in 12mo; 8. Lettres
                    touchant l’Histoire des quatre Gordiens, prouvée par les Médailles, Paris, 1696,
                    in 12mo; 4. Lettre touchant quatre médailles antiques, publiées par le P.
                    Chamillard, Caen, 1697, in 12mo; 5. Lettre touchant la nouvelle explication
                    d’une médaille d’or du cabinet du Roi, Caen, 1698, in 12mo; 6. Lettre sur le
                    même sujet, printed in the Journal des Savants, 15th August 1705: 7.
                    Observations sur quelques médailles de Tétricus le père, et d’autres tirées du
                    cabinet de Μ. Ballonseaux, Caen, 1701, in</p>
                <p>8vo; 8. De l’origine et du progrès du Caffé, translated from an Arabie manuscript
                    in the library of the king, Caen, 1699, in 12mo; 9. Les Mille et Une Nuits,
                    contes Arabes, traduits en Français, Paris, in 12 vols. 12mo; 10. Relation de la
                    Mort du Sultan Osman, et du couronnement du Sultan Mustapha, translated from the
                    Turkish, Paris, 1678, in 12mo; 11. Several articles in the Journal de Trévoux;
                    12. Letters written from Smyrna and Constantinople; 13. Contributions to the
                    Menagiana, as well as to the Bibliothèque Orientale of D’Herbelot, who died
                    before the printing of the work was completed; 14. Ten dissertations and memoirs
                    for the collection of the academy of which he was a member. Since the death of
                    Galíand there have been published of his, 1. Contes et Fables Indiennes de
                    Pidpaī et de Lokman, Paris, 1724, in 12mo; 2. Dissertation sur one médaille
                    Grecque de l’Empereur Diadumé-nien, frappée à Ephèse, 1739; 3. Relation de
                    l’esclavage d’un Marchand Français de la ville de Cassis à Tunis, 1809. The
                    manuscripts left by Galland were, 1. Histoire des Princes de la lignée de
                    Tamerlan, depuis le Sultan Abou-Saïd-Bahadur, jusqu’au Sultan Abou-Saïd-Kourkan;
                    2. Histoire Othomane, traduite du Turc de Naīma Effendi; 3. Vocabularium
                    TurcicoLatinum; 4. A translation of the History of Djenguyz-Khan, extracted from
                    the Persian History of Mirkhoud; 5. Catalogue d’écrivains Arabes, Persans, et
                    Tures; 6. Journal de mon séjour à Constantinople pendant l’année 1672 et' 1673;
                    7. Dictionnaire Numismatique; 8. Relation de ses Voyages; 9. Traduction de
                    l’Alcoran; 10. Nécrologie de la mort des Savants pour chaque jour de l’année de
                    1500 à 1701; 11. Relation d’un Voyage fait à Constantinople en 1679 et 1680; 12.
                    Etat présent des ties de Samos, de Nicaire, de Patmos, et du Mont Athos; 13.
                    Description de la Ville de Constantinople en 1671 et 1672; 14. Relation des
                    Evénemens qui se sont passés à Constantinople en 1671 et 1672. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
