<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0710-8803-0372-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GAUL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 10, page 372</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:850410">Celts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j09w45x">Celts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z186">Gallicisms</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193518803" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GAUL</label>, an extensive country in the west of Europe, the
                    boundaries of which in the later times of the Romans were, on the west the
                    Atlantic, on the north the German Ocean, on the east the river Rhine and Alps,
                    and on the south the Mediterranean and Pyrenees.</p>
                <p>To the earliest writers we find no part of this country known, except a small
                    portion to the south along the coast of the Mediterranean, and at that time it
                    seems to have had no general name. The tribes on the coast were Bebryces and
                    Ligures, and in the interior they only knew that the people were called Celtae.
                    The extent of their kingdom, and the shape of their land, remained perfectly
                    unknown to the Greeks. Through Pytheas (about 334, B. c.) they first discovered
                    that it was bounded to the north by the ocean, and that the inhabitants in the
                    interior resembled each other in their manner of living. They therefore
                    concluded that the Celtae extended over the whole of the north-western portion
                    of Europe. It was not till the conclusion of the second Punic war (201, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b. c.)</hi> that the Romans began to acquire a firm footing in
                    the south of Gaul, and thereby to obtain somewhat more accurate information
                    respecting the interior. Scipio the elder discovered that there was a river
                    Liger, <hi rend="italic">Loire,</hi> in the country, and a commercial city of
                    the Celtae situated upon it. Still their knowledge was confined to a few scanty
                    facts, and it was the Gallic wars of Caesar which at last enabled them to form a
                    correct idea of the country. They saw that the river Rhine separated the Celtae
                    from a perfectly different people, the Germani, and they became acquainted with
                    the Belgae, formed by a mixture of the two, and whose name they had never before
                    heard. From this period no province of the kingdom became better known, nor more
                    frequently travelled through, than Gallia, on account of the wars with the
                    Germani, and its proximity to Britain.</p>
                <p>Gaul was inhabited by four tribes, dissimilar to each other both in language and
                    customs. The Aquitani, of Iberian origin; the Ligures, dwelling from the foot of
                    the Pyrenees along the coast as far as the river Arno in Italy; the Belgae, of
                    Germanic and Celtic origin; and the Celtae or Galli in the Roman language, who
                    may be considered as the principal nation in the country. Their possessions
                    extended from the extremities of Bretagne, through the whole country lying
                    between the Seine and Garonne, as far as the Rhine and the Alps. There seems
                    every reason to believe that these Celtae came from the east, along the banks of
                    the Danube; at least we find them in the very earliest ages settled in the south
                    of Germany, and in the greater part of Hungary. That their occupation of Gaul
                    must have taken place at an early period, is proved by the immigration of large
                    bodies into Italy in the re⅛n of Tarquinius Priscus (616-578, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b c.).</hi></p>
                <p>Before the time of Caesar, the Celts lived throughout the country, divided into a
                    number of small tribes, having each an aristocratic constitution, such as Poland
                    once enjoyed. There was no king over the whole; but in many of the tribes we
                    find a prince at their head. Every thing was transacted in the national
                    assemblies, where the nobles only had a place. The lower orders seem to have
                    been regarded in not much better light than slaves. In a country possessed by so
                    many independent tribes, there must of course have been continual disputes; and
                    scarcely a year passed without war. The less strong united themselves to their
                    more powerful neighbours, and made common cause with them in their wars. The
                    whole power seems to have been generally in the hands of the nobility, who had
                    regular guards to protect their persons and dig nity. AD ancient writers speak
                    of the strange mixture of excessive levity in the character of the Celts with
                    foolhardiness and timidity. They were of a slender form, robust, furious in the
                    first assault, but unable to persevere when fatigue and hardships were to be
                    endured.</p>
                <p>In the reign of Augustus, Gallia was first divided into regular provinces by
                    Agrippa. These were Aquitanica, Belgica, Lugdunensis, and Provincia Romana, or
                    Narbonensis. The inhabitante led a quiet and peaceful life under the dominion of
                    the Romans, though they occasionally broke out in rebellion, which was generally
                    caused by the oppression of the tax-gatherers and governors. Julius Vindex, a
                    noble of Gaul, made an attempt in the reign of Nero to free his country from a
                    foreign yoke; but though he managed to collect an army of a hundred thousand
                    men, they were easily defeated by the disciplined troops of the Romans. The
                    rebellion of the Batavi, and of the German and Belgic tribes, threatened more
                    danger at a later period; but it was put down partly by force and partly by
                    conciliatory measures. The inhabitants of Gaul continued to cultivate their
                    fields in peace till the end of the second and third centuries, when the Francs
                    and Alemanni began to make incursions into their territory. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">France.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
