<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0710-3912-0765-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GREGORY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 10, page 765</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:1063025">Physics</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933759">Franks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198483">Brown</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gx2h">Physics</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193523912" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GREGORY</label>, surnamed the Great, born at Rome, was
                    descended of an illustrious patrician family, and the son of the senator
                    Gordian. He discovered such abilities in the exercise of the senatorial
                    employments, that Justin the younger appointed him prefect of Rome, and
                    Pelasgius II. sent him as nuncio to Constantinople, to demand succours against
                    the Lombards. When he had thoughts of retiring to enjoy a solitary life, he was,
                    in the year 590, elected pope by tire clergy, the senate, and the people of
                    Rome, and succeeded Pelasgius II. Besides his learning and diligence in
                    instrocting the church, both by writing and preaching, he had a happy talent in
                    winning over princes in favour of the temporal as well as spiritual interests of
                    religion. He undertook the conversion of the English, and sent over some monks,
                    under the direction of Augustin their superior, by whom the seeds of
                    Christianity were first planted in this island. His morality with respect to the
                    chastity of churchmen was so rigid, that according to him a man who had ever
                    known a woman ought not to be admitted to the priesthood; and he always caused
                    the candidates for holy orders to be examined upon that point. He likewise
                    exerted himself most vigorously against such as were found guilty of calumny and
                    other vices. But, notwithstanding all this zeal, he flattered the emperor
                    Phocas, whilst the hands of that prince were yet red with the blood of Mauritius
                    and his three children, who had been butchered in his sight. He likewise
                    flattered Bmnehaut, queen of the Franks, whose character was worse than
                    doubtful. He is further accused of having destroyed the monuments of ancient
                    Roman magnificence, that those who visited the eternal city might not attend to
                    the triumphal arches rather than Ao holy things; and burned a multitude of
                    heathen books, including amongst these the History of Livy. He died in 604. Of
                    all the popes, he is the one who left the greatest number of writings. The best
                    edition of his works is that of Paris, 1705, in four vols. folio, published
                    under the auspices of Denis de Sainte-Marthe and Guillaume Bessin of the
                    congregation of St Maur.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gregory</hi> of Nazianzen, in Cappadocia, one of the most '
                    illustrious ornaments of the Greek church in the fourth ' century, was born in
                    328, and having studied at Caesarea in Palestine, and also at Alexandria, he
                    accompanied his countryman, St Basil, to Athens. He was chosen Bishop of
                    Constantinople in 379; but finding his election contested by the bishops of
                    Egypt, he voluntarily resigned his dignity into the hands of the general
                    council, which had been assembled at Constantinople, in the year 381, and died
                    about the year 389. His works, consisting of a hundred and fifty discourses or
                    sermons, a hundred and fifty-eight poems or pieces in verse, and two hundred and
                    thirty-five letters, the greater part of them interesting, were collected and
                    printed at Bale in 1550. In the Paris edition of 1609, 1611, in two vols. folio,
                    a Latin version by the Abbé de Belly is printed opposite the Greek text. The
                    Benedictines of the congregation of St Maur commenced a beautiful edition, Greek
                    and Latin, in three vols. folio, of which, however, only one volume was
                    published, Paris, 1788, containing the discourses, with a life of the author
                    compiled from his works.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gregory,</hi><hi rend="italic">Theodorus,</hi> surnamed <hi
                    rend="italic">Thaumalurgus</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Wonder-worker,</hi> on
                    account of his alleged miracles, was the scholar of Origen, and was elected
                    Bishop of Neocaesarea in Pontus, the place of his birth, about the year 240. He
                    assisted at the council of Antioch, in 255, against Paid of Samosata; and died
                    in 270. He had the satisfaction of leaving only seventeen idolaters in his
                    diocese, where there were scarcely as many Christians when he was ordained.
                    There are still extant of his, a congratulatory oration to Origen, a canonical
                    epistle, a paraphrase on Ecclesiastes, and some other compositions, which have
                    been published in the collection entitled &lt;SS ’. <hi rend="italic">Patrum
                    Gregorii Thauma-turgi, Macarii Egyptii,</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Basilii Seleuciensis Opera Graeco-Latina,</hi> Paris, 1622, in
                    folio.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gregory,</hi> bishop of Nyssa, one of the Fathers of the
                    Church, and author of the Nicene creed, was born in Cappadocia, about the year
                    331 or 332. He was chosen bishop of Nyssa in 371 or 372, and banished by the
                    Emperor Valens for adhering to the council of Nice. He was nevertheless
                    afterwards employed by the bishops in several important affairs, and died about
                    the year 396. He wrote Commentaries on the Scriptures, Sermons on the Mysteries,
                    Moral Discourses, Dogmatical Treatises, Panegyrics on the Saints, Letters on
                    Church Discipline, and various works. The Bishop of Nyssa yields to none of the
                    fathers either in the solidity of his matter, the fertility and soundness of his
                    views, the force of his reasoning, or the beauty and richness of his style. Of
                    his works there have been a great number of editions, the principal of which are
                    those of Cologne, 1537; Bale, 1567 and 1571; Paris, 1573 and 1603, all in folio;
                    also Paris, 1615 and 1618, in two vols. folio, with a third volume by way of
                    appendix, containing various pieces which had not before appeared.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gregory</hi> of Tours, an illustrious bishop and writer of
                    the sixth century, was descended from a noble family in Auvergne. He was
                    educated by his uncle Saint-Gal, or Gallus, bishop of Clermont; and
                    distinguished himself so much by his learning and virtue, that in 573 he was
                    chosen Bishop of Tours. He afterwards went to Rome to visit the tomb of the
                    apostles, there contracted a friendship with Gregory the Great, and died in 593,
                    at the age of fifty-four. His principal work is his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">Francorum,</hi> or History of the Franks,
                    divided into sixteen books, comprehending a period of 174 years from the
                    establishment of the Franks in Gaul. It is written in Latin, which is not only
                    grammatically barbarous, but without force, without expression, and, if we may
                    be allowed the use of the term, without complexion. Gregory of Tours had read
                    the Fathers, and acquired some knowledge of Roman literature; for he cites
                    Virgil and Sallust, Pliny and Aulus Gellius. But the language, <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193523925" xml:id="kp-eb0710-3925-0766"/>formerly so masculine and
                    vigorous, had shared the rate of the civilization of which it was the type, and
                    had fallen into a state of extreme debility and decay. Yet it had in it more of
                    degradation than of barbarism. The Gothic tribes had not yet, by an intimate
                    union, renovated the nations who had degenerated under the shattered yoke of the
                    Roman empire. The victors oppressed the vanquished, without being as yet
                    confounded with them.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gregory,</hi><hi rend="italic">David,</hi> the son of the
                    reverend John Gregory, minister of Drumoak, in the county of Aberdeen. He was
                    born about the year 1628, educated by his father for business, and bound as an
                    apprentice to a mercantile house in Holland. But as his love of letters exceeded
                    his desire of money, he relinquished commerce in the year 1655, and upon the
                    death of an elder brother he succeeded to the estate of Kinnardie, about forty
                    miles from Aberdeen, where he resided many years, and had no fewer than
                    thirty-two children born to him by two wives. Three of his sons became eminent
                    for their extensive literature, and were at one time professors of mathematics
                    in the universities of Oxford, Edinburgh, and St Andrews.</p>
                <p>In the country where he dwelt he was the first person who had a barometer, to the
                    oscillations of which, according to the changes of the weather, he paid great
                    attention, and was once in danger of being tried by the presbytery for
                    witchcraft or conjuration. He was waited upon by a deputation of ministers, who
                    inquired into the truth of certain reports which had come to their ears; but he
                    so far satisfied them as to induce them to waive a prosecution against a man
                    who, by the extensive knowledge he possessed of medicine, was a public blessing
                    to the country.</p>
                <p>About the beginning of the eighteenth century he removed to Aberdeen, and during
                    the wars of Queen Anne’s reign, turned his attention to the improvement of
                    artillery, and executed a model of an engine intended to render cannon more
                    destructive. Dr Reid knew a clock-maker who had been employed to make the model
                    of this engine; but as he made many different pieces without knowing their
                    design, or the method of uniting them, he could give no consistent account of
                    the engine. Satisfied with his invention by various experiments, Mr Gregory
                    desired his son to show it to Sir Isaac Newton, but to conceal the name of the
                    inventor; Sir Isaac however was much displeased with it, and declared that the
                    inventor was more entitled to punishment than reward, as it was solely
                    calculated for destruction, and might come to be known to the enemy. That great
                    man urged the necessity of destroying it; and it is probable that Mr Gregory’s
                    son, the Savilian professor, followed his advice, for the model was never
                    found.</p>
                <p>When the rebellion broke out in 1715, the old gentleman went a second time to
                    Holland; but when the insurrection had been put down, he returned to Aberdeen,
                    where he died about 1720, in the ninety-third year of his age, leaving behind
                    him a history of his own times, which was never published.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gregory,</hi><hi rend="italic">James,</hi> one of the most
                    eminent mathematicians of the seventeenth century, was a son of the reverend
                    John Gregory, minister of Drumoak, in the county of Aberdeen, and was born at
                    Aberdeen in 1638. His mother was a daughter of Mr David Anderson of Finzaugh, a
                    gentleman who possessed a singular turn for mathematical and mechanical
                    knowledge. Mathematical genius was indeed hereditary in the family of the
                    Andersons, and from them it seems to have been transmitted to their descendants
                    of the name of Gregory. Alexander Anderson, cousin-german of David Gregory above
                    mentioned, was professor of mathematics at Paris in the beginning of the
                    seventeenth century, and published there, <hi rend="italic">Supplementum
                    Apollonii Redivivi,</hi> 1612. The mother of James Gregory inherited the genius
                    of her family; and observing in her son, whilst yet a child, a strong propensity
                    to mathematics, she instructed him herself in the elements of that science. He
                    received his education in the languages at the grammarschool of Aberdeen, and
                    went through the usual course of academical studies in the Marischal
                    College.</p>
                <p>At the age of twenty-four he published his treatise, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Optica</hi><hi rend="italic">Promota, seu abdita Radiorum Reflexorum et
                    Refractorum mysteria, geometrice enucleata; cui subnectitur appendix
                    subtilissimorum Astronomia problematum resolutionem exhibens,</hi> London, 1663:
                    a work of great genius, in which he gave the world an invention of his own, one
                    of the most valuable of modern discoveries, namely, the construction of the
                    reflecting telescope. This discovery immediately attracted the attention of
                    mathematicians, both in our own and in foreign countries, all of whom were soon
                    convinced of its great importance to the sciences of optics and astronomy. As
                    the manner of placing the two specula upon the same axis appeared to Sir Isaac
                    Newton to be attended with the disadvantage of losing the central rays of the
                    larger speculum, he proposed an improvement on the instrument, by giving an
                    oblique position to the smaller speculum, and placing the eye-glass in the side
                    of the tube. But it is worth remarking, that the Newtonian construction of the
                    instrument was abandoned for the original or Gregorian, which is now generally
                    employed where the instrument is of a moderate size; though Sir William Herschel
                    preferred the Newtonian form for the construction of those immense telescopes
                    which he so successfully employed in observing the heavens.</p>
                <p>The university of Padua being at this time in high repute for mathematical
                    studies, James Gregory went thither soon after the publication of his first
                    work; and, fixing his residence there for some years, he published, in 1667, <hi
                    rend="italic">Vera</hi><hi rend="italic">Circuli</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >et</hi><hi rend="italic">Hyperboles</hi><hi rend="italic">Quadratura,</hi> in
                    which he propounded another discovery of his own, the invention of an infinitely
                    converging series for the areas of the circle and hyperbole. To this treatise,
                    when republished in 1668, he added a new work, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geometria</hi><hi rend="italic">Pars Universalis,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >inserviens quantitatum curvarum transmutationi et mensura,</hi> in which he is
                    allowed to have shown, for the first time, a method for the transmutation of
                    curves. These works engaged the notice, and procured the author the
                    correspondence, of the greatest mathematicians of the age, Newton, Huygens,
                    Halley, and Wallis; and as he was soon afterwards chosen a fellow of the Royal
                    Society of London, he contributed to enrich the Philosophical
                    Transactionsbymanyexcellent papers. Through thischan-nel, in particular, he
                    carried on a dispute with Huygens, on the occasion of his treatise on the
                    Quadrature of the Circle and Hyperbole, to which that able mathematician had
                    started some objections. It is unnecessary to enter into the particulars of this
                    controversy; but, in the opinion of Leibnitz, who allows Mr Gregory the highest
                    merit for his genius and discoveries, Huygens pointed out considerable
                    deficiencies in the treatise above mentioned, and showed a much simpler method
                    of attaining the end proposed.</p>
                <p>In 1688 he published at London another work, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Exercitationes Geometrica,</hi> which contributed still further to extend his
                    reputation. About this time he was elected professor of mathematics in the
                    university of St Andrews; an ofiice which he held for six years. During his
                    residence there, he married (in 1669) Mary, the daughter of George Jameson, the
                    celebrated painter, whom Mr Walpole has termed the Vandyke of Scotland, and who
                    was a fellow disciple of that great artist in the school of Rubens at Antwerp.
                    In 1674 he was called to Edinburgh to fill the chair of mathematics in that
                    university; but he had held this place for little more than a year, when, in
                    October 1675, being employed in showing the satellites of Jupiter through a
                    telescope to some of his pupils, he was <pb break="no" facs="nls:193523938"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0710-3938-0767"/>suddenly struck with total blindness, and died a
                    few days after, at the early age of thirty-seven.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gregory,</hi><hi rend="italic">David,</hi> Savilian
                    professor of astronomy at Oxford, and termed by Dr Smith <hi rend="italic"
                    >subtilissimi ingenii mathematicus,</hi> was the eldest son of Mr Gregory of
                    Kinnardie, brother of the before-mentioned Mr James Gregory. He was born at
                    Aberdeen in the year 1661, and received the earlier part of his education in
                    that city. He completed his studies at Edinburgh; and, being possessed of the
                    mathematical papers of his uncle, soon distinguished himself as the heir of his
                    genius. In the twenty-third year of his age he was elected professor of
                    mathematics in the university of Edinburgh; and published, in the same year, <hi
                    rend="italic">Exercitatio Geometrica</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dimensione Figurarum, sive specimen methodi generalis dimetiendi
                    quasvis Figuras,</hi> Edinburgh, 1684, 4to. He early perceived the excellence of
                    the Newtonian philosophy, and had the merit of being the first who introduced it
                    into the schools by his public lectures at Edinburgh. “He had already caused
                    several of his scholars to keep acts, as we call them,” says Whiston, “upon
                    several branchesof the Newtonian philosophy; while we at Cambridge, poor
                    wretches, were ignominiously studying the fictitious hypotheses of the
                    Cartesian.”</p>
                <p>In 1691, on the report of Dr Bernard’s'intention of resigning the Savilian
                    professorship of astronomy at Oxford, David Gregory repaired to London; and
                    being patronized by Sir Isaac Newton, and warmly befriended by Mr Flamsteed, the
                    astronomer-royal, he obtained the vacant professorship, for which Dr Halley was
                    a competitor. This rivalship, however, instead of animosity, laid the foundation
                    of a lasting friendship between these eminent men; and Halley soon afterwards
                    became the colleague of Gregory, by obtaining the professorship of geometry in
                    the same university. Soon after his arrival in London, Mr Gregory had been
                    elected a fellow of the Royal Society; and, previously to his election as
                    Savilian professor, he had the degree of doctor of physic conferred on him by
                    the university of Oxford.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>On obtaining this professorship, he was succeeded in the mathematical chair
                    at Edinburgh by his brother James, likewise an eminent mathematician, who held
                    that office for thirty-three years, and when he retired in 1725, was succeeded
                    by the celebrated Mac-Iaurin. A daughter of this Professor James Gregory, a
                    young lady of great beauty and accomplishments, was the victim of an unfortunate
                    attachment, which furnished the subject of Malíet’s well-known ballad of william
                    and Margaret. Ln 1707, another brother, Charles, was appointed by Queen Anne
                    professor of mathematics at St Andrews. This office he held with reputation and
                    ability for Lhirty-two years; and, on his resignation in 1739, was succeeded by
                    his son, who eminently inherited the talents of his family," and died in
                    I7β3.</p></note></p>
                <p>In 1693 he published, in the Philosophical Transactions, a resolution of the
                    Florentine problem <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Testudine</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">veli-formi quadribili</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and he
                    continued to communicate to the public, from time to time, many ingenious
                    mathematical papers, through the same channel. In 1695 he printed at Oxford <hi
                    rend="italic">Catoptricae</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Dioptrica</hi><hi rend="italic">Spherica Elementa</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    a work which, as he informs us in the preface, contains the substance of some of
                    his public lectures, read, eleven years before, at Edinburgh. This valuable
                    treatise was republished first with additions by Dr William Brown, and the
                    recommendations of Mr Jones and Dr Desaguliers; and afterwards by the latter of
                    these gentlemen, with an appendix containing an account of the Gregorian and
                    Newtonian telescopes, together with Mr Hadley’s tables for the construction of
                    both instruments. It is not unworthy of remark, that, at the end of this
                    treatise, there is an observation which shows, that what is generally believed
                    to be a discovery of a much later date, namely, the construction of achromatic
                    telescopes, which Mr Dollond and Mr Ramsden carried to a high degree of
                    perfection, had suggested itself to the mind of David Gregory, from reflecting
                    on the admirable contrivance in nature in combining the different humours of the
                    eye. The passage is as follows: ’ * Quod si ob difficultates physicas in
                    speculis idoneis torno elaborandis et poliendis, etiamnum lentibus uti oporteat,
                    fortassis media diversae densitatis ad lentem objectivam componendam adhibere
                    utile foret, ut a natura factum observamus in oculi fabrica, ubi cristallinus
                    humor (fere ejusdem cum vitro virtutis ad radios lucis refringendos) aqueo et
                    vitreo (aquae quoad refractionem haud absimilibus) conjungitur, ad imaginem quam
                    distincte fieri poterit, a natura nihil frustra moliente, in oculi fundo
                    depingendam.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Catoptrics</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Dioptrics</hi><hi rend="italic">Spherica Elementa,</hi> Oxon. 1695, p.
                    98.</p></note></p>
                <p>In 1702 our author published at Oxford, <hi rend="italic">Astronomia Physica et
                    Geometrica Elementa,</hi> a work which is accounted his masterpiece. It is
                    founded on the Newtonian doctrines, and was esteemed by Sir Isaac Newton himself
                    an excellent explanation and defence of his philosophy. In the following year he
                    gave to the world an edition in folio of the works of Euclid, Greek and Latin,
                    in prosecution of a design, formed by his predecessor Dr Bernard, of printing
                    the works of all the ancient mathematicians. In this work, which contains all
                    the treatises attributed to Euclid, Dr Gregory has been careful to point out
                    such as he found reason to believe, from internal evidence, to be the
                    productions of some inferior geometrician. In prosecution of Dr Bernard’s
                    scheme, Dr Gregory soon afterwards engaged with his colleague Halley in the
                    publication of the Conics of Apollonius; but he had proceeded only a little way
                    in this undertaking when, in 1710, he died at Maidenhead, in Berkshire, in the
                    forty-ninth year of his age. To the genius and abilities of David Gregory, the
                    most celebrated mathematicians of the age, Sir Isaac Newton, Dr Halley, and Dr
                    Keill, have borne ample testimony. Indeed it appears that he enjoyed, in a high
                    degree, the confidence and friendship of Sir Isaac Newton. This illustrious
                    philosopher intrusted him with a manuscript copy of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Principia,</hi> for the purpose of making observations on that work. These
                    observations came too late for the first edition of Newton’s great work; but he
                    availed himself of them in the second edition. Besides the works published in
                    his lifetime, he left in manuscript A short Treatise on the Nature and
                    Arithmetic of Logarithms, which is printed at the end of Dr Keill’s translation
                    of Commandine’s Euclid; and a Treatise of Practical Geometry, which was
                    afterwards translated, and published in 1745, by Mr Maclaurin.</p>
                <p>Dr David Gregory married, in 1695, Elizabeth, the daughter of Mr Oliphant of
                    Langtown in Scotland, and by her had four sons, the eklest of whom, David, was
                    appointed regius professor of modern history at Oxford by King George I. and
                    died in 1767, at an advanced age, after enjoying for many years the dignity of
                    dean of Christ Church in that university.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gregory,</hi><hi rend="italic">Dr John,</hi> professor of
                    medicine in the university of Edinburgh, was the son of Dr James Gregory,
                    professor of medicine in King’s College, Aberdeen, and grandson of James, the
                    inventor of the Gregorian telescope. His father was married first to Catharine
                    Forbes, daughter of Sir John Forbes of Monymusk, by whom he had six children,
                    most of whom died in infancy; and afterwards to Ann Chalmers, only daughter of
                    the Reverend George Chalmers, principal of King’s College, by whom he had two
                    sons and a daughter. John, the youngest of the three, was born at Aberdeen on
                    the 3d of June 1724. Having lost his father when only in the seventh year of <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193523951" xml:id="kp-eb0710-3951-0768"/> his age, the care
                    of his education devolved on his grandfather Principal Chalmers, and on his
                    elder brother Dr James Gregory, who, upon the resignation of their father a
                    short time before his death, had been appointed to succeed him in the
                    professorship in King’s College. He likewise owed much in his infant years, and
                    indeed during the whole course of his studies, to the care and attention of his
                    cousin, the celebrated Dr Reid, afterwards of the university of Glasgow. The
                    rudiments of his classical education he received at the grammar-school of
                    Aberdeen; and under the eye of his grandfather he completed, in King’s College,
                    his studies in the Latin and Greek languages, and in the sciences of ethics,
                    mathematics, and natural philosophy. His master in philosophy and in mathematics
                    was Thomas Gordon, professor of philosophy in King’s College, who ably filled an
                    academical chair for above half a century.</p>
                <p>In 1742 Mr Gregory went to Edinburgh, where the school of medicine was then
                    rising into that celebrity for which it has since been so remarkably
                    distinguished. Here he attended the anatomical lectures of the elder Dr Monro,
                    of Dr Sinclair on the theory of medicine, and of Dr Rutherford on the practice
                    of physic. He heard likewise the prelections of Dr Alston on the materia medica
                    and botany, and of Dr Plummer on chemistry. The Medical Society of Edinburgh,
                    instituted for the free discussion of all questions relative to medicine and
                    philosophy, had begun to meet in 1737. Of this society we find Mr Gregory a
                    member in 1742, at the time when Dr Mark Akenside, his fellow-student and
                    intimate companion, was a member of the same institution.</p>
                <p>In the year 1745 our author went to Leyden, and attended the lectures of
                    Professors Gaubius, Albinus, and Van Royen. Whilst at this university he had the
                    honour of receiving from the King’s College of Aberdeen, his <hi rend="italic"
                    >alma mater,</hi> an unsolicited degree of doctor of physic; and soon
                    afterwards, on his return from Holland, he was elected professor of philosophy
                    in the same university. In this capacity he read lectures during the years 1747,
                    1748, and 1749, on mathematics, experimental philosophy, and ethics. In the end
                    of 1749, however, he resigned his professorship of philosophy, his views being
                    turned chiefly to the practice of physic, with which the duties of this
                    professorship. occupying as they did a great portion of his time, too much
                    interfered. Previously, however, to his settling ąs a physician at Aberdeen, he
                    went for a few months to the Continent; a tour of which the chief motive was
                    probably amusement, though to a mind like his certainly not without advantage in
                    the enlargement of ideas, and an increased knowledge of mankind.</p>
                <p>Some time after his return to Scotland, Dr Gregory married, in 1752, Elizabeth,
                    daughter of William Lord Forbes, a young lady who, to the exterior endowments of
                    great beauty and engaging manners, joined a very superior understanding and an
                    uncommon share of wit. With her he received a handsome addition of fortune; and
                    during the whole period of their union, which was only for the space of nine
                    years, he enjoyed the highest portion of domestic happiness. Of her character it
                    is enough to say, that her husband, in the admired little work, A Father’s
                    Legacy to his Daughters, the last proof of his affection for them, declares,
                    that “while he endeavours to point out what they should be, he draws but a very
                    faint and imperfect picture of what their mother was.” The field of medical
                    practice at Aberdeen being at that time in a great measure pre-occupied by his
                    elder brother Dr James Gregory, and· others of some note in their profession,
                    our author determined to try his fortune in London. Thither accordingly he
                    proceeded in 1754; and being already known by reputation as a man of genius, he
                    found an easy introduction to many persons of distinction, both in the literary
                    and polite world. Amongst these may be mentioned George Lord Lyttleton, who
                    became his friend and patron. An acquaintance, which had been founded on a
                    striking similarity of manners, tastes, and dispositions, grew up into a firm
                    and permanent friendship; and to that nobleman, to whom Dr Gregory was
                    accustomed to communicate all hisΙiterary productions, the world is indebted for
                    the publication of the Comparative View of the State and Faculties of Man, which
                    made him first known as an author. Dr Gregory likewise enjoyed the friendship of
                    Edward Montagu and his lady, the celebrated champion of the fame of Shakspeare,
                    against the cavils and calumnies of Voltaire.</p>
                <p>In 1754 Dr Gregory was chosen fellow of the Royal Society of London; and as he
                    made daily advances in the public esteem, it is not to be doubted that, had he
                    continued his residence in the metropolis, his professional talents would have
                    found their reward in an extensive practice. But the death of his brother, Dr
                    James Gregory, in November 1755, having occasioned a vacancy in the
                    professorship of physic in King’s College, Aberdeen, which he was solicited to
                    fill, he returned to his native country in the þeginning of the following year,
                    and took upon him the duties of that office, to which he had been elected in his
                    absence.</p>
                <p>Here he remained until the end of the year 1764, when, urged by a laudable
                    ambition, and presuming on the reputation he had acquired as affording a
                    reasonable prospect of success in a more extended field of practice, he changed
                    his place of residence for Edinburgh. His friends in that metropolis had
                    represented to him the situation of the medical school as favourable to his
                    views of filling a chair in that university; and this accordingly he obtained in
                    1766, on the resignation of Dr Rutherford, professor of the practice of physic.
                    In the same year he had’ the honour of being appointed first physician to his
                    majesty for Scotland on the death of Dr Whytt.</p>
                <p>On his first establishment in the university of Edinburgh, Dr Gregory gave
                    lectures on the practice of physic during the years 1767, 1768, and 1769.
                    Afterwards, by agreement with Dr Cullen, professor of the theory of physic,
                    these two eminent men gave alternate courses on the theory and practice of
                    physic. As a public speaker, Dr Gregory’s manner was simple, natural, and
                    animated. Without the graces of oratory, which the subject he had to treat in a
                    great degree precluded, he expressed his ideas with uncommon perspicuity, and in
                    a style happily attempered between the formality of studied composition and the
                    ease of conversation. It was his custom to premeditate, for a short time before
                    entering the college, the subject of his lecture, consulting those authors to
                    whom he had occasion to refer, and marking in short notes the arrangement of his
                    intended discourse; then, fully master of his subject, and confident of his own
                    powers, he trusted to his natural facility of expression to convey those
                    opinions which he had maturely deliberated. The only lectures which he committed
                    fully to writing were those introductory discourses which he read at the
                    beginning of his annual course, and which are published under the title of
                    Lectures on the Duties and Qualifications of a Physician. Of these, which were
                    written with no view to publication, many copies were taken by his pupils, and
                    some from the original manuscript, which he freely lent for their perusal. On
                    hearing that a copy had been offered for sale to a bookseller, it became
                    necessary to anticipate a fraudulent, and perhaps a mutilated publication, by
                    authorizing an impression from a corrected copy, of which he gave the profits to
                    a favourite pupil. These lectures were first published in 1770, and afterwards
                    in an enlarged and more perfect form in 1772.</p>
                <p>In the same year, 1772, Dr Gregory published EIe-ments<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193523964" xml:id="kp-eb0710-3964-0769"/> of the Practice of Physic,
                    for the use of Students; ' a work intended solely for his own pupils, and to be
                    used by himself as a text-book to be commented upon in his course of lectures.
                    In an advertisement prefixed to this work, he signified his intention of
                    comprehending in it the whole series of diseases of which he had treated in his
                    Lectures on the Practice of Physic; but this intention he did not live to
                    accomplish, having brought down the work no further than to the end of the class
                    of Febrile Diseases.</p>
                <p>Dr Gregory became early a victim to the gout, which began to show itself at
                    irregular intervals even from the eighteenth year of his age. His mother, from
                    whom he inherited that disease, died suddenly in 1770, whilst sitting at table.
                    Dr Gregory had prognosticated for himself a similar death; an event of which,
                    amongst his friends, he often talked, but had no apprehension of the nearness of
                    its approach. In the beginning of the year 1773, whilst in conversation with his
                    son Dr James Gregory, the latter remarked, that having for the three preceding
                    years had no return of an attack, he might expect a pretty severe shock that
                    season; and he received the observation with some degree of anger, as he felt
                    himself then in his usual state of health. The prediction, however, proved but
                    too true; for having gone to bed on the 9th of February 1773, with no apparent
                    disorder, he was found dead in the morning. His death had been instantaneous,
                    and probably in his sleep; for there was not the smallest discomposure of limb
                    or feature.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gregoby,</hi><hi rend="italic">Dr James,</hi> professor of
                    the Practice of Medicine in the University of Edinburgh, and eldest son of the
                    subject of the preceding notice, was born at Aberdeen in the year 1753, and
                    there received the rudiments of his education. He accompanied his father to
                    Edinburgh in 1764; and after going through the usual course of literary studies
                    at Edinburgh, was for a short time a student at Christ Church College, Oxford,
                    of which his relation Dr David Gregory had been dean. It was there probably that
                    he acquired that taste for classical learning, and that admiration for the
                    character of an accomplished classical scholar, which ever afterwards
                    distinguished him. He entered early on the study of medicine at Edinburgh, and
                    was a student in that faculty at the time of his father’s sudden, death, in
                    February 1773. The extraordinary exertion which he then made to complete his
                    father’s course of lectures, was regarded by many of his friends as sufficient
                    indication of his ability to continue and extend the hereditary reputation of
                    his family. He took the degree of doctor of physic at Edinburgh in 1774, and
                    spent the greater part of the next two years in Holland, France, and Italy. It
                    is worthy of notice, that his most intimate friend and companion on the
                    Continent was Mr A. Macdonald, afterwards lord chief baron of the Court of
                    Exchequer, in London.</p>
                <p>After the death of Dr John Gregory, the chair of the Institutes of Medicine (then
                    finally separated from that of the Practice of Medicine, of which Dr Cullen
                    remained professor) was offered to Dr Drummond, who was at that time abroad, and
                    who ultimately declined accepting it. For two winters the class was taught by Dr
                    Duncan, whose appointment, however, was only temporary. In 1776 the chair was
                    again declared vacant, and on the 1st of August of that year Dr Gregory was
                    appointed professor. He began to lecture on the Institutes the next winter
                    session, and in the succeeding year he commenced also the duty of teacher of
                    Clinical Medicine in the Royal Infirmary, and continued to deliver at least one
                    course of clinical lectures annually, for more than twenty years.</p>
                <p>From the time of commencing his duties as professor Dr Gregory was continually
                    engaged in medical practice ;, but his practice amongst the higher ranks of
                    society was not extensive until many of his pupils had been settled in business,
                    and were desirous of availing themselves of his assistance. For the last
                    twenty-five years of his life he was much engaged in consulting practice; and
                    for the last ten he was decidedly at the head of his profession in Scotland.
                    Indeed, the boldness, originality, and strength of his intellect, and the energy
                    and decision of his character, were so strongly marked in his conversation,
                    that, wherever his professional character was known, it could hardly fail to
                    inspire general confidence.</p>
                <p>In 1778 he published his <hi rend="italic">Conspectus Medicince
                    Theoretic&lt;ε,</hi> as a text-book for his lectures on the Institutes. This
                    work passed through several editions, both during his lifetime and since his
                    death, and has been very generally admired, partly on account of the accurate
                    view which it affords of the state of medical science at the period when it was
                    composed, and partly for the ease, perspicuity, and elegance of its Latinity.
                    The greater part of the work is occupied by the principles of Therapeutics; and
                    as it must be confessed that there has been less improvement since that time in
                    the investigation of the powers of remedies, than of the principles either of
                    Physiology or Pathology, that portion of it may still be studied with advantage
                    by all medical men.</p>
                <p>On the illness of Dr Cullen in 1790, he was appointed joint-professor of the
                    Practice of Medicine; he became sole professor on the death of Dr Cullen in the
                    same year; and continued to deliver lectures on that subject, to audiences
                    almost regularly increasing, until his last illness in 1821. He died on the 2d
                    of April of that year.</p>
                <p>As a practitioner and teacher of medicine, it may be stated that Dr Gregory was
                    chiefly distinguished by his clear perception, and constant application, of the
                    truth contained in a maxim which he was accustomed to quote from a favourite
                    Greek author: “The best physician is he who can distinguish what he can do from
                    what he cannot do.” He distrusted all theories in regard to the intimate nature
                    of diseased actions, as premature and visionary; but he had early and carefully
                    studied the diagnostic and prognostic symptoms, and the various forms of the
                    most important diseases, and the agency of the most powerful remedies; and,
                    without entering into the minutiae of morbid anatomy, he had a clear
                    understanding of the changes of structure to be apprehended from disease in the
                    different internal parts of the body. On these points, and their immediate
                    practical bearing, he fixed all his attention. When he thought that these
                    changes were approaching, and could be arrested by active treatment, he urged
                    the truly effectual remedies with the peculiar energy of his character;
                    restrained only by his strong good sense and ample experience, and despising all
                    parade of nicety, pr variety of prescription. When he was satisfied that the
                    nature or the stage of the disease did not admit of effectual cure, his decision
                    of character was equally shown in abstaining from useless interference, and
                    confining his views to the relief of suffering.</p>
                <p>As a teacher, he was always strongly impressed with the duty of fixing the
                    attention of his pupils on those points in the history of disease, and in the
                    application of remedies, the knowledge of which he had found by experience to be
                    most practically important,and the ignorance of which he thought practically
                    dangerous. The characteristic symptoms and varieties of inflammatory diseases,
                    and the extent to which the antiphlogistic treatment might be carried in
                    opposing them, were, therefore, subjects on which he dwelt with peculiar
                    earnestness; and in regard to the use of those remedies in such diseases, he had
                    acquired, by long and keen observation, a <hi rend="italic">tact</hi> and
                    decision which probably were never surpassed. On the other hand, in regard to
                    those numerous chronic diseases, where <hi rend="italic">remedies</hi> are so
                    frequently ineffectual, he was equally zealous in inculcating those means of <hi
                    rend="italic">prevention</hi> which he thought most effectual and most
                    attainable; and whilst he was incredulous as to the alleged virtue of most
                    medicines in such diseases, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193523977"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0710-3977-0770"/>he omitted no opportunity of illustrating the
                    efficacy of temperance, even of abstinence, of bodily exertion without fatigue,
                    and mental occupation without anxiety, in averting their approach, or even
                    arresting their progress. From these great practical objects of his labours as a
                    teacher, no consideration ever turned him aside. His extensive reading,
                    particularly of the older authors, never led to pedantic displays of learning;
                    his logical acuteness never beguiled him into useless controversies; his
                    fertility of imagination never carried him beyond the simplest and most
                    practical views of the subjects of which he treated.</p>
                <p>As a lecturer, he possessed the great advantages of a command of language, which
                    made him almost independent of any written notes, and of a tenacity of memory
                    which enabled him to detail cases, in illustration of his principles, year after
                    year, from the whole range of his experience, merely from having the names of
                    the patients before him, without the slightest inaccuracy or omission. The
                    commanding energy and quickness of intellect which his lectures displayed, the
                    frank and fearless exposition of his opinions which they containea, the
                    classical allusions with which they abounded, and the genuine humour by which
                    they were often enlivened, rendered them peculiarly attractive and interesting,
                    and acquired for him a remarkable ascendency over the minds of his pupils.</p>
                <p>In the practice of the profession he was remarkable for the frankness and candour
                    of his communications with the relations and friends of the sick; and for the
                    zealous and even tender interest, always increasing with the difficulty and
                    danger of the case, which he took in his patients. This made the more
                    impression, as it contrasted with a certain roughness of external manner, and a
                    constitutional hilarity and whimsical humour, which on some occasions, it must
                    be owned, like thatofa celebrated fictitious character, made him “not hesitate
                    between his friend and his joke.”</p>
                <p>His conduct with his professional brethren in consultation was eminently
                    distinguished by candour and liberality, and the total absence of all
                    professional trick. He never attempted to make himself of importance, but was
                    ever ready to give the strongest commendation to the treatment previously
                    pursued, when he thought it judicious; always laying stress on the great and
                    essential points of practice, and never giving an undue importance to favourite
                    nostrums, or remedies of a secondary or frivolous kind. Thus the young
                    practitioner, who was attentive to his duties, and honourable in his conduct,
                    always found in him a zealous friend; those only had to dread coming into
                    collision with him, who were wanting in professional zeal or professional
                    integrity.</p>
                <p>Dr Gregory’s more intimate friends and connections were strongly attached to him
                    on account of the warmth and steadiness of his attachments, of a generosity of
                    disposition bordering on profusion, and of a high and somewhat aristocratic
                    sense of honour, which made him instinctively shrink from any proceeding liable
                    to the slightest Imputation of meanness, selfishness, or duplicity.</p>
                <p>He had therefore an utter detestation for all those professional arts by which
                    the favour of the public is sometimes too successfully propitiated; and this was
                    the true origin of various controversies in which he was at different times
                    engaged with his professional brethren, and to which his strong sense of humour,
                    his fondness for logical disputation, and (it must be confessed) a somewhat
                    irascible temper, led him to devote more of his .time and attention than their
                    importance deserved. For the interests of the Medical School, and of the medical
                    profession of Edinburgh, the continuance of these disputes was a matter of
                    serious regret; but the feelings which led him to engage in them were too well
                    understood and appreciated, to permit them to occasion him any loss, either of
                    private friendships or of public estimation.</p>
                <p>No medical teacher or practitioner of eminence was ever more ready to acknowledge
                    the imperfection of his art, more distrustful of medical theories, or even of
                    the alleged results of medical practice, when not in accordance with his own
                    experience; or more careless of posthumous reputation. But none was ever more
                    solicitous to give, both to his pupils and his patients, the full benefit of
                    those principles of medical science, of the truth and importance of which he was
                    himself convinced; and on this account his professional character had assumed,
                    long before his death, a superiority over most of his contemporaries, of which
                    those who judge of it only from his own contributions to medical science or
                    literature cannot form an adequate conception.</p>
                <p>Dr Gregory used to say, that whilst physic had been the business, metaphysics had
                    been the amusement, of his life. Of this predilection we have a highly
                    honourable testimony, in Dr Reid’s Dedication to him and to his illustrious
                    friend Mr Dugald Stewart, of his <hi rend="italic">Essays on the Intellectual
                    Powers,</hi> published in 1785; and, at a much later period of his life, in the
                    cordial friendship which united him with the late Dr Thomas Brown, and the warm
                    interest which he took in the appointment of that eminent metaphysician to the
                    Chair of Moral Philosophy, on Mr Stewart’s resignation of it, and retirement
                    from the University. It is proper to add, however, that on some important
                    metaphysical questions the opinions of Dr Brown were different from those of Dr
                    Gregory, and probably never were the subject of discussion between them.</p>
                <p>His own metaphysical and literary works are, <hi rend="italic">A Theory of the
                    Moods of Verbs,</hi> published in the Edinburgh Philosophical Transactions for
                    1787; and his <hi rend="italic">Literary and Philosophical Essays,</hi> in two
                    volumes, published in 1792. The main object of the latter work was to explain
                    and defend a new argument on the old controversy as to the liberty or necessity
                    of human actions; and whatever may be thought of the soundness of the argument,
                    no one has ever disputed the acuteness and power of logical reasoning which he
                    displayed in defence of it. It must be admitted, however, that his ideas of
                    metaphysical inquiry were in some respects limited. He regarded metaphysics
                    rather as a field for syllogistic reasoning, than as a subject of inquiry
                    directed to the establishment of general principles by induction; and one of his
                    favourite doctrines, that metaphysics admit of no <hi rend="italic"
                    >discoveries,</hi> if admitted as literally correct, would almost imply that the
                    study can lead to no useful practical results.</p>
                <p>He retained throughout life a fervent admiration for the classical authors, and a
                    severe and somewhat fastidious taste in literature, which was formed on the
                    classical models. Several of the lighter and controversial writings with which
                    he amused himself, particularly his Memorials on certain changes in the
                    arrangements of the Royal Infirmary in 1800 and 1803, exhibit very numerous
                    examples of his ready recollection and happy application of quotations from the
                    classics; and a number of Latin epitaphs and inscriptions of various kinds,
                    which he composed at different periods of his life, attest an accuracy of
                    knowledge of the Latin language, and a purity of taste in Latin composition,
                    which few men have the faculty of retaining throughout a lifetime of incessant
                    professional labour.</p>
                <p>Dr Gregory was married in 1782, to Miss Mary Ross; but within a few months after
                    her marriage, this lady, to the extreme regret of all her friends, became
                    decidedly consumptive, and survived only two years. After her death her two
                    sisters continued to reside with their brother-in-law, until they both
                    successively sunk under the same cruel disease. In 1796, he married one of the
                    daughters of the late Mr M*Leod of Geanies, by whom he had a large family. His
                    second son devoted himself with zeal and ability to the profession of medicine.
                    He had entered on <pb break="no" facs="nls:193523990"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0710-3990-0771"/>practice, had already been placed in several
                    responsible situations in Edinburgh, and distinguished himself by some papers on
                    medical subjects, when he was unfortunately carried off by a fever contracted in
                    the course of his duties, in 1832. But other sons survive, and it is hoped that
                    they may still afford another application of the proud anti singularly
                    appropriate motto of the family, <hi rend="italic">Nec deficit alter.</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(a. a. a. a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
