<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0710-0415-0496-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GHILAN, or Gheełan</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 10, page 496</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204622">Georgia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w237">Running</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39453">Silk</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp6g">Cossacks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49p2wf9z">Travel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:880643">Cossacks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1155691">Travelers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1155558">Travel</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355164">Travels</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1101348">Running</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193520415" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GHILAN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Gheełan</hi></label>, a
                    province of Persia, which runs along the south-western shore of the Caspian Sea.
                    It is bounded on the south and south-east by Irak and Mazunderan, on the north
                    by Shirvan, and on the west by Azerbijan. It is hemmed in on the south and west
                    by the Elburz range of mountains, which, at the distance of about fifty miles,
                    runs along the shore of the Caspian Sea, and rises to a great height, like a
                    steep wall. The breadth of the low country, from the sea to the foot of the
                    hills, varies exceedingly; the mountains advancing sometimes to the water’s
                    edge, and in other places retiring to a distance of thirty or forty miles. The
                    boundary of the province, along with that of the contiguous province of
                    Azerbijan, runs along the elevated crests of the mountains in a very irregular
                    and indefinite line; in some places contracting its whole breadth to thirty, in
                    others enlarging it to seventy miles. The whole coast of Ghilan is lined with a
                    belt of impenetrable forest; and behind this barrier are deep back-waters and
                    extensive morasses. On the south, the passes through the mountains are of
                    extreme steepness, difficulty, and length; so that the province is strongly
                    defended by nature against an invading enemy. The plains extending from the
                    Caspian Sea to the mountains are well watered, verdant, and beautiful; the soil
                    is fertile, and yields abundantly rice, wheat, hemp, hops, and many kinds of
                    fruit, such as lemons, oranges, peaches, and pomegranates. Grapes are in the
                    greatest plenty; and the vines which grow wild in the mountains, support
                    themselves, as in Georgia, on the trunks and branches of trees. From want of
                    attention to their culture, they are not however of the best quality, and, like
                    other fruits in Ghilan, are esteemed unwholesome. But of all the productions in
                    this province, that of silk is the most celebrated. The cultivation of this
                    commodity, which employs the industry of the country, and enriches the natives,
                    constitutes the principal trade of Ghilan, and is annually exported in great
                    quantities from Resht and Lankeroon to Astrakhan. The only river of any
                    consequence is the Kizilozien, which descends from the Elburz Mountains with the
                    rapidity of a torrent, and flows with a meandering course through Ghilan to the
                    Caspian Sea. There are few places in Ghilan deserving the appellation of towns.
                    Resht, containing about 80,000 inhabitants, and Lahajan, stand almost alone.
                    Enzellee is but a poor shipping village, dependent on Resht; and Lankeroon, an
                    open roadstead at the mouth of a river, is upon Laliajan. Fornen, Massouleh,
                    Kiskar, and Terego-raum, are large villages, in which there are tolerable
                    bazars; <pb break="no" facs="nls:193520428" xml:id="kp-eb0710-0428-0497"/>and
                    there may be many other villages as populous, though not so well established
                    marts for trade. On the other hand, markets are periodically held at places
                    which, except at these particular times, are almost destitute of inhabitants.
                    Throughout the whole of Ghilan, and the neighbouring provinces of Astrabad and
                    Mazunderan, the population may be divided into two classes; the first inhabiting
                    the plains, and living stationary in towns or villages, where they cultivate
                    rice, wheat, cotton, sugar, silk, and are of peaceable and industrious habits;
                    the second class, inhabiting the skirts of the hills, and the valleys amongst
                    them, as well as the villages nearest their base, but who retire during the heat
                    of summer to elevated regions, thus migrating with their flocks in quest of
                    pasture, according to the change of seasons. In the northern parts of Ghilan are
                    the Talish, a fierce tribe of mountaineers, who unite many of the better
                    qualities of highlanders with the barbarity of savages. They are continually
                    marauding among themselves, and plundering their immediate neighbours; and
                    neither property nor life are safe in their hands. They are brave, and devoted
                    to their chiefs; and they are also active, and patient of fatigue; but they are
                    treacherous, merciless, and rapacious towards all the world besides. They are
                    for the most part spare, raw-boned men, of robust though not tall frames. Their
                    dress consists of a loose pair of trousers; the only vest they wear is fitted
                    tight to the body; and the head is covered by a sheepskin cap of red or black
                    wool. About the waist they wear a leathern girdle, from which depends the
                    formidable Ghilanee knife, broad and two-edged, its blade varying from one to
                    two feet in length, and from two to three inches in breadth, exceedingly sharp,
                    and ending in a point, and very deadly in brawls and private quarrels. Over
                    their shoulder they carry their toffing or matchlock, in the use of which they
                    are exceedingly expert. The revenue yielded by this province amounts to about
                    210,000 tomauns, or L.l 15,000 sterling, a year. This revenue arises from a tax
                    on the export of silk goods and silk, a tax on imports, and a land-tax. We have
                    no accurate account of the population. The cattle are not of a very large size.
                    The cows resemble the lesser breeds of that animal in India; the sheep are also
                    small; and no large horses are bred in these provinces; but there are excellent
                    ponies, which answer all purposes much better, as they are strong and stout, and
                    carry enormous loads through the worst roads in winter, although after long
                    showers they sink to the girths at every step. Ghilan was ceded by the king of
                    Persia to Russia in 1724; it was taken possession of by Catherine II. in 1780,
                    and restored to Aga Mahommed Khan in 1797. The southern parts are subject to
                    Persia; but towards the north, the extensive district of Talish is held by
                    Mustapha Khan, a rebellious and independent chief, who, finding the power of
                    Persia too great for him, invited the Russians to his assistance, promising at
                    the same time to yield them obedience as sovereigns. In the year 1812, he, along
                    with a Russian garrison consisting of 300 men, were driven by the Persians out
                    of Lankeroon, which was garrisoned by 1500 irregular Ghilanee troops, besides
                    two battalions of Persian infantry, and a company of artillery. It was attacked
                    on 13th June with 2000 infantry, 1000 Cossacks, and three vessels of war, and
                    was Carried by assault, with a loss of 1200 men. Mustapha Khan continued till
                    his death in possession of Russian Talish, acknowledging a nominal obedience to
                    the authorities of that empire, who never demanded more; and he has been
                    succeeded by seven sons, who have shared between them the whole country.
                    (Kinneir’s <hi rend="italic">Geographical Memoir of the Persian Entpire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> Fraser’s <hi rend="italic">Travels and Adventures in the
                    Persian Provinces, &amp;c.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
