<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0710-3262-0715-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GRAVINA, John Vincent</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 10, page 715</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1026097">Moralities</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1026093">Morale</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:814307">Argentines</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1063893">Piers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hx2m">Piers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r48v">Passions</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20m3b">Moralities</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40k55d">Morals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193523262" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GRAVINA, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Vincent</hi></label>, one
                    of the most distinguished men of letters that the kingdom of Naples ever
                    produced, was born at Rogiano, a small town near Cosenza, in Calabria-Ulteriore,
                    on the 20th of January 1664. His parents, who, <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193523275" xml:id="kp-eb0710-3275-0716"/>by their station and their
                    fortune, held the first rank in the place, neglected nöthing to promote his
                    early education; but the precocity of mind, the vivacity of imagination, and the
                    ardour to instruct himself evinced by their son, soon made them sensible that he
                    required other cares at their hands, and needed to be restrained rather than
                    stimulated. Gregorio Caloprese, his uncle, after having cultivated, with
                    success, at Naples, poetry and philosophy, had retired to his native place,
                    Scalea, a maritime city in that part of Calabria. The education of a nephew, who
                    inspired so high hopes, appeared to him an agreeable task, and he willingly
                    undertook it. Under the auspices of his uncle, young Ġravina learned Latin,
                    rhetoric, history, and the principles of geometry; acquisitions well calculated
                    to pave the way for the study of philosophy, which was then beginning to cast
                    off the yoke under which it had languished in the schools. Thus occupied,
                    Gravina attained his sixteenth year, when Caloprese, finding that the education
                    of his nephew, on which he had bestowed so great care, required his removal to
                    another and wider field, desired to conduct him to Naples; but some domestic
                    embarrassments obstructed the proposed arrangement, and the young student might
                    have been left to his fate, had not his generous relation taken on himself the
                    expense of carrying this proposal into effect, and sent him to the capital, with
                    a strong recommendation to Seraphino Biscardi of Cosenza, then considered as the
                    head of the Neapolitan bar. Charmed with the dispositions evinced by Gravina,
                    Biscardi divided his attentions between him and Cajetano Argentin, particularly
                    directing the application of the former towards Greek, in which he had only
                    received a few lessons from his uncle, but of which he soon acquired a perfect
                    knowledge under Gregorio Massere, then regarded as the first Hellenist of
                    Naples. In the mean time Biscardi taught them all the secrets of the art of
                    oratory, not forgetting that of declamation; but Gravina, who at the same time
                    cultivated poetry', did not so far abandon this pursuit as to devote himself
                    exclusively to the study of eloquence.· It was about this time in fact that he
                    composed, on the subject of the Passion, a drama, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tragedia di Cristo</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> a piece which has not been
                    printed, but which he most probably translated, with some additions, from the
                    Greek drama of the same name attributed to Gregory of Nazianzen. Of another
                    drama also composed by Gravina, there remains only the title, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sant’ Atanasio.</hi> As the relations of Gravina had destined him for the
                    profession of the law, the time was now approaching when it would be necessary
                    to make jurisprudence a serious study; but for that science he had conceived an
                    aversion which appeared to be insurmountable. The barbarous language of chicane,
                    as he considered the technical nomenclature of the law, appeared to him an
                    offence committed against the worship of the muses, and the riches which the bar
                    often produces, a sordid means of existence. Biscardi had much difficulty in
                    convincing him of the difference which exists between the science of laws, and
                    the mere conduct of processes, or ordinary practice. He repeated, for some time
                    in vain, that this science rests on a profound knowledge of the classics; and
                    that, if modern jurisconsults had corrupted the Latinity of the schools, it
                    might still be brought back to the standard of the purer ages of Alciat and
                    Cujas. The prejudices of Gravina at length vanished; he applied himself
                    vigorously to the study of the civil and canon law, and at the same time
                    extended his knowledge of theology by an attentive perusal of the works of the
                    Fathers. He sought the conversation of the learned, and continually studied the
                    five books which he regarded as the sources of the knowledge to which he
                    aspired; we mean the Holy Scriptures, the body of the civil law, the works of
                    Plato, those of Cicero, and the poems of Homer. Gravina had long desired to
                    visit Rome; but his uncle, Caloprese, who still superintended his education,
                    opposed his wish until he should have completed his course of study. When this
                    was accomplished, he repaired to the ancient capital of the world in 1689. Paolo
                    Coardo, of Turin, afterwards chamberlain to Clement XI. received him into his
                    house, where he remained several years, and also procured him the acquaintance
                    of the most celebrated men of their time, Ciampini, Fabretti, Bianchini,
                    Buonaroti, Emmanuel Martino, and Father Miro. In conversation, they were
                    accustomed to discuss the most important questions; and as it often turned upon
                    the relaxation of morals, Gravina undertook to treat this subject, applying to
                    it the theological knowledge which he had acquired in the course of his studies.
                    Accordingly, in 1691, he published, under the supposititious name of Priscus
                    Censorinus, a dialogue, entitled <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >corrupta Morali Doctrina,</hi> Naples, 4to, the object of which was to prove
                    that the corrupters of morals do more injury to the church than the boldest
                    heresiarchs. Gravina was then only twenty-six years of age. But the eloquence of
                    the style and the solidity of the reasonings ensured the success of the book,
                    which at the same time excited lively dissatisfaction amongst the numerous
                    partisans of convenient doctrines and loose practice. Father Concina has
                    inserted this dialogue almost entire in his treatise <hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Incredulis.</hi> Nor did poetry escape the
                    contamination which had so deeply infected morals. A single writer, Alessandro
                    Guidi, a friend of Gravina, struggled at Rome against the prevailing debasement
                    of taste, and, at the request of Christina, queen of Sweden, had, under the
                    Arcadian name of Erillo Cleoneo, written a comedy, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Endimione.</hi> As this piece became the object of the most virulent attacks,
                    Gravina, under the name of Bione Crateo, undertook the defence of his friend,
                    which he read in a literary assembly, and which was afterwards printed under the
                    title of <hi rend="italic">Discorso sopra Endimione,</hi> Rome, 1692. This
                    little work, in which he laid down excellent’ principles, drew upon the author
                    new adversaries, who considered it equally strange and unpardonable that Gravina
                    should attempt to constitute himself at once the censor of morals and the
                    reformer of taste. A jealousy, almost amounting to fury, was excited against the
                    young Neapolitan; whilst his disposition to censure the works of others, and the
                    confidence which he appeared to repose in his own opinions, were but little
                    calculated to calm the spirits of his enemies. Gravina sometimes commended, but
                    he more frequently censured, and his decisions were often expressed in
                    contemptuous terms. This tendency made him a host of enemies. His least actions
                    were watched in order to calumniate him, and he was assailed with the most
                    malignant invectives. Then appeared in succession, under the name of Quintio
                    Settano, the Arcadian <hi rend="italic">alias of</hi> LudovicoSergardi, sixteen
                    satires against Philodemus, the name under which Gravina was therein designated.
                    These satires, which were equally spirited and bitter, obtained great success,
                    and were circulated in profusion. Gravina at first affected indifference. It is
                    a fault of the age, said he, to take pleasure in outraging merit. But as this
                    tranquillity did not reduce his enemies to silence, he could no longer restrain
                    his resentment, and composed some declamations of the nature of <hi
                    rend="italic">verrine,</hi> and also some iambics; but he has not published
                    these retaliatory effusions, probably because he thought them inferior to the
                    satires of Settano. The malignity of the enemies of Gravina did not lessen the
                    esteem which he had inspired, nor abate his zeal for useful and wholesome
                    pursuits. He united with several other literary men who had associated together
                    for the purpose of cultivating poetry in silence. There were only fifteen of
                    them, but their number soon increased, and Gravina assembled them for the first
                    time, in November 1695, at a house which he had provided for the purpose on
                    Mount Janiculum. They framed for the association a democratic constitution, and
                    took the name of <hi rend="italic">Arcadi,</hi> or Area-dians<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193523288" xml:id="kp-eb0710-3288-0717"/>. In summer, they were to
                    assemble in the gardens, and there invoke the Muses: and, by their manner of
                    living and the simplicity of their writings, they were to endeavour to imitate
                    the ancient shepherds, without distinction of rank or fortune. Each assumed a
                    pastoral name. As the number of members increased, it became necessary to give
                    laws to the association, and decemvirs were named for the purpose of preparing
                    them. Called to discharge this duty, Gravina reviewed the numerous and
                    incoherent regulations adopted by the Arcadians, and reduced them into a single
                    code. These laws, written in Latin, with an elegant conciseness, and rare
                    propriety in the selection of terms, in imitation of those of the Twelve Tables,
                    soon spread throughout Europe, and were universally admired. Lastly, on the 20th
                    of May 1696, the <hi rend="italic">Arcadi</hi> held a general assembly on the
                    Palatine Hill. Gravina, after an eloquent discourse, presented the marble
                    tablets containing the laws, which he established with the expressions
                    consecrated in the Roman jurisprudence, and on this occasion also he assumed the
                    name of Opizio Eri-manteo. During this period, Gravina had composed several
                    dissertations, which he collected under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Opuscula,</hi> Rome, 1696, and in which are included, 1. Specimen prisci Juris;
                    2. De Lingua Latina dialogus; 3. Epistola ad Gabrielern Reignerium à Gallum; 4.
                    De contemptu Mortis; 5. Epistola ad Trojanum Mirabellam; and, 6. Delie Favole
                    Antiche, which has been translated into French by Joseph Regnauld. After the
                    death of Alexander VIII. Antonio Pignatelli, having obtained the pontifical
                    throne under the name of Innocent XII. wished to raise Gravina to the highest
                    ecclesiastical honours; but the latter refused to embrace the clerical
                    profession, as all his ambition was confined to teaching the laws, and his taste
                    led him towards profane erudition. Nor was his ambition disappointed. In 1699,
                    he obtained the chair of civil law, and in his opening discourse traced the
                    history of that science; whilst, in order to make his system of instruction
                    better known, he composed the treatise <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Instauratione Studiorum,</hi> which he dedicated to the new
                    pontiff. The discourse <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sapientia,</hi> which he delivered in 1700, also relates to the same subject.
                    In that one which is entitled <hi rend="italic">Pro</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Legibus</hi><hi rend="italic">ad magnum Moschorum regem,</hi> after speaking of
                    the pre-eminence and dignity of the Roman laws, he considers them in reference
                    to the influence which they were likely to have in the civilization of the
                    states of the czar, Peter the Great. The subjects of the other dissertations of
                    Gravina we need not indicate, as they have been collected in his works. We shall
                    merely refer to that one on the <hi rend="italic">internal rule,</hi> because it
                    makes known the religious sentiments with which the mind of this great civilian
                    was deeply imbued. In 1703, Gravina passed from the chair of civil to that of
                    canon law. From the commencement of his career as a public instructor he had
                    abolished the usage of scholastic argumentation; and each succeeding year
                    brought some useful change. He thought that the only means of establishing sound
                    doctrine was to ascend to the sources or fountain-head of the laws; and this
                    accordingly is the object of his treatise <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">repetendis Doctrinarum Fontibus.</hi> But these little treatises,
                    which he composed with extreme facility, did not prevent him from continuing his
                    great work, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Ortu et Progressu</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Juris</hi><hi rend="italic">Civilis,</hi> the first book of which
                    appeared at Naples in 1701, and the whole was completed in three books, and
                    printed in 1713. Europe resounded with the praises bestowed on this great work;
                    the celebrated Maffei made an abridgment of it; and it was reprinted several
                    times in different places. The writings of Gravina attest the extent of his
                    knowledge, and his ardour in the cause of education; but the greatest proof of
                    his general zeal and discrimination consists in giving to literature Metastasio,
                    who owed to him his education and his fortune, and who, in his writings,
                    particularly in his poetry, takes pleasure in acknowledging the gratitude he
                    owed, not only to the beneficence, but still more to the instructions of his
                    adoptive father. During the period which elapsed from 1711 to 1714, Gravina
                    completed and published several works, particularly his Discourses, his book <hi
                    rend="italic">De Romano</hi><hi rend="italic">Imperio,</hi> Naples, 1712, in
                    12mo; his tragedies, <hi rend="italic">Palamede, Andromede, Appius</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Claudius,</hi><hi rend="italic">Papinianus,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Servius Tullius,</hi> Naples, 1712, in 12mo; and his treatises,
                    <hi rend="italic">Della Ragione</hi><hi rend="italic">Poetica,</hi> Rome, 1708,
                    and <hi rend="italic">Della Tragedia,</hi> Naples, 1714, in 4to. Gregorio
                    Caloprese died at Scalea in the summer of 1714. As soon as Gravina heard of his
                    illness, he hastened to pay his last duties to a relation to whom he lay under
                    so many obligations. He passed nearly two years in Calabria, and it was not
                    until 1716 that he returned to Rome, where he died on the 6th of January 1718,
                    leaving to his mother, Anna Lombarde, the property which he possessed in
                    Calabria, and to Metastasio all that he had acquired at Rome, excepting some
                    legacies to his other pupils, Giuliano Pier-Santi, Lorenzo Gori, and Horazio
                    Bianchi, all men of reputation in letters. The works of Gravina have been
                    collected in three volumes, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Opere</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">del Gravina,</hi> Leipsic, 1737, in 4to, and Naples, 1756, with
                    notes by Mascovius the editor. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Gravina,</hi> a city of the province of Bari, in the kingdom of
                    Naples. It is a rocky height, watered at its foot by the rivers Casale and
                    Gravina. It contains 8693 inhabitants, who are employed in cultivating wheat and
                    aniseseed, and in preparing saltpetre.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
