<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0710-2001-0618-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GOTHS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 10, page 618</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vd72">Scythians</term>
                    <term n="36" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v99v">Pelasgi</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4j09w45x">Celts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="31" ref="fasttopic:945091">Goths</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1056644">Pelasgi</term>
                    <term n="32" ref="fasttopic:1109953">Scythians</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:850410">Celts</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="fasttopic:1048190">Originality</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193522001" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GOTHS</label> (in Latin <hi rend="smallcaps">Gothi,
                    Goti,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Gothones),</hi> a secondary denomination of
                    that great, powerful, and victorious race which, after a protracted struggle, at
                    length overturned the Roman empire, and diffused itself throughout the whole of
                    Europe, excepting Russia, Poland, and Hungary. The Scythians or Goths were
                    distinguished from the Celts, with whom they have often been confounded, by
                    characteristics equally obvious and remarkable. This we shall have occasion to
                    establish in the sequel of the present article. Many learned authors, however,
                    have contended for the identity of these races; all antiquity has been ransacked
                    for proofs and authorities by the writers on the opposite sides of the question;
                    and in a discussion which might surely have been carried on with moderation and
                    good manners, the utmost heat and exacerbation of feeling have unaccountably
                    been evinced. Amongst those who have contended for the identity of the Goths and
                    Celts, the first place is due to Cluverius and Pelloutier, who have asserted
                    this proposition in its most unqualified form; and likewise to Sir William
                    Jones, though he contends for nothing more than an identity of origin, leaving
                    the question of subsequent divergence and secondary distinction untouched. On
                    the other hand, of all the champions for the diversity of these races, Mr
                    Pinkerton is by far the most formidable, and, seconded as his views have been by
                    an able writer in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review,</hi> and also by Dr
                    Jamieson in his <hi rend="italic">Hermes Sythicus,</hi> they must be allowed to
                    have great weight by all who attentively consider and examine the question at
                    issue. Conceiving that the arguments and reasonings of Cluverius and Pelloutier
                    have been entirely overthrown, and that the diversity contended for has been
                    established by a mass of evidence and authority which cannot be shaken, what we
                    propose in this article, therefore, is to lay before our readers the substance
                    of Mr Pinkerton’s very learned argument, modified however by the views of
                    succeeding writers.</p>
                <p>Of the <hi rend="italic">Scythians</hi> an ample account is given by Herodotus in
                    his fourth book, where he also mentions the <hi rend="italic">Gerae,</hi> whom
                    Darius subdued whilst advancing against the wandering Scythians who lived on the
                    other side of the Ister or Danube. From the earliest periods of history,
                    therefore, mention is made of the <hi rend="italic">Scytha</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Geta</hi> as only separated by a river. But the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">Goths</hi> is not nearly so ancient. The first mention of it
                    occurs in the time of the Emperor Decius, in the year of Christ 250, when part
                    of them invaded the empire from Getia, and Decius, in attempting to expel them
                    from Thrace, was vanquished and slain. After this they are as frequently
                    mentioned in the Latin authors by the names of <hi rend="italic">Geta</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Gothi,</hi> as the <hi rend="italic">Scytha</hi> formerly were
                    in the Greek; and, subsequently to this period, all the Greek writers uniformly
                    call those <hi rend="italic">Scytha</hi> whom the Latin authors denominate <hi
                    rend="italic">Gothi.</hi> This being the case, Mr Pinkerton shows, first, that
                    the <hi rend="italic">Geta</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gothi</hi> were the same
                    people; and, secondly, that the <hi rend="italic">Geta</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gothi</hi> were the same with the <hi rend="italic">Scytha.</hi></p>
                <p>1. That the <hi rend="italic">Geta</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gothi</hi> were the
                    same, is proved by a multitude of authorities, which our limits prevent us from
                    enumerating in detail. It may sufiice to mention, that Dio, who wrote under
                    Alexander Severus, about the year 230, entitles his history of the Goths
                    Γιr&lt;xo∣⅛ or the <hi rend="italic">Getic</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193522014" xml:id="kp-eb0710-2014-0619"/>history; that Spartian, who
                    wrote about the year 300, says, in his Life of Antoninus Caracallus, <hi
                    rend="italic">Gotti Getae</hi><hi rend="italic">dicerentur,</hi> “the Goths were
                    then called Getae,” and, again, in his Life of Antoninus Geta, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Getticus quasi Gotticus,</hi> “Getic as we would now say Gothic that Claudian
                    always calls the Goths <hi rend="italic">Getae,</hi> and entitles his poem on
                    the Gothic war <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">bello Getico</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">,∙</hi> that Sidonius Apollinaris frequently calls the Goths <hi
                    rend="italic">Get&lt;e,</hi> and denominates the Ostrogoths <hi rend="italic"
                    >Massagetae</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> that Orosius says, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Getae</hi><hi rend="italic">qui et</hi><hi rend="italic">nunc</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Gothi,</hi> “the Getae, who are now also called Goths that St
                    Jerome states that the Goths were anciently called Getae; that in the panegyric
                    of Ennodius, on Theodoric, king of the Goths, it is said, “Nam illud quo ore
                    celebrandum est quod <hi rend="italic">Getici</hi> instrumenta roboris, dum
                    provides ne interpellentur otia nostra, custodis that, according to Procopius,
                    “the Goths are a Getic race ;” that Jemandes entitles his history <hi
                    rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Getarum sive Gothorum origine et rebus
                    Gestis,</hi> and constantly uses the names <hi rend="italic">Getae</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Gothi</hi> as synonymous; and, finally, that Isidorus says the
                    Getae and Gothi are the same. This identity, therefore, seems to be completely
                    established; especially as there is not even a shadow of authority on the
                    opposite side.</p>
                <p>2. It appears equally certain that the <hi rend="italic">Getae</hi> or Goths were
                    the same with the Scythians. Strabo, Pliny, and Ptolemy, all rank the Getae as
                    Scythians. Trebellius Pollio, <hi rend="italic">in Galieno,</hi> says, “<hi
                    rend="italic">Scythae</hi> autem, id est, peri <hi rend="italic">Gothorum,</hi>
                    Asiam vastabant.” Dexippus, who is supposed to have written in the reign of
                    Gallienus, entitled his history of the wars between the Romans and Goths
                    ΣKTΘIKA, or Scythic histories, and called the Goths ∑xuda&lt;, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Scythae.</hi> Priscus employs the words <hi rend="italic">Scythians</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Goths</hi> synonymously. Eunapius denominates the <hi
                    rend="italic">Scythians,</hi> whom Valens planted in Moesia, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Goths.</hi> Procopius speaks of “all the other Gothic nations, who were also
                    called <hi rend="italic">Scythians</hi> in ancient times.” Theophanes, writing
                    in the year 370, states “that the Scythians are in their tongue called Goths,”
                    according to the relation of Trajanus Patricius, “in the history of his own
                    time.” Syncellus states that “the Scythians are also called Goths in their own
                    language and the same author likewise says, “when a great many Scythians, called
                    Goths, had passed the river Ister in the time of Decius, they ravaged the Roman
                    empire.” Jemandes always speaks of the Goths, Getae, and Scythae, as one people,
                    and uses these names synonymously. Isidorus commences his chronicle of the Goths
                    in Spain with these words: “Gothorum antiquissimum esse regnum certum est, quod
                    ex regno <hi rend="italic">Scytha-rum</hi> est exortum.” Procopius frequently
                    calls the Fede-rati, so well known in the Lower Empire, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Goths</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and Suidas, <hi rend="italic">in voce,</hi>
                    denominates them <hi rend="italic">Scythians.</hi> Lastly, Ammianus Marcellinus,
                    mentioning the death of Decius, who fell in battle against the Goths or Getae,
                    denominates the latter <hi rend="italic">Scytl.icae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >gentes.</hi> “That the <hi rend="italic">Scythians</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Getae</hi> were the same people,” says Dr Jamieson, “is attested by
                    incontrovertible evidence.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">/termes Scythicus,</hi> Dissert, on the Origin of the
                    Greeks, sec. 2.</p></note></p>
                <p>Having thus established that the Scythians, Getae, and Goths, are all one people,
                    Pinkerton next proceeds to consider the question whether the Scythians or Goths
                    went from Scandinavia into Asia, or whether, on the contrary, they came from
                    Asia into Europe. And, in prosecution of this curious and important inquiry, he
                    endeavours, in the first place, to show that the common notion of the Scythians
                    having originated from Scandinavia is groundless. This opinion, which has been
                    somewhat hastily adopted by Montesquieu, Gibbon, and other writers of the first
                    name, has been built on a single sentence in the fourth chapter of Jemandes,
                    namely, “Ex hac igitur Scania insula, quasi <hi rend="italic">officina</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">gentium,</hi> aut certe velut <hi rend="italic">vagina</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">nationum,</hi> cum rege suo nomine Berig Gothi quondam memorantur
                    egressi.” But no weight can reasonably be attached to this single authority,
                    however direct and explicit; first, because the work of Jemandes being, as is
                    commonly supposed, only an abridgment of a large history of the Goths by his
                    contemporary Cassiodorus, it is possible that in this as well as in other
                    particulars, the abridgment may be inaccurate, more especially as it would seem
                    to have been written solely from memory, after a perusal of three days;
                    secondly, because though he generally followed Cassiodorus, he added many things
                    from the Greek and Roman writers; thirdly, because Scandinavia having been, down
                    to a late period, almost overrun with impenetrable forests, there was neither
                    room nor subsistence in that country for so vast a population as that which so
                    often invaded, and at last overturned, the Roman empire; fourthly, because we
                    learn from Adam of Bremen, who wrote in the eleventh century, that, even in
                    Denmark, the sea coasts alone were then peopled, whilst the interior parts of
                    the country were one immense forest; and, lastly, because it can be proved from
                    many authorities, in opposition to the single one of Jemandes, which is moreover
                    highly improbable in itself, that the Scythians originated from Asia. On this
                    last point some of Pinkerton’s authorities have been disputed both by the author
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Vindication of the Cells,</hi> and also by the able
                    writer in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> already referred to, who
                    have each convicted him of sundry errors and inaccuracies of detail; but such is
                    the redundancy of evidence which he has produced in support of his views, that,
                    after every reasonable deduction has been made, enough remains to establish the
                    position, that at a period probably as early as the year 1400 before Christ, the
                    Scythians had advanced fron» the vicinity of the river Araxes, entered the
                    Cimmerian Bosphorus, whence they afterwards spread themselves westward and
                    northward over a considerable part of Europe. He shows that Herodotus, Diodorus,
                    and indeed all the writers who have occasion to mention the subject, down to the
                    sixth century, when Jemandes wrote, are in opposition to this monastic
                    historian, and uniformly represent the Scythians as having passed, from the
                    south of Asia, in a north-westerly direction, until, in process of time, they
                    spread themselves all over Europe.</p>
                <p>We pass over the chapter upon the real origin and first progress of the Scythians
                    or Goths, whom Pinkerton traces from the banks of the Indus, through Persia, to
                    the shores of the Caspian, and proceed to state the results at which he has
                    arrived in the succeeding one, which treats of the western settlements of this
                    people. From their intermediate position on the Euxine, the Scythians gradually
                    extended themselves over the most part of Europe; and, according to Pinkerton,
                    the Greeks and Romans, though refined by adventitious circumstances, certainly
                    belonged to the same great family of mankind. We may also mention here, that,
                    both on historical and on philological grounds, Dr Jamieson, in his Dissertation
                    and in his <hi rend="italic">Hermes</hi><hi rend="italic">Scythicus,</hi>
                    contends strenuously for the Scythian origin of the Greeks, and, by many new and
                    ingenious arguments, supports this, which forms one of the principal points of
                    Pinkerton’s hypothesis. According to the latter, the Scythians successively
                    invaded and settled in Thrace, Illyricum, Greece, Italy, Germany, and
                    Scandinavia; in other words, he endeavours to show that the Thracians,
                    Illyrians, Greeks, Italians, Germans, and Scandinavians, were all Scythians or
                    Goths. And all this seems to us to be proved, as far at least as such a subject
                    can be established by ancient authorities. The Scythian origin of the Thracians
                    and Illyrians is indisputable. But there is more difficulty respecting the
                    ancient inhabitants of Greece, taking that denomination in the large sense given
                    to <hi rend="italic">Hellas,</hi> as including Macedon, <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193522027" xml:id="kp-eb0710-2027-0620"/>and extending from Thrace and
                    Hlyricum to the Cretan, Ionian, and Sicilian Seas. From the concurrent testimony
                    of the Greek writers, it appears, first, that the ancient inhabitants of Hellas
                    were the <hi rend="italic">Pelasgi</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and, secondly,
                    that the <hi rend="italic">Hellenes</hi> were the same people who had formerly
                    been called the Pelasgi, being, in fact, a small tribe of the Pelasgi who,
                    having last settled in the country, had the good fortune to give their name to
                    the whole. Pinkerton next considers, first, who the Pelasgi were not, and,
                    secondly, who they were. They were not Egyptians, because the two small colonies
                    of Egyptians who settled in Athens and Argos from the earliest times, were
                    specially distinguished as a different people from the Pelasgi; because the
                    Greek mythology has little or no affinity to the Egyptian; and because the Greek
                    language differs entirely from the Coptic, in which are embodied the remains of
                    the old Egyptian. They were not Phoenicians, because of all the reasons urged
                    respecting the Egyptians. They were not Celts, because the latter were confined
                    to the farthest west, whereas Greece was surrounded by Scythians; because the
                    form and structure of the Celtic tongue are as remote as possible from that of
                    the Greek; and because the manners, customs, and usages of the Celts, as
                    described by the Greek and Roman authors, are entirely dissimilar to those of
                    the earliest Greeks. They were not Sarmatae, because there is reason to doubt
                    whether the latter entered Europe more than a thousand years before our era,
                    whereas the progressive advancement of the Scythians dates from a much earlier
                    period; because the manners of the earliest Greeks had nothing in common with
                    those of the Sarmatic or Tartar tribes; and because the Slavonic language, which
                    was spoken by the Sarmatians, differs from the Greek in grammatical structure as
                    well as in nomenclature. But the Pelasgi, or Hellenes, were Scythians of Thrace;
                    a position which, besides being established by authority, is rendered highly
                    probable from the circumstance that ancient Hellas was everywhere surrounded
                    either by the Scythians or the sea. For the full illustration of this branch of
                    the subject, however, we must refer the reader to the fourth chapter of Mr
                    Pinkerton’s Dissertation, to Dr Doig’s paper on the Ancient Hellenes,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Tramactionl
                    of the Royal Society of Edinburgh,</hi> vol. iii. part 2, p. 131.</p></note> and
                    to the <hi rend="italic">Hermes</hi><hi rend="italic">Scythicus</hi> of Dr
                    Jamieson, <hi rend="italic">passim.</hi> A similar mode of reasoning leads to
                    the conclusion that the Italians, as well as the Greeks, were Scythians.</p>
                <p>In the second part of his Dissertation, where he contemplates the extended
                    settlements of the Scythians or Goths over all Germany, and in Scandinavia, Mr
                    Pinkerton endeavours, in the first place, to show, negatively, that the Germans
                    were not of Sarmatic nor of Celtic origin; and, secondly, he attempts to prove,
                    positively, that they were Scythians, from identity of language, from the
                    testimonies of the ancient authors, and from similarity of manners and
                    institutions. The details required for the illustration of both branches of his
                    argument are necessarily complicated, and do not admit of abridgment. But the
                    reasoning is throughout strictly logical, and the conclusion can only be
                    affected by impeaching the accuracy or validity of the premises. This, we are
                    aware, has, to a considerable extent, been done in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vindication of the Cells,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Her∙iew,</hi>
                    and in other works; and it must be confessed that the most unsparing severity of
                    criticism is provoked, and in some measure justified, by the tone of insolent
                    dogmatism which Pinkerton thought proper to assume, no less than by the
                    contemptuous language in which he is pleased to characterise almost every writer
                    whose opinions happened to differ from his own. But notwithstanding all his
                    errors, aggravated as they unfortunately are by some misrepresentations, the
                    stability of his argument remains as yet unshaken; and even those who have been
                    most successful in detecting his blunders, will, if impartial, be the first to
                    admit the great learning which he has brought to bear on his subject, and the
                    ability with which he has throughout conducted his reasoning. In tracing the
                    distinctive characteristics of the Goths and the Celts, he has, in fact,
                    established his case, independently altogether of the positive evidence derived
                    from authorities, which is afterwards supplied in profusion. Races of men which
                    are found to differ in person, in manners, in laws, in religion, and in
                    language, cannot, upon any known principle of reason, be admitted to bave had a
                    common origin, whatever we may be led to believe upon the paramount authority of
                    revelation.</p>
                <p>Upon the whole, in reference to the subject of the Goths and Celts, the following
                    points may be considered as established by the best evidence which the case
                    admits of, viz. 1. At a period so early as the age of Sesostris, that is, at
                    least 1400 years before Christ, the Scythians, previously established on the
                    western shores of the Caspian and the eastern shores of the Euxine, had extended
                    their conquests into Europe, and advanced at least as far as Thrace and the
                    surrounding countries. 2. About 640 years before Christ, the Scythians drove the
                    Cimmerians (believed to be the same people with the Cimbri and the Cymry) out of
                    Europe, or forced them to take refuge in wild, mountainous, and inaccessible
                    regions. 3. The Scythae were afterwards known in history by the names of <hi
                    rend="italic">Gerae,</hi><hi rend="italic">Gothi,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Germani</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but whether distinguished by these names,
                    or by the more comprehensive appellation of <hi rend="italic">Scythians,</hi>
                    they are to be regarded as one and the same people. 4. The principal part of the
                    population of every country in Europe, excepting Russia, Poland, and Hungary,
                    where the Slavonic race predominates, is of Gothic origin and descent, though
                    variously modified by the force of adventitious circumstances. 5. With regard to
                    the Celts, the testimony of the earliest writers authorizes us to place their
                    principal settlement, in the fifth century before our era, in the southwest of
                    Gaul, or neighbourhood of the Pyrenees, whence they appear to have been driven
                    by the Germans or Goths on the east, and the Aquitani (probably an Iberian race)
                    on the south, to that part of Gaul where they were found in the time of Caesar.
                    6. The Slavi, who invaded the north-west of Europe after the destruction of the
                    Roman empire, were an Asiatic tribe; and the present inhabitants and languages
                    of Russia, Bohemia, Hungary, Poland, and Dalmatia, are derived from them.</p>
                <p>Dr Jamieson, in the Dissertation prefixed to his <hi rend="italic">Hermes</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Scythicus,</hi> adopts the same views, and follows nearly the same
                    line of argument, as Mr Pinkerton, in considering the historical proofs of the
                    Scythian origin of the Greeks. He shows that the Scythians and Getae were one
                    people, that the Goths were identical with the Getae, and that the Thracians
                    were of Scythian origin. He then treats of the diffusion of the Pelasgi
                    throughout Greece; the identity of the Hellenes with the Pelasgi; the erroneous
                    opinions which have been entertained respecting the origin of this people; the
                    origin of their name; the proofs from testimony of the Scythian origin of the
                    Pelasgi; the progress of this people as illustrative of their origin; the
                    language of the Pelasgi; and, lastly, the resemblance of the Greek language to
                    that of the Scythians. He next adverts to the origin of the religion of the
                    Greeks, and of those called Hyperboreans, and, by an elaborate analytical
                    examination, endeavours to show that the mythology of the Greeks, or at least
                    their theocracy, was of Scythian descent, and merely an improved or polished
                    form of the ruder system of superstition which the Goths imported into Europe
                    from their <pb break="no" facs="nls:193522040" xml:id="kp-eb0710-2040-0621"
                    />original settlements, and of which the principal features are still preserved
                    in the Scandinavian mythology. These topics exhaust the historical disquisition,
                    which, however, is in no small degree purely philological. But, in the second
                    part of his work entitled <hi rend="italic">Hermes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Scythicus,</hi> the learned and estimable author applies himself to demonstrate
                    the-affinity of the Scythian and Greek language by a critical and etymological
                    examination of the purely elementary parts of the one, with cognatç or
                    corresponding forms of expression in the other; and, in prosecuting this refined
                    and delicate analysis, he displays equal erudition and ingenuity, accompanied,
                    however, it must be admitted, with a little occasional straining. Whatever may
                    be thought of the hypothesis, therefore, the learning brought to bear upon the
                    subject is worthy of all acceptation; and every philosophical inquirer into the
                    origin and structure of languages must feel grateful to Dr Jamieson for the
                    curious and interesting information which he has so laboriously accumulated.</p>
                <p>The most ancient proofs of the affinity of Scythian and Greek, which the doctor
                    has referred to in his inquiry, are derived from the celebrated version oſ
                    Ulphilas, bishop of the Moeso-Goths, which appears to have been executed about
                    the year 360 of our era, though some learned writers have affirmed that it was
                    executed in the reign of Constantine the Great. It is much to be regretted, that
                    of the labours of Ulphilas, all that remains is his version of the four gospels,
                    nearly one half of which has been lost; and some fragments of his translation of
                    the Epistle to the Romans. The proofs derivable from the Moeso-Gothic are thus
                    extremely limited. But recourse may be had to the Anglo-Saxon, a derivative
                    dialect of the ancient Gothic, introduced into England about the year 450, or
                    nearly a century after the date of the version of Ulphilas. There is not,
                    indeed, extant any Anglo-Saxon writer older than Caedmon, who flourished about
                    three centuries later than the Bishop of Moesia; but so close is the affinity of
                    these two languages, that Hickes, the learned author of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Thesaurus</hi><hi rend="italic">Linguarum Septentrionalium</hi> has included
                    both in the same grammar. The form of speech which has the next claim in point
                    of antiquity is the Alemanic or Franco-Theotiscan; but of this there exist no
                    memorials of an earlier date than the reign of Charlemagne. The Islandic is the
                    oldest and purest dialect of the Gothic which still exists as a living language.
                    This language, in its more ancient form, has been called the Runic, from the
                    character in which it was written; and in it Saemund the Wise wrote the Edda
                    which bears his name, towards the close of the eleventh century. The
                    Suio-Gothic, including the ancient language of Sweden, is nearly allied to
                    theTslandic, and constitutes one of the sources from which the proofs of
                    affinity are principally derived. Finally, without attempting to pronounce any
                    opinion as to the result of Dr Jamieson’s analytical investigation, we may
                    however be permitted to observe, that, if there exist such an affinity as that
                    contended for between the Gothic and Greek, and if an argument be thence deduced
                    as to the Scythian origin of the people by whom the latter was spoken, the
                    well-known fact of the striking affinity, amounting almost to identity, which is
                    found to subsist between the Greek and the sacred language of India, the
                    Sanscrit, must give an entirely new direction to the inquiry into the origin and
                    descent of nations, and lead us to extend our views on this subject far beyond
                    the range to which Dr Jamieson, and those who have followed in his footsteps,
                    have confined their researches.</p>
                <p>(Pinkerton’s <hi rend="italic">History of Scotland,</hi> vol. ii. Dissertation on
                    the Origin and Progress of the Scythians and Goths, Edinburgh, 1814, in 8vo.
                    Vindication of the Celts, from Ancient Authorities; with observations on Mr
                    Pinkerton’s Hypothesis concerning the Origin of the European Nations, London,
                    1803. Edinburgh Review, vol. ii. p. 355</p>
                <p>et seqq. Jamieson’s <hi rend="italic">Hermes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Scythicus,</hi> or the Radical Affinities of the Greek and Latin Languages to
                    the Gothic, &amp;c. Edinburgh, 1814. Doig on the Ancient Hellenes, <hi
                    rend="italic">Edinburgh Transactions,</hi> vol. iii.) <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
