<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0710-1832-0605-05" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">GOLDONI, Charles</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 10, page 605</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1057086">Pensions</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1137041">Success</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z5k">Pensions</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193521832" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">GOLDONI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi></label>, the most
                    celebrated comic writer of Italy in the eighteenth century, and in his own
                    country styled the Italian Molière, was born at Venice in the year 1707, in
                    which city his father acted in the capacity of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193521845" xml:id="kp-eb0710-1845-0606"/>physician. His
                    attachment to the drama became conspicuous even in childhood, and this his
                    father countenanced and cherished, by erecting a theatre in his own house, where
                    young Goldoni and some of his companions were the actors. It is said that he
                    even drew the outline of a comedy of his own invention when he was not more than
                    eight years of age; a most extraordinary, though not very credible, indication
                    of future eminence. He was taught rhetoric at Perugia, in the college of the
                    Jesuits, and prosecuted his philosophical studies at Rimini. The stage, however,
                    had too many attractions for him, to admit of his paying much attention to
                    Aristotle or Quintilian, and he eloped from Rimini with a company of comedians,
                    when they removed to Chiozza. His father attempted in vain to induce him to
                    study either physic or the law; yet his ardent imagination was so forcibly
                    struck with a particular ceremony of the church, that he conceived the intention
                    of turning capuchin: but the dissipation of Venice soon extinguished this fancy.
                    After the demise of his father he was prevailed upon by his surviving parent to
                    engage in the profession of the law for immediate support; but some unknown
                    causes induced him to leave the bar, after which he proceeded to Milan, and was
                    there appointed secretary to the Venetian resident</p><p>At Milan he brought out his first performance, under the title of <hi rend="italic">II</hi><hi rend="italic">Gondoliere</hi><hi rend="italic">Veneziano,</hi> which had all the success that could be expected from such a
                    composition. He afterwards removed to Verona, where he joined himself to a
                    company of players, and also entered into the state of wedlock. He composed a
                    number of pieces for the company to which he attached himself, and amongst these
                    his tragedy of Belisarius, which was performed for the first time at Venice on
                    the 24th of November 1734, with the greatest success. Whilst as Venice he formed
                    the laudable resolution of reforming the Italian stage, which at that time was
                    disgraced by contemptible farce and low buffoonery. With this view, having made
                    himself acquainted with the true nature of comedy, ne kept within the limits of
                    nature and decorum; and such was the fertility of his genius, such his
                    indefatigable industry, that he produced no fewer than sixteen comedies and
                    forty-two other theatrical pieces in the course of about twelve months. Nor is
                    it a less remarkable circumstance that some of these hasty performances are
                    considered as his masterpieces. His works, in ten volumes 8vo, were first
                    printed in 1753, and in 1761 his new pieces amounted to fifty-nine. And here
                    ends the literary life of Goldoni in Italy; for about this time he accepted an
                    engagement of two years in Paris, where he found a numerous company of excellent
                    performers in the Italian theatre. His first attempt was unsuccessful, because
                    he had to contend with the pantomimic drollery which was most agreeable to the
                    depraved taste of the times. When about to leave Paris on the expiration of his
                    engagement, he was introduced to the court, and appointed teacher of the Italian
                    languages to the princesses. He had lodgings assigned him in Versailles, but his
                    allowance was not sufficient to enable him to dispense with writing for the
                    stage. Meanwhile, being anxious to show the French nation that he merited a high
                    place among their dramatic writers, he neglected no means calculated to render
                    him master of the French language; and, at the age of sixty-two, he ventured to
                    write a comedy in French, which was brought out under the title of <hi rend="italic">Le Bourru Bienfaisant,</hi> and received great applause in the
                    court theatre. His next production was <hi rend="italic">L’</hi><hi rend="italic">Avare Fastueux,</hi> also a comedy·, and this was succeeded by <hi rend="italic">Volponi,</hi> which he wrote after he had retired from court. The
                    last work which he undertook was the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires pour servir</hi>
                    à <hi rend="italic">l’</hi><hi rend="italic">Histoire de sa Vie et à celle de
                    son Théâtre,</hi> which, after having been about three years occupied with the
                    composition, appeared in 1787., when he entered into the eightieth year of his
                    age. These Memoirs, written with unaffected simplicity and ∣ sincerity, display
                    the real character both of the author and the man, and supply the most ample
                    Information respecting the history of his life. Deprived of his pension soon
                    after the commencement of the revolution, Goldoni was reduced to absolute
                    indigence, and passed the evening of his life in extreme distress. At length he
                    fell sick; and it was only in his last moments, on the 7th of January 1793, that
                    the Convention, apprised of his situation, decreed, on the report of Chenier,
                    that his pension should in fiiture be paid out of the national treasury, and
                    that the arrears due to him should be immediately discharged. But it was too
                    late. Goldoni died on the day after this decree was passed. But, on the
                    recommendation of Chenier, a pension of 1200 francs was granted to his widow,
                    aged seventy-six, and the arrears due to her husband were also paid to her. If
                    the rapidity with which Goldoni composed prevented him from attaining the first
                    rank as a comic writer, it will easily be conceded that he stands foremost in
                    the second. His fertility is prodigious, and if his works betray marks of haste
                    or of carelessness, they at least show ready invention, and, considering the
                    diversity of his subjects, extraordinary resources as a comic writer. The
                    greatest fault with which he is reproached is having contributed to corrupt the
                    language of his country, which he seems to have been unable to write with
                    purity, elegance, and propriety; and, in fact, we find ease, originality, and,
                    if we may so express it, purity of style only in his comedies written in the
                    Venetian dialect, which was his vernacular idiom. His merits are, having
                    contributed to reform the Italian stage, supplanted farce and low buffoonery,
                    naturalised genuine comedy in his native country, and replaced the extravagances
                    which had so long corrupted the public taste, by pieces in which a regular plot
                    and natural characters supply the place of nonsensical ribaldry and ridiculous
                    exaggeration. His comic opera entitled <hi rend="italic">Buona Figliuola,</hi>
                    with music by Piccini, was the first production which introduced both the poet
                    and the composer to the knowledge of our countrymen. The only complete edition
                    of Goldoni’s works is that printed at Leghorn, 1788, 1791, in thirty-one vols.
                    8vo.</p></div></body></text></TEI>