<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0710-0064-0469-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">GEORGIA</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 10, page 469</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:880858">Cotton</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1097334">Rice</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1124682">Soils</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1072068">Porters</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1072067">Porter</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw7t">Porter</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term><term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="14" ref="fastgeo:1204622">Georgia</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204694">Alabama</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205150">Florida</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193520064" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">GEORGIA</label>, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Grusia.</hi> This
                    extensive tract of country, which is situated between the Black and the Caspian
                    Seas, now forms a province of Russia by the encroachments of that power on the
                    side of Persia. It is diversified by great inequalities of surface; but contains
                    many fertile and beautiful valleys, which are finely contrasted with the
                    mountainous character of the regions of Caucasus. The hills are clothed with the
                    finest woods, consisting of oak, ash, chestnut, beech, and elm. Some vines grow
                    perfectly wild, producing the finest grapes; and the wines produced have always,
                    according to the report of Sir R. K. Porter, been esteemed for softness,
                    lightness, and delicacy of taste. The valleys are extremely fertile, producing
                    cotton, as well as the finest European fruit trees, and abundance of hemp, flax,
                    rice, millet, barley, and wheat. The country is copiously watered by the rivers
                    which flow from the mountains, and produce great variety of delicious fish.
                    Pheasants, wild fowl of every kind, antelopes, deer, sheep, with all sorts of
                    domestic cattle, are found in the valleys. In the mountains are found mines of
                    gold, silver, and other minerals. The habits of the people are such as might be
                    expected in their low state of civilization. A struggle for independence was
                    long maintained by the Georgians against the inroads of Persia. But it was at
                    last reduced into a province of that vast monarchy, and it was afterwards the
                    arena of the Persian and Russian wars, by which the country was ravaged; and the
                    people, far from being naturally industrious, appeared to despise every pursuit
                    which required labour. They neglected agriculture, and were often engaged in
                    intestine wars, or in forays on their neighbours for the sakeof plunder; and
                    were frequently exposed, in consequence, to severe retaliation from the
                    Lesghees, a barbarous tribe, subsisting, like most of the mountain tribes of
                    Asia, by pillage. But about the year 1800 it was reduced into a province of the
                    Russian empire; and, under the iron rule of that despotic power, order has been
                    re-established, the traveller has been protected from robbery, commerce and
                    agriculture begin to be followed, and a favourable revolution appears to have
                    taken place in the habits and manners of the people. Sir R. K. Porter, who has
                    given an interesting account of these newly-conquered provinces, mentions that
                    the different European governors have generally endeavoured to conciliate the
                    people and the nobles, and that the country being now effectually guarded from
                    the destructive inroads of plundering banditti or foreign enemies, the nobles
                    begin to feel the importance of the station they hold in the country; whilst
                    they have been still further countenanced by the distribution of medals and
                    orders of distinction amongst the leading men, with titles also and commissions
                    of military rank in the Russian armies. The Georgians are tall and well formed.
                    The Georgian noble is distinguished by a sombre cast of visage, which, though
                    stem, is of a fine contour, and harmonizes well with the minuteness of his
                    figure, and the style of his dress, which consists of an under garment of fine
                    pink cloth worn as a shirt, but leaving the neck entirely bare; a vest of cloth
                    with sleeves sitting easy on the arm; a tunic descending over this to the knees,
                    opening before, and bound round with a white sash, to which is attached the
                    sword trousers to the knees; whilst a sort of stocking, and a close-laced half
                    boot, complete this picturesque costume. The Georgian women equal the men in
                    grace, and are famed all over the East. Their dress is cumbersome and overloaded
                    with ornament, and the face painted so as entirely to injure its expression.
                    Under its gallant prince Heraclius, Georgia rose to the dignity of a separate
                    kingdom. This country originally included nearly the whole northern declivity of
                    the Caucasus, extending from the Black Sea to the Caspian. It is now divided
                    into the four provinces of Cartuel, Kaket or Kacheti, Kisik called sometimes
                    Tomehet, and Georgian Armenia. The inhabitants consist chiefly of Christians of
                    the Greek communion; to which are added Jews, Tartars, Armenians, and Russians.
                    The chief rivers are the Kur and the Araxes, which fall into the Caspian. The
                    chief, and indeed the only place of any consequence, is Tiflis, which, under the
                    protecting policy of Russia, has rapidly grown up into a considerable mart of
                    eastern commerce, and is on the increase. The inhabitants are not estimated at
                    more than 320,000.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Georgia,</hi> one of the United States of North America, is
                    situated between 30. 19. and 35. north latitude, and 3. 52. and 8. 47. west
                    longitude. It is bounded on the north by Tennessee and North Carolina, on the
                    northeast by South Carolina, on the south-east by the Atlantic, on the south by
                    Florida, and on the west by Alabama. In length it extends 300 miles, having an
                    average breadth of about 200 miles, and containing about 58,000 square miles.
                    For nearly 100 miles along the sea-shore there is a broad maritime belt of level
                    country. Along the coast there are a number of islands; whilst the numerous
                    rivers, creeks, and inlets of the sea overflow the swamps or marshes with which
                    they are bordered at almost every return of the tide. These swamps, however,
                    constitute the rice plantations. Beyond the sea-marshes commences an extensive
                    belt of pine barrens, extending from sixty to ninety miles from the sea, and
                    closely resembling those of South Carolina. Beyond this belt the country becomes
                    diversified with hills and mountains, and possesses a strong rich soil, called
                    technically <hi rend="italic">mulatto soil.</hi> This region is bounded on the
                    west by a chain of hills called the Blue Ridge, which here swells into
                    elevations about 1500 feet in height. An extensive track of table-land now
                    succeeds, possessing a black soil of great fertility, in which pines and
                    evergreens are more rare, their place being supplied by black walnut and other
                    forest trees, which indicate a rich soil.</p><p>The principal rivers are, the Savannah, Ogeechee, Alatamaha, Satilla, Oakmulgee,
                    Oconee, St Mary’s Flint, Chatahoochee, Tallapoosa, and Coosa. Tides flow up the
                    Savannah for twenty-five miles, and the largest vessels can approach within
                    three miles of the city of Savannah, eighteen miles from the ocean. The Ogeechee
                    river pursues a south-east course through the state for 200 miles. A canal from
                    the Savannah to the Ogeechee has been finished, and it is in contemplation to
                    extend it to the Alatamaha, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193520077" xml:id="kp-eb0710-0077-0470"/>which will make in all seventy-two miles. The
                    latter river is a broad and deep stream, having numerous branches.</p><p>Amongst the mineral productions of Georgia may be mentioned copper and iron ores,
                    the latter being found in great abundance. The gold region extends in a broad
                    belt through this state; and it is conjectured that gold would be found much
                    more abundantly in the high lands of Georgia and Alabama than in the eastern
                    section of the gold region.</p><p>In front of the broad belt of salt marsh which skirts the sea-shore, there is a
                    chain of islands of great value for their capability of yielding sea-island
                    cotton, and as retreats, during the sickly months, for the low country planters.
                    The soil of these islands is rich, and covered with pine, hickory, and live oak,
                    in their natural state. The names of the principal of these are, Tybee, Assaw,
                    Ossa-baw, St Catherine’s, Cumberland, Jeíćyl, Sapelo, and St Symon’s.</p><p>The climate is similar to that of South Carolina; indeed in a variety of its
                    features Georgia resembles that state. The low countries have their sickly
                    season, and the planters are compelled to fly in summer to retreats amongst the
                    high .pine woods. The districts central to the rice swamps are invariably
                    insalubrious. In some portions of Georgia the temperature approaches the
                    tropical more than it does in any part of South Carolina, and these districts
                    are accordingly better adapted to .the cultivation of the sugarcane, the olive,
                    and sweet orange. The hilly and western parts of the state are as healthy as any
                    part of America. Winter may be said to commence in the middle of December, and
                    to end in the middle of February.</p><p>The staple production of the country is cotton, of which both the black-seeded
                    and sea-island kinds are reared. The product next in importance is rice, with
                    which grain the swamps are sowed. Indigo and tobacco are also cultivated to some
                    extent, but sugar and wine are only produced in small quantities. The
                    cultivation of silk has been successfully attempted, and the quality is said to
                    be excellent. The forests afford an abundant supply of fine timber, consisting
                    chiefly of oak, pine, hickory, mulberry, and cedar. Melons grow in high
                    perfection, and figs are also common. Oranges, limes, citrons, pears, peaches,
                    and a few other fruits of mild climates, are likewise cultivated. The exports,
                    consisting chiefly of cotton, rice, deer skins, timber, &amp;c. amounted in 1828
                    to 4,981,376 dollars. The tonnage was at that period 13,959 tons.</p><p>Savannah is the commercial capital of Georgia. It is situated on the western bank
                    of the river of the same name, at about eighteen miles from its estuary. It
                    stands upon a low sandy plain, and contains twelve public buildings and eight
                    churches. There are ten public squares planted with trees, amongst which the
                    beautiful China trees are conspicuous. Savannah is a place of considerable
                    trade, and occasionally exports annually 120,000 bales of cotton, besides large
                    amounts of rice and tobacco. The exports of rice were, in 1826, 11,455 tierces,
                    and of tobacco 170 hogsheads. The town is defended by two forts, and the
                    entrance to the river is indicated by a lighthouse on Tybee Island. The
                    population was, in 1830, 7473. Augusta is a handsome town, situated on the
                    western bank of the Savannah, about 127 miles above Savannah. It is well laid
                    out, and chiefly built of brick. Being midway between the upper and lower
                    country, it constitutes a central emporium of business; no town of the same size
                    enjoys more. There is a communication by means of steam-boats between it and
                    Savannah. The population in 1830 amounted to 6696. Milledgeville is situated on
                    the western bank of the Oconee, 300 miles, by the curves of the river, from the
                    ocean. Its situation is elevated and pleasant, and it is central to a fertile
                    and populous country. It contains several public buildings, two or three
                    churches, and about 3000 inhabitants. Athens, which also lies on the west bank
                    of the Oconee, is the seat of the university of Georgia. The names of the other
                    principal towns or villages are, Waynesborough, Louisville, Georgetown,
                    Warrenton, Dublin, Laudersville, Sparta, Eatonton, Greensburgh, Madison,
                    Jefferson, Clarksborough, Watkinsville, Marion, Darien, Hinton, Monticello,
                    Sunbury, and St Mary’s.</p><p>The legislature of Georgia, which is called the general assembly, consists of a
                    senate and a house of representatives. It meets on the first Monday of November.
                    The members are chosen by the counties, each county sending one senator, and
                    from one to four representatives, according to the amount of its population. In
                    various parts of the state a number of negroes are employed by government in
                    working on roads, rivers, &amp;c. The university at Athens is a well-built
                    edifice, furnished with a respectable library, and an assortment of
                    philosophical apparatus. The funds amount to 136,000 dollars. According to a
                    Gazetteer of Georgia, there are about eighty incorporated academies in this
                    state, sixty-four of which have been brought into operation. The average number
                    of pupils in each is forty-seven, making in all 3008. In the northern and
                    southern sections of the state there are probably five common schools in each
                    county, forty counties, thirty pupils each, 6000; in the middle section say
                    seven common schools in each county, twenty-five counties, 5250; total number of
                    pupils in the academies and common schools, 14,258. The state possesses academy
                    and poor-school funds to a considerable amount. In 1792 an act was passed by
                    which every county was allowed to purchase the value of L.1000 of confiscated
                    property; in each county 1000 acres of land were granted for the support of
                    schools, and also a fund of 250,000 dollars to be vested in stocks for the same
                    purpose. The prevailing religious denominations of Georgia are the baptists and
                    methodists.</p><p>The first settlement of this state was made at Savannah by General Oglethorpe in
                    the year 1733. The native Indians of this state having been more disposed to
                    adopt the arts and modes of civilized life than in others, the white inhabitants
                    have gradually acquired a superiority over the lands. The greater portions of
                    two considerable tribes, the Cherokees and Creeks, reside within the chartered
                    limits of Georgia. Those of the former tribe in particular have made very
                    considerable advancement in civilization. They possess good houses, live in
                    villages, pursue agriculture, and have 1277 slaves. They have amongst them
                    carpenters and blacksmiths, and the women spin and weave, and make butter and
                    cheese. The number of these Indians is about 15,000, and they have increased
                    within the last six years. Their form of government is similar to that of the
                    country in which they live. Numerous missionary establishments have been fixed
                    amongst them, in the schools of which, according to the Gazetteer formerly
                    referred to, 500 children are learning the English language. Georgia is divided
                    into seventy-eight counties, and the population in 1830 amounted to 516,504, of
                    which number between the third and the half are slaves.</p></div></body></text></TEI>