<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0132-0121-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MYRRH (9th edition, volume 17, page 121)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1031561">Myrrh</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1125730">Somalis</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827573">Bark</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j96096v">Bark</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vb4q">Liberalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tw2z">Gums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tk2p">Resins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1213323">Aden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n132/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MYRRH</label> is a gum-resin highly esteemed by the ancients
                    as an unguent and perfume, used for incense in temples and also in embalming.
                    The word is Semitic; it appears in the Old Testament as *10 (Exod. xxx. 23; Ps.
                    xlv. 8; Cant, <hi rend="italic">passim),</hi> in Arabic as “morr.” In Exod. <hi
                    rend="italic">(l.c.)</hi> “pure myrrh” should rather be “flowing myrrh,” that
                    is, the “myrrha stacte” of classical writers,—the finest myrrh, according to
                    Pliny (xii. 35), exuding without incisions in the bark. So Johnson<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Travels in
                    Abyssinia,</hi> i. 249.</p></note> says that it exudes from cracks in the trunk
                    near the root and flows freely on stones underneath, the exudation being
                    sometimes aided by bruising the bark with a stone. Myrrh was one of the gifts
                    offered by the Magi, and a royal oblation of gold, frankincense, and myrrh is
                    still annually presented by the queen on the feast of Epiphany in the Chapel
                    Royal in London, this custom having been in existence certainly as early as the
                    reign of Edward I.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Liber</hi><hi rend="italic">quotidianus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Contra-rotulatoris</hi><hi rend="italic">Garderobae</hi><hi rend="italic">Edw.
                    I.,</hi> Lond., 1787, pp. xxxii. and 27.</p></note> Until the present century
                    the botanical source of myrrh was enveloped in great obscurity. In 1826
                    Ehrenberg brought home specimens of the myrrh trees found at Jizân on the east
                    side of the Red Sea, in lat. 16° 40' N., and also on the neighbouring mountains
                    of Jara. The more recent investigations of Hildebrandt (1878) show that one of
                    the plants brought home by Ehrenberg and named <hi rend="italic">Balsamodendron
                    Myrrha</hi> yields the true myrrh. It was found by Hildebrandt growing on sunny
                    slopes of the Sarât mountains at an elevation of 1600 to 3200 feet. It forms a
                    low tree, attaining a height of not more than 10 to 12 feet, with thorny
                    branches and a light grey bark, bearing some resemblance to those of the
                    hawthorn. The leaves are ternate, the two lateral leaflets being minute in
                    comparison with the central one; they are smooth, obovate, and denticulate. The
                    fruit is about the size of a pea, oval and somewhat compressed. The tree grows
                    interspersed among <hi rend="italic">Acaciae</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Euphorbiae</hi> in dwarfish thickets. The myrrh, according to Ehrenberg, when
                    it first exudes is of an oily and then of a buttery consistence, and of a
                    yellowish white colour, gradually assuming a golden and ultimately a reddish
                    tinge as it hardens. Myrrh is chiefly collected, according to Vaughan,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Pharm.
                    Journ.,</hi> (1), xii. p. 227.</p></note> in the Somali country and in the
                    neighbourhood of Harar (9° 20' N., 42° 17' E.) south-west of Zeila, in the
                    months of July and August (Johnson, <hi rend="italic">loc. cit.),</hi> and is
                    brought to the great fair of Berbera held in November, December, and January.
                    Thence it is transported to Aden and shipped to Bombay, where it is sorted, the
                    inferior kinds being sent chiefly to China and the finer sorts to Europe. The
                    Banians of India, who trade in myrrh, have their business houses at Bombay, but
                    employ partners or agents, who reside at Makallah and Aden to attend the fair at
                    Berbera, and exchange Indian or English piece goods for myrrh, bdellium, and
                    frankincense. Myrrh of the best quality is known as Turkey myrrh, and the
                    inferior quality as East Indian myrrh, from being exported from Bombay. At the
                    present time, however, all myrrh is imported either direct from Aden or from
                    Bombay. The Somalis also cross over to the Arabian shore and collect this
                    gum-resin on the hills about Shugra and Sureea to the east of Aden, where myrrh
                    trees abound. The myrrh of this district differs slightly in appearance, and is
                    less resinous than that of Somali Land, and in the opinion of Hanbury <hi
                    rend="italic">(Pharm.,</hi> p. 143) is probably the produce of a distinct
                    species of <hi rend="italic">Balsamodendron.</hi> The difference between African
                    and Arabian myrrh was known to the ancients, who considered the Troglodyte or
                    African myrrh the best. At Bombay this difference is still recognized. Specimens
                    of the Arabian myrrh tree collected by Wykeham Perry in 1878 were less spinous
                    than those of the Somali plant, but were too imperfect to determine if they
                    belonged to a distinct species. <hi rend="italic">Balsamodendron Kua,</hi> R.
                    Br., a small spiny Abyssinian species allied to <hi rend="italic">B.
                    Myrrha,</hi> as yet undescribed, was found by Salt to yield myrrh.</p>
                <p>Myrrh is usually imported in chests containing from one to two cwt., and is mixed
                    with other gum-resins obtained from different species of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Balsamodendron.</hi> The principal of these are subjoined.</p>
                <p>(1) <hi rend="italic">Baisa Bol,</hi><hi rend="italic">Bhesa</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Bol,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Bissa Bol,</hi> probably the
                    produce of <hi rend="italic">Balsamodendron Kataf,</hi> Kunth, a tree which is
                    known to the Somalis as <hi rend="italic">hebbdkhade,</hi> and which has much
                    larger leaves than the myrrh tree. This gum-resin resembles myrrh in appearance,
                    but has a disagreeable taste and is scarcely bitter. At Aden bissa bol is worth
                    only 21 rupees per maund (28 δ&gt;), while myrrh sells for 9∣ rupees per maund.
                    It is used in China, mixed with food, to give to milch cows to improve the
                    quality and increase the quantity of milk, and when mixed with lime as a size to
                    impart a gloss to walls. (2) Opaque bdellium, probably identical with the gum
                    hotai described by Vaughan <hi rend="italic">(loc. cit.),</hi> and produced by
                    <hi rend="italic">B. Playfairii.</hi> When shaken with water it forms a slight
                    but permanent lather, and on this account is used by the Somali women for
                    cleansing their hair and by the men to whiten their shields. It is known as <hi
                    rend="italic">meena hdrma</hi> in Bombay, and is there used for the extraction
                    of the guinea-worm. (3) African bdellium is the produce of <hi rend="italic">B.
                    africanum,</hi> and is probably the tree described by Adanson as <hi
                    rend="italic">Nistoutt.</hi> The last two gum-resins are without the white
                    streaks which are characteristic of myrrh and bissa bol; the former presents an
                    opaque and the latter a resinous appearance, both being acrid, but having
                    scarcely any bitterness or aroma. (4) Indian bdellium, probably identical with
                    the Indian drug googul obtained in Scinde and Baluchistân from <hi rend="italic"
                    >Balsamodendron Mukul</hi> and <hi rend="italic">B. pubescens,</hi> Hook, has an
                    acrid taste, an odour resembling cedar-wood, and softens in the hand. It is
                    probably the produce of <hi rend="italic">B. Mukul</hi> which has recently been
                    found by Balfour in Socotra.</p>
                <p>As met with in commerce true myrrh occurs in pieces of irregular size and shape,
                    from half an inch to 2 or 3 inches in diameter, and of a reddish-brown colour.
                    The transverse fracture has a resinous appearance with white streaks; the
                    flavour is bitter and aromatic and the odour characteristic. It consists of a
                    mixture of resin, gum, and essential oil in varying proportions from 23 to 44
                    per cent., the resin being present in good specimens to the extent of 27 per
                    cent., and the oil from f to 3 per cent. The resin appears to be a complex body,
                    partly soluble in ether and partly in bisulphide of carbon. The gum is soluble
                    in water and forms an adhesive mucilage. The odour of myrrh is due to the
                    volatile oil, which is heavier than water. The bitterness is believed to be due
                    to a glucoside, the chemical constitution of which has not been ascertained. It
                    is obtained by treating with warm water the resin extracted by means of
                    alcohol.</p>
                <p>Myrrh is used in medicine at present chiefly as an auxiliary to other drugs, such
                    as iron and aloes, in order to strengthen and modify their action. It appears to
                    have a special action on the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n133/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0133-0122"/> mucous membrane, improving the quality of its
                    secretions and diminishing them in quantity when excessive. When taken
                    internally it produces a sensation of warmth extending over the whole abdomen.
                    The appetite is increased and the digestive process much facilitated, especially
                    in cases in which there is weakness and torpidity of the intestinal canal. As an
                    emmenagogue it is found especially useful where pulmonary complications exist.
                    The tincture diluted with water is used as an application to spongy gums and the
                    aphthous sore mouth of children.</p>
                <p>The Hebrew <hi rend="italic">I6t,</hi> erroneously translated myrrh in Genesis
                    xxxvii. 25; xliii. 11 (Sept, <hi rend="italic">στακτή</hi>; Vulg. <hi
                    rend="italic">stacte),</hi> is generally identified with <hi rend="italic"
                    >ladanum</hi> (vol. xii. p. 718), which has been used as a medicine and perfume
                    from the earliest times,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Celsus, <hi rend="italic">Hierobot.</hi> i. 280-286; Herod., iii.112;
                    Dioscorides, p. 128.</p></note> and is still an article of commerce in Turkey.
                    An excellent account of the mode of collecting it is given by Tournefort <hi
                    rend="italic">(Voyage,</hi> i. 79).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography. —</hi> Forskâl, <hi rend="italic">Fl.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Aegypt.</hi><hi rend="italic">Arab.,</hi> p. 80; Nees, <hi
                    rend="italic">Beschreib.</hi><hi rend="italic">0fficin.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Pflanzen,</hi> p. 357, 1829; Marchand, <hi rend="italic">Adansonia,</hi> vii.
                    p. 258; <hi rend="italic">Pharmacographia,</hi> 2d ed., pp. 140-146; Bentley and
                    Trimen, <hi rend="italic">Medicinal Plants,</hi> p. 60; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pharmaceutical Journal,</hi> (1), xii. pp. 226, 227; (3), vi. p. 661; (3), ix.
                    p. 893; (3), x. pp. 80-84; xi. pp. 41, 42; Cooke, <hi rend="italic">Report on
                    Gum-Resins in the India Museum,</hi> 1874, p. 72; Hildebrandt in <hi
                    rend="italic">Sitzungsbericht</hi><hi rend="italic">d. Gesellsch.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">naturforsch. Freunde,</hi> Berlin, November 1878, p. 196. (E. Μ.
                    H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
