<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0135-0124-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MYSTERIES (9th edition, volume 17, page 124)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bv79x75">Coras</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45v4z">Hymns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vj0c">Ritual</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44x54q60">Ritualism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1062222">Phrygians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:965486">Hymns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:841533">Bulls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098241">Ritual</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098260">Ritualization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n135/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MYSTERIES</label>. This name was applied to certain
                    ceremonies in Greek religion which were esteemed peculiarly sacred and might not
                    be freely spoken about. The subject is one of great difficulty on account of the
                    absolute silence maintained with regard to it by many writers, and the guarded
                    terms in which the few references to it are couched. The obligation to silence
                    was not felt by the Christian writers, and it is to them that we owe most of our
                    knowledge. Their testimony is of doubtful value, and it has been keenly debated
                    whether any trust can be placed in it; but it is in such perfect accord with the
                    few references in pagan authors that this scepticism is unjustifiable. The
                    Christian writers on whom we have to depend were arguing against pagan
                    opponents, and their arguments would have lost all force if it had been possible
                    to retort that the descriptions and facts were inaccurate. The Mysteries were
                    the chief stronghold of those pagan controversialists who maintained that all
                    the truths and the morality advocated by the Christian writers were contained in
                    the Greek religion, and therefore the Christians directed their arguments
                    chiefly against this strongest part of their opponents’ case. It results from a
                    study of the evidence that, on the whole, they stated the case in favour of the
                    Mysteries with much clearness and fairness, admitting the good points, but
                    directing their polemic against the weak side.</p>
                <p>Of the many Mysteries which existed in different parts of Greece, the Eleusinian
                    were the most famous, the most widely popular, the most representative in every
                    way. In several parts of Greece— <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> at Phlius—there
                    were Mysteries directly adopted from Eleusis; in other places, such as Lerna,
                    Andania, &amp;c., a genuine old mystic cultus was greatly modified by the same
                    example.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The contrast
                    between the account given by Pausanias of the Mysteries of Andania in the 2d
                    century after Christ and the account given in the great inscription 91 B.c.
                    shows how the example of Eleusis had worked in the interval.</p></note> The
                    Christian writers therefore direct their polemic mainly against the Eleusinian
                    Mysteries, and the material for study is far less scanty in their case than in
                    any other. The following remarks, accordingly, will be almost entirely confined
                    to them. Any discussion of the subject must be founded on Lobeck’s great work
                    <hi rend="italic">Aglaophamus</hi> (1829), in which, with equal learning and
                    acuteness, he destroyed once for all the <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi>
                    theories current before his time, that the Mysteries enshrined a primitive
                    revelation of divine truth made to mankind, or contained a philosophic doctrine
                    borrowed by the Greeks from the wisdom of the East and handed down unmodified
                    from generation to generation.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The chief older theories of the Mysteries were those of
                    Warburton, St Croix, and Creuzer.</p></note> As a constructive work, Lobeck’s
                    treatise is not so perfect. What we are in search of is not so much the
                    objective facts of the Mysteries as the place which they held in the Greek mind.
                    The effect of a religious institution like the Mysteries depends chiefly on
                    subjective considerations; actions and rites in themselves quite commonplace may
                    bear to the eye of faith the most sacred and impressive character. This point of
                    view is not taken into account by Lobeck. Again, the polemical character
                    detracts from the value of his work as a final statement of the question; he is
                    sometimes satisfied with proving that ancient evidence does not bear out the
                    theories which he combats, but he does not estimate duly its actual worth.
                    Finally, additional evidence has been accumulated since his time; inscriptions
                    and works of art have afforded important corroborative evidence, and it is
                    certain that statements which Lobeck set aside as not referring to the
                    Eleusinian religion do really relate to it.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The principal special authorities on the Mysteries since
                    Lobeck are :—Sauppe, <hi rend="italic">Mystericninschr. von Andania</hi>;
                    Foucart ’ s commentary on this inscription in Le Bas, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Voyage</hi><hi rend="italic">Archéol.</hi> (1847-77), <hi rend="italic">Inscr.
                    de la Pdoponn.;</hi> Foucart, “Inscr. d’Eleus.” in <hi rend="italic">Bull. Corr.
                    Hell.,</hi> 1880; id., <hi rend="italic">Associations Relig.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">chez les Grecs</hi>; C. Lenormant in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mêm.</hi><hi rend="italic">de l</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Acad. d'Inscr.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">de Belles</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Lettres,</hi> xxiv. 343; Guignaut, “Myst. de Cer. et de Pros.,” <hi
                    rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> xxi. 68; K. O. Μ tiller in Erseh and Gruber’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Ally. Encyk.,</hi> art. ‘Eleusinia ;” id. in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Orchomenos,</hi> p. 453; Preller in Pauli’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Realencyklop.,</hi> arts. “Eleusinia,” “Mysteria,” “Orpheus,”—the best
                    statement of the subject; id., <hi rend="italic">Demet.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >und</hi><hi rend="italic">Perseph.;</hi> Gerhard, <hi rend="italic">Gτiech.
                    Mysterienbilder</hi>; id., <hi rend="italic">Ueber d.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Bilderkreis</hi><hi rend="italic">von El.</hi> (1863-65); Stephani in <hi
                    rend="italic">Compte</hi><hi rend="italic">Rendu,</hi> St Petersb., 1859;
                    Millingen in <hi rend="italic">Annali</hi><hi rend="italic">Inst. Arch.,</hi>
                    vol. XV.; A. Mommsen, <hi rend="italic">Heortologie</hi> (1864); F. Lenormant,
                    <hi rend="italic">Réch. Archéol. à</hi><hi rend="italic">El.;</hi> id., <hi
                    rend="italic">La Voie Sacrée</hi><hi rend="italic">Eleus.;</hi> id., “Eleus.
                    Myst.” in <hi rend="italic">Nineteenth Century,</hi> 1881, May, July,
                    September.</p></note></p>
                <p>There is no ancient authority to show that the ritual of the Mysteries differed
                    essentially from that of the general religion of Greece. All ancient testimony
                    tends to prove that the ritual was based on religious myths, similar to those
                    which were common in Greece, and that the difference between mystic and exoteric
                    rites lay chiefly in the accompaniments. Athenaeus<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Athen., ii. p. 40 D.</p></note> says that the
                    Mysteries were distinguished from the ordinary festivals by their peculiar
                    magnificence and expense, and by the “mystic paradosis” which took place at
                    them, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> certain sacred things were exposed in a
                    peculiarly impressive manner to the worship of the participants. Their
                    magnificence must have been very great. Painting, sculpture, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n136/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0136-0125"/> architecture, music, dancing, &lt;fcc., were
                    combined with lavish skill to form one grand and impressive spectacle. Other
                    great festivals were displays of Attic splendour, but the Mysteries were
                    intended, in the Periclean scheme, to be the great religious ceremony of all
                    Greece; the allies were required, and the other Greeks requested, to pay homage
                    and first-fruits to the two goddesses of Eleusis.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Inscription published by Foucart in <hi
                    rend="italic">Bull. Corr. Hell.,</hi> 1880.</p></note></p>
                <p>The strictest secrecy was enjoined and observed in regard to the Mysteries and
                    everything connected with them; but this secrecy was not that of a narrow cult,
                    confined to a small number of participants. The Eleusinian Mysteries were open
                    as early as the time of Herodotus to any of the Greeks who wished to be
                    initiated.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Herod., viii.
                    65. It was an accusation against Socrates that he alone of all the Athenians had
                    not been initiated, Lucian, <hi rend="italic">Dem.,</hi> ix. 237; Lobeck, p.
                    21.</p></note> There was, therefore, no secret to keep inviolate from the
                    uninitiated. Just as in the actual representation of the Mysteries a silence so
                    strict as to be proverbial<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Philostr., <hi rend="italic">Vit.</hi><hi rend="italic">ApoU.,∖,</hi> 15,
                    17, <hi rend="italic">ωσιrεp</hi><hi rend="italic">êv</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >μύστη</hi><hi rend="italic">plots</hi><hi rend="italic">Ισιώπων,</hi> &amp;c.;
                    see Lobeck, p. 67.</p></note> was maintained, so it was a condition of their
                    good effect that they should not hereafter be lightly spoken of.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Strab., p. 357, ⅞ <hi
                    rend="italic">κρυψιs</hi><hi rend="italic">ή μυστική</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >σeμvoπoιel</hi><hi rend="italic">το θειον.</hi></p></note> Those who believed
                    in the Mysteries kept in their heart, as a saving and sacred possession, the
                    knowledge of what they had seen and heard and kissed and handled; the thought
                    was too holy to be rashly spoken of, even to the initiated.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Macrob., <hi rend="italic">Sat.,</hi> i. 18,
                    236; Lobeck, p. 135.</p></note> Numerous references prove that this mystic
                    silence was generally very carefully observed. In the poets we sometimes find an
                    affectation of observing silence about myths which are quite common property;
                    and writers of religious or superstitious character frequently make a mystic
                    secret of matters that less scrupulous writers speak freely about.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Theocr., iii. 50, and many
                    passages in Herod, and Paus.</p></note> The degree to which silence was observed
                    depended entirely on the individual conscience, and the fact that it was in
                    general so strictly maintained is the best proof of the vitality and power of
                    the Mysteries over the popular mind.</p>
                <p>The saving and healthy effect of the Eleusinian Mysteries was believed in not
                    only by the mass of the people but by many of the most thoughtful and educated
                    intellects, Pindar, Sophocles, Isocrates, Plutarch, &lt;fcc.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Pind.,∕r. 102; Soph.,∕r. 719,
                    D&lt;lf.; Isocr., <hi rend="italic">Pan.,</hi> vi. p. 59, § 28; Crinagoras in
                    Jac., <hi rend="italic">Anthol.,</hi> ii. 332; Cic., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Legg.,</hi> ii. 14; Lobeck, § 11.</p></note> Plato, who finds no language too
                    strong to stigmatize the demoralizing effect of the Orphic Mysteries, speaks of
                    the Eleusinia with great respect; he compares the contemplation of the “ideas”
                    by the disembodied souls to the contemplation of the “phasmata”<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plat., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Phsedr.,</hi> p. 250, <hi rend="italic">Epin.,</hi> p. 986.</p></note> revealed
                    in the Mysteries. This saving power is expressly connected with the future life;
                    he that has been initiated has learned what will ensure his happiness hereafter.
                    This point, which is ridiculed by Lobeck (pp. 70-1), must be examined carefully.
                    The words of Pindar, Sophocles, Isocrates agree with the words of the Homeric
                    <hi rend="italic">Hym,n</hi> (1. 480) that the initiated have peculiar
                    advantages in the future world, and many other passages are equally clear and
                    distinct. Lobeck maintains that they have no special meaning, inasmuch as
                    Isocrates says the same about all men who live an upright life.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Isocr., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Symmach.,</hi> xii. 266.</p></note> This argument misses the most important
                    religious question with regard to the subject,—Is the salvation in the future
                    life, which is assured by initiation, attained by mere ritualistic observances,
                    or does it depend on the effect produced by initiation on the life and character
                    of the initiated person <hi rend="italic">1</hi> Plato condemns in the strongest
                    terms the Orphic Mysteries, which promise salvation in return for mere
                    ritualistic acts of purification and initiation; if he respects the Eleusinian
                    Mysteries, which also promise salvation as the reward of initiation, this can be
                    only because he believes that they promise it on different grounds. The reason
                    is explained by Isocrates, who expressly says that this salvation in the future
                    life, the reward of the initiated, is gained by all who live a pious and just
                    life. In like manner, Diodorus says that the initiated are said to grow better;
                    and Andocides makes a similar remark about the object of the Mysteries.
                    According to Sopater, initiation establishes a kinship of the soul with the
                    divine nature; and Theon Smyrnaeus says that the final stage of initiation is
                    the state of bliss and divine favour which results from it.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Diod. Sic., <hi rend="italic">Hist.,</hi> v.
                    48; Andoc., <hi rend="italic">De Myst.,</hi> § 31; Sopat., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Diaer.</hi><hi rend="italic">Zetem.,</hi> p. 120, in Walz, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Rhet.</hi><hi rend="italic">Graec.</hi>; Theon Smyrn., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Afatħem.,</hi> i. p. 18, ed. Bull; see Lobeck, pp. 39, 189.</p></note></p>
                <p>These quotations prove the general belief that the aim of the Eleusinian
                    Mysteries was high, and that a lasting effect was produced by them on the
                    initiated. This implies a high stage of religious thought, such as no other
                    ancient faith, except that of the Hebrews, attained; but a.passage in a Rhodian
                    inscription of the 5th century B.c. shows that this idea was not wholly
                    unfamiliar in Greek religion. The first and most important condition required of
                    those who would enter the temple at Lindus is that they be pure in heart, and
                    not conscious of any crime; conditions of ceremonial purity are enumerated as
                    secondary matters.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Inscription quoted by Foucart in <hi rend="italic">Inscr. de la
                    Peloponn.,</hi> p. 171, in Le Bas, <hi rend="italic">Voy.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Archéol.</hi></p></note> Now, with regard to the profanation of the Mysteries
                    by those persons who ridiculed them, it is easy to understand that the very
                    simple character of the rites, the commonplace nature of the sacred things which
                    were exposed as the crowning ceremony of the Mysteries to the adoration of the
                    people, lent themselves readily to ridicule when contrasted with the solemn
                    preparations that led up to the crowning act, and the great effects that were
                    expected from the initiation. The people who had been initiated, who believed in
                    the salutary effect of the admission to handle and kiss the sacred objects, were
                    naturally both shocked and indignant at the ridicule thus cast on their holy
                    sacrament by the pitiless analysis of a cold disbelieving intellect. They felt
                    that more than met the eye existed in these sacred things. The Mysteries
                    occupied a place among the ancients analogous to that of the Holy Sacrament in
                    the Christian church. The intention was to admit all that were not notoriously
                    wicked; the disqualifying crime was unexpiated murder. The belief was
                    entertained that the solemnity and impressiveness of the ceremony tended to
                    produce a strong effect on the character of the initiated.</p>
                <p>There is overwhelming proof in ancient writers that the effect of the Mysteries
                    was not dependent on any dogmatic instruction. Even the doctrine of a future
                    life, which is always associated in the old writers with the Mysteries, was not
                    expressly inculcated in them, but left to the spectators to gather for
                    themselves from the spectacle presented to them.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Lobeck, §§ 216-19.</p></note> On the other
                    hand, ancient testimony shows a striking unanimity in describing the manner in
                    which the Mysteries were believed to educate the people. One of the most
                    important passages is that where Galen maintains that the study of nature, if
                    prosecuted with the concentrated attention given to the Mysteries, is even more
                    fitted than they are to reveal the power and wisdom of God, inasmuch as these
                    truths are more obscurely expressed in the Mysteries than in nature. Plato
                    compares the contemplation of the “ideas” with that of the Mysteries; Chrysippus
                    calls the discussion on the nature of the gods, which forms the last section of
                    the Stoic physic, τcλeπp<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Lobeck, §§ 19-20.</p></note> From <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n137/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0137-0126"/> these passages we may infer the belief of the
                    writers that important truths were enigmatically<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The word “enigma” is used by Sopater, <hi
                    rend="italic">Diaer.</hi><hi rend="italic">Zetem,.,</hi> p. 120; Clem. Alex.,
                    <hi rend="italic">Strom.,</hi> p. 658, and Christian writers frequently; Lobeck,
                    pp. 143, 189.</p></note> expressed in the Mysteries, and that the intellect
                    which could penetrate beneath the surface was able to apprehend them. Plutarch
                    says that it required a philosophic training and a reverent religious frame of
                    mind to comprehend the Mysteries. Similarly Aristotle expressly says that no
                    instruction was given to the <hi rend="italic">μvστaι,</hi> but that, while in a
                    suitable state of receptivity, their emotions and character were acted upon. The
                    testimony of the Christian writers is entirely to the same effect; while
                    stigmatizing the impure character of some of the rites, they always admit that
                    the Mysteries were intended to lead the people up to a knowledge of religious
                    truth.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plut., <hi
                    rend="italic">Isid.,</hi> Ixviii.; Aristot. ap. Synes., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Or.,</hi> p. 48 (ed. Petav.); Cic., Λ <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi>. <hi
                    rend="italic">D.,</hi> i. 42, is important, <hi rend="italic">rerum magis natura
                    cognoscitur quam deorum.</hi></p></note> It is obvious that the essential point
                    on which the effect of the ceremony depended was that the mind of the initiated
                    should be wrought up to a pitch of eager, rapt expectancy and breathless
                    attention. The attentive silence of the spectators at the Mysteries was
                    proverbial. Many means contributed to produce this state. A certain amount of
                    previous training and instruction was imparted by the <hi rend="italic"
                    >μvστaγωγoi</hi> to the candidates. It is true that all who had been initiated
                    had the right to act as <hi rend="italic">μυστaγωγoi,</hi> that they were left
                    legally free to introduce any one whom they thought fit, that the amount of
                    instruction they could impart varied according to their character and education.
                    Lobeck has emphasized all these elements which tended to impair the character
                    and lessen the effect of the Mysteries. But though this point is incapable of
                    proof, the general character of the Mysteries suggests that custom may have
                    modified to some degree the freedom allowed by law, and that the Eleusinian
                    officials tried to regulate the instruction given. Moreover, the lesser
                    Mysteries were a kind of preparation for the greater, and Clement mentions that
                    in them, and in them alone, a certain amount of instruction was given to the
                    ∕zυcrτ&lt;χι.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>CI. Alex.,
                    <hi rend="italic">Strom.,</hi> v. 689; Lobeck, p. 140.</p></note> These
                    circumstances combined with the general belief of the people in the holiness and
                    power of the Mysteries to produce in the mind of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >μv&lt;rτ&lt;u</hi> an expectant feeling and a disposition to look for some
                    meaning in the spectacle.</p>
                <p>The grades of admission to the Mysteries tended to produce the same impression.
                    The process of initiation was not a momentary one, completed in one act; it
                    extended over an elaborate series of stages, and the ancients certainly
                    associated these successive steps with a gradual increase of knowledge and
                    insight. The candidate was initiated in the lesser Mysteries in Anthesterion
                    (February) at Athens; he was admitted as a <hi rend="italic">μv&lt;rτης</hi> at
                    Eleusis in the following Boedromion (September), but he could not attain the
                    higher initiation as <hi rend="italic">επόπτης</hi> till at least one year more
                    had elapsed. It was also believed that a higher order of initiation was reserved
                    for those who were qualified.for the offices of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ιεροφάντης</hi> and δpδoυχos, in which the last knowledge of the cultus was
                    imparted to them.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Theon
                    Smyrn., <hi rend="italic">Mathern.,</hi> i. p. 18, quoted by Lobeck, p.
                    39.</p></note></p>
                <p>Finally, the physical circumstances of the initiation were such as to produce an
                    excited and high-strung nervous condition. The nine days’ fast, very strictly
                    observed,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>It is nowhere
                    mentioned that the <hi rend="italic">μύστου.</hi> fasted nine days, but the
                    analogy of the nine days’ fast of Demeter makes it quite safe to assume that
                    this was the rule for her worshippers; see <hi rend="italic">Hymn,</hi> 1. 47-9.
                    The fast was perhaps, like the Mohammedan Ramadan, observed only while the sun
                    was up; but, in addition to this, various kinds of food were wholly prohibited,
                    see Lobeck, pp. 189-91.</p></note> the long march from Athens to Eleusis and the
                    frequent religious ceremonies with which it was marked, the wandering by night
                    around the shores and plain of Eleusis with torches in search of the lost
                    Cora,—all tended to produce a strained enthusiastic state. And the season of the
                    year and of the month—for the nights were dark—co-operated; Boedromion fell
                    about the end of the hot season, when the bodily strength is usually low. Then
                    came the actual Mysteries: the <hi rend="italic">μυστaε</hi> were admitted to
                    the holy building; the splendid illumination seemed dazzlingly bright after the
                    darkness outside; the strange apparitions, the impressive voices, the gorgeous
                    dresses of the actors, the magnificence of the sacred drama, to which the highly
                    suggestive and symbolic art of Greece no doubt contributed largely,—all these
                    they saw and heard in awestruck silence. Then came the crowning act of the
                    ceremony: they had perhaps before this drunk the sacred draught with which the
                    goddess had refreshed herself after her long fast, but now the holy things which
                    the goddess had herself shown to the daughters of Celeus were revealed to them.
                    They were admitted one by one to touch, to kiss the holy things, to lift them
                    from the cist, to put them into the basket, to taste them, to replace them in
                    the cist, and to pronounce the sacred formula. The scene that takes place in
                    every modern Greek church on the eve of Easter Sunday gives some faint idea of
                    the character of this <hi rend="italic">παράδοσις.</hi></p>
                <p>This state of enthusiasm was common to all Mysteries, especially to the Phrygian.
                    It was susceptible of great abuses, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> the
                    self-mutilation and the immorality of the Phrygian rites. But the spirit of
                    Hellenism toned down the excesses, while it tried to preserve the fervour and
                    self-forgetfulness of the Phrygian and Bacchic orgies. The relation of the state
                    to the Mysteries contributed to regulate the excited fervour of the celebrants.
                    While it never interfered with the established ritual, the state was the last
                    judge in cases of misdemeanour; it appointed officials to control the
                    expenditure and conduct the public part of the ceremony. Inscriptions<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See the inscription of
                    Andania, and the important inscription of Eleusis published in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bull. Corr. Hdl.,</hi> 1880.</p></note> have thrown much light on this point,
                    but it is not possible here to dwell on it. The Mysteries of Eleusis were the
                    one great attempt made by the Hellenic genius to construct for itself a religion
                    that should keep pace with the growth of thought and civilization in Greece. The
                    strained enthusiasm attendant upon them seems at first strange and unhellenic to
                    a mind accustomed to the moderated chastened tone of Greek art and literature,
                    and to the spectacular character of Greek exoteric religion with its utter want
                    of vitality and religious fervour. The public religion either became, like the
                    Panathenaia, a purely political display of the power and splendour of Athens, or
                    else, like much of the old ceremonial of the acropolis, was performed
                    perfunctorily. It had no hold on the mind of the people; its simple antique
                    ceremonies told nothing of the subjects which troubled men’s minds, the thoughts
                    of sin, of a future life, and of punishment for guilt. But the Mysteries
                    concerned themselves precisely with these subjects: they provided a series of
                    preliminary purifications for their votaries; they turned men’s minds to the
                    deeper problems of life and death, and gave them new views; they made some
                    attempt to reach and touch the individual mind. Thus, while the public Hellenic
                    religion sank into disrepute, the Mysteries became more and more important as
                    time elapsed.</p>
                <p>It is impossible to reconstruct the mystic ceremonial, but sufficient indications
                    are given for us to understand its general character. It consisted of acts and
                    words, <hi rend="italic">όρώμενσ.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">λεγόμενο.,</hi>
                    which supplemented one another, and were both required to make an intelligible
                    whole.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The case of the
                    young man in Sopater’s imaginary trial proves this very clearly.</p></note></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n138/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0138-0127"/>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">λεγάμενα</hi> were obscurely-worded phrases and traditional
                    songs, whose sanctity was due to their antiquity. They had no didactic
                    character, and were hardly intelligible without preparatory instruction. They
                    were chanted by the hierophant, and that a fine voice was one of the requisites
                    for this office several epigrams and inscriptions bear witness. The mythic
                    ancestor of the family, in whom are embodied the requirements for the office,
                    was called Eumolpus. The <hi rend="italic">8pωμεva</hi> appear to have been a
                    dramatic representation of the life of the deities by whom the Mysteries had
                    been instituted. These deities were presented on the stage in appropriate
                    dresses, the parts being played by the ministers of the cultus. At Andania this
                    is known to have been the case,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See 1. 24, όσα <hi rend="italic">ôè</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >δει διασκευάζεσθαι</hi><hi rend="italic">els</hi><hi rend="italic">θεών
                    διάθεσιν,</hi> with Sauppe’s and Foucart’s commentaries.</p></note> and Porphyry
                    enumerates the parts played by the chief officials of Eleusis at one point in
                    the mystic drama.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Ap.
                    Euseb., <hi rend="italic">Prsep. Ewing.,</hi> iii. 12, p. 117.</p></note> It is
                    also certain that figures, probably of great size, were introduced by machinery.
                    The terms <hi rend="italic">φάσματα άγια,</hi><hi rend="italic">eυ8ai-
                    μova,</hi><hi rend="italic">θεία, άρρητα,</hi> are applied to the mystic
                    sights.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Themist., <hi
                    rend="italic">Or.,</hi> xvi. p. 244, <hi rend="italic">τηv elpηvηv εlσηyev ωσπεp
                    lv</hi><hi rend="italic">τελετή άψοφητί</hi><hi rend="italic">κal
                    dπρayμδvωs</hi>; Stob., <hi rend="italic">Serm.,</hi> cxix. p. 604; Aristid.,
                    <hi rend="italic">Or.,</hi> xix. 416, &amp;c.</p></note></p>
                <p>The Homeric <hi rend="italic">Hymn</hi> to Demeter is a religious, not an
                    historical myth. It does not relate the origin of agriculture, for the gift with
                    which the goddess rewards her Eleusinian hosts is not the art of agriculture but
                    the knowledge of the Mysteries (1. 273, 474). It springs directly from the
                    cultus of Eleusis, and contains the iepos λόγο?, the fortunes of the two
                    goddesses, mother and daughter, the periodical representation of which formed
                    the basis of the ritual. It is, of course, not a complete description of the
                    ritual; it is an exoteric and poetic statement, in which the most holy of the
                    rites and the most mysterious of the personages are alluded to only in an
                    indirect way. The express statement of Clement,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Cl. Alex., <hi rend="italic">Protrept.,</hi>
                    ii. p. 12.</p></note> that the whole myth of Cora was represented at Eleusis,
                    confirms the inference drawn from the <hi rend="italic">Hymn.</hi> Many
                    writers<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Themist,, <hi
                    rend="italic">Or.,</hi> xx. p. 235 (p. 288, ed. Dind.); Lobeck, p. 52; Claudian,
                    <hi rend="italic">De Rapt. Proserp.,</hi> 1. 5-15; Lucian, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Catapl.,</hi> 22; Plut. ap. Stob., <hi rend="italic">Serai.</hi>, cxix. p. 604,
                    and Plut., <hi rend="italic">Prof. Virt. Sent.,</hi> i. p. 312 (ed.
                    Wytt).</p></note> refer to the appearance presented by the shores and bay of
                    Eleusis on the <hi rend="italic">dies</hi><hi rend="italic">lampadum,</hi> when
                    the worshippers wandered in the darkness with torches searching for the lost
                    Cora. This ceremony took place in the open country, and was therefore not a part
                    of the mystic ritual revealed to the <hi rend="italic">μvστaι</hi> in the <hi
                    rend="italic">τελεστηpιov.</hi> It probably took place on Boedromion 21, on the
                    night before the mystic rites proper began. The <hi rend="italic">μvστaι</hi>
                    waited outside the sacred enclosure in perfect darkness on the moonless eve of
                    Boedromion 22. Suddenly the τrpoτrυλαια were thrown open, and the light was seen
                    streaming through the <hi rend="italic">oπaιov</hi> in the roof of the <hi
                    rend="italic">τελεστηpιov</hi> and through the open door in which stood the
                    δαδούχος holding up the sacred torches. This scene is frequently alluded
                    to.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Ar., <hi
                    rend="italic">Ran.,</hi> 340-52; Soph., <hi rend="italic">Oed. Col.,</hi> 1045;
                    Eur., <hi rend="italic">Ion,</hi> 1075 <hi rend="italic">sg.;</hi> Aesch., <hi
                    rend="italic">Fragm.,</hi> quoted by schol. on Soph., l.c., &amp;c.</p></note>
                    The scenes inside the <hi rend="italic">τελεστηpιov</hi> are mentioned less
                    frequently,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Procl. on
                    Plat., <hi rend="italic">Polit.,</hi> p. 384, <hi rend="italic">aιrτηs τηs
                    μεylστηs θeas</hi><hi rend="italic">ιερούς</hi><hi rend="italic">rivas</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">εv aπopρr</hi><hi rend="italic">τoιs θpτf</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >voυs al τeλeτal</hi><hi rend="italic">παραδιδοΰσι</hi>; Apollod. ap. schol.
                    Theocr., ii. 36, <hi rend="italic">'λθfyτ</hi><hi rend="italic">σι</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">τον Ιεροφάντην</hi><hi rend="italic">τηs ^Kdpηs</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">επικαλούμενης επικρούειν τδ καλού μεν ον ήχεϊον</hi>; Hecate
                    appeared on the stage <hi rend="italic">{Hymn,</hi> 1. 52); Claud., <hi
                    rend="italic">Rapt. Pros.,</hi> 15; Helios and Hermes <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Hymn,</hi> 1. 74, 346) both appeared on the stage, see note 2
                    above.</p></note> but the few references point to episodes in the myth of
                    Demeter and Cora. The hymn refers in guarded terms to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >παρά8οσις</hi><hi rend="italic">τG&gt;v lepωv,</hi> the central act of the
                    mystic ritual. Clement enumerates the simple objects that were displayed, and
                    gives the formula in which each <hi rend="italic">μύστης</hi> replied as he
                    received from the hierophant the holy objects: “I have fasted, and I have drunk
                    the <hi rend="italic">κvκεωv</hi>; I have taken from the <hi rend="italic"
                    >κιστη;</hi> after tasting I have deposited in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >κάλαθος,</hi> and from the <hi rend="italic">κάλαθος</hi> in the <hi
                    rend="italic">κίστη.”</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">Protrept.,</hi> p. 18; Arnob., v. 26, “quae rogati
                    sacrorum in acceptionibus respondeant.”</p></note> In these words he professed
                    that he had fulfilled the sacred duties.</p>
                <p>This whole myth bears most evidently the character of having been acted
                    continuously at one time. It could not have been divided without losing its
                    power over the attention and emotions of the <hi rend="italic">μvστat,</hi> But
                    it seems almost certain that there were two nights of mystic ceremonial, 22 and
                    23 Boedromion.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Mommsen
                    and Lenormant have given several reasons to think that there were two nights of
                    Mysteries.</p></note> It is probable, therefore, that another play with a
                    distinct subject was acted on one of these nights, and as the play just
                    described is certainly the original and central point in the Eleusinian ritual
                    it was probably acted on the first night. Again, it is certain that there was a
                    distinction between <hi rend="italic">μvστaι</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >επoπτai</hi> at Eleusis. As the <hi rend="italic">μύσται</hi> were not admitted
                    to witness the ritual of <hi rend="italic">επoφις,</hi> it is highly probable
                    that the second night was devoted to the higher ceremonial. It would be
                    exceedingly difficult to effect a change in the middle of the night from the <hi
                    rend="italic">μvησις</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">επoψις,</hi> and the good
                    order and regularity for which the Eleusinia were famed could hardly have been
                    maintained. The <hi rend="italic">Hymn</hi> refers in covert terms to the holy
                    child Iacchus, to his death and resurrection (262-4). There seems no place for
                    Iacchus in the ritual as yet described. It is therefore a plausible conjecture
                    that the <hi rend="italic">ετroφις</hi> was devoted more especially to the
                    mystic child; and further examination will make this conjecture almost a
                    certainty.</p>
                <p>The development of the Eleusinian religion is a matter of speculation, but cannot
                    be wholly passed over. Several elements must be distinguished.</p>
                <p>1. Demeter always represents the productive and nourishing power of the earth,
                    (a) In the simplest form of her cultus the act by which the earth-goddess is
                    fertilized is conceived as an outrage and a deed of violence. The goddess,
                    enraged, hides herself in a cave; winter and death reign in the world. At last
                    she is appeased; she bathes in the sacred stream; her child is born, and the
                    life of spring blooms on the earth. This cultus is most distinctly seen in
                    Arcadia. (&amp;) The worship of Demeter Thesmophorus is the religion of a more
                    educated race; the goddess is the giver of all law, especially of the law of
                    marriage, on which all society is founded. The worship of Demeter Thesmophorus
                    is restricted more or less completely to women. It appears to have been the
                    national religion of the Cadmeones, and the house of Cadmus at Thebes was the
                    first temple of the goddess; but it spread early into Attica. The Argolic
                    Demeter is very similar, but her cultus has been affected by Eleusinian
                    influence. The Thesmophoric rites are so obscure that no sure idea can be gained
                    of the relation between them and the simpler Arcadian cultus. The anger of
                    Demeter Achea or Achaia formed part of them, and the ritual has, as A. Mommsen
                    observes,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Heortol.,</hi> under “Thesmophoria”; cf. Plut., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Solon,</hi> 12.</p></note> an Oriental character of vehement mourning; but we
                    know not how the wrath of the goddess was kindled and allayed, how the
                    alternation of winter and summer was conceived, (c) Eleusis was apparently the
                    original seat of a modified form of this cultus, in which Demeter was associated
                    with Cora. The modification perhaps arose through the fusion of the religions of
                    two races which united in the fertile Eleusinian plain.</p>
                <p>2. The marriage of Cora is a form of the widespread idea that the marriage of the
                    god and goddess each spring is the pledge and cause of the fertility of earth.
                    The “holy marriage” was celebrated in Samos, Argos, &amp;c., with the rites of
                    an earthly marriage, and vestiges of the primitive custom of marriage by capture
                    can be traced in the ceremony. According to the <hi rend="italic">ιeρδs
                    λδyos</hi> of Eleusis, the rape of Cora takes place in the spring <hi
                    rend="italic">{Hymn,</hi> 1. 6, 425); it is the holy marriage by capture. But
                    the Eleusinian myth is marked as composite and not original by an important
                    fact; it does not explain the vicissitude of winter and summer. The abduction
                    takes place once in the spring; winter arises from the anger of Demeter; but
                    ever afterwards Cora goes to her husband in the autumn with her mother’s consent
                    and returns in the spring. The myth has ceased to be closely and obviously
                    connected with the life of nature. The two cults each lost something when they
                    were amalgamated. The annual Theogamia, a central point in the original worship
                    of Cora,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>At Nysa,
                    Cyzicus, and elsewhere.</p></note> becomes a mere disagreeable episode in the
                    life of the two <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n139/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0139-0128"/> goddesses. Demeter ceases to be directly
                    connected with the life of the year, and affects it only through the fortunes of
                    her daughter. It is an important point that the vehement self-forgetting
                    enthusiasm characterizing devotees who feel their complete dependence on their
                    deities can be traced from the beginning in the worship of the mother of all
                    earthly life. This enthusiasm was increased by the next stage in the development
                    of the Mysteries, the fusion of the cults of Demeter-Persephone and of Dionysus.
                    It is uncertain how and when this fusion began; it is certain that it was not
                    completed till after the union of Eleusis and Athens.</p>
                <p>3. The worship of Dionysus can be traced in two phases. The cultus of the
                    wine-god with simple rural character, rude and gross symbolism, was the religion
                    of uneducated peasants, its chief seat being in the borderland of Attica and
                    Boeotia. Another form of the religion of Dionysus with its orgiastic enthusiasm
                    and its mystic character penetrated into Greece from Thrace, was accepted at
                    Delphi alongside of the Apolline worship,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Apollo ruled at Delphi for nine months of the year, Dionysus
                    for the other three.</p></note> and established itself at Eleutherae and on
                    Mount Parnassus, where the women of Phocis and Attica united in the rites and
                    revels of the god every second winter. The Dionysus of Eleutherae was carried to
                    Athens when the places were united, and the worship of Dionysus Eleuthereus was
                    one of the most splendid and most impressive in the state; under its shelter
                    grew the Attic drama.</p>
                <p>The unification of the Attic land required as its pledge and completion the
                    unification of the Attic religion. A common religion bound together every
                    association in Greece; a people united politically, yet divided religiously, was
                    an unintelligible idea to the ancient mind. When, through the decay of the
                    Megarian power, the Eleusinian valley was incorporated in the Attic state, the
                    worship of the Eleusinian goddess was established under the Athenian acropolis,
                    and the whole land united in her worship. Eleusis always occupied a peculiarly
                    independent position in Attica; it retained its own cultus in its own hands, and
                    it had, like Salamis, the right of issuing coins.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Köhler in <hi rend="italic">Mittheil. Inst. A
                    th.,</hi> iv. 250.</p></note> It seems to have been only at a late date that the
                    religious fusion was completed, and the relation between the Eleusinian and
                    Attic religions was conceived in a very different style from the crude fictions
                    by which at an earlier time Poseidon and Apollo had been incorporated in the
                    Attic state religion.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>The god ∏o&lt;rεcδωp <hi rend="italic">Taιηoχos κal Εpeχθebs,</hi> a fiction
                    of the state religion; Apollo, a son of Athena and Hephaestus in Attic legend;
                    cf. Harpocr. on <hi rend="italic">θebs πaτρφos</hi> with Cic., <hi rend="italic"
                    >N. D.,</hi> iii. 22.</p></note> The political and religious system which
                    produced peace among the warring sections of the Attic people was due to Solon.
                    His friendship with the mystic Epimenides, an historical fact encrusted with
                    much legend, shows the tone in which the religious part of the task was
                    executed. But the work of Solon would not have proved efficient if it had done
                    more than formulate and legalize the actual tendencies of the country.
                    Especially in religion the system was growing before Solon and continued to grow
                    after him. To this period— <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> the 6th century <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b,c.</hi> —and to the spirit of mysticism which was so strong
                    in Attica and in Greece generally at this time we must attribute the final
                    moulding of the Eleusinian ritual.</p>
                <p>According to the mystic theory, the multitude of deities are merely forms of the
                    ultimate single divine nature dividing itself into male and female to become the
                    origin of life on the earth. This theory was that of the Orphic theology, and
                    many facts show that the Orphic theology moulded the Eleusinian ritual.
                    Dionysus, under the mystic name Iacchus, was identified with the son of Demeter,
                    Plutus, the prosperity that she bestows on the world. Eleusis and Athens were
                    united in one mystic ritual, part of which was performed in Athens, part on the
                    road from Athens to Eleusis, and the most important rites in Eleusis. The
                    process by which the shrines along the Sacred Way became connected with the
                    religion of Demeter and Iacchus was doubtless gradual; but the outlines of the
                    system were certainly complete before the battle of Salamis (Herod., viii. 65).
                    Not only in the Eleusinian ritual, but throughout Attic religion, a tendency to
                    mix the cult of Athena with that of Demeter can be traced. They are very often
                    enshrined in the same temple. In the autumn the holy ploughings were performed
                    in the Rharian plain, at Sciron, and under the acropolis by the <hi
                    rend="italic">βoυξυγηs.</hi> Demeter in her anger wears the <hi rend="italic"
                    >yopybveιov</hi> on her breast; she was so represented in the colossal statue at
                    Eleusis, a fragment of which is now in Cambridge. The religious thought which
                    expressed itself in this way obviously identified Demeter with Athena. Again, we
                    find through Attic art and literature in the 5th century <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi> a tendency to mix Apollo and Dionysus, to show an Apollo Cisseus, a
                    Dionysus Melpomenus, to invoke δέσποτα <hi rend="italic">φι</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">bδaφve</hi> Βάκχε τταιάν <hi rend="italic"
                    >Απbλλov e(iλυρe.</hi> Apollo and Dionysus shared the presidency of Delphi.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Eur., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ion,</hi> 1075 <hi rend="italic">so.</hi></p></note> The tendency which Gerhard
                    has proved to represent Demeter and Cora as undistinguishable springs from the
                    same mystic system. The identification of Artemis and Persephone, which
                    Aeschylus makes, was probably taught at Eleusis <hi rend="italic">(Hymn,</hi> 1.
                    440).</p>
                <p>If material existed to study the ritual of the shrines along the Sacred Way, we
                    should find abundant examples of the working of the mystic system. Pausanias
                    tells that the cultus of Apollo in the pass of Dafni grew into a worship of
                    Demeter, Cora, Athena, and Apollo. Again, in reference to the worship of the
                    hero Cya-mites on the Sacred Way, he says that those who have been initiated at
                    Eleusis, or who have read the Orphic books, will understand his religious
                    silence. The same writer<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Paus., i. 14; ix. 27.</p></note><hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> mentions that
                    Orphic hymns were used in the Eleusinian ritual, and Prellèr has conclusively
                    proved the great influence exerted by Orphic teaching at Eleusis. Through this
                    close connexion of Orphism with the Eleusinian Mysteries, we understand how,
                    when the family of the Dadouchi died out in the, 4th century <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> the office was not filled up from the closely
                    related family of the Ceryces, but given to the Lycomidae, who held in their
                    hands the Orphizing mystic cultus of Phlya. If there had not been a great
                    similarity between the ritual of Eleusis and of Phlya, it is inconceivable that
                    the high office of δ{tδoOχos should have been given to a family unconnected with
                    Eleusis. It is easy to trace the same mystic tendency in later time. In the
                    Alexandrine period it was usual to identify Isis with Demeter, and even to
                    maintain that the Eleusinian Mysteries were derived from Egypt. In later times
                    the Neo-Platonic philosophy acquired influence at Eleusis, and hence we find
                    that, according to Porphyry, the hierophant represented the “demiurgos.”</p>
                <p>There is every reason to believe that the Bacchic rites can be traced through
                    Thrace to Phrygian influence, and that the spirit of Orphism was that of the
                    Oriental Phrygian cultus. Moreover, the most holy and perfect rite in the
                    Eleusinian Mysteries was to show an ear of corn mowed down in silence,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic"
                    >Philosophumena,</hi> ed. Miller, v. 8, p. 115.</p></note> ® and this was a
                    symbol of the Phrygian Atys. Now Clement describes in great detail a mystic
                    ceremony, some parts of which he attributes to Phrygia, though the general tone
                    of the passage rather refers it to Eleusis; some of the grossest details of this
                    ceremony are expressly referred to Eleusis by other Christian writers.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Cl., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Protr.,</hi> p. 11; see quotations in Lobeck, p. 199 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.</hi></p></note> These facts lead to the belief—(1) that Clement purposely
                    mixes up two ceremonies which were similar to one another, Phrygian and
                    Eleusinian Mysteries; (2) that this scene was acted at Eleusis on the eve of
                    Boedr. 23; (3) that it was introduced under the influence of the Orphic mystic
                    philosophy. Knowing that the Phrygian rites were decried by many who praised the
                    Eleusinian, Clement delights to emphasize points of resemblance between them.
                    The details given in the long account of Clement fully justify the invectives of
                    the Christian writers. It is, however, easy to understand the answer that the
                    Neo-Platonic philosophers who admired the Mysteries would make to their
                    assailants. Religion places men face to face with the actual facts of life; when
                    the mind is exalted and ennobled by intense religious enthusiasm it is able to
                    look with pure insight at phenomena of life in which the vulgar unpurified mind
                    sees nothing but gross materialism. The language of religion is plainer and more
                    direct than the language of common life. Those who distinguished between the
                    character of the Eleusinian and Phrygian rites might say that the same symbolism
                    can be looked at with gross eyes or with idealized eyes, and might quote the
                    contrast between the Aphrodite of Praxiteles and its rude Phoenician prototype;
                    the attitude, the position of the hands is the same, but the whole meaning is
                    changed.</p>
                <p>It is unnecessary to enter into the question whether the Mysteries go back to a
                    primitive “Pelasgic” religion, or are borrowed from Oriental religion. All that
                    gives elevation and ideality to them was added by the Hellenic genius. But that
                    spirit of enthusiastic self-abandonment which made the <hi rend="italic"
                    >μύσται</hi> forget themselves in the divine nature never belonged to the true
                    Hellenic temperament; the Mysteries were an attempt of the Hellenic genius to
                    take into its service the spirit of Oriental religion.</p>
                <p>It is impossible here to speak of the other Mysteries; subjects of similar nature
                    are referred to under <hi rend="smallcaps">Mithras, Orpheus, Phrygia.</hi> The
                    Eleusinian Mysteries were the most perfect example of the type in Greece; but
                    our scanty information leads to the belief that all Hellenic Mysteries tried
                    more or less successfully to attain the same results. Those non-Hellenic
                    Mysteries which found their way into Greece from the 5th century <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> onwards are of course excluded from this
                    statement.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>On these
                    non-Hellenic Mysteries see Foucart, <hi rend="italic">Assoc.
                    Relig.</hi></p></note> (W. Μ. RA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
