<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0074-0063-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MURSHIDÁBÁD, or Moorshed (9th edition, volume 17, page
                    63)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1097334">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883965">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174325">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:798948">Afghans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h77">Mohammedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh0c">Afghans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h12vb7j">Frontiers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n74/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MURSHIDÁBÁD, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Moorshed</hi></label><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">ab</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">ad,</hi> a district in the
                    lieutenant-governorship of Bengal, lying between 23° 43' and 24° 52' N. lat. and
                    87° 43' and 88 <hi rend="superscript"> α</hi> 47' E. long., is bounded along its
                    whole frontier from the extreme N. to the S.E. by the Ganges, separating it from
                    the Nadiyâ and Râjshâhi districts; on the S. byNadiyâ and Bardwân —the Jalangi
                    river marking its boundary for a considerable distance; and on the E. by Birbhum
                    and the Santâl Parganâs district. The area is 2141 square miles. The district is
                    divided into two nearly equal portions by the Bhâgirathi, the ancient channel of
                    the Ganges, which flows due north and south. The tract to the west, known as the
                    Rârh, consists of hard clay and nodular limestone. The general level is high,
                    but interspersed with <hi rend="italic">l&gt;ils</hi> or broad marshes and
                    seamed by hill torrents. The Bâgri or eastern half differs in no respect from
                    the ordinary alluvial plains of eastern Bengal. There are few permanent swamps;
                    but the whole country is low-lying, and liable to annual inundation. In the
                    north-west are a few small detached hillocks, said to be of basaltic formation.
                    The river system is constituted by the Ganges or Padma, and its offshoots and
                    tributaries the Bhâgirathi, Bhairab,</p>
                <p>Siâlmâri, Jalangi, and Singâ,—the first mentioned being by far the most important
                    river within Murshidâbâd, though only navigable during half the year. It is
                    embanked along the entire length of its left bank. There are no canals in the
                    district.</p>
                <p>The census of 1881 returned the population of the district at 1,226,790 (males
                    586,483, females 640,307),—Hindus numbering 634,796, Mohammedans 589,957, native
                    Christians 250, and aborigines 836. The population comprises Bengalis of the
                    delta, hill tribes from Chutia Nagpur, and the peculiar Hindu castes of Behar,
                    while the presence of the court has introduced Rajputs from the north-west for
                    railway service or trade, Afghans and Persians from beyond the frontier, and a
                    bodyguard of Habshis from the east coast of Africa. The six following towns
                    contained in 1872 a population exceeding 5000,—Murshidâbâd, 46,182; Barhanymr,
                    27,210; Kandi, 12,016; Jangipur, 11,361; Beldanga, 6037; and Margrâm, 5766.
                    Other places of some importance are the river marts of Azimganj and Jiaganj,
                    situated opposite each other on the Bhâgirathi, Bhagwangola and Dhulian on the
                    Ganges, and the railway stations of Murarai and Nalhâti. Sites of historical
                    interest include the now deserted Kâsimbazar, Badrihat, Rângâmâti, and the
                    battlefield of Gheria.</p>
                <p>Rice constitutes the staple crop, the <hi rend="italic">àman</hi> or winter rice
                    being prevalent in the western half of the district, and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >aus</hi> or early rice in the*eastern. A second or cold weather crop of wheat,
                    barley, and many varieties of oil-seeds and pulses is also grown in this latter
                    tract, jute is but little grown, and the cultivation of indigo and of mulberry
                    for silkworms is on the decline. There is little that is peculiar in the land
                    tenures of the district beyond the <hi rend="italic">rdmnds</hi> or deer parks,
                    held revenue-free by the nawâb, and the cultivating tenure known as <hi
                    rend="italic">ut-bandi,</hi> according to which the peasant pays rent, not for
                    his entire holding, but only for the land actually cultivated, the amount being
                    determined by the nature of the crops grown, and being paid in kind. Silk is
                    still manufactured, but the industry is rapidly losing its importance. At
                    Murshidâbâd city and at Barhampur there are special industries of ivory-carving,
                    bell-metal work, and gold and silver embroidery. The district is favourably
                    situated for trade, both by river and rail. In 1876-77 the exports amounted to
                    £1,020,124; the imports to £739,906. The principal exports consisted of rice,
                    gram and pulses, wheat, silk, and indigo; the principal imports of European
                    piece goods, salt, and raw cotton.</p>
                <p>In 1881-82 the net revenue amounted to 1,803,828 rupees, of which 1,298,735 were
                    derived from the land-tax. Education in 1876 was afforded by 506 schools,
                    attended by 14,664 pupils. The special educational institutions are the
                    Barhampur College, founded in 1853; the Nizâmat College, limited to the
                    education of the relatives of the nawâb; and the Nizâmat free school in
                    Murshidâbâd city. The climate does not differ from that common to Lower Bengal,
                    except that it experiences to some extent the burning winds of Central India
                    during the hot season. The average annual temperature is 78° '6 Fahr. In 1880-81
                    it was 59'82, and in 1881-82 it was 47'76. The average annual rainfall is 54'30
                    inches. The district has a low standard of health. The stagnant pools formed by
                    the Bhâgirathi during the dry season constitute a perennial source of malaria,
                    and cholera is rarely absent from the city and suburbs. Elephantiasis and
                    hydrocele are also endemic.</p>
                <p>The history of the district centres round the city of Murshidâbâd, the latest
                    Mohammedan capital of Bengal. In 1704 the nawâb Murshid Kulia Khan changed the
                    seat of government to the little town of Maksudâbâd, but when All Vardi Khan won
                    the throne by conquest in 1740 he also adopted Murshidâbâd as his capital. The
                    great family of Jagat Seth maintained their position as state bankers at
                    Murshidâbâd from generation to generation. Even after the conquest of Bengal by
                    the British, Murshidâbâd remained for some time the seat of administration.
                    Warren Hastings removed the supreme civil and criminal courts to Calcutta in
                    1772, but in 1775 the latter court was brought back to Murshidâbâd again. In
                    1790, under Lord Cornwallis, both the entire revenue and judicial stalls were
                    ultimately fixed at Calcutta.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Murshidâbâd,</hi> principal city of the above district, is
                    situated on the left bank of the Bhâgirathi river, in 24° 1Γ N. lat. and 88° 18'
                    E. long. Its importance has entirely departed since it ceased to be the capital
                    of Bengal, and its population has steadily diminished. In 1872 the population
                    was 46,182 (Hindus 27,211, Mohammedans 18,824, Christians 38, “others” 109). It
                    is still a great centre of trade and manufacture, and the Jain merchants of
                    Murshidâbâd still rank as the wealthiest of their class in Bengal. Their
                    dealings in gold and silver bullion are especially large, and some of their
                    number almost monopolize the local traffic on the Brahmaputra as <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n75/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0075-0064"/> far as the north-east frontier of Assam. The
                    principal industries of the city are those fostered by the luxury of the native
                    court. Carving in ivory, conducted with much skill and finish, is an old
                    speciality of the city. The principal building is the new palace of the nawâb
                    nâzim, a large and imposing pile of buildings on the banks of the river, and
                    nearly in the centre of the city.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
