<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-9053-0137-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COMET (7th edition, volume 7, page 137)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736mb9b">Wrens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fx73z5s">Bins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr70">Sin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jq0t035">Tanning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1181567">Wrens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:831918">Bins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1119194">Sin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1119629">Sins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142827">Tanning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1001952">Logging</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194749053?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COMET</label>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">In</hi> the article Astronomy we have given a general
                    description of the orbits and physical appearances of comets. In the present
                    article it is our purpose to give a solution of the problem of determining the
                    approximate elements of a comet’s orbit from three geocentric observations,— a
                    problem of very great importance in astronomy, since it is only from the
                    circumstance of moving in the same orbit, that the identity of a comet, in its
                    successive revolutions, can be inferred with certainty.</p>
                <p>The astronomy of comets may be said to have originated with Tycho Brahé, who
                    showed that, by reason of the smallness of their parallaxes, their distances
                    from the earth must be greater than that of the moon. Before this era they had
                    been generally regarded as meteors casually engendered in the atmosphere, and
                    having no permanent duration or connection with the solar system. The
                    conclusions of the Danish astronomer were confirmed by the observations of
                    Galileo, Snell, and Kepler, on the comet which appeared in the beginning of the
                    seventeenth century; and as it was now certain that the comets do not belong to
                    the earth, but move in the region of the planets, the determination of their
                    orbits, and their relations to the other known bodies of the universe, became a
                    problem of the highest interest. Kepler attempted to represent their apparent
                    paths by supposing them to move in straight lines, with a variable velocity; and
                    on this hypothesis the orbits of several comets were computed by Dominic
                    Cassini, with a degree of success that might appear remarkable, were it not
                    known that the apparent path of a comet differs little from a straight line
                    during a considerable portion of the time that it is visible from the earth. But
                    it could not fail soon to be perceived that the hypothesis of rectilinear motion
                    is not only improbable in itself, but inconsistent with accurate observation.
                    Hevelius demonstrated, in his <hi rend="italic">Cometographia,</hi> published in
                    16G8, that the path of the comet of 1G65 was curvilinear, and concave towards
                    the sun; and he even supposed the orbit <hi rend="italic">might</hi> be a
                    parabola, without hinting, however, that the sun is placed in the focus. But the
                    individual who, before the grand discoveries of Newton, approximated most nearly
                    to a correct knowledge of the true nature of the cometary orbits, was Dörfel,
                    protestant minister of Wieda, a village near Plauen, in Upper Saxony. Dörfel
                    observed the comet of 1680-1, from the 22d of December till the end of the
                    following January, and recognised its identity on its emerging from the sun’s
                    rays, after passing through the perihelion of its orbit; and he proved the orbit
                    to be a parabola, having the sun in the focus. The observations of Dörfel were
                    published in 1681, consequently before the appearance of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Principia,</hi> in a small work, which has become so extremely rare, that
                    neither Montucla nor Delambre had been able to procure a copy of it. To Dörfel,
                    therefore, belongs the honour of having been the first to point out the true
                    orbit of a comet, though his merit has passed almost unnoticed in consequence of
                    the more important discoveries which followed so soon after. It is not known
                    whether Newton was aware of the observations of Dörfel; but it is certain that
                    the latter had no idea of the great principle of attraction, in virtue of which
                    the comets as well as the planets perform stated revolutions about the <hi
                    rend="superscript"> sun</hi> ∙ In his hands the parabolic orbit was simply an
                    astronomical hypothesis, connected with no system, and framed only to satisfy a
                    few observations. Newton, on the other hand, demonstrated that the comets form a
                    part of the solar system, that they describe orbits about the sun in virtue of
                    his attractive force, obeying the same laws of motion as the planets; and he
                    showed, moreover, in ,what manner the elements of their orbits may be computed,
                    on the parabolic hypothesis, from three geocentric observations of their
                    longitudes and latitudes.</p>
                <p>Newton has given, in the <hi rend="italic">Principia,</hi> two different
                    solutions of the problem of determining a parabolic orbit from three
                    observations. In the first he supposes that a small portion of the trajectory’
                    may be regarded as a straight line, described with a uniform motion, so that its
                    segments, intercepted by straight lines drawn from the earth to the comet, at
                    the times of the respective observations, are proportional to the intervals of
                    time between the observations. According to this supposition, the ratio of these
                    segments is known. It follows, also, since the portion of the trajectory
                    included between the extreme observations is a straight line, that its
                    projection on the plane of the ecliptic is also a straight line, and divided
                    similarly to the trajectory itself, by the projections of the straight lines
                    joining the places of the earth and the comet. In order, therefore, to determine
                    the projected orbit, it might seem to be only necessary to draw a straight line
                    in such a manner that its segments, intercepted by straight lines whose
                    positions are given (being determined by the observed longitudes), shall have to
                    each other given ratios. But this problem, in the case in which there are only
                    three observations, or three given straight lines, is altogether indeterminate;
                    for having assumed any point whatever in one of the three given straight lines,
                    it is always possible to draw through that point a straight line, which shall be
                    divided into segments having a given ratio, by the other two given straight
                    lines. But it is obvious that the position of the transversal line will be
                    different for every different position of the assumed point; consequently the
                    number of solutions is infinite. When the number of observations is four, the
                    problem is to draw a straight line, so that it may be divided into parts having
                    given ratios to one another, by four straight lines given in position. In this
                    state of the data, it becomes, generally speaking, determinate, and admits of
                    only a single solution. This problem had been already resolved by Dr Wallis and
                    Sir Christopher Wren, and to their solutions Newton added two others of his own.
                    There is still a case, however, in which, even when four straight lines are
                    given, the problem is indeterminate; and it happens, by a remarkable
                    coincidence, that it is this case precisely which occurs in the application to
                    the cometary motions. If the position of the four given lines is such that <hi
                    rend="italic">two</hi> transversal lines can be drawn so that the segments of
                    both of them are respectively proportional to given lines, then innumerable
                    other straight lines may be drawn which shall be all cut in the same ratio. Now
                    this is the case with regard to the four straight lines which join the places of
                    the earth and comet at the instants of the respective observations. During the
                    short interval that elapses between the extreme observations, the earth, as well
                    as the comet, may be regarded as moving in a straight line with a uniform
                    velocity; so that the orbit of the earth, and the trajectory of the comet, are
                    both divided into segments proportional to the intervals between the
                    observations, and consequently proportional to each other. This circumstance,
                    which was first pointed out by Boscovich, renders the problem inapplicable to
                    astronomy; for although the eartli’s motion should not be regarded as entirely
                    rectilinear and uniform, yet the data necessarily approach so <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194749066?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9066-0138"/> near to the
                    indeterminate case, that no satisfactory conclusion can be deduced from them.
                    Hence all attempts to compute the orbit of a comet in this manner have failed.
                    (See Playfair’s Memoir on the Origin and Investigation of Porisms, in vol. iii.
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Transactions,</hi> or in the third volume of
                    his <hi rend="italic">Works.')</hi></p>
                <p>The second method proposed by Newton forms Proposition 41 of the third book of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Principia.</hi> Though unexceptionable in theory, it
                    leads, when actually applied to the determination of an orbit, to computations
                    excessively complicated and laborious, and is consequently now entirely disused.
                    It is probable that it was this method which was followed by Dr Halley, who
                    computed the orbits of a great number of comets, though he has nowhere explained
                    the process of computation he adopted. It is illustrated by Dr David Gregory in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Astronomia Physica,</hi> and by Lemonnier in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Théorie des Comètes.</hi></p>
                <p>The problem of the comets remained for many years in the state in which it was
                    left by Newton, and astronomers were still in want of a practical method by
                    which a parabolic orbit could be determined with tolerable ease and accuracy. In
                    the absence of a direct solution, it was usual to have recourse to the methods
                    of trial and error, and to approximate, by successive suppositions, to an orbit
                    that would nearly represent the observations. This method was practised by
                    Bradley, and by Lemonnier in his <hi rend="italic">Institutions</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Astronomiques.</hi> Lacaille also published a method of the same
                    kind in 1746, which was long followed by the continental astronomers, and is
                    recommended by Delambre as possessing some advantages over those which are now
                    generally preferred. In fact, all the methods which have yet been devised
                    involve more or less of hypothesis, and require to be corrected by successive
                    trials. Various other solutions of the problem were published about the same
                    time, among which, those of Séjour, Hennert, Templehoff, and Bouguer, may be
                    mentioned, though they are now entirely abandoned. The celebrated Boscovich,
                    also, in the third volume of his <hi rend="italic">Opera</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Pertinentia</hi><hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic">Opticam et
                    Astronomiam,</hi> undertook to consider this subject; and the solution which be
                    gave is remarkable, as being the first in which the velocity of the comet in its
                    orbit was taken into account as one of the essential conditions of the problem.
                    It is, however, excessively complicated, and contains a mixture of algebraic
                    formulae and graphical operations susceptible of very little accuracy. Delambre,
                    in speaking of this method, doubts if it was ever employed in the actual
                    computation of an orbit by any astronomer, excepting the author himself, or
                    perhaps some of his friends, though it is destitute neither of science nor
                    address. <hi rend="italic">(Astr. du X,VIIl</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    mβ</hi><hi rend="italic">Siècle,</hi> p. 653.) But the most important work which
                    appeared on the subject of the cometary motions, previous to the investigations
                    of Lagrange and Laplace, was that of Lambert, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Insigniores</hi><hi rend="italic">Orbitae</hi><hi rend="italic">Cometarum
                    Proprietates.</hi> Among the formulae which it contains relative to the motion
                    of a body in a parabolic orbit, there is one, extremely remarkable on account of
                    its elegance, which gives the time of describing an arc in terms of its chord,
                    and the two radii vectores drawn through its extremities. This formula, which
                    retains the name of <hi rend="italic">Lambert's Theorem,</hi> though Gauss has
                    shown that it really belongs to Euler, is of great use in the cometary theory,
                    as it affords a very easy means of correcting the hypothetical values which it
                    is necessary to substitute in the equations of the problem. Lambert also pointed
                    out rules for determining, without solving the equations, whether the distance
                    of the comet from the sun is greater or less than the distance of the sun from
                    the earth; a knowledge of which circumstance affords considerable aid in forming
                    a first hypothesis, and serves to abridge the preliminary computations.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the repeated attempts of so many celebrated astronomers and
                    mathematicians, the problem of determining a cometary orbit had not received a
                    direct or satisfactory solution, when it was taken up by Lagrange in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Berlin Memoirs</hi> for 1778. After examining and pointing out the
                    defects of the different methods then known, Lagrange gave a new method, which
                    has formed the basis of the greater part of the analytical solutions which have
                    been proposed since. The principle of his analysis is at once simple and direct.
                    It will be recollected that the data of the problem are three observed positions
                    of the comet, or three geocentric longitudes and latitudes. Lagrange first gives
                    formulae to express the co-ordinates of the comet at the epochs of the first and
                    third observations, in terms of its co-ordinates at the second observation; he
                    then proceeds to substitute these values in the differential equations of
                    motion; and in this manner, without making any hypothesis respecting the nature
                    of the orbit, he obtains the necessary number of independent equations for
                    eliminating the three co-ordinates, together with their differential
                    co-efficients, leaving three final equations, in which the unknown quantities
                    are the three distances of the comet from the earth at the epoch of the
                    respective observations. On eliminating two of these distances, the resulting
                    equation is found to rise to the eighth degree. It is easily reducible to the
                    seventh; but unfortunately there are no other means of determining its roots
                    than by repeated trials according to the methods of false position. Assuming,
                    however, that a sufficiently approximate value of the comet’s distances from the
                    earth has been found in this way, it is thence easy to deduce its corresponding
                    radii vectores, or distances from the sun, together with the angles they
                    include, from which data all the elements of the orbit can be determined without
                    difficulty.</p>
                <p>Theoretically considered, the solution of Lagrange may be considered as perfect;
                    but when it comes to be actually applied in the computation of an orbit,
                    difficulties arise which can only be overcome, or eluded, by certain
                    modifications of the general method, which the illustrious author has not
                    explained. He did not himself attempt the applications, or he could not have
                    failed to perceive, and would doubtless have provided for, the circumstances
                    which, in following his method, occasion so much embarrassment to the computer.
                    Lagrange made some important additions to his original analysis in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Berlin Memoirs</hi> for 1783, and it is also explained in the
                    second volume of the <hi rend="italic">Mécanique Analytique.</hi></p>
                <p>Another method of obtaining a solution of the problem, entirely different from
                    the above, was purposed by Laplace in the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the
                    Academy of Sciences</hi> of Paris for 1780, and is developed with all the
                    necessary details, in the second book of the <hi rend="italic">Mécanique</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Celeste.</hi> The peculiarity of Laplace’s method consists in its
                    being supposed that a small portion of the orbit is accurately known from
                    observation; that is to say, it is assumed that the longitude and latitude of
                    the comet at a given epoch, together with the first and second differentials of
                    those quantities, have been precisely determined. From these data the elements
                    of the orbit can be deduced more simply than by any other method yet proposed;
                    but it is found in practice that the determination of the first and second
                    differentials of the comet’s longitude and latitude is generally a matter of
                    difficulty or uncertainty, and in some cases altogether impracticable. Laplace
                    had at first imagined, that when a considerable number of observations have been
                    obtained, as is most frequently the case, the differential values or the
                    longitude and latitude would be found with greater accuracy by combining the
                    whole of the observations; but it was subsequently shown by Legendre, that when
                    more than a few observations are employed, the errors unavoidably<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194749079?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9079-0139"/> introduced in
                    the arithmetical operations necessary for interpolating the observed places of
                    the comet, are such as to increase, instead of diminishing, the errors of
                    observation. It is therefore advantageous to confine ourselves to the number of
                    observations strictly necessary, namely three; and to employ the remaining
                    observations in correcting the elements deduced from these three. With three
                    observations only, it cannot be expected that the results will have a high
                    degree of accuracy; but when approximate values of the elements of an orbit have
                    been found, it is in general easy to introduce such corrections as will give an
                    orbit representing the observations within the limits of unavoidable errors.
                    Laplace’s method affords the simplest means of obtaining such approximations of
                    any hitherto proposed, and is applicable perhaps in as great a number of cases
                    as any other; it is consequently very frequently adopted by computers. Cases
                    indeed occur in which it fails altogether, as happened in regard to the comet of
                    1814; but the same thing takes place with every other method that has yet been
                    devised; nor is it always possible to discover, till actual trial has been made,
                    the particular circumstances connected with the position or motion of the comet,
                    which render one method more applicable than another.</p>
                <p>Of the numerous methods of determining the approximate elements of an orbit from
                    tlíree observations, that of Olbers is one of the simplest and most direct,
                    though the approximations which it gives arc not very exact. Olbers supposes the
                    orbit to be a parabola; a supposition which gives one equation more than the
                    number of unknown quantities. He supposes, moreover, that the chord of the arc
                    which joins the places of the comet at the epoch of the first and third
                    observations, is divided, by the radius vector corresponding to the middle
                    observation, into segments proportional to the intervals of time between the
                    observations. The last supposition can only be admitted when the intervals
                    between the observations are nearly equal; if a considerable inequality exists
                    in the intervals, and more especially, if, at the same time, the radius vector
                    of the comet is less than that of the earth, it leads to very inaccurate
                    results. The author, indeed, shows how the errors of the hypothesis may be in
                    some degree corrected; but, after all, his approximation includes only
                    quantities of the second order in respect of the time. This may be sufficient in
                    some cases; but in general it will be necessary to include quantities of the
                    third order. The method of Olbers is explained at considerable length in the
                    third volume of Delambre’s <hi rend="italic">Astronomie.</hi></p>
                <p>In 1806 Legendre published his <hi rend="italic">Nouvelles</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Methodes pour la determination</hi><hi rend="italic">des Orbites des
                    Comètes;</hi> a work very remarkable, not only by reason of the important light
                    it threw on the question under consideration, but alsoon account of its
                    containing the first exposition of the method of combining the results of a
                    great number of observations, known by the name of the <hi rend="italic">method
                    of least squares,</hi> and which is so extensively useful in many questions of
                    natural philosophy and astronomy. The method of determining an orbit given in
                    this memoir is in some respects the same as that of Lagrange; but the equations
                    of the problem are put under a form which admits of an easier application, and
                    gives surer results; and the circumstances are fully developed and explained,
                    which had so frequently caused Lagrange’s method to fail in actual trial.
                    Legendre also adopted a different method of treating the fundamental equations
                    of the problem. Instead of deducing the elements of the orbit from two radii
                    vectores and the contained angle, he eliminates those radii, and deduces
                    expressions for the three rectangular co-ordinates of the comet at the epoch of
                    the mean observation, and their three differential coefficients regarded as
                    functions of the time. When the coordinates and their differential co-efficients
                    Jιave been determined, the elements of the orbit can be easily deduced from them
                    by known methods applicable to orbits of all descriptions. In the case in which
                    the intervals between the observations are equal (and this condition can in
                    general be satisfied by interpolating the observed places of the comet), the
                    equations take a remarkably simple form, and the analytical solution is obtained
                    with great facility. In the general case, that is to say, when the intervals
                    between the observations are unequal, the equations are somewhat more
                    complicated; but they have still an analogous form, and the additional labour
                    required for their computation is perhaps compensated by the absence of
                    preliminary interpolation, and by the greater certainty that arises from
                    employing directly the data furnished by observation. This method of determining
                    an orbit is exhibited in a very clear and elegant manner by Pontécoulant in his
                    <hi rend="italic">Théorie Analytique du Système du Monde,</hi> tome ii.</p>
                <p>In the <hi rend="italic">Transactions</hi><hi rend="italic">of the</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Royal Society</hi> for 1814, Mr Ivory has given a method of
                    obtaining a first approximation to the orbit of a comet, explained with all the
                    perspicuity and analytical elegance which so peculiarly characterize the
                    writings of this eminent and justly celebrated mathematician. Mr Ivory’s
                    solution is founded on the same principles as that of Olbers, but it gives a
                    nearer approximation, and is also adapted to a case in which the ordinary
                    methods fail, namely, when the comet and the earth are nearly at the same
                    distance from the sun. Like Olbers, and indeed Newton, Mr Ivory supposes the
                    chord of the parabolic arc, described in the interval between the extreme
                    observations, to be divided by the radius vector corresponding to the middle
                    observation in the ratio of the times between the observations; a supposition
                    which, as we have already remarked, though it simplifies the analysis and
                    computations, cannot always be admitted, and which, in fact, leads, in some
                    cases, to very sensible errors. It has been objected to this solution, that it
                    is needlessly encumbered with auxiliary formulae.</p>
                <p>The facility with which an orbit can be computed according to this method,
                    induced Legendre to resume the investigation of the subject, in order to obtain,
                    if possible, from the same method, more approximate elements. In 1820 a second
                    supplement was published to the <hi rend="italic">Nouvelles Méthodes,</hi>
                    containing a solution grounded on the same principles as those of Olbers and
                    Ivory. Instead of assuming, however, like those two mathematicians, the chord of
                    the parabolic arc to be divided by the radius vector of the middle observation
                    in the ratio of the elapsed times, Legendre finds an expression for the value of
                    each of its segments in terms of the time; and the degree of approximation
                    ultimately obtained depends on the number of terms of the series expressing
                    those values that are included in the computation. This method possesses several
                    advantages. In the first place, it requires no preliminary interpolations; in
                    the second place, it is simple, and can be understood without a very high degree
                    of algebraic skill; and lastly, which is of most importance, it will be found to
                    give, we believe, in a great majority of cases, especially when the intervals
                    between the observations are considerably unequal, a nearer approximation than
                    any of the other methods, with the same degree of labour. For these reasons we
                    have adopted it in the present article. In particular cases other methods may be
                    found more applicable; but the same objection may be made to those of Laplace,
                    Olbers, and indeed every other which has been proposed. No method will answer
                    equally well in every case.</p>
                <p>The last work on this subject to which we shall refer is a paper by Mr Lubbock,
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Royal Astronomical Society,</hi> vol.
                    iv. part i., 1830. We have already remarked, that the final equation which gives
                    the radius <pb break="no" facs="nls:194749092?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0707-9092-0140"/> vector of the comet, or its distance from the
                    earth, rises to the seventh degree, and that consequently the solution of the
                    problem can only be obtained by the method of trial and error. Mr Lubbock
                    proposes the following method of finding a value of the radius vector by means
                    of a quadratic equation. The accelerating forces acting on the comet, in the
                    direction of the three rectangular co-ordinates of its orbit, the sun’s mass
                    being unit, are, <hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">x x _ d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">y 'y _ d?z z _</hi> √p+,^=&gt; <hi rend="smallcaps">λ'</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript                     smallcaps"> +</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >7</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> γ</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">-</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> 0</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">'</hi> from the
                    integration of which the following equation is obtained, which gives the square
                    of the velocity, namely, <hi rend="italic">dx</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">+ dy</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    i</hi><hi rend="italic">+ dz</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi> 2 1 _ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> m</hi><hi rend="italic">Ί»</hi><hi rend="italic">~</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> +</hi><hi rend="italic">“</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> J</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> w</hi></p>
                <p>But since <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">χ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi> + 3∕ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + <hi rend="italic">z</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> we have also, in
                    consequence of the above three equations, <hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">r dx</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">+ dy</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">+ dz</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi> 1</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">2dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >~</hi> ⅛ r <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> therefore,</p>
                <p>ŵ _ 2 1 1 <hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi> 1 &gt; 1 _ <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi> ∕Q∖</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">2dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >~ r a √°* 2dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">ř
                    a</hi></p>
                <p>On eliminating between the equations (1) and (2), the problem is reduced to the
                    solution of a quadratic. But this method, in consequence of the smallness of the
                    quantities which enter into equation (2), is attended with no practical
                    advantage. In certain cases, when the state of the observations is favourable,
                    it may be employed in finding an approximation to the value of <hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but in general it will not give <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi> more nearly than may be guessed at from certain criteria
                    established by Lambert, by means of which we can estimate the comparative
                    distances of the comet and the sun from the earth. At all events it gives only
                    an approximation, which must be corrected by subsequent trials.</p>
                <p>The reduction of the problem to the solution of a quadratic equation is not new;
                    it was already accomplished by Séjour, and also by Olbers. (See Delambre, <hi
                    rend="italic">Λstr. du XVIII™</hi><hi rend="italic">Siècle,</hi> p. 733.)</p>
                <p>In all the methods which we have here alluded to, it is assumed that the comet
                    moves in a parabolic orbit, and their success is owing entirely to this
                    assumption. But it is certain that the true orbit of some comets, and most
                    probably of all comets, is an ellipse, and not <hi rend="italic">a</hi>
                    parabola. The question will therefore naturally suggest itself, whether it would
                    not be better to investigate an ellipse at once, than to concern ourselves about
                    a parabolic orbit, which, with whatever care it may be computed, can never be
                    perfectly exact, nor even be expected to satisfy observations made at
                    considerably distant intervals. To this it mav be replied, that on the first
                    appearance of a comet it can seldom be of any use to seek an ellipse, the
                    computation of which is greatly more tedious. For every practical purpose it is
                    sufficient to have a parabola which represents the observations within a few
                    seconds; first, because in the case of a comet the observations are scarcely
                    ever more accurate than the computations founded on this assumption; and,
                    secondly, because the approximation obtained by supposing the orbit to be a
                    parabola, will enable us to determine the position of the node, the inclination
                    of the orbit, and the perihelion distance, more exactly than we can expect to
                    find them on the return of the comet, the perturbations of the planets giving
                    rise to variations in the elements of the orbit probably exceeding the errors of
                    the first computation. It is enough that we are able to recognise its identity.
                    When this has been done we have the periodic time, and consequently the greater
                    axis of the orbit. With these data we are enabled to compute the other elements
                    by the methods employed for determining the elliptic orbits of the planets.</p>
                <p>The problem of determining a cometary orbit resolves itself into two parts. In
                    the first it is required to assign an orbit which will represent all the
                    observations made during a single appearance of the comet; and in the second, to
                    compute the effects of the disturbing forces of the planets, so as to predict
                    the changes which will take place in the form and position of the orbit during
                    an indefinite number of revolutions. The <hi rend="italic">perturbations,</hi>
                    however, which are computed in the same manner whether the disturbed body be a
                    comet or a planet, form a problem of <hi rend="smallcaps">Physical
                    Astronomy</hi> by far too important to be undertaken in this place. We will
                    therefore confine ourselves to the approximate determination of a parabolic
                    orbit from three observations. The method which we have followed, as we have
                    already intimated, is that which was proposed by Legendre in the second
                    Supplement to his <hi rend="italic">Nouvelles Méthodes.</hi></p>
                <p>Let C <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, C, C' be the places of the comet at the
                    instants of the first, second, and third observations respectively. Let the
                    interval between the first and second observations be denoted by <hi
                    rend="italic">ô,</hi> and that between the second and third by &amp;; then, if
                    the epoch, or instant from which the time is reckoned, be made to fall on the
                    second observation, and be denoted by <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> the epochs of
                    the first and third observations will be respectively <hi rend="italic"
                    >t</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">ð,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ŧ
                    -]- O’.</hi> Next, let <hi rend="italic">x,y, z,</hi> be the rectangular
                    co-ordinates of C referred to the plane of the ecliptic and a straight line
                    drawn through S, the centre of the sun, to the first point of Aries, the origin
                    of the co-ordinates being at S. Similarly, let <hi rend="smallcaps">λ?°,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 0</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >,z°,</hi> be the co-ordinates of C <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, and a/, <hi
                    rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">,
                    z</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">,</hi> those of C ’. The first step of the process is
                    to find expressions for <hi rend="italic">x°, y°, z°,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >a!, y</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">, z',</hi> in terms of <hi rend="italic">x, y,
                    z,</hi> the latter being regarded as functions of the time <hi rend="italic"
                    >t.</hi></p>
                <p>By Taylor’s theorem we have <hi rend="italic subscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dx ô . d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">x ô</hi><hi
                    rend="italic                     superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">x ff</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> X</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >~</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> x</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">~^~dti</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> +</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >~dr' V2~</hi> Λ <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> 'L2^3 ÷’ <hi rend="superscript">
                    &amp;c</hi> *</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">, . dx &amp; , d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">x ff</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">.
                    d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi> 0 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> z3</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> af</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">=</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript">
                    x+</hi><hi rend="italic">Λ-l</hi><hi rend="superscript"> +</hi> ⅛∙Γ2 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> +</hi> Ι*Γ∙Γ∑S <hi rend="superscript"> +</hi> '* <hi
                    rend="superscript"> c</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> ι</hi> in which series the
                    intervals <hi rend="italic">6</hi> and may be regarded as so small, that the
                    values of <hi rend="italic">x°</hi> and <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi> will be determined with "sufficient exactness when the
                    terms affected with the fifth, and all the higher powers of ∂ and &amp;, are
                    omitted.</p>
                <p>Let r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, <hi rend="italic">r, r</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> be the three radii vectores of the
                    comet corresponding to the three observations, or the distances SC <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi>, SC, SC'. The accelerating forces acting on the comet
                    at C in the directions of the co-ordinates are expressed by the equations <hi
                    rend="italic">(Px _ X d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">y _</hi><hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">ċPz z</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >τ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi> r <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ’</p>
                <p>the mass of the sun being assumed to be unit, and the mass of the comet being
                    neglected in comparison of that of the sun.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:194749105?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9105-0141"/>
                <p>By differentiating the first of the above equations, we</p>
                <p>ŵ _ <hi rend="italic">dx 3xt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dr _ 3xrdr dx</hi><hi rend="italic">^dfi τ</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 6</hi><hi rend="italic">dt ~ ~Vdt τ</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ,
                    1</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> r, by making <hi rend="italic">κ,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">cPx 3k 1 dx</hi><hi rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ,
                    ,</hi><hi rend="italic">' r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dt</hi></p>
                <p>Differentiating again, and making the necessary reductions, we obtain <hi
                    rend="italic">d*x_</hi>- Λl 4. 4. <hi rend="superscript underline"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="underline">’</hi><hi rend="superscript underline"> 3</hi><hi
                    rend="underline">’</hi><hi rend="superscript underline"> Ă dx</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">~dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >~~</hi> ∖ r <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">dt</hi> r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 7</hi> r <hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi> √ r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 5</hi><hi rend="italic">dť</hi><hi rend="italic">d?x
                    d^x</hi></p>
                <p>If we now substitute these values of —and —τ-, in the foregoing series for <hi
                    rend="italic">x°</hi> and a/, we shall have, on rejecting the superfluous terms,
                    <hi rend="subscript"> o</hi> Zì <hi rend="superscript"> 1 02 3k 03</hi> ∖</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> x -a</hi> Λ <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> 'l∙2 r <hi rend="superscript"> δ</hi> * 1∙2∙3∕</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> d</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Λ(</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> d +</hi><hi rend="italic">L</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> +</hi></p>
                <p>^ <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> √A τ <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> *1∙2∙3 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> τ</hi> r <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> 1∙2∙3∙4∕</p>
                <p>∕ 1 <hi rend="italic">if</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">3k</hi> O' <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ∖</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript">? -</hi> ∖ <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ^^ r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> i</hi> ‘ 1∙2 <hi rend="superscript"> +</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> r</hi> &lt; 1∙2∙3 <hi rend="italic">J</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> +</hi> (⅛V r? 1∙2∙3 <hi rend="superscript"> +</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">r&gt;</hi> Ι∙2∙3∙4Λ</p>
                <p>For the sake of abridging, let us assume</p>
                <p>, ö <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> λ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Ô</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> u</hi><hi rend="italic">-~</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 0</hi><hi rend="italic">+ 6^ + ^</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">
                    .</hi><hi rend="italic subscript smallcaps"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic
                    smallcaps"> &amp;</hi><hi rend="italic superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic smallcaps"> ^'</hi><hi rend="italic superscript
                    smallcaps"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic subscript smallcaps"> j λ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic smallcaps"> ,</hi><hi rend="superscript"> l</hi> '~ 2r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3 +</hi> 2r <hi rend="superscript"> δ, U</hi> ~ 6r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3 +</hi><hi rend="italic">4r</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 5</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi> and we shall have <hi rend="italic"
                    >, dx , , ,dx</hi><hi rend="italic">x° = vx -ŧ~ u -1-</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> t</hi><hi rend="italic">X</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">vx + u'</hi><hi rend="italic">—.</hi><hi rend="italic">at
                    at</hi></p>
                <p>It is evident that <hi rend="italic">y° y'</hi> and <hi rend="italic">z° zĩ</hi>
                    may be expressed exactly in the same manner; hence the co-ordinates of the comet
                    at the first and third observations are given in terms of its co-ordinates at
                    the middle observation and their differential co-efficients, by the following
                    system of equations, due to Lagrange:</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> λ</hi> d⅛ , , <hi rend="italic">. dx^^</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">X° = vx</hi> 4- W — <hi rend="italic">Xf</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">V</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">X ∙i~ U'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic smallcaps"> -γ^</hi><hi rend="italic">~ dt ~ dt</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">= vy
                    + u⅛</hi> y = <hi rend="italic">dy</hi> 4- √ ⅛ &gt; (ŋ</p>
                <p>o <hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> dz</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">, , ,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dz</hi><hi rend="italic">z° =</hi><hi rend="italic">vz</hi> 4- <hi
                    rend="italic">u —</hi><hi rend="italic">ź = ťz</hi> 4- <hi rend="italic"
                    >u'</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> τ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">-</hi><hi rend="italic">dt _ dt</hi></p>
                <p>If from these equations we eliminate ⅞,⅛,^r, we shall <hi rend="italic">at at
                    at</hi> find, on making <hi rend="italic">w</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">vυ!</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">v'u,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">u'x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> a</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">ux</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">= wx, u'y°</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">uy'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">wy, u'z°</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">uz' ~
                    wz;</hi> (2) but from the values of <hi rend="italic">v, u, v', u',</hi> given
                    above, we have evidently <hi rend="subscript strikethrough smallcaps"> w</hi><hi
                    rend="strikethrough                     smallcaps"> = (^</hi><hi rend="subscript
                    strikethrough smallcaps"> +</hi><hi rend="strikethrough
                    smallcaps"> ^)</hi><hi rend="subscript strikethrough
                    smallcaps"> +</hi><hi rend="strikethrough smallcaps"> (L+</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript strikethrough smallcaps"> 3</hi><hi rend="strikethrough
                    smallcaps"> ⅞</hi><hi rend="subscript strikethrough smallcaps"> +</hi> + G-đ);
                    therefore, by eliminating <hi rend="italic">v, u,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >w,</hi> from equations (2), there results <hi rend="italic">x(i1°ζ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">y</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">z°)</hi>-J- <hi
                    rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">(z°x</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">z'x°)</hi>-f- <hi
                    rend="italic">z(x°yf</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">y°) =</hi> 0, an equation to
                    a plane, which denotes that the three points C <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>,
                    C, C', are situated in the same plane with S, the origin of the
                    co-ordinates.</p>
                <p>2. Let the chord of the arc C <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> C' intersect the
                    radius</p>
                <p>SC in D, and let the ratio of C <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> D to C'D be that
                    of λ to λ'. Make λ -fλ' = 1, and the chord C <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> C'
                    <hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> we have
                    then C <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> D = λc and C'D = λ'c. Farther, let DC =
                    <hi rend="italic">er,</hi> so that SD = <hi rend="italic">τ</hi> (1 — <hi
                    rend="italic">e),</hi><hi rend="italic">e</hi> being an infinitely small
                    quantity of the second order in respect of <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">O',</hi> which are supposed infinitesimals of the first order.</p>
                <p>In order to find the ratio of λ to λ', suppose the three points C <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi>, D, C', to be projected on the plane of the ecliptic;
                    then the projections of the lines C <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> D and C'D
                    will necessarilybe to one another in the same ratio as these lines themselves,
                    that is, as λ to λ'. But the co-ordinates of the projections of C <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi>, D, and C', in the direction of the axis of <hi
                    rend="italic">X,</hi> are respectively <hi rend="italic">x°,</hi> (1 — <hi
                    rend="italic">e) x,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">,∙</hi> therefore also (1 — <hi
                    rend="italic">e)</hi><hi rend="italic">X</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >∙.x</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">—</hi> (1 — <hi rend="italic">e) x</hi>:: λ: λ',
                    whence</p>
                <p>λ {a∕ — (1 — <hi rend="italic">e) x} =</hi> λ' {(1 — <hi rend="italic">e)
                    x</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">x°}</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    and, since λ 4- λ' = 1,</p>
                <p>λa∕ 4- λ⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> = (1 — <hi rend="italic">e)</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">X.</hi></p>
                <p>Substituting in this last equation the values of ŉ/ and <hi rend="italic"
                    >x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 0</hi> given by equations (1), we get <hi
                    rend="italic">dx</hi><hi rend="italic">(λv</hi> ’ + λ'y) <hi rend="italic"
                    >X</hi> 4- (λu' 4- <hi rend="italic">λ'u)</hi> — = (1 — <hi rend="italic">e)
                    x</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and by proceeding in the same manner, we shall
                    find relatively to <hi rend="italic">y</hi> and <hi rend="italic">z,</hi></p>
                <p>(λ√ 4- λ⅛) <hi rend="italic">y</hi> 4- (λu' 4- λ'w)^ = (1— <hi rend="italic"
                    >e)y</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">dz</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(λυ</hi> ’ 4- <hi rend="italic">λ</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">v)</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">z</hi> 4- <hi rend="italic">(λu'</hi> 4- λ'u) — = (1 — <hi
                    rend="italic">e) z.</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> τ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >.</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic">.
                    dx</hi><hi rend="italic">da dz</hi></p>
                <p>In these last equations the quantities <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >y</hi><hi rend="italic">z,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> —, are independent of
                    any particular values of <hi rend="italic">vu</hi><hi rend="italic">d u'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> they cannot therefore hold true, unless we have also the
                    two equations of condition λv' 4- <hi rend="italic">λ'v =</hi> 1 — <hi
                    rend="italic">e,</hi> and λw' 4- <hi rend="italic">λu</hi> = 0. Joining to these
                    the equation λ4-λ' = l,we shall have, in order to determine <hi rend="italic">λ,
                    λ',</hi> and <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> the following system of equations:</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">λv</hi> ’ 4- <hi rend="italic">λ'v =</hi> 1 — <hi rend="italic"
                    >e, λu'</hi> 4- <hi rend="italic">λ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> u</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> 0, λ 4- λ' = 1. (3)</p>
                <p>From the second and third of these we get λ = ———, <hi rend="italic">u'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi></p>
                <p>λ' ≡ — —; and consequently from the first, 1 — <hi rend="italic">e</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ĩt!v</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">uť w</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> ττ</hi><hi rend="subscript"> =</hi><hi rend="subscript"
                    > =</hi>, Hence <hi rend="italic">u'</hi><hi rend="italic">U ιl'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic">λ =</hi>, λ' = , 1
                    — <hi rend="italic">e =</hi>. (4)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">τc</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u u!</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—u</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> x ,</hi></p>
                <p>The accuracy of the values now found of λ, λ', and <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> will
                    depend on the number of terms of the series represented by <hi rend="italic">u,
                    u</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">w,</hi> that are taken
                    into account. We shall distinguish three different degrees of approximation.</p>
                <p>I. Retaining only the first terms of the series, or those which depend on the
                    simple powers of <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> and ff, we have <hi rend="italic">u
                    =</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">ô, u' = ff, w</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">&amp;</hi> 4- <hi rend="italic">ô,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">τι</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u = 0'
                    -ļ-ô,</hi> whence</p>
                <p>λ = * = e = 0; (5)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">ô'</hi> 4- <hi rend="italic">ô ô'</hi> 4- <hi rend="italic"
                    >â</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> v 7</hi> consequently - <hi
                    rend="subscript"> z</hi> = ~, that is to say, the chord which joins λ u'</p>
                <p>the places of the comet at the extreme observations is divided, by the radius
                    vector belonging to the middle observation, into segments proportional to the
                    intervals between the observations.- This is the approximation of Newton <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:194749118?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9118-0142"/> and
                    01bers. In the method we are about to follow, the results thus obtained serve
                    only to direct the subsequent calculations.</p>
                <p>IL By including a second term of the series represented by <hi rend="italic">u,
                    υ!,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">w,</hi> we have <hi rend="italic">ô 6'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">~</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> u</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    i</hi><hi rend="italic">~W'</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> u</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">'=</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript">
                    6</hi><hi rend="italic">~^</hi></p>
                <p>(ff 4. ø) <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>, <hi rend="subscript"> a</hi>, <hi
                    rend="subscript"> λ</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> ô'</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript smallcaps"> 3</hi> + 0 <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">w = V</hi> + đ + <hi rend="superscript"> k</hi>-⅛Γ-, <hi
                    rend="italic">W-u=0 + Ô</hi> θ≡-, whence <hi rend="italic">∕ 0</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >_</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi> 6r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ∕ _ <hi rend="italic">ô</hi><hi rend="italic
                    underline"> 6r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript underline"> 3</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> λi i λ</hi> 0' <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>-∣-0 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> 0'+ <hi rend="italic">ô</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">ff'</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    i</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> —</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> ôô -]-
                    0</hi><hi rend="italic superscript underline"> i</hi><hi rend="superscript">
                    ff</hi> + <hi rend="superscript"> θ</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 6r</hi> Γ — 6r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> and therefore by division <hi rend="italic">ô</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">ffô Ô'—Ô</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> λ</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">ff±ô</hi> + 0 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> z</hi> + <hi rend="italic">ô'</hi> 6r <hi rend="superscript"
                    > 3</hi> ’</p>
                <p>In like manner, from the equation λ' = — we find <hi rend="italic superscript">
                    1</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >u</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">_ &amp; &amp;Ô Ô' —
                    Ô</hi><hi rend="superscript"> λ</hi> ~ ľ+~0 ~ F+ <hi rend="italic">ô ‘</hi> 6r
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> *</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> ff</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic subscript"> 0</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">-(l±Δ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> τ</hi>, <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> 6r <hi rend="superscript"
                    > 3</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> 30'0</p>
                <p>Butl-e _ <hi rend="subscript"> =</hi><hi rend="italic">ô</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> +</hi><hi rend="italic">ô</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi></p>
                <p>Whence we have in this case the following values of λ, λ', and e, namely, <hi
                    rend="italic">_</hi><hi rend="italic">ô</hi><hi rend="italic">ô'ô /0'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> 0∖ '</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> λ</hi>- øųľļj + 0'4.0 ∖~6T <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>
                    ")</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ff</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >∙</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ff6</hi><hi rend="italic">(</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> û</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> è</hi><hi rend="italic">\ ∕n</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">~ ô'+ ô ~ ff^+~0</hi> k~6Τ <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ^ <hi
                    rend="italic">J</hi> j <hi rend="italic">Ô’Ô</hi> I</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic superscript"> e</hi><hi rend="italic">~ 2r</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 3</hi> J</p>
                <p>The values of λ, λ', and e, thus found, will be sufficiently exact in ordinary
                    cases; but it will sometimes be necessary to carry the approximation farther,
                    and to include the third terms of the series represented by <hi rend="italic">u,
                    u',</hi> and <hi rend="italic">w.</hi></p>
                <p>III. In order to obtain convenient expressions when a third term of the series is
                    taken into account, it will be necessary to introduce the extreme radii vectores
                    <hi rend="italic">r°</hi> and <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> For this purpose we may
                    suppose <hi rend="italic">r° = r</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dr,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">d τdτ</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi>-ļ- <hi rend="italic">dr</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but we
                    have already assumed <hi rend="italic">k</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> therefore
                    <hi rend="italic">dr</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> — —. Hence <hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">γ</hi><hi rend="italic">lìô</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">r° = r</hi><hi rend="italic">—,</hi><hi rend="italic">r°r =
                    7</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">kô,</hi><hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 5</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 3</hi> whence (r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> r) <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">kô,</hi> and consequently <hi
                    rend="underline">i</hi> _ <hi rend="underline">ł</hi> _ _ı_ <hi rend="subscript"
                    > +</hi><hi rend="italic">kô_ Q(r°ry</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi> 6r <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> — 4ÄØ 6r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 4r <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi></p>
                <p>In the same manner we find <hi rend="underline">1</hi> _ <hi rend="underline"
                    >ĭ</hi> _ J <hi rend="italic                     underline"> k(f</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Q(rd')</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> 6r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi>-∣- <hi rend="italic">⅛k(ff Qr</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 3</hi> 4r <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi></p>
                <p>Substituting these expressions in the series denoted by <hi rend="italic">u</hi>
                    and ι√, we get</p>
                <p>- <hi rend="subscript"> κ</hi> = <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> fι- * ι <hi
                    rend="subscript"> t</hi>,=,∣ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> —</p>
                <p>I 6(r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> r) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> J I 6(rr')
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> J</p>
                <p>f <hi rend="italic">ô'</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ô</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi> ļ</p>
                <p>w' — <hi rend="italic">u = 0</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">+ 6</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi> J 3- -I 3 I; t6(rr') <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 6(r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi> r) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> J</p>
                <p>consequently,</p>
                <p>√ <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ——4</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi> _ I 6 <hi rend="underline"
                    >(r</hi><hi rend="superscript underline"> 0</hi><hi rend="underline">r)</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript underline"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> J</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> u</hi> '~ <hi rend="superscript"> u</hi> ^ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> + ð</hi> _f_Éĩ_ <hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> _2ì_ ì t6(rr <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi>) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 6(r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> r ’) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> J</p>
                <p>whence by division, <hi rend="italic">ô ô’ô ( ' tf</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> z</hi><hi rend="italic">S</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    i</hi> Ί</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> λ</hi>- __ <hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> J I</p>
                <p>0'4-0 (0 <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> 4_ 0)2 (θ(rr') <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> 6(r <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> r) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    J</p>
                <p>By proceeding in a similar manner with respect to λ', we find <hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> χ</hi><hi rend="italic">, _</hi><hi rend="italic
                    underline"> ôf</hi><hi rend="underline">0</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">
                    ,</hi><hi rend="underline">0</hi> j <hi rend="underline">ff</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript underline"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> ô</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript underline"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">
                    λ</hi></p>
                <p>0'4-0 (0'4-0)2 I6(rr') <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 6(r°r≠J*</p>
                <p>To find <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> we have in this case</p>
                <p>_ <hi rend="subscript"> w</hi> _ <hi rend="superscript"> β</hi> +</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> c-m,-m</hi> ~ <hi rend="superscript"> i,</hi> + <hi
                    rend="superscript"> i</hi>-∙⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> f</hi>-+⅛</p>
                <p>- <hi rend="superscript underline"> (¢,÷¢)</hi> c+o { <hi rend="superscript">
                    1</hi>-^=⅛&gt;- +⅛(^ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +oσ→} hence, on dividing and
                    neglecting the terms which involve the fourth and higher powers of 0 and 0', <hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> 1 1</hi><hi rend="italic">ô'ô kffôbff — ô)</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 7 <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> = <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi>-^ + -⅛≡ <hi rend="superscript"> lj</hi> ∙</p>
                <p>But <hi rend="italic">r° =r</hi><hi rend="italic">——,</hi><hi rend="italic">d
                    —r</hi> 4- —, therefore <hi rend="italic">r°rd</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> r
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> 4- <hi rend="italic">k τ τ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >k^&amp;ô</hi></p>
                <p>(0' — 0) <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic">— ——.</hi> The last term of
                    this expression is a quantity of the order of those that may be neglected;
                    therefore simply <hi rend="underline">1</hi> _ <hi rend="underline">1</hi> j <hi
                    rend="underline">⅞(^-Q</hi></p>
                <p>4_ <hi rend="italic">k(0</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">— Ô)r r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ď</hi></p>
                <p>Substituting this in the above expression for 1 — <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> it
                    becomes</p>
                <p>. , 00' <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">ô'ô</hi></p>
                <p>1 — <hi rend="italic">e</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> 1 — ———-, whence e — s <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 7—Γ∙ 2r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> rr' ’ <hi
                    rend="italic">2r rd</hi></p>
                <p>It follows, therefore, that ⅛his third degree of approximation gives</p>
                <p>_ <hi rend="underline">0</hi><hi rend="underline">0</hi><hi rend="superscript
                    underline"> ,</hi><hi rend="underline">0</hi> j 0^ _ <hi rend="underline"
                    >0</hi><hi rend="superscript underline"> 2</hi> ļ '</p>
                <p>0'4- 0 (0'4_ 0) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> I <hi rend="italic">Q(rr</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">Q(r°ry~</hi> J</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> λ</hi>.= Jl ⅛ <hi rend="subscript"> (î)</hi></p>
                <p>0*4-0 (0'4- 0) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> I 6(r∕) 6(r <hi rend="superscript">
                    0</hi> r) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> J</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">-</hi><hi rend="italic superscript underline"> ôô</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">2r°rd</hi></p>
                <p>3. We now proceed to apply the above results to the solution of the problem.</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">a°, a, a',</hi> be the three geocentric longitudes of the
                    comet at the instants of the first, second, and third observations respectively;
                    <hi rend="italic">b°, b, b',</hi> its three geocentric latitudes; g <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">g, g</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> the three curtate distances, that
                    is to say, the three distances of the comet from the earth projected on the
                    plane of the ecliptic; A <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, A, A', the three
                    corresponding heliocentric longitudes of the earth; and R <hi rend="superscript"
                    > o</hi>, R, R', the three radii vectores of the earth. Finally, let X <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi> Y <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> &gt; XY, X'Y', be
                    the co-ordinates of the earth, referred to the centre of the sun, so that <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:194749131?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9131-0143"/> X
                    <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> = R <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> cos. A <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi>, X — R cos. A, X' = 'R∕ cos. A' ì z <hi
                    rend="subscript"> β</hi> × Y <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> = R <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> sin. A <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, Y = R sin. A,
                    Y' = R' sin. A <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> J × ' For the sake of abridging,
                    let us assume <hi rend="italic">γn°</hi> = cos. <hi rend="italic">a° n</hi><hi
                    rend="italic                     superscript"> 0</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi>
                    sin. <hi rend="italic">a° p° =</hi> tan. ò°ì</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">m</hi> — cos. <hi rend="italic">a n</hi> — sin. <hi
                    rend="italic">a p</hi> — tan. <hi rend="italic">b &gt;</hi> (9)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">m'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> cos. <hi rend="italic">a!
                    n'</hi> = sin. <hi rend="italic">a! p'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> tan. <hi
                    rend="italic">b'</hi> J</p>
                <p>then, on transferring the origin of the co-ordinates from the centre of the sun
                    to the earth, we shall have relatively to the points C <hi rend="superscript">
                    o</hi>, C, C', <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 0</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">= m° ξ°</hi> + X <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">X
                    -</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> m</hi><hi rend="italic">ξ,</hi> + X <hi
                    rend="italic">x'=m'</hi><hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">- X')</hi> y <hi rend="superscript">
                    o</hi> = n <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> g <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>-fY
                    <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 3/ = W f + Y <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">~</hi><hi rend="superscript"> n</hi> ' ť + Y' ŗ ( ιθ)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">z</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> a</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 0</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ξ°</hi><hi rend="italic">Z —</hi><hi rend="italic">p ļ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Z —</hi><hi rend="italic">p'</hi><hi rend="italic">g )</hi></p>
                <p>It has already been shown (2) that</p>
                <p>λ ť -Jλ' <hi rend="italic">x°</hi> = ( 1 — e) <hi rend="italic">x,</hi> and it is
                    obvious that the same condition must be fulfilled in regard to <hi rend="italic"
                    >y</hi> and <hi rend="italic">z,</hi> or the projection of the chord C <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> C' on the other two co-ordinate planes. Hence we have
                    the following system of equations :—</p>
                <p>λ a∕ + λ' <hi rend="italic">x°</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> (1 — e) <hi
                    rend="italic">X = O')</hi><hi rend="italic">λy</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">+
                    λ'y</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">—(1-e)y = OÍ
                    (11)</hi></p>
                <p>λ <hi rend="italic">z</hi> ’ 4- λ' <hi rend="italic">z°</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi> (1 — <hi rend="italic">e) z</hi> = 0j</p>
                <p>Substituting in these last equations (10) the values of ae, <hi rend="italic"
                    >y</hi><hi rend="italic">z, x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">y° z</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> a</hi><hi rend="italic">,
                    x! y'</hi> given in equations (9), and making at the same time</p>
                <p>M = λX'+ λ'X <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> — (1 — e)Xi , <hi rend="subscript">
                    λ</hi></p>
                <p>N = λY' + λ'Y <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> — (1 — e)Y∫ &lt; <hi
                    rend="superscript"> i</hi> &lt; ’ we obtain</p>
                <p>0 — λ <hi rend="italic">m'</hi> g' 4- λ' <hi rend="italic">m° ξ°</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> (1 — <hi rend="italic">e) m ξ</hi> 4- Mļ</p>
                <p>0 = λ <hi rend="italic subscript"> n</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">į</hi> 4- λ' <hi
                    rend="italic">n°</hi><hi rend="italic                     smallcaps"> p°</hi> —
                    (1 — e) <hi rend="italic">11 e</hi> 4- N &gt; (13)</p>
                <p>0 = <hi rend="subscript"> λ</hi> χ <hi rend="subscript"> f</hi> '+ λ' <hi
                    rend="subscript"> j</hi> o°f-(l-&lt;0 2&gt;f )</p>
                <p>on which equations the solution of the problem essentially depends. Before we
                    proceed to their discussion, however, it will be necessary to find more
                    convenient expressions for M and N.</p>
                <p>4. In order to express X <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> Y <hi rend="superscript">
                    o</hi>, X ’ Y <hi rend="superscript"> z</hi>, the co-ordinates of the earth,
                    which belong to the extreme observations, in a function of the time, and of the
                    co-ordinates X Y relative to the time <hi rend="italic">ô</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi> 0, let us assume, as in § 2.</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> v</hi> _ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> đ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> Kđ <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="subscript"
                    > ττ</hi> _ , đ <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ≡</p>
                <p>2R <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> 2R <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> ’ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> +</hi> 2R <hi rend="superscript"> 3 +</hi> 4R5’</p>
                <p>V- = 1-J <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> _ ÍSf U' = ^-A. <hi rend="subscript">
                    +</hi> Σ"2,</p>
                <p>2R <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> 2R <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> ' 2R, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3 +</hi> 4R <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> and we shall
                    have</p>
                <p>χ <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> = VX 4- U —, X' = V'X 4- U' ~; the symbols V, U,
                    R, K, having now the same signification relatively to the orbit of the earth
                    which <hi rend="italic">v, u, r, k,</hi> had before relatively to the orbit of
                    the comet.</p>
                <p>Inconsequence of these last equations, and of the equations (4), we have <hi
                    rend="subscript"> v</hi> wV' <hi rend="subscript"> v</hi><hi rend="italic">uU'
                    dX</hi></p>
                <p>A X <hi rend="superscript"> z</hi> — <hi rend="italic">∙ X</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi>. —7-</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">u u</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> f</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">zι at</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u u'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">u at</hi></p>
                <p>(i- <hi rend="subscript"> e</hi>)X =-^L,χ, <hi rend="italic superscript">
                    z</hi><hi rend="italic">u'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi>
                    and substituting these values, in the first of equations (12), <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi></p>
                <p>M=≤y= <hi rend="italic underline"> uN'—w</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    χ</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> u'U-u</hi><hi rend="italic underline">
                    ∖</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> J'</hi><hi rend="italic">dX</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">u'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u ‘ u'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u dt '</hi></p>
                <p>Substituting now for <hi rend="italic">u', u, N, N',</hi> their values in terms
                    of đ and <hi rend="italic">O',</hi> we obtain w'V — wV ’ — J' 4~ 0 —</p>
                <p>2R <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi></p>
                <p>^ <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> 4-d <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>, /Kđ’đ ,</p>
                <p>Gr <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> + ∖ 2R <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> ÷ 4 <hi
                    rend="subscript"> r</hi> 5 ) (<hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> ' <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi>) ’</p>
                <p>but <hi rend="superscript"> w</hi> '- <hi rend="superscript"> w</hi> = <hi
                    rend="superscript"> d</hi> '+ <hi rend="superscript"> d</hi> ~⅛ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> f</hi><hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> therefore, by dividing,
                    and retaining only the terms which do not exceed the third order in respect of
                    &amp;' and <hi rend="italic">ũ,</hi><hi rend="italic">u'N</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">uV</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">d'ô</hi> Kċľđ . <hi
                    rend="subscript"> λ</hi><hi rend="italic">u' — u ~</hi> ~ 2R <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3 +</hi> 2Ĩĭð</p>
                <p>whence w'V— <hi rend="italic">uN'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">w
                    ff∂</hi> Kđ'J z <hi rend="subscript"> j</hi>, <hi rend="subscript"> x</hi></p>
                <p>—Í7~,;— = <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi>-2IΓ <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> + 2ÎP
                    &lt;'-^∙</p>
                <p>In like manner we have</p>
                <p>,υ-.σ = '¾^&gt;⅛-⅛) <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> _ .</p>
                <p>therefore, by division, <hi rend="underline">√U</hi><hi rend="underline"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic                     underline"> u</hi><hi rend="italic
                    underline"> ∖</hi><hi rend="italic                     underline"> J'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">_</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> ð'ð(ô'— ð)</hi> /J_ 1_\</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">u'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi> 6 ∖r
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> R <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ∕"</p>
                <p>The value of M therefore becomes <hi rend="superscript"> m</hi> = { <hi
                    rend="superscript"> e</hi>-⅜+⅛≈&lt;*→} <hi rend="superscript"> κ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> ι</hi><hi rend="italic">ð'ô(ð’ — Ô) ſĩ l</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">dX</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    +</hi><hi rend="italic">6</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">ll</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">J dť</hi></p>
                <p>∂'∂ Kíľđ It will be remarked that the quantity <hi rend="subscript"> p</hi>- 4-
                    —— (∂'—∂) is exactly analogous to that which has already been denoted by <hi
                    rend="italic">e.</hi> Let us therefore suppose it to be represented, by E, and
                    the last equation will become <hi rend="smallcaps">,,≡&lt;,-</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript smallcaps"> 1</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">,x</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript smallcaps"> +</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">^⅛2&gt;(⅜-⅛⅞,</hi> but on
                    rejecting quantities involving higher powers than the third of Ĵ and J', we have
                    obviously</p>
                <p>___ (<hi rend="subscript"> e</hi> _ E) - <hi rend="subscript"> lp</hi> J ,
                    therefore ultimately <hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 7</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >,</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> τ</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">∕ γλ</hi> fv d
                    <hi rend="superscript"> z</hi> — đ &lt;ZX 1</p>
                <p>M-(β-E) ļX 4.—ļ.</p>
                <p>Since the epoch or instant from which the time is reckoned is supposed to fall on
                    the second observation, it is evident that — - is the instant corresponding to
                    the mean time of the three observations. Let the value of X at this instant be
                    denoted by X <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, and the corresponding values of R and
                    A by R <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> and A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, then</p>
                <p>M = <hi rend="italic">(e—</hi> E)X <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>.</p>
                <p>By proceeding exactly in the same manner with regard to N, we shall find</p>
                <p>N = <hi rend="italic">(e</hi> — E)Y <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>; therefore, on
                    substituting for X and Y their values in terms of R and A, we have at the mean
                    time of the three observations</p>
                <p>M = <hi rend="italic">(e —</hi> E) R <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> cos. A <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> 1 <hi rend="subscript"> fi4</hi> χ</p>
                <p>N <hi rend="italic">= (e—</hi> E) R <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> sin. A <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ĵ &lt; <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> *'</p>
                <p>5. We now resume the equations (13). The unknown quantities which they contain
                    are the three curtate distances <hi rend="italic">ξ° ğ g',</hi> together with
                    <hi rend="italic">r,</hi> the radius vector of the comet, which is involved in
                    the values of λ, λ', and e. They may be combined in various ways, and the
                    different combinations will afford so many different expressions for <hi
                    rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">,
                    g,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> f</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">,</hi> which will be more or less easily computed according to the
                    circumstances of the case. The most obvious solution<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194749144?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9144-0144"/> will be
                    obtained by eliminating g <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                    >g,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">g'.</hi> For this purpose the third of equations
                    (13) gives</p>
                <p>O — <hi rend="underline">(</hi><hi rend="superscript underline"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="italic underline"> ~</hi><hi rend="italic superscript underline">
                    e</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> )Pξ~ ×p'¢</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    S</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">'p°</hi> ’ and on substituting
                    this value of g <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> in the first and second of these
                    equations, they become respectively 0 — <hi rend="italic">(m'p°</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">m°p</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">'')</hi> λg ’ ~p <hi rend="italic"
                    >(m°p</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">mp°</hi>) (1 — <hi
                    rend="italic">e^)</hi><hi rend="italic">g</hi> + ∕&gt; <hi rend="superscript">
                    0</hi> M 0 = <hi rend="italic">(n</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    o</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">n°p</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">')</hi> λ^' 4- <hi rend="italic"
                    >(n°p</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">np°)</hi> (1 — <hi
                    rend="italic">e)</hi><hi rend="italic">g</hi> 4~ ∕&gt; <hi rend="superscript">
                    o</hi> N. On eliminating λ <hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi> from the two equations now found, we get <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">(n'p°</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">p')</hi> M — <hi rend="italic"
                    >(m'p°</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">- m°p</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">)</hi> N</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 1 — <hi rend="italic">∙e (m</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">p°</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">m°p</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">)
                    (n°p</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">np° )</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">( m°p</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">mp°
                    ) ( n</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">p°</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">n °p</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    ,</hi><hi rend="italic">)</hi> an equation which becomes by reduction</p>
                <p>1 (rø°N — ⅞ <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> M) <hi rend="underline">τ&gt;'</hi><hi
                    rend="underline">—</hi><hi rend="underline">(ffl'N -</hi> —n'M)7&gt; <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi></p>
                <p>1— <hi rend="italic">e (m</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> l</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">m°n')p</hi> 4- <hi rend="italic">(mn'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">nι'n)p</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    o</hi>-ļ- <hi rend="italic">(m°n</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >mn</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> n</hi><hi rend="italic">)p</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi> and on restoring the
                    values of M, N, <hi rend="italic">in, n, p,</hi> &amp;c. given by equations (14)
                    and (9), and recollecting that sin. <hi rend="italic">(x</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi> y) = sin. <hi rend="italic">x</hi> cos. <hi rend="italic">y —</hi> cos.
                    <hi rend="italic">x</hi> sin. <hi rend="italic">y,</hi> we get e—E <hi
                    rend="subscript"> n</hi> g— ļ ~ ' *ι ×</p>
                <p>sin. (A, — <hi rend="italic">a°^)</hi> ta <hi rend="underline">n. Ž/</hi><hi
                    rend="underline">—</hi><hi rend="underline">sin.</hi><hi rend="underline
                    smallcaps"> (A</hi><hi rend="subscript underline smallcaps"> i</hi><hi
                    rend="underline">—</hi><hi rend="underline">α') tan. Z&gt;</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript underline"> o</hi> sin(α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> —β')
                    <hi rend="superscript"> tan</hi> ∙^* + sin.(α'—α)tan∙Z&gt; <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 4- sin.(o-Ω <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>)tan.Z∕ × '
                    <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> '</p>
                <p>Let us assume</p>
                <p>P=sin,(A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> —β <hi rend="superscript">
                    o</hi>)tan.6'—sin.(A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> —α')tan.δ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi></p>
                <p>Q=sin.(o <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> —α')tan.Z&gt; 4- sin.(α'—α)tan.Z&gt; <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> 4- sin.(α—α <hi rend="superscript">
                    0</hi>)tan.Z&gt;∖∙ this assumption gives</p>
                <p>__P <hi rend="superscript underline"> c</hi><hi rend="underline">~</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript underline"> e</hi><hi rend="subscript"> π</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">eQ</hi> ’ 1 __ <hi rend="subscript"> e</hi> ' 1’</p>
                <p>but on carrying the approximation only to quantities of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >„</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">. e</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> E <hi rend="italic">ð'ð ſ</hi> 1 1 λ</p>
                <p>third order in respcctot the tιme,-j — — — í—ŗ = <hi rend="italic">j</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi></p>
                <p>MPR therefore if we make —ğQ~ <hi rend="superscript"> =</hi> ¼ the last equation
                    will become g = <hi rend="superscript"> 7i</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(ţš</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> ' pa) (<hi rend="superscript"> 16</hi>)</p>
                <p>6. The equation which has now been obtained contains two unknown quantities <hi
                    rend="italic">g</hi> and <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but
                    another equation between the same variables may be readily found from the
                    equations (10). These give, on restoring the values of <hi rend="italic">m,
                    n,p,</hi> X, and Y <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">X</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">ô</hi> cos. <hi rend="italic">a</hi> 4- R
                    cos. A, <hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">= ô</hi> sin. <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> 4- R sin. A, <hi rend="italic">z =</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >g</hi> tan. <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> whence, by squaring and adding a? <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 4 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> ⅛ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,2</hi> + * <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — g <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (l + tan. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> δ) 4-
                    2fRcos.(A — <hi rend="italic">a)</hi> 4- R <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; but
                    <hi rend="italic">a?</hi> 4- w <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 4- z <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = r <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; and 1 4- tan. <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 6 = —ι <hi rend="subscript"> 737</hi>-; <hi
                    rend="superscript"> τ j</hi> ‘ ~ cos.¾</p>
                <p>therefore r <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = R <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 4-
                    <hi rend="italic">2g</hi> R cos. (A — α) 4- —Ł— (17)</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> b y</hi> cos. <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi></p>
                <p>We have now arrived at two equations between <hi rend="italic">r</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">g,</hi> by means óf which the values of those quantities become
                    known. In order to eliminate r, let equation (16) be put under the form <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(ħ</hi> 4- R⅞) = ΛR <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>, the square of which is r
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi> (Ä 4- R <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> g) <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = Λ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> R <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 6</hi>; then, by substituting in this the value of <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 6</hi> given by equation (17)
                    raised to the cube, there results { R <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + ?£ R cos·
                    (A - <hi rend="italic">a)</hi><hi rend="subscript"> +</hi>-L j . (A <hi
                    rend="subscript"> +</hi> R⅞)≡ = Λ¾≡, an equation of the eighth degree in respect
                    of the unknown quantity <hi rend="italic">g.</hi> It is evident, however, that
                    on being developed, Λ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> R <hi rend="superscript">
                    6</hi> will disappear from both sides of it, after which the whole will be
                    divisible by <hi rend="italic">g</hi>; it belongs, therefore, in fact, only to
                    the seventh degree. On being resolved by approximation it will give a value of
                    <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> but in practice it is more commodious to determine <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi> and <hi rend="italic">g</hi> simultaneously from the
                    equations (16) and (17), by the ordinary methods of false position.</p>
                <p>7. Although the equations (16) and (17) thus appear to lead to a complete
                    solution of the problem, it seldom happens in practice that an orbit can be
                    determined in this manner. The reason of this is, that the quantity which we
                    have represented by Q is always very small (it is not difficult to prove that it
                    is óf the third order in respect of <hi rend="italic">đ),</hi> and liable to be
                    greatly affected by the errors of observation. If Q — 0, we have the equation
                    sin.(α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> —ď)tan.Z&lt;4-sin.(ď—α)tan.δ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 4-sin.(α—α <hi rend="superscript">
                    o</hi>)tan.Z&gt;'=0, which denotes that the three apparent places of the comet
                    are situated in the same great circle of the sphere. The value of Q therefore
                    depends solely on the deviation of the comet's apparent path from a great circle
                    of the heavens, during the short interval between the extreme observations; and
                    this deviation is in general so small, that a slight error of observation, which
                    it is impossible to guard against, may cause it to become evanescent, or even to
                    change its sigŋ. On this account the equation (16), which is called by Legendre
                    the <hi rend="italic">doubtful equation,</hi> can only be employed in very
                    favourable circumstances; and it becomes necessary, in the greater number of
                    cases, to have recourse to other methods of solution. Some conclusions may,
                    however, be deduced from it, which will materially assist in guiding the
                    subsequent calculations.</p>
                <p>In the first place, as the curtate distance <hi rend="italic">g</hi> is
                    necessarily a finite quantity, if the denominator of the fraction expressed by
                    <hi rend="italic">h</hi> vanishes, that is, if Q = 0, the numerator must vanish
                    at the same time. Now this can happen only in two ways: either by supposing P =
                    0, or ∙i- = <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> jτy∙ If we suppose P = 0, we have the
                    equation sin. (A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> — α <hi rend="superscript">
                    0</hi>) tan. Z&gt;' — sin. (A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> — α') tan. <hi
                    rend="italic">b°</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> 0, which indicates that the place
                    of the sun at the instant <hi rend="italic">ff ŷ</hi></p>
                <p>—3—, corresponding to the mean time of the three observations, is situated in the
                    same great circle of the sphere with the three apparent places of the comet. Now
                    it is easy to see, that although the sun may not be exactly in the same great
                    circle with the three apparent places of the comet, yet if it is near one of the
                    intersections of that circle with the ecliptic, the quantity P will be very
                    small, and the equation (16) in consequence will not lead to any satisfactory
                    result.</p>
                <p>In the second place, if Q vanishes while the value of P continues so great that
                    its sign would not be changed by supposing its component parts to vary to the
                    extent of the errors of observation, we must then have -Ļ = rL· or <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">τ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> i</hi> R <hi rend="superscript"> j</hi></p>
                <p>R; that is to say, the comet and the earth are at the same distance from the sun.
                    This circumstance, therefore, also renders equation (16) indeterminate. It maybe
                    remarked, however, that in this case we obtain an easy approximation to the
                    value of <hi rend="italic">g</hi> from equation (17), which, when <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi> is equal to R, becomes <hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">= 2</hi> R cos. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >b</hi> cos. (180 4- A — <hi rend="italic">a),</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194749157?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9157-0145"/> where 180 4- A
                    is the longitude of the sun at the instant of the middle observation.</p>
                <p>In the third place, when the quantities P and Q are both so great that their
                    signs can be determined without ambiguity, equation (16) will show whether the
                    distance of the comet from the sun is greater or less than the radius vector of
                    the earth. For since <hi rend="italic">g</hi> is necessarily posi-</p>
                <p>p tive, the sign of — must be the same as that of <hi rend="italic">e</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> E or</p>
                <p>11 p</p>
                <p>—-; consequently, the sign of being known, we also know whether <hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi> is greater or less than R.</p>
                <p>8. Since the state of the observations will seldom permit equation (16) to be
                    employed with advantage, it becomes necessary to attempt some other combination
                    of the three fundamental equations (13). Instead of eliminating the three
                    curtate distances g, g <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, g' from these equations,
                    we may determine two of them, for example g <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> and
                    g', in terms of the third, g; by which means we shall obtain at least the ratios
                    of these distances to one another. This may be effected in various ways; but we
                    shall confine ourselves to the two following combinations, the one or other of
                    which will be applicable in every case.</p>
                <p>Let the first of the equations (13) be multiplied by N, and the second by M; the
                    difference of the products is χg'(Nm' Mzι') + λ'g <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>
                    (NMi <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> —.M∕ι <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>)—(
                    1—e)g(NMi—Mzι) —0.</p>
                <p>Combining this with the third equation, so as to eliminate first g' and then g
                    <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, we get <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi> __ <hi
                    rend="underline">(l</hi><hi rend="underline">—</hi><hi rend="underline"
                    >e)g</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(Nmi</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">—</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Mm)</hi> ∕f — <hi rend="smallcaps">(Nmi'</hi> — Mn')/* £ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> λ' (Nffi <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> — <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Mm</hi><hi rend="superscript                     smallcaps">
                    0</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">)//</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">—</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(Nmi'</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">—</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Mm')</hi><hi rend="italic">p°</hi></p>
                <p>_ (1—e)g (‰ <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> — <hi rend="smallcaps">Mm</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> o</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">)</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(Nmi</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">—</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Mm)</hi><hi rend="italic">p°</hi> λ
                    (Nm <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> — <hi rend="italic">Mn°) p'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(Nmi'</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Mm')</hi><hi rend="italic">ρ°</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >’</hi> and, on substituting the values of M, N, <hi rend="smallcaps">mi,</hi>
                    &amp;c. before found, <hi rend="subscript"> o</hi> (1—e)g sin.(A <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> —o)tan.δ'—sin.(A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>
                    —ft')tan.δ ļ</p>
                <p>λ' *sin.(A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> —ft <hi rend="superscript">
                    o</hi>)tan.∕∕—sin.(Λ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> —n')tan.6° (<hi
                    rend="smallcaps">∕iq</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">∖</hi></p>
                <p>(1—e)g sin.(A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> —α <hi rend="superscript">
                    o</hi>)tanΛ—sin.(A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> — <hi rend="smallcaps">íz)</hi>
                    tan.6</p>
                <p>λ sin.(A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> —α <hi rend="superscript">
                    o</hi>)tan.0'—sin.(A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> — <hi rend="italic">a!)</hi>
                    tan.∕&gt; <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> J</p>
                <p>• ’ * p <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> f</hi></p>
                <p>These two equations will give the ratios —, , in all b <hi rend="italic">ζ</hi>
                    cases when the common denominator (the quantity we have already denoted by P) is
                    not so small as to render the expressions indeterminate. In general they will be
                    most applicable when the motion of the comet in latitude is greater than its
                    motion in longitude.</p>
                <p>The other combination to which we have alluded, is formed by employing only the
                    two first of the equations (13). Let the first be multiplied by <hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >,</hi> and the second by <hi rend="smallcaps">mi';</hi> the difference of the
                    products gives <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> _ (1 — <hi rend="italic">e)</hi> g
                    <hi rend="italic">(nιn</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> f</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">irin)</hi> 4- <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Nmi'</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">—</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Mm'</hi> λ' <hi
                    rend="italic">(m</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >n'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">m'n°')</hi></p>
                <p>In like manner, if we multiply the first by <hi rend="italic">n°,</hi> and the
                    second by <hi rend="smallcaps">mi</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps">
                    o</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">,</hi> in order to eliminate g <hi rend="superscript"
                    > o</hi>, w e find</p>
                <p>, _ (1 — <hi rend="italic">e) ζ (nι°n</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">mn</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >)</hi> 4- <hi rend="smallcaps">Nmi</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps">
                    0</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">—</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Mm</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> 0</hi> λ <hi rend="italic">(m°n'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">m'n°')</hi></p>
                <p>On substituting the values of M, N, <hi rend="smallcaps">mi,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">n, &amp;c.</hi> in these last equations, they become <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 0</hi> _ <hi rend="underline">(1—e)g.sin.(n'-α)</hi> 4- (e—E)R
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> sin.(A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>-ď)ļ</p>
                <p>λ'sin. (α'— α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>) I</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">(1—e)g∙ sin.(o-</hi> α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>)— <hi
                    rend="italic">(e</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> E)R <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>
                    sin.(A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> — <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">)</hi> ſ ' λ sin. (α' — <hi rend="italic"
                    >a°)</hi> J</p>
                <p>ſhe equations now found will be most applicable when the motion of the comet in
                    longitude is greater than its motion in latitude.</p>
                <p>It may be proper to remark, that on employing the equations (18) or (19) to
                    determine the ratio of the curtate distances, we may suppose in the first trials
                    <hi rend="italic">e =</hi> 0,</p>
                <p>E — 0, λ — ~ -, λ' — ~—On this supposition the equations (19) become simply</p>
                <p>0 _ <hi rend="underline">÷</hi><hi rend="underline">g</hi><hi rend="underline"
                    >sin·</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> (a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript
                    underline"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">a )</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="superscript"> ŝ</hi> ~ ‘ sin. (α'^F)( ∕ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> θ)</p>
                <p>, _ &amp; 4* <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> g sin. (α — <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">) ſ ' '</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ô '</hi> sin. (α' — « )√</p>
                <p>11. From what has now been shown it may be inferred that the equations (13) can
                    in general be used only in determining the ratios of g <hi rend="superscript">
                    o</hi> and g' to g; on account of the smallness and consequent uncertainty of
                    the denominator Q, they leave the absolute value of g indeterminate. It is
                    therefore necessary to seek some other equation among the variables employed,
                    before we can obtain a complete solution of the problem. For this purpose we
                    must have recourse to some of the properties connected with the comet’s motion
                    in its orbit. No hypothesis has as yet been made respecting the nature of the
                    orbit. If we suppose it to be a parabola, the laws of parabolic motion will give
                    a new equation, without introducing any other variable than those which have
                    already been employed, which may either be combined with equation (16), for the
                    purpose of determining <hi rend="italic">r</hi> and g directly, or which may be
                    employed to correct the results obtained by assigning a hypothetical value to g
                    in the equations (18) or (lθ)∙ There are various methods of introducing the
                    condition derived from the nature of the parabolic motion; but, in the method of
                    solution which we here follow, it is most convenient to employ the theorem of
                    Lambert, which gives the time of describing a parabolic arc in terms of its
                    chord, and the two radii vectores drawn to its extremities. Before demonstrating
                    this theorem, however, it will be proper to show how the chord may be
                    computed.</p>
                <p>Let c be the chord which joins C <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> C'. The
                    co-ordinates of its extremities being <hi rend="italic">x'y'z'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">x°y°z°</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> i</hi> we have c <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — (a/—a? <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi>) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 4- (y — ^ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi>) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + (-z'—~ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi>) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>— a/ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 4 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> r2</hi> + z <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,2</hi> + ^° <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 4 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi><hi rend="italic">y°</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">+ ~°</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">2x</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic"
                    >x°</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">Zy'y°</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">2z'z°</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> that is, <hi rend="subscript">
                    t</hi> s — <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi>-2 4_ <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> 02 — 2
                    (a⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 4^ <hi rend="italic">y</hi> ’ <hi
                    rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi> + z'z <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi>). But by reason of the equations (8) and (10), a,⅛
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> = g'g <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> Mi'Mi <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> + Mi <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> g <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> R ’ cos. A' 4* Mi'g'R <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>
                    cos. A <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 4 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> R'R <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> cos. A' cos. <hi rend="italic">A°,y'y°</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">ζg°n'1ι</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 0</hi> 4^ M <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> g <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> R' sin. A + M ’ g'R <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>
                    sin. A <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 4^ R'R <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> sin.
                    A' sin. A <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">z'z° =
                    gg°p'p</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi>
                    therefore, by adding and substituting for <hi rend="smallcaps">mi, m,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="italic                     subscript"> i</hi>
                    &amp;c. their values given in equations (9) a⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 4^
                    <hi rend="italic">ÿy°</hi> + z ’ ~ <hi rend="superscript"> o =</hi> g'g <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi> cos. (α'—α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>) + g <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> R' cos. (A'—α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>)</p>
                <p>+ g ’ R <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> cos.(A <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> —
                    α')</p>
                <p>4- g'g <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> tan. <hi rend="italic">V</hi> tan. <hi
                    rend="italic">b°</hi> 4"K'R°cos.(A'—A <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>) hence,
                    denoting the right hand side of this equation byF, c <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> = r' <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 4. <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> o <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> _2F. (21)</p>
                <p>Comparing this last equation with <hi rend="subscript"> c</hi> 2 — /2 4- <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 7</hi> ∙°2— 2r'r <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> cos. &lt;p,
                    which is given by the triangle C <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> SC', we have F =
                    <hi rend="italic">r'r°</hi> p cos. p, or cos. 0 = —, <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>
                    being the angle included betw een the two radii vectores <hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi> ’ and r <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>.</p>
                <p>12. We now proceed with the demonstration of Lambert’s theorem.</p>
                <p>According to the doctrine of central forces, when a <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194749170?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9170-0146"/> body describes
                    an orbit in virtue of a force varying inversely as the square of the distance,
                    the square of the velocity at the distance <hi rend="italic">τ</hi> is given by
                    the equation</p>
                <p>1 1 _ <hi rend="italic">dx</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">&lt;⅞∕</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >r a dť</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">dť</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi> in which <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> is the major axis of the orbit, and the sum of the masses
                    is supposed equal to unit. In the case of the parabola, the major axis is
                    infinite, and the equation becomes simply</p>
                <p>1 <hi rend="italic">dx</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic
                    underline"> .</hi><hi rend="italic">&lt;⅞∕</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">r dC</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    2</hi><hi rend="italic">dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">'</hi></p>
                <p>Let D be the perihelion distance SP, and -ψ the <hi rend="superscript"> true
                    an0</hi> ^ maly, or the angle PSC. We have then <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">r</hi> cos. -ψ, <hi rend="italic">.
                    dx</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">. dy</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">dr</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi> + r <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> iAL <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="subscript"> j</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi>, = , sin. ∙ψ, whence + - — <hi rend="italic">āĩ~∙</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> and c0n</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi> sequently</p>
                <p>2 <hi rend="italic">dr</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi> + r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> cZψ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">ř
                    ~ dt</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">'</hi></p>
                <p>But from the property of the parabola <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi> 2D — <hi rend="italic">r</hi> cos. -ψ; whence <hi rend="italic">τ</hi>
                    (1 + cos. -ψ) = 2D, or <hi rend="italic">r</hi> cos. <hi rend="superscript">
                    2</hi> ⅛∙ψ = D, therefore <hi rend="italic">r =</hi> D ( 1 4- tan. <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ⅛∙ψ)∙</p>
                <p>J√J,</p>
                <p>Let tan. ⅜4'=zz&lt;,∙ then <hi rend="italic">dr = 2T)udu</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> and <hi rend="italic">du—</hi><hi rend="superscript strikethrough">
                    2</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">Ţ .∙</hi> cos. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    ⅛&gt;ψ</p>
                <p>= ⅜√∙ψ(l 4^ tan. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ⅜-ψ), whence &lt;∕ψ = —-.
                    Substitut-</p>
                <p>. 2 <hi rend="italic">dr</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">+ i</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >d-^</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
                <p>ιng these expressions m the equation - — ———, it becomes <hi rend="italic"
                    >dt?</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> 2D <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> (1 + w <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >du</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">,</hi> whence <hi rend="italic">dt =</hi> √2D <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> (1 + <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">) du</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> which,
                    on being integrated, becomes <hi rend="italic">t</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi>
                    V2D <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">(u</hi> + ģw <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi>).</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">u°, u’</hi> be the values of <hi rend="italic">u</hi> in
                    this equation at the times <hi rend="italic">t + ff, t</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">ô</hi> respectively; we have then <hi rend="italic">t +
                    0</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">=</hi> √2D <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> (√ + ⅜√ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi>) <hi rend="italic">ŧ—û =</hi> √2D <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">(u°</hi> + ⅜w <hi rend="superscript"
                    > o3</hi>), and, by subtracting,</p>
                <p>&amp; 4^ <hi rend="italic">ò =</hi> √2D <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> {w'— <hi
                    rend="italic">u°</hi>-f- <hi rend="italic">į (√</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 7z</hi><hi rend="italic">°)}∙</hi></p>
                <p>In order to transform this expression into another containing only <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 0</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi> ’ and <hi rend="italic">c,</hi> let ∙ψ <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> be
                    the anomaly corresponding to C <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, ∙ψ' that
                    corresponding to C', <hi rend="italic">φ</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> ∙ψ' — ∙ψ°
                    — angle C <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> SC', and tan. ļp = <hi rend="italic"
                    >υ.</hi> We have then ψ =∙ψ <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 4 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> p <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> and consequently tan.
                    į ψ = tan. ∙⅜ (-ψ <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 4“ <hi rend="italic">φ) =</hi>
                    tan. ∙⅜ψ <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 4^ tan. ⅜ ® . w <hi rend="superscript">
                    0</hi> 4" <hi rend="italic">v .</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> τ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> n</hi></p>
                <p>¶ r —∏ <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi>-&gt; that is, w' = —. Now, if we</p>
                <p>1 — tan. i∙ψ <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> tan. Łp 1 — <hi rend="subscript">
                    u</hi> ° <hi rend="subscript"> v</hi> &gt; put</p>
                <p>Z = u' — <hi rend="italic">u°</hi> 4" ⅜ <hi rend="italic">(u’</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >u</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 03</hi><hi rend="italic">),</hi> we shall
                    have evidently <hi rend="italic">Z = (u</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >)</hi> {1 4^ ⅜ <hi rend="italic">(u'</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    4^ <hi rend="italic">u'u°</hi> 4 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> u <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 02</hi>)}</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">= (u'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 0</hi><hi rend="italic">)</hi> {1 — I <hi
                    rend="italic">[(u'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">u°)</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> 4- <hi rend="italic">3u'u°^</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">}&gt;</hi></p>
                <p>“f" <hi rend="italic">V</hi> therefore, substituting <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi>
                    — for <hi rend="italic">u',</hi></p>
                <p>1 — <hi rend="italic">u°v</hi></p>
                <p>_ <hi rend="underline">¾? (1 4- w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">
                    02</hi><hi rend="underline">)</hi> J <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="underline"/><hi rend="italic underline"> u</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript                     underline"> 02</hi><hi rend="italic underline">
                    + u°υ</hi><hi rend="italic                     subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="italic underline"> v~(l</hi><hi rend="underline">4-</hi> w <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o2</hi>) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ^∣</p>
                <p>1 — <hi rend="italic">u°v</hi> Į_ 1 — <hi rend="italic">u°v</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> (1 — <hi rend="italic">u°vy</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi> J ’ that is, <hi rend="italic subscript"> 7</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">~</hi><hi rend="italic                     underline"> v(l +
                    u°</hi><hi rend="italic superscript underline"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic
                    underline"> )</hi><hi rend="italic superscript underline"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi> ^ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="underline">(l
                    +</hi> ^ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)1</p>
                <p>(1 — <hi rend="italic">u°v)</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">(</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ì — <hi rend="italic"
                    >u°v</hi> J ’</p>
                <p>hence the formula for the time becomes a 4→= <hi rend="smallcaps">√⅞d</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> 3</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">. ⅜</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> ι</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">~</hi><hi
                    rend="strikethrough">f</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">y</hi> {i+⅜ - <hi
                    rend="strikethrough">ιp</hi><hi rend="superscript
                    strikethrough"> +</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">θ</hi><hi rend="superscript
                    strikethrough"> o2)</hi> ļ.</p>
                <p>(1— <hi rend="italic">u°v)</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">(</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> I — <hi rend="italic">u°υ
                    J</hi></p>
                <p>Again, the triangle C <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> SC' gives the equation c <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = r <hi rend="superscript"> z2</hi> 4- <hi
                    rend="italic">r°</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">2dr°</hi> cos. <hi rend="italic">&lt;p,</hi> but tan.
                    <hi rend="italic">ļ-&lt;p = v;</hi> therefore, from the trigonometrical for-</p>
                <p>1 — <hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> mulae, cos. <hi
                    rend="italic">&lt;p =</hi> whence, substituting and reducing,</p>
                <p>4Pr <hi rend="superscript"> σ</hi><hi rend="subscript"> (/ + r</hi> o <hi
                    rend="subscript"> )2</hi> _ <hi rend="subscript"> c2=</hi> ___.</p>
                <p>For the sake of abridging, we shall put <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> r</hi> 4 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi><hi rend="italic">r°</hi>
                    4- <hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">2s,
                    r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">-ļ-r°</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">c = 2d,</hi> whence <hi rend="italic"
                    >τ</hi> ’ 4~ <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> ° — $ 4* <hi rend="italic"
                    >d,</hi><hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >s</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">d,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >(τ</hi> ’ + r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> —
                    <hi rend="subscript"> c</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = 4sď. Comparing
                    these with the above equation, we</p>
                <p>1</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">, r'r° ,</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">(r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >r°</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">sd)</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi> have ļ—p—g — <hi rend="superscript"> sc</hi> ⅛ whence <hi
                    rend="italic">v = -</hi><hi rend="italic">~—</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    1 + v</hi><hi rend="italic">(sd)</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>Now the polar equation to the parabola gives r <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> —D
                    ( 14^ <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">), r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> f</hi> = D (1 + <hi
                    rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> t2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >^)</hi> = D . ïì±£ľ×⅛⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> v</hi> (1 — <hi rend="italic"
                    >u°υ)&lt;</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="subscript"> r</hi>
                    &gt; <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> ° /ļ_ļ_ <hi rend="subscript"> M</hi> oe\2</p>
                <p>therefore <hi rend="italic">sd =</hi> yyyyy — ŋ <hi rend="strikethrough">¢ļ
                    .</hi><hi rend="subscript strikethrough"> 7</hi> ~⅛yj&gt; <hi rend="superscript"
                    > anc</hi> ^ consequently, <hi rend="underline">1 +</hi><hi rend="italic
                    underline"> u°</hi><hi rend="italic superscript underline"> t2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">_</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> (sd)</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript underline"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>1 — <hi rend="italic">u°v</hi> D</p>
                <p>From the same values of <hi rend="italic">r°</hi> and <hi rend="italic">r</hi> ’
                    we get</p>
                <p>→^ = D(l + ^){l + <hi rend="subscript"> f</hi> ⅛⅞}</p>
                <p>_ <hi rend="underline">2D(1 4~¾°</hi><hi rend="superscript underline"> 2</hi><hi
                    rend="underline">)</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> Όν</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript underline"> 2</hi><hi rend="underline">(1 4-</hi><hi rend="italic
                    underline"> u</hi><hi rend="italic superscript underline"> o2</hi><hi
                    rend="italic underline"> )</hi><hi rend="italic superscript underline">
                    2</hi></p>
                <p>1 — <hi rend="italic">u°v</hi> 1 — <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> ĩi°v</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript smallcaps"> ,</hi></p>
                <p>1 "4“ τzθ <hi rend="superscript"> z</hi> V^ <hi rend="italic">sd</hi> but <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi> ’ 4“ <hi rend="italic">r° = s</hi> 4^ <hi rend="italic"
                    >d,</hi> and γ — = - <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> ~-, therefore</p>
                <p>1 — <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic">V</hi> D</p>
                <p>. <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi> /— i <hi rend="italic">υ'</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">^∕sd</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    1</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic subscript smallcaps">
                    tλ</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> V</hi><hi rend="italic superscript
                    smallcaps"> s</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">∕d</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">s + d — 2Vsd</hi> 4 ŋ—, whence <hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> √D ∙ —yyy—*</p>
                <p>1 4- <hi rend="italic">u°</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ι2</hi></p>
                <p>Substituting these values oí <hi rend="italic">v</hi> and <hi rend="subscript">
                    7</hi> —- in the equa-</p>
                <p>1 — <hi rend="italic">u°v</hi> tion for the time, it becomes <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ô</hi> + 0' = √2√^(√5 — √J) ∫ 1 4- i ļ,</p>
                <p>I <hi rend="italic">Vsd</hi> 4</p>
                <p>that is <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> 4- ∂' = <hi rend="italic">(</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> y</hi><hi rend="italic">∕</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> s</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">√√) (s</hi> 4- <hi rend="italic">V7d</hi>
                    4- <hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi> or</p>
                <p>√2 ž</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">D + 0' = ~(s</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">-~</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">ćZ</hi><hi rend="superscript
                    smallcaps"> 3</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">);</hi> and, finally, on restoring the
                    values of s and <hi rend="italic">d,</hi><hi rend="italic">û + 0' = ⅜ (r</hi> ’
                    4- 4 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> c) — ⅛ (f 4 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> r
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> — c) (24)</p>
                <p>This is the very elegant theorem found by Euler, but commonly attributed to
                    Lambert, by means of which we are enabled to correct the hypothetical values
                    successively given to ę, till a value of that quantity is found which will
                    satisfy all the equations as nearly as the observations will admit.</p>
                <p>13. We shall now collect into one view the different processes indicated in the
                    preceding investigations; and in order to throw every necessary light on the
                    subject, we shall give, at the same time an example of the actual computation of
                    an orbit from Legendre. The comet is that of 1805, and the data from which the
                    computation is made are contained in the following table:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Epochs.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Longitudes.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Latitudes.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>October 22∙68488</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi
                            rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> 163° 20'
                            53"</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi
                            rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> 22°
                            59'53"</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>30∙68670</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">a</hi> = 183 48
                            32</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">b</hi> = 15 37
                            21</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>34∙72088</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">a' =</hi> 191 46
                            15</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">V -</hi> 12 2
                            29</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:194749183?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9183-0147"/>
                <p>I. The first step is to compute the arc described by the mean motion of the earth
                    in the time <hi rend="italic">ê + ff.</hi> Let this arc be represented by Θ;
                    then since <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> and ff are expressed in gţŗ <hi
                    rend="italic">ſğ</hi> _ļ_ <hi rend="italic">ğ</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi> mean
                    solar days, we have Θ = <hi rend="subscript strikethrough"> 3</hi><hi
                    rend="strikethrough">g</hi><hi rend="subscript strikethrough"> 5</hi><hi
                    rend="strikethrough">.g</hi><hi rend="subscript strikethrough"> 5633</hi><hi
                    rend="strikethrough">&gt;</hi><hi rend="superscript strikethrough"> 2ςr
                    bein</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">≡</hi><hi rend="superscript strikethrough">
                    the</hi> circumference of a circle whose radius is unit, and 365*25638 the mean
                    solar days in a sidereal year. The lo°*arithm of Θ will therefore be found by
                    adding the constant logarithm 8*2355821 (which is the logarithm of</p>
                <p>—-i to the logarithm of <hi rend="italic">ô + ff.</hi> 365*25638/</p>
                <p>From the above table we have <hi rend="italic">å =</hi> 8*00182 days, ff = 4Ό3418
                    days, <hi rend="italic">ô + ff =</hi> 12*03600 days; hence taking the logarithms
                    of these numbers, and adding 8*2355821, we have the following results expressed
                    in logarithms:</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">ô = 9*1387708</hi> ff = 8*8413373</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">ô + ff =</hi> 9*3160643 <hi rend="italic">ô ⅛ i' =</hi>
                    9*3160643</p>
                <p>—- 9*8227065 <hi rend="italic">—ļ—</hi> 9*5252730</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ô + &amp; ŏ + ff</hi></p>
                <p>It may be here remarked, that although the computations are considerably
                    shortened when <hi rend="italic">ô</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ff,</hi> a condition which may in general be satisfied by interpolation, yet it
                    is preferable to avoid any preliminary calculations, and to employ the direct
                    results of observation. The intervals, however, should not be greatly different;
                    and as the solution is founded on the supposition that quantities of the fourth
                    order in respect of the time may be neglected, the longest interval cannot
                    safely exceed ten days. In the present example, <hi rend="italic">ô</hi> is
                    considerably greater than ff ∙, it therefore affords no facilities for
                    computation, and the approximations must be carried as far as the method
                    admits.</p>
                <p>II. The places of the sun at the time of the respective observations are next to
                    be taken from the solar tables.’ These places, increased by 180°, give the three
                    longitudes of the earth A <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, A, A'. The same tables
                    also give the corresponding distances R <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, 11, R'*,
                    and the quantities A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> and R <hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi>, which denote the longitude and radius vector of the earth at the time
                    <hi rend="italic">t + ⅛∙ (ô + ff),</hi> corresponding to the mean epoch <hi
                    rend="italic">of</hi> the three observations, will be obtained with sufficient
                    accuracy by assuming A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = ⅛ (A <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> + A + A'), and log. R <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =
                    ⅜ log. (R <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> RR ’)∙</p>
                <p>At the epochs given in the above table, we find from the solar tables,</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>A <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> =
                            29° 19' 50"</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>log. R <hi rend="superscript">
                            o</hi>...9*997421</p><p>log. R ...9*996496</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>A =37</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>19 48</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>A <hi rend="superscript"> z</hi>
                            =41</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>22</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>26</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>log. R <hi rend="superscript">
                            z</hi>...9*996053</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>By taking a mean among these numbers we shall have <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> 36° 0' 41" log. R <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>... 9*9966567.</p>
                <p>III. With the results now found, we may proceed to compute the quantities P, Q
                    from the expressions given in § 5, namely,</p>
                <p>P = sin. (A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> — <hi rend="italic">a°)</hi> tan. <hi
                    rend="italic">b'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> sin. (A <hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi> — <hi rend="italic">a')</hi> tan. <hi rend="italic">b°</hi></p>
                <p>Q = sin. (α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> — α') tan. <hi rend="italic">b</hi> +
                    sin. (tſ — <hi rend="italic">a)</hi> tan. <hi rend="italic">b° +</hi> sin. <hi
                    rend="italic">(a</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">a°)</hi> tan. <hi
                    rend="italic">Iff.</hi></p>
                <p>For this purpose the following logarithms are required:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>sin. (α'</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">a )</hi> 9*1414978 tan. <hi rend="italic">b°</hi>
                            9*6278110</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>sin. (α'</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>-α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>)
                            9*6775831 tan. <hi rend="italic">b</hi> 9*4465812</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>sin. <hi rend="italic"
                            >(a</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">a°)</hi> 9*5435305 tan. <hi rend="italic">U</hi>
                            9*3290147</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>sin. (α <hi rend="superscript">
                            z</hi> — A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>) 9*6133857</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>sin. <hi rend="italic">(a°</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">—</hi> A, ) 9*9004139</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>On computing P and Q by means of these numbers, we find P = 0*0046585, and Q =
                    0*0002617. The signs of both are positive, and though Q is thus a very small
                    number, yet its sign could not become negative without supposing errors in the
                    observations amounting to four or five minutes. By reason of the smallness of P
                    and Q, no use can be made of the equation (16); we can only infer from it, since
                    P and Q have the same sign, that r &lt; R; that is to say, the distance of the
                    comet from the sun is less than the sun’s distance from the earth.</p>
                <p>IV. It is now necessary to make a supposition with regard to the value <hi
                    rend="italic">ξ.</hi> In general a few trials will suffice to give an
                    approximate value, by means of which g <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> and g' may
                    be computed from the formulae (19) or (20), according to the different cases. In
                    the first trials we may suppose E = 0, <hi rend="italic">û</hi><hi rend="italic
                    smallcaps"> p'</hi><hi rend="italic">e</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">0, λ</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi><hi
                    rend="strikethrough">-ų_</hi> —, λ' — î but when approximations to the values of
                    g <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> and g' have been obtained on this supposition,
                    we must employ the more exact expressions given in the ſormulae (6.) In the
                    present case, on account <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the great inequality between
                    <hi rend="italic">Ô</hi> and ff, the values of g <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>
                    and g <hi rend="superscript"> z</hi> deduced from the supposition of E = 0, e =
                    0, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> w ould not have that degree of approximation
                    which would render them of any use in directing the subsequent hypotheses; we
                    may therefore have recourse at once to the second degree of approximation. The
                    ſormulae (6) give <hi rend="italic">_ ôff _ ôff</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> β</hi><hi rend="italic">~ 2r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    3</hi><hi rend="italic">∙</hi> ’ ^ <hi rend="superscript"> b</hi> ~ 2R <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ’</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> λ</hi>- <hi rend="superscript"> û</hi> Λ <hi rend="italic
                    underline"> ff(0-ff)</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">ff (
                    ,</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> 0(0~ff)</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> λ</hi><hi rend="italic">ðq-0'’V 6r</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> t</hi><hi rend="italic">)’</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> X</hi><hi rend="italic">“ð + ð’V</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ÷</hi><hi rend="italic">6r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    3</hi><hi rend="italic">J’</hi> from which we deduce</p>
                <p>1 —e _ đ ÷ <hi rend="italic">0' f ff(20</hi> + 4')^ <hi rend="italic">~T~
                    ~</hi><hi rend="italic">~Ύ~</hi> V 6^ <hi rend="italic">J' \—e_ô + ffí 0(2ff +
                    ff)</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">λ</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">~ ff</hi> ∖~ 6r <hi rend="superscript">
                    3</hi>) ’ <hi rend="italic">e_ _ £(£ + ff) e__</hi><hi rend="italic underline">
                    ô(ô + ff)</hi> λ 2r <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ’ λ <hi rend="superscript">
                    z</hi> 2z* <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ’</p>
                <p>E <hi rend="italic">ff(ô + ff)</hi> _E _ <hi rend="italic underline"> û(ô +
                    ff)</hi> λ “2R <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ’ λ <hi rend="superscript"> z</hi>
                    2R <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> '</p>
                <p>In order to convert these ſormulae into numbers, we must recollect that if <hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi> is a small number in comparison of <hi rend="italic">a,
                    we</hi> have log. <hi rend="italic">(a + b)</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> log. α
                    + M, where M denotes the modulus of the tables, or the number 4342945, the
                    logarithm of which is 6*6377843; and reciprocally, if we have log. <hi
                    rend="italic">x =</hi> log. <hi rend="italic">a + b,</hi> then <hi rend="italic"
                    >x = a +</hi> According to these ſormulae</p>
                <p>1 — <hi rend="subscript"> e</hi> đ + đ' 4'(24+d') <hi rend="subscript"> λz</hi>,
                    log. = log. —- —- ∙ Μ.</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> λ <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ô</hi> 6r <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="italic">Δ</hi> _L_ <hi
                    rend="italic">Δ'</hi></p>
                <p>Now log. = 0*1772935; and to find the number <hi rend="italic superscript">
                    0</hi><hi rend="italic">ô</hi><hi rend="italic strikethrough"> 0(26+ff)</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> w</hi> θ 1 <hi rend="subscript"> 1ave</hi><hi rend="italic
                    smallcaps"> 2ô</hi><hi rend="italic">Ą-ff =</hi> 20*03782 days, therefore 6r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi> log. <hi rend="italic">(2Ô + ff) =</hi> 1*3018505 add
                    8*2355821 log. ff = 8*8413373</p>
                <p>8*3787699 log. <hi rend="italic">6=</hi> 0*7781513</p>
                <p>log ŁÍŁL+Ιλ <hi rend="subscript"> =</hi> 7*6006186 <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi>
                    6</p>
                <p>If therefore we denote by (L) the number whose logarithm is L, we shall have</p>
                <p>] <hi rend="subscript"> 0g</hi>. Lľľl£ <hi rend="subscript"> =</hi> o∙1772935 —
                    (7*6006186); <pb break="no" facs="nls:194749196?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0707-9196-0148"/> and passing to numbers</p>
                <p>= (0∙1772935)-(7-7779121) L λ <hi rend="superscript"> x</hi> r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 3</hi></p>
                <p>By proceeding in the same manner, we find l <hi rend="subscript"> 0g</hi>. Izi£ =
                    0-4747270 — (7-8022223)</p>
                <p>whence</p>
                <p>≥≡- <hi rend="superscript"> β</hi> = (0-4747270) — (8∙2769493) į λ '</p>
                <p>The following logarithms are found without difficulty: log. - = log. -=
                    7∙8563716</p>
                <p>° λ 2r <hi rend="superscript"> j</hi></p>
                <p>ļog.į = log. = 8-1038051</p>
                <p>l <hi rend="subscript"> 0g</hi>,∣= log.¾Û = 7∙S668836 ⅛≤=log∙ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> i</hi> ⅞i^=8∙1643171.</p>
                <p>In the present example the motion in longitude is more considerable than in
                    latitude; it is therefore preferable to employ the equations (20), namely, <hi
                    rend="subscript"> o</hi> _ ( 1 — <hi rend="italic">e) ζ</hi> sin. (ď — <hi
                    rend="italic">a)</hi> + (E — e) R <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> sin. («'— A <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>)</p>
                <p>* ~ λ'sin. (α' — <hi rend="italic">a°)</hi></p>
                <p>_ (1 — e) <hi rend="italic">g</hi> sin. <hi rend="italic">(a</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">a°)</hi><hi rend="underline">+ (g</hi><hi
                    rend="underline">—</hi><hi rend="underline">E) R</hi><hi rend="subscript
                    underline"> 1</hi><hi rend="underline">sin.(α</hi><hi rend="superscript
                    underline"> o</hi><hi rend="underline">—</hi><hi rend="underline">A</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript underline"> 1</hi><hi rend="underline">)</hi>. ’ λ sin. (α' —
                    <hi rend="italic">a°)</hi> to compute which, the following logarithms are
                    required in addition to those already found, namely, log. <hi rend="superscript"
                    > sιn</hi> ∙(<hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> '-_ 9-4639147</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> b</hi> sin. (ď— α <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>)</p>
                <p>log. <hi rend="superscript"> ι</hi> i <hi rend="strikethrough">l⅞ (≤-~-</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript strikethrough smallcaps"> a</hi><hi rend="strikethrough
                    smallcaps"> j</hi> J <hi rend="subscript"> =</hi> 9-9324593</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> sm.(α'-α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>)</p>
                <p>lo <hi rend="subscript"> g</hi>. <hi rend="superscript"> sι</hi>. <hi
                    rend="superscript"> n</hi> ∙(<hi rend="superscript"> α</hi> ~ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> t</hi> ¾-= 9-8659474</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> sιn.(β' — α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>)</p>
                <p>log. <hi rend="superscript strikethrough"> R</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">ı
                    sm.(α</hi><hi rend="superscript strikethrough"> o</hi><hi rend="strikethrough"
                    >-A</hi><hi rend="subscript strikethrough"> 1</hi><hi rend="strikethrough"
                    >)</hi> = 0-2194875, <hi rend="superscript"> b</hi> sιn.(α'— <hi rend="italic"
                    >a°)</hi></p>
                <p>1 — <hi rend="italic">e</hi> by adding which to the values of , Ac. the above
                    two</p>
                <p>λ</p>
                <p>equations become <hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 0</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">=</hi><hi rend="subscript"> f</hi> (9∙9386417) — 1 (7-7408640) +
                    (8∙0967764) — į (8-0862644)</p>
                <p>= ^(0∙0432409) — í (7-6438595)</p>
                <p>— (8-0863711) + 1 (8-0758591)</p>
                <p>V. Having assumed a hypothetical value of <hi rend="italic">g.</hi> the radius
                    vector <hi rend="italic">τ</hi> will be obtained from the equation (17), namely,
                    r <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = R <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 2gR cos.
                    (A — α) + <hi rend="smallcaps">p</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi>
                    sec. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 5, which, on taking the logarithms of the
                    known quantities, becomes r <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = 0-9839930 — <hi
                    rend="italic">g</hi> (0*2185267) + <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (0∙0326962); and on substituting this value of <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi> in the above two equations, we shall obtain the values of g
                    <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> and g'.</p>
                <p>It is now necessary to calculate r°, r', and <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> With
                    regard to <hi rend="italic">r°</hi> and r ’, we have the two equations,
                    corresponding to equation (17), <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> o2 - <hi
                    rend="subscript"> R</hi> O2 <hi rend="subscript"> + 2f</hi> o <hi
                    rend="subscript"> R</hi> o <hi rend="subscript"> cos&gt;</hi> ζ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> A</hi> o _ <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> o) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> +</hi> ^O2 <hi rend="subscript"> sec 2</hi> įo,</p>
                <p>∕ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — R <hi rend="superscript"> ,2</hi> = 2^R'cos.
                    (A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> — α <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>) + <hi
                    rend="italic">g'</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> sec. <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">b',</hi> which being reduced to
                    numbers, become <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    c3</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> 0-9881934 — s"(0∙1403596) + f <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (0-0719354), r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> ' =
                    O∙9S19876 — √ (0-2363369) + <hi rend="italic">g-</hi> (0-0193249). The chord <hi
                    rend="italic">c</hi> is determined bv the equation c <hi rend="superscript">
                    3</hi> = <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> * + r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> —2F,
                    in which F —</p>
                <p>R <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> R'cos.(A'—A <hi rend="superscript"> c</hi>) ÷
                    e^∕{cos. <hi rend="italic">(a</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >a°)</hi> + tan.5'tan.δ <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>} + e <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi> R' ccs. (A’ — α <hi rend="superscript"> c</hi>) + f'R
                    <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> cos. (A <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> — α').</p>
                <p>On taking the logarithms of the constant quantities, this becomes</p>
                <p>F= 0∙963W42-f^!∞^) + <hi rend="subscript"> rs</hi> '(9∙9S67701).</p>
                <p>Lastly, the error of the hypothesis will be found from the equation of the time
                    6(d + <hi rend="italic">r)</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(τ=</hi><hi rend="italic">÷</hi><hi rend="italic">ť + cfi</hi> + (r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> 4- <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">-c)-</hi> = 1-2422687.</p>
                <p>As the present object is merely to illustrate the method of computation, it is
                    unnecessary to begin with an assumption verv far from the truth. Suppose, in the
                    first place, <hi rend="italic">p</hi> = 0*6 = (9∙77S1512). This will give the
                    following results:</p>
                <p>r <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = 0-3797624 = (9-5795120), <hi rend="italic"
                    >r</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> (9∙7S97560) f = (9∙6695O87), √ = (9∙S389800) <hi
                    rend="italic">τ=</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >=</hi> 0-6003290 = (9-7783893) <hi rend="italic">r-</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >=</hi> 0-2906613 = (9-4634172)</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> ≈ + <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi>- = 0∙S909903 2F =
                    0-7537670</p>
                <p>e <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = 0-1372233 = (9-1374278)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >=</hi> (9∙SS91946) = 0∙774S089 √ = (9∙73170S6) = 0-5391475</p>
                <p>r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> + <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> f</hi><hi rend="italic">...............</hi> = 1-3139564 <hi
                    rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> (9∙56S7139) = 0∙37S4366</p>
                <p>r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> +∕ + e = σ= l∙6S43930 r <hi rend="superscript">
                    a</hi> ⅛r ’-c = δ = 0∙943520S</p>
                <p>a <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = 2-1860775</p>
                <p>b⅛ = 0*9164SS8</p>
                <p>a⅛ — b- = 1∙2695S87 but 6(i + /) = <hi rend="underline">1∙24226S7</hi> Error -ļ-
                    -0273200</p>
                <p>For a second hvpothesis let us make <hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >=</hi> 0∙5S = (9∙76342S0). On going through the same calculations, there will
                    result r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 4-r'4-c=a = L6S33303, a≡ = 2∙1S4O7O3</p>
                <p>r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 4-F-c = b= 0-9631377, b- ’ = <hi
                    rend="underline">0-9452192</hi> a <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — b⅛ =
                    1-2388511 6(<hi rend="italic">ê</hi><hi rend="italic">+</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >f)</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi><hi rend="underline">1-2422687</hi> Error —
                    -0034176</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript strikethrough"> Let n</hi><hi rend="strikethrough"
                    >=</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">⅞32°+</hi><hi rend="superscript strikethrough">
                    4</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">∙W¾l⅞6</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">= °∙</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript strikethrough"> 11119</hi><hi rend="strikethrough"
                    >&gt;</hi><hi rend="superscript strikethrough"> tl</hi><hi rend="strikethrough"
                    >'</hi><hi rend="superscript strikethrough"> en the true</hi> value of any
                    quantity which is denoted by A in the first hypothesis, and by Bin the second,
                    will be B — <hi rend="italic">n</hi> (B — A). Computing from this formula, there
                    results, <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> (9-6569463) r <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi> = (9∙S906184)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">g</hi> = (9-7650651) r = (9-7935971 ∕</p>
                <p>√ = (9∙S25959S) <hi rend="italic">τ'</hi> = (9-7362737)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> (9∙5577⅛5S).</p>
                <p>VI. In most cases the solution which has now been obtained would be sufiicientlv
                    approximate; but in the present case, on account of the great inequality between
                    <pb break="no" facs="nls:194749209?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9209-0149"/>
                    the intervals <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> and it is necessary to recommence the
                    calculations, and to determine λ. λ', and <hi rend="italic">e</hi> from the more
                    accurate expressions which form the third degree of approximation. Let</p>
                <p>Mđ* , . .</p>
                <p>ð = y the equations (∕) give</p>
                <p>6(r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> r') <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 6(rr')⅛</p>
                <p>log· λ = log- (<hi rend="subscript"> 7t7j</hi>) - Ĵ+7 ⅛ ' =</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">(</hi><hi rend="italic">ff</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ğ į.r</hi></p>
                <p>Γ+ιJ <hi rend="superscript"> +</hi><hi rend="italic">ð</hi> T7 <hi
                    rend="superscript">;</hi><hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> = sr <hi
                    rend="superscript"> c</hi> rγ∕</p>
                <p>from which, employing the approximate values of r <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>,
                    r, and <hi rend="italic">r</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">,</hi> already obtained,
                    there results</p>
                <p>3 = (7'3643107), <hi rend="italic">(e-Σ)</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi>
                    (84358552),</p>
                <p>λ = (9∙S219310), ( 1 — <hi rend="italic">e )</hi> = (9∙9919393),</p>
                <p>λ' = (9'5268112).</p>
                <p>If we now proceed to substitute these results in the equations (17), we shall
                    find the following expressions for <hi rend="italic">ζ°</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">ģ</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    ξ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> ζ</hi><hi rend="italic">(9'929042S)</hi> — (S∙5415033),
                    <hi rend="italic">g</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">=</hi> p(0O359557) — (S'5334117),
                    in which the only indeterminate quantity is j&gt;. We must now make another
                    hypothesis with respect to ş. If we assume the value given by the last
                    approximation, namely <hi rend="italic">t&gt; =</hi> (9∙7650651), we shall find
                    that it is considerably too small, and that the first approximation is
                    consequently insufficient, ow,ng to the imperfect values it gave of the
                    quantities λ and λ', and <hi rend="italic">e.</hi></p>
                <p>Let us suppose ş = 0∙6045 = (9∙7813963). By proceeding as before with the
                    corrected values now found, we obtain <hi rend="subscript"> g</hi> ° =
                    (9'6799602), √ = (9'S393705), r° <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = 0∙5973194
                    =’(94 762067) r° <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = 0∙290501 = (94631582) c <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = 04313662 = (941S4S36)</p>
                <p>whence -</p>
                <p>r <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> + r ’ + c = a= 1'6742972, a <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = 24664512 <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> oq- <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 7</hi> √ - <hi rend="subscript"> c</hi>- b = 0∙9494078, b⅛ =
                    0-9250798</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> a</hi> i _ b⅛ = 1∙2413714 6(đ -j- <hi rend="italic"
                    >ð)</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> 1'242'26S7</p>
                <p>Error— ’ OOOS973 Suppose, therefore, = 0-6055 = (9-7821141). Computing as above
                    <hi rend="subscript">;</hi> we shall find r <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>-1-r
                    ’-1-c=a = 1'6742754, <hi rend="italic">t.-</hi> = 24664090</p>
                <p>r <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>-J-r'-c = b = 0-948593S, b^ = 0'9238902</p>
                <p><hi rend="subscript"> a</hi> ⅞ — b-= 1∙242518S 6(4 + <hi rend="italic">ð)</hi> =
                    1"2422687</p>
                <p>Error - <hi rend="superscript"> u</hi> ∙0002501</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">n =</hi> = 0*218; the mean between the</p>
                <p>89/3 + 2o01</p>
                <p>two values of the same quantity in the two hypotheses is B + (A — B) (0∙218), by
                    taking which, there results <hi rend="italic">r° =</hi> (9∙8880427), <hi
                    rend="italic">r =</hi> (9∙7S86S2S), <hi rend="italic">τ'</hi> = (9∙7314028).</p>
                <p>These values being considerably different from those found by the first
                    approximation, it becomes necessary to have recourse to a third operation.</p>
                <p>The values of λ. λ ’, and 1 — <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> deduced from the values
                    of <hi rend="italic">r°, τ, ť</hi> now found, are λ = (9'8219155), λ' =
                    (9∙526S419), 1 — e = (9∙99181SS).</p>
                <p>In order to find a more exact value of A <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> than
                    results from taking the mean of the three longitudes of the earth, we may make
                    use of the equations (13), namely, 0 = λζη? + λ⅛V — (1 — <hi rend="italic">e)
                    mg</hi> + M, 0 = λ∕∕'√ + λn <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> f — (1 <hi
                    rend="italic">—e)</hi> «g + N, in which M = (e — E) R <hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi> cos. A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = σ cos. A <hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi>,</p>
                <p>— ~ sin. A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, and we shall have in the present example
                    r cos. A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = λ(9'8713530) + λ'(9∙9378419) — (1 — <hi
                    rend="italic">e)</hi> (9∙89694S4) <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi></p>
                <p>«· sin. A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = λ(9∙8162347) + λ'(9∙68748J9) — (1 — <hi
                    rend="subscript"> e</hi>) (9∙77925S7)</p>
                <p>whence, substituting for λ, λ', and (1— <hi rend="italic">e),</hi> the above
                    values,</p>
                <p>σ cos. A J = (8Ό399020), tan. A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = (9∙8969484) r sin.
                    A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = (7'9115731), A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =
                    36° 39' 20", σ = (84355982).</p>
                <p>The value of A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, thus found, differs considerably
                    from that which was employed in the previous approximation, namely, A <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = 36° O' 41".</p>
                <p>On substituting c for (e — E) R <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, the equations (20)
                    become</p>
                <p>_ <hi rend="underline">(1</hi><hi rend="underline">—</hi><hi rend="italic
                    underline"> e) ξ</hi><hi rend="underline">sin,</hi><hi rend="italic underline">
                    (a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript underline"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic
                    underline"> —</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> ci)</hi><hi rend="italic">∙</hi>
                    — σ sin. <hi rend="italic">(a!</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> A <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>) <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> λ' sin. (α' — α <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi>) ’</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">j</hi> _ ( 1 — e) <hi rend="italic">p</hi> sin. <hi
                    rend="italic">(a'</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">a)</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">&lt;s</hi> ’ sin. <hi rend="italic"
                    >(a°</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> A <hi rend="subscript"> j</hi>) <hi
                    rend="superscript"> i</hi> λ sin. (α'— <hi rend="smallcaps">íz°)</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">’</hi> whence, making A <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> = 36° 39'
                    26", f = <hi rend="subscript"> ř</hi> (9 928S916) _ (8∙5552427), <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">√ = p(0O35S507)</hi> + (8'5401948), from which two equations we
                    shall obtain the nearest approximation of which this method of solving the
                    problem is susceptible.</p>
                <p>Suppose » = (9'7790000). On going through the same computation as before, we
                    shall find r≈4-r' + c = a= 1'6758479, ał = 24694623 <hi rend="italic">r°</hi>-J-
                    <hi rend="italic">τ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> j</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">c</hi> = b = 0'9509163, b⅛ = 0'9272854</p>
                <p>a <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — b <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = 1'2421769
                    6(đ + <hi rend="italic">0</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> f</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">)</hi> = 1∙2422687</p>
                <p>Error —918</p>
                <p>Suppose, secondly, <hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> (9'7791000).
                    This supposition will give r <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> _ļ_ √ _ļ_ <hi
                    rend="italic">c =</hi> a = 1'6758426, a <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =
                    24694511</p>
                <p>r <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> + √-c = b = 0∙9508021, ∙b <hi rend="superscript"
                    > 2</hi> = 0∙9271186</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic subscript"> ã</hi><hi rend="italic">ĩ</hi> — b <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = 1'2423325</p>
                <p>• 6(đ + ff) = 1∙2422687</p>
                <p>Error + 638 From these errors, the mean to take between A and B, the two values
                    of the same quantity in the two hypotheses, is B + (A — B) (∩'41), whence the
                    following solution:</p>
                <p>f = (9'6762680), <hi rend="italic">r° =</hi> (9∙8884811 ) = 0'77353695, ∕ =
                    (9'83738895), <hi rend="italic">τ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> j</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">=</hi> (9∙7322409) = 0∙53981000, <hi rend="italic">c =</hi>
                    (9∙5593056) = 0∙3624980.</p>
                <p>VI. It now remains only to indicate the method of computing, from the foregoing
                    solution, the elements of the parabolic orbit.</p>
                <p>ą/ <hi rend="italic">sd</hi></p>
                <p>It was shown in § 12 that <hi rend="italic">υ</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> tan.
                    ⅜p = -=—,</p>
                <p>~ V <hi rend="italic">sd</hi> and also that <hi rend="italic">v</hi> = √D ∙ <hi
                    rend="strikethrough">=X</hi> Comparing these <hi rend="italic">Vsd</hi><pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:194749222?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9222-0150"/>
                    values, ^∕z∙ ’ r <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> — <hi rend="italic">sd —</hi> Vŋ
                    (<hi rend="superscript"> λ</hi> ∕ <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> V ’ r∕),and,
                    consequently} <hi rend="italic">τ</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">r°</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">sd (s</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">r°) (s</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">τ</hi><hi
                    rend="italic                     superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >)</hi></p>
                <p>(v <hi rend="superscript"> z</hi> s — V ’ J) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (√ ’
                    ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> V&lt;∕) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>Having obtained the perihelion distance D, the true anomaly ∙ψ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi> of the point C <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> will be
                    given by the equation of the parabola, namely, <hi rend="italic">τ°</hi> cos.
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ⅜∙ψ <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> = D, from
                    which</p>
                <p>2Ý r"(√s-√d)</p>
                <p>The calculation of D and ∙ψ <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> is as follows: <hi
                    rend="italic">⅜ (r° + r'</hi> + c) <hi rend="italic">= s =</hi> (9 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 9232039) <hi rend="italic">l(</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">° + ť — c) = d =</hi> (9∙6770815) <hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> s</hi><hi rend="italic">-r</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi> (8∙80878805) <hi rend="italic">s-r'
                    =</hi> (9∙47438015)</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="subscript"> s</hi>-r <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>) <hi rend="italic"
                    >(s-ι</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> j</hi><hi rend="italic">) =</hi>
                    (8∙2831682)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Vď =</hi> (9’8385407) √s = (9∙9616019)</p>
                <p>= (9∙8769388) = ∙7532495</p>
                <p>1 _ <hi rend="subscript"> =</hi>-2467505 = (9∙39225808)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Vs</hi><hi rend="italic">Vs =</hi> (9∙9616019)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Vs</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">Vd =</hi> √.s
                    ( 1 = ) = (9∙35385998)</p>
                <p>∖ .</p>
                <p>(√s — <hi rend="italic">V</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> d</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">i</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >=</hi> (8’70771996)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">(s — r°) (s-r') =</hi> (8’2831682)</p>
                <p>D = (9∙5754482) <hi rend="italic">r</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi> =
                    (9∙8884811)</p>
                <p>cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ⅜∙ψ <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> =
                    (9∙6869671) tan.'∣∙ψ = (0∙0118412).</p>
                <p>Having thus obtained the perihelion distance and the true anomaly, we must now
                    find the time required for describing this anomaly. For this purpose it is usual
                    to employ a table constructed from the following property of bodies moving in a
                    parabolic orbit, namely, if T and T' be the times of describing the same anomaly
                    in two parabolas whose perihelion distances are respectively D and D', then T:
                    T':: D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: D' <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. Hence,
                    if a table is formed showing the time T' in which every degree, &amp;c. is
                    described in a parabola whose perihelion distance is D' = 1, it will give the
                    time T' in which the same anomaly is described in the parabola whose perihelion
                    distance is D, by simply multiplying the tabular .time by D <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; for when</p>
                <p>D' = 1, we have T = D <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> T'. The’time T must be added
                    to the epoch of the first observation, if the comet is approaching the
                    perihelion of its orbit, but subtracted from that epoch if it has already passed
                    the perihelion.</p>
                <p>But instead of employing a table of parabolic motion, the time may be computed
                    directly from the formula</p>
                <p>T = √2D (tan. ⅜p + ⅜ tan. <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ∣p), observing to add to
                    the logarithm of T the constant logarithm 1∙7644179 (the compliment of
                    8’2355821), in order that T may be expressed in mean solar days.</p>
                <p>Computing from this formula, there results in the present case,</p>
                <p>T = 26∙35895 Epoch of first observation, October 22∙68488</p>
                <p>Passage through perihelion, November 18∙04383.</p>
                <p>To determine the position of the orbit, we must first compute the heliocentric
                    latitudes and longitudes. Let α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 5 a</hi> ' be the heliocentric longitudes of the points C <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> and O'; <hi rend="italic">β°, β</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi> their heliocentric latitudes; then, denoting for an instant
                    by &lt;r the comet’s distance from the sun, we shall have <hi rend="italic"
                    >τ</hi> sin. <hi rend="italic">β — ΰ</hi> sin. 6; but <hi rend="italic">6
                    =</hi><hi rend="italic">g</hi> sec. 6, therefore <hi rend="italic subscript">
                    e</hi><hi rend="italic">°</hi><hi rend="italic">τsin. β =</hi> tan. 6°, whence
                    sin. /3° = η <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> ∙ tan. ó°, sin. <hi rend="italic"
                    >β</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">=</hi> tan. <hi rend="italic">b.</hi></p>
                <p>These two formulae, which are very easily computed, give the heliocentric
                    latitudes at the extreme observations. In the present case they become sin. <hi
                    rend="italic">β</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >=</hi> (9’4155979), sin. /3' = (9∙4341627).</p>
                <p>Now, to compute the heliocentric longitudes, let us suppose K to be the
                    projection of C on the plane of the ecliptic. In the rectilinear triangle ESK,
                    formed by joining the positions of the earth, the sun, and the projected place
                    of the comet, we have EK <hi rend="italic">= g;</hi> SK = <hi rend="italic"
                    >τ</hi> cos. <hi rend="italic">ß;</hi> the angle ESK, opposite to EK, = α— A,
                    the difference between the heliocentric longitude of the comet and the longitude
                    of the sun; and the angle KES, opposite to SK, <hi rend="italic">= a</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> A, the difference between the geocentric longitude of the
                    comet and the longitude of the sun; therefore <hi rend="italic">&gt;</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">:</hi><hi rend="italic">τ</hi> cos. <hi rend="italic">β</hi>::
                    sin. (α — A): sin. (α — A), from which, since - = <hi rend="subscript"> we</hi>
                    deduce for the first and <hi rend="italic">r</hi> tan. <hi rend="italic">υ</hi>
                    third observations, sin. (α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> — A <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi>) = sin. (a — A), sin. (a' — A') = <hi
                    rend="superscript"> t</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript
                    strikethrough"> an</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">* f</hi> sin. <hi rend="italic"
                    >(a</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">—</hi> A').</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> κ z</hi> tan. <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi></p>
                <p>In the present case these formulae become <hi rend="subscript"> sin</hi>,(<hi
                    rend="subscript"> α</hi> o-A <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>) = (9∙6598371),
                    sin.(α'- A') = (9∙8155230) <hi rend="subscript"> α</hi> o — A <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> = 27° 11' 18", a'—A' = 40° 50 ’ 15"∙45</p>
                <p>A <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> = 29 19 50, A' =41 22 26</p>
                <p>a <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> = 59 31 8 a' = 82 12 41’45</p>
                <p>Let N be the ascending node, <hi rend="italic">γ</hi> its longitude, and I the
                    inclination of the orbit. In the spherical triangle NCK, the side NK <hi
                    rend="italic">= a</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">γ,</hi> CK = <hi
                    rend="italic">β,</hi> and the angle CNK = I. Therefore, by Napier’s analogies,
                    cot. I = cot. <hi rend="italic">β</hi> sin. (α — <hi rend="italic">γ),</hi>
                    which, on substituting the longitudes a <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> and «',
                    gives the double equation cot. I = cot. <hi rend="italic">β°</hi> sin. (α <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi> — <hi rend="italic">γ)</hi> = cot. <hi rend="italic"
                    >β</hi> ’ sin. (α — y); from which we have sin. (α <hi rend="superscript">
                    0</hi><hi rend="underline">—</hi><hi rend="italic                     underline"
                    > γ)</hi><hi rend="italic">_</hi><hi rend="underline">tan,</hi><hi rend="italic
                    underline"> β°</hi> sin. (α' — <hi rend="italic">γ)</hi> tan. <hi rend="italic"
                    >β'</hi> ’ whence sin. (α <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> — <hi rend="italic"
                    >γ)</hi> + sin. (α' — 7) tan. <hi rend="italic underline"> β°</hi><hi
                    rend="underline">+ tan,</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> β'</hi> sin. (α <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0</hi> — <hi rend="italic">γ)</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi>
                    sin. (a — <hi rend="italic">γ) ~</hi> tan. <hi rend="italic">β</hi><hi
                    rend="italic                     superscript"> σ</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi>
                    tan. <hi rend="italic">β'</hi> But if A and B represent two arcs, then, by the
                    trigonometrical formulae, sin. A + sin. B _ t <hi rend="underline">an. ^(A +
                    B)</hi> sin. A — sin. B <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> tan. ⅛ ( A — B)' and tan.
                    A + tan. B _ <hi rend="underline">sin. (A + B)</hi> _ tan. A — tan. B sin. (A —
                    B) ’ whence the above equation becomes tan. {⅜ (<hi rend="superscript"> α</hi> °
                    <hi rend="underline">÷</hi><hi rend="underline">“') —</hi><hi rend="italic
                    underline"> 7}</hi> _ sin. <hi rend="underline">(∕3</hi><hi rend="superscript
                    underline"> z</hi><hi rend="underline">-⅜- ∕3</hi><hi rend="superscript
                    underline"> 0</hi><hi rend="underline">)</hi> tan. ⅜ (α' — a <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi>) sin. <hi rend="italic">(β'</hi> — β <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi>) ’ consequently</p>
                <p>ſ 1 ∕ <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi> i ,x X <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> * <hi
                    rend="superscript"> n</hi> ∙ (ß' ÷ ß°) <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> ' — <hi
                    rend="superscript"> a</hi> °</p>
                <p>tan. {i («’ + «) - <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi>} = — ⅛=j3φ *”· —2- <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194749235?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-9235-0151"/> The tangent
                    now found belongs to two different angles; but this circumstance can occasion no
                    ambiguity; for as the inclination I is supposed to be always less than 90°, the
                    cotangent of I must be always positive, so that sin. ζ <hi rend="subscript">
                    α</hi> °— must always have the same sign as cot. <hi rend="italic">β.</hi> This
                    consideration will enable the computer to choose between the two values of <hi
                    rend="italic">γ,</hi> which correspond to tan. (α <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>
                    + <hi rend="italic">a') y</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
                    With regard to the sign of <hi rend="italic">β,</hi> the northern latitudes are
                    supposed positive, and the southern negative; and the motion will be direct or
                    retrograde, according as <hi rend="subscript"> ci</hi> ' — <hi rend="subscript">
                    a</hi> ° is positive or negative.</p>
                <p>On computing the above formula, there results <hi rend="italic">į (a° +
                    a')</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">γ =</hi> 84° 14' 30'' but
                    ⅜(<hi rend="superscript"> α</hi> ° ÷ a') = 69 21 54 therefore —7 =14 52 36</p>
                <p>and consequently <hi rend="italic">γ =</hi> 345 7 24.</p>
                <p>By correcting this value from the double equation given above, Legendre finds <hi
                    rend="italic">-γ =</hi> 14° 52' 34"∙5 <hi rend="subscript"> γ</hi> = 345 7 25
                    ∙5.</p>
                <p>Having found the longitude of the node, the inclination I is given by the formula
                    cot. I = cot. /3° sin. (α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> — <hi rend="italic"
                    >γ),</hi> from which we deduce log. cot. I = 0∙5458488, I = 15° 53' 0"∙5.</p>
                <p>Lastly, let. H be the angular distance of the comet from the node, and ∏ be the
                    longitude of the perihelion. Then cos. H <hi rend="italic">=z</hi> cos. <hi
                    rend="italic">β°</hi> cos. (α <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> — <hi rend="italic"
                    >γ)</hi></p>
                <p>∏ = H + 7 + ∙ψ <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, if the comet is ad vancing to the
                    perihelion; or</p>
                <p>∏ = II + <hi rend="italic">γ</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> ∙ψ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o</hi>, if it has already passed the perihelion.</p>
                <p>In the present example,</p>
                <p>α° — <hi rend="italic">γ =</hi> 71° 23' 42"∙5 H = 72° 3' 32"∙9</p>
                <p>cos. (α <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>- <hi rend="italic">γ) =</hi> 9∙5038445 <hi
                    rend="italic">γ =</hi> 345 7 25 ∙5</p>
                <p>cos. <hi rend="italic">β°</hi> =9∙9847558 ∙ψ <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> = 91
                    33 43 ∙3</p>
                <p>cos. H = 9∙488G003 ∏ = 148 44 41 ∙7</p>
                <p>The elements of the orbit of this comet, therefore, as deduced from the above
                    solution, are as follows:</p>
                <p>Log. ∏ 9∙5754481</p>
                <p>Passage through the perihelion, November 18Ό4383</p>
                <p>Inclination 15° 53' 0'' ’ 5</p>
                <p>Longitude of ascending node 345 7 25 ∙5</p>
                <p>Longitude of the perihelion 148 44 41 ∙7</p>
                <p>Motion direct.</p>
                <p>The orbit determined according to the method which has here been explained, will
                    always satisfy the first and third observations. In general it will also
                    represent the second; but should it occur that the place of the comet at the
                    second observation, computed from the elements thus found, differs considerably
                    from its observed place, we may then conclude that the true orbit cannot be
                    represented by a parabola. In this case recourse must be had to the ellipse, for
                    computing which, the best method is that which is given by Gauss in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Theoria Motuum Corporum Coelestium.</hi> (s.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
