<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-2849-0429-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COUNCIL (7th edition, volume 7, page 429)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:866909">Coke</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916956">Eutychians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s296">Coke</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80t2w">Feasts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194752849?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COUNCIL</label>, in a general sense, an assembly of various
                    considerable persons, to concert measures relative to the state.</p>
                <p>In Britain, the law, in order to assist the king in the discharge of his duties,
                    the maintenance of his dignity, and the exertion of his prerogative, has
                    assigned him a diversity of councils to advise withal.</p>
                <p>The first of these is the high court of parliament.</p>
                <p>The peers of the realm are by their birth hereditary counsellors of the crown,
                    and may be called together by the king, to impart their advice in all matters of
                    importance to the realm, either in time of parliament, or, which has been their
                    principal use, when there is no parliament in being. Accordingly, Bracton,
                    speaking of the nobility of his time, says, they might properly be called <hi
                    rend="italic">consules</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >consulendo</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">reges enim
                    sibi</hi><hi rend="italic">associant ad</hi><hi rend="italic">consulendum.</hi>
                    And in the law books it is laid down, that the peers arc created for two
                    reasons; first, <hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic">consulendum,</hi>
                    and, secondly, <hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic">defendendum,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">regem</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> for which reasons the law gives
                    them certain great and high privileges, such as freedom from arrest, even when
                    no parliament is sitting, because the law holds that they are always assisting
                    the king with their counsel for the commonwealth, or keeping the realm in safety
                    by their prowess and valour.</p>
                <p>Instances of conventions of the peers to advise the king were frequent in former
                    times, though they have now fallen into disusê by reason of the more regular
                    meetings of parliament. Sir Edward Coke gives us an extract of a record, 5 Henry
                    IV. concerning an exchange of lands between the king and the Earl of
                    Northumberland, in which the value of each wás agreed to be settled by advice of
                    parliament, if any should be called before the feast of St Lucia, or otherwise
                    by advice of the grand council of peers, which the king promised to assemble
                    before the said feast in case no parliament should be called. Many-other
                    instances of this kind of meeting are to be found under our ancient kings;
                    though the formal method of convoking them had been so long left off, that when
                    King Charles 1. in 1640 issued writs under the great seal, calling a council of
                    all the peers of England to meet and attend his majesty at York, previously to
                    the meeting of the long parliament, the Earl of Clarendon mentions it as a new
                    invention not before heard of; that is, as he explains, so old, that it had not
                    been practised during some hundreds of years. But though there had not for a
                    long time before been an instance, nor has there been any since, of assembling
                    them in so solemn a manner, yet in cases of emergency our princes have at
                    several times thought proper to call for and consult as many of the nobility as
                    could easily be brought together. This was done by King James II. after the
                    landing of the Prince of Orange, and by the Prince of Orange himself before he
                    summoned the convention parliament which afterwards called him to the
                    throne.</p>
                <p>Besides this general meeting, it is usually looked upon as the right of each
                    particular peer of the realm to demand an audience of the king, and to lay
                    before him, with decency and respect, such matters as he shall judge of
                    importance to the public weal. And therefore, in the reign of Edward II. it was
                    made an article of impeachment in parliament against the Hugh Spencers, father
                    and son, for which they were banished the kingdom, “that they by their evil
                    covin would not suffer the great men of the realm, the king’s good counsellors,
                    to speak with the king, or to come near him; but only in presence and hearing of
                    said Hugh the father and Hugh the son, or one of them, and at their will, and
                    according to such things as pleased them.”</p>
                <p>A third council belonging to the king is, according to Sir Edward Coke, composed
                    of his judges of the courts of law, for law matters. And this appears frequently
                    in the English statutes, particularly 14 Edward III. c. 5, and in other books of
                    law. So that when the king’s council is mentioned generally, it must be
                    defined,particularized, and understood <hi rend="italic">secundum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">subjectam materiem,</hi> according to the subject matter; and if
                    the subject be of a legal nature, then by the king’s council is understood his
                    council for matters of law, namely', his judges. Therefore, when by statute 16
                    Richard II. c. 5, it was declared a high offence to import into England any
                    papal bulls, or other processes, from Rome, and when it was enacted that the
                    offenders should be attached by their bodies, and brought before the king and
                    his council to answer for such offence. By the expression of king’s <hi
                    rend="italic">council,</hi> here made use of, was understood the king’s judges
                    of his courts of justice, the subject-matter being legal, and this being the
                    general way of interpreting the word <hi rend="italic">council.</hi></p>
                <p>But the principal council belonging to the king is his Privy Council, which is
                    generally, by way of eminence, called The Council. For an account of its
                    constitution and powers, sec <hi rend="smallcaps">Privy Council.</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Council</hi><hi rend="italic">of War (</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Conseil</hi><hi rend="italic">de Guerre),</hi> an assembly of the principal
                    officers of an army or fleet, called by the general or admiral who commands, to
                    concert measures for their conduct. It has been remarked that councils of war
                    never fight.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Council,</hi> in church history, an assembly of prelates and
                    doctors, convened for regulating matters relative to the doctrine or discipline
                    of the church.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">National</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Council</hi> is an
                    assembly of the prelates of a nation under their primate or patriarch.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">(Ecumenical</hi> or <hi rend="italic">General</hi><hi
                    rend="italic smallcaps"> Council</hi> is an assembly which represents the body
                    of the universal church. The Romanists reckon eighteen of these; Bullinger, in
                    his Treatise <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Conciliis,</hi> six; and
                    Dr Prideaux, seven: but Bishop Beveridge has increased the number to eight,
                    which, he says, includes all the general councils that have ever been held since
                    the time of the first Christian emperor. They are as follow: The council of
                    Nice, held in the reign of Constantine the Great, on account of the heresy of
                    Arius; the council of Constantinople, called under the reign and by the command
                    of Theodosius the Great, for nearly the same purpose as the former; the council
                    of Ephesus, convened by Theodosius the younger at the suit of Nestorius; the
                    council of Chalcedon, held in the reign of Martimιs, which approved of the
                    Eutychian heresy; the second council of Constantinople, assembled by the Emperor
                    Justinian, which condemned the three chapters taken out of the book of Theodorus
                    of Mopsuestia (having first decided that it was lawful to anathematise the
                    dead), and also, according to some, the errors of Origen concerning the
                    Trinity<pb break="no" facs="nls:194752862?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0707-2862-0430"/>, a plurality of worlds, and the pre-existence of
                    souls; the third council of Constantinople, held by command of Constantius
                    Pogonatus, the emperor, in which were received the definitions of the five first
                    general councils, and particularly that against Origen and Theodorus of
                    Mopsueštia; the second Nicene council; and the fourth council of Constantinople,
                    assembled when Louis II. was emperor of the West. There arc several collections
                    of the canons or decrees of councils. The most extensive and valuable is that of
                    Hardouin, entitled <hi rend="italic">Conciliorum Collectio</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Regia maxima,</hi><hi rend="italic">edita</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi
                    rend="italic                     smallcaps"> Joanne Harωuino,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Soc. Icsu.</hi><hi rend="italic">Parisiis,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ex typographid rcgid.</hi> 1715, 12 vols, folio.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
