<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-5785-0686-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">OXFORDSHIRE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 686</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1053705">Parks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1013121">Meadows</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1139635">Surveys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1139579">Surveying</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f71c">Meadows</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zd00">Surveys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194565785" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">OXFORDSHIRE</label>, an inland county of England, chiefly
                    celebrated on account of its capital, which is one of the principal seats of
                    learning in the British dominions, and from which city it has derived its name.
                    It is bounded on the east by Buckinghamshire; on the south, south-west, and
                    south-east by Berkshire; on the north-east by Northamptonshire; and on the
                    north-west by the county of Warwick. The river Thames (called sometimes the Isis
                    till it reaches Oxford) is the line of demarcation on the whole of its southern
                    boundary; running between this county and Berkshire with various, and, in the
                    latter part of its course, most beautiful sinuosities. The county is of a most
                    irregular figure. Near the centre, in which the city of Oxford stands, it is not
                    more than seven miles in breadth, and at no great distance to the north it is
                    thirty-eight miles. Towards the north it resembles a çone, and to the south it
                    is similarly contracted. Its extreme length is fifty miles. The extent is
                    estimated at 742 square miles, or 474,880 English acres. It contains one city,
                    twelve market-towns, and 207 parishes, and is divided into fourteen
                    hundreds.</p>
                <p>This county is by no means uniformly beautiful. On the north, the absence of
                    hedges, which are supplied by stone walls, gives a dreary appearance to the face
                    of the country. In the centre it is generally flat and woody, affording few
                    pleasant prospects, though its trees and verdure give it the semblance of
                    wealth. The southern part, from the beauty of its rivers, the gentle swelling of
                    its hills, the verdant meadows between them, and the number of highly
                    embellished residences of rich proprietors, is a district abounding with rural
                    charms. The Chiltern Hills, the highest range in England south of the river
                    Trent, belong to this portion. They are in many parts adorned with beech-woods,
                    and in every interval of these woods cultivated quite to their summits.</p>
                <p>The climate of the county varies according to the elevation and exposure. In the
                    north, where no hedges impede the winter winds, the cold is somewhat severe; and
                    the Chiltern Hills are frequently enveloped in damp fogs, especially in the more
                    woody parts of them. Mr Arthur Young, in his Agricultural Survey of Oxfordshire,
                    has formed a classification of the soils in the different districts of the
                    county, which, like all similar estimates, must be received with hesitation, or
                    at least with many exceptions. The red soil, found chiefly in the north, and by
                    far the most fertile, he estimates at 79,635 acres. The land, provincially
                    called <hi rend="italic">stone-brash,</hi> found in the centre, and the surface
                    of which is often covered with stones, amounts to 164,023 acres. The Chiltern
                    lands, the soil of which is a loam resting everywhere on a bed of chalk, and
                    covered with flint stones, are 64,778 acres. To these are added 166,400 acres
                    under the description of miscellaneous, which comprehends all sorts of soil,
                    from loose sand to the heaviest clay, and includes the rich meadows on the banks
                    of the rivers.</p>
                <p>Although this is wholly an agricultural county, and although much progress in
                    improvement has been made of late years, yet the general practices are by no
                    means equal to the average of those of the rest of England. The most beneficial
                    husbandry is founded upon the valuable water-meadows on the banks of the
                    different streams. These are naturally so fertile that they appear to have
                    prevented that care which would render them still more productive. Little
                    attention is paid to draining, and still less to irrigation; though the good
                    effects of both these practices are obvious, and their accomplishment easy in
                    many circumstances. Some few oxen are fattened, and butter and cheese made in
                    the dairies, but the facility of navigation induces the farmers to make more hay
                    than is consumed by their stock, and to send it to distant and higher markets
                    than their own, nearer to the metropolis. On the arable fields, especially on
                    the stony lands near Burford, the use of oxen for the plough is very common; and
                    the Herefordshire breed is generally preferred for that purpose. The practice of
                    paring and burning the surface prevails in many parts of the county; and in the
                    newly enclosed lands the application of lime as a manure is highly beneficial;
                    whilst on the Chiltern lands it is not found to produce a good effect equal to
                    the expense which attends it.</p>
                <p>Where the soils are so very various, the rotation of crops must necessarily vary
                    with them. On the red soils, the most usual course is, 1st, turnips; 2d, barley,
                    or springwheat; 3d, clover; 4th, wheat; 5th, peas or beans; and, 6th, oats. On
                    the stone-brash lands, the usual rotation is, 1st, turnips; 2d, barley; 3d,
                    clover, to stand for two years; 4th, wheat; and, oth, oats, peas, or sometimes,
                    but rarely, beans. On the Chiltern lands the rotations are the same, with only
                    slight variations. On both these last tracts of country, the cultivation of
                    sainfoin is very extensive; occupying on most farms from one seventh to one
                    eighth of the whole. This valuable artificial grass produces heavy crops. When
                    it was first introduced, it would remain productive for fifteen or sixteen
                    years; but since it has become more familiarized to the soil, it seldom lasts
                    more than seven years so as to be fit to make hay, but yields food for sheep for
                    one or two years afterwards. The sheep, which were formerly almost all of the
                    Berkshire breed, have of late years been superseded by the race of the South
                    Downs.</p>
                <p>Oxfordshire is not a manufacturing district. Witney was long celebrated for its
                    blankets, and still retains its fame; but, in spite of the machinery which has
                    been introduced to diminish the price, the manufacturers of Yorkshire and
                    Lancashire excel those produced here. At present, however, this trade gives
                    employment to 270 persons in the town and two adjoining hamlets. At Banbury, and
                    its adjacent hamlet Neithrop, 125 persons are occupied in making plushes and
                    girth-webs, and a number in some other parishes within the county. Gloves of a
                    superior kind are made at Woodstock and its vicinity; and <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194565798" xml:id="kp-eb0716-5798-0687"/>there are some of the finer
                    kinds of cutlery made in that town. Sacking is made at Abingdon and at Henley;
                    and many axles and coach-wheels at Henley-on-Thames.</p>
                <p>The rivers all discharge themselves into the Thames. They are formed by the
                    numerous small springs which are everywhere to be seen; and before they join the
                    Thames, are called the Windrush, coming from Burford and Witney; the Evenlode,
                    from Wichwood and Charlbury; and the Cherwell, from the vicinity of Banbury. The
                    Thames, composed of the stream of that name and the Isis (on which a strange
                    confusion has arisen), is navigable from near one of its sources, not far from
                    Leachlade, to the sea. The barges navigating it are from seventy-five to one
                    hundred tons burden, but the larger ones ascend no higher than Oxford. From the
                    frequent recurrence of shoals, owing to the floods in winter, and the scarcity
                    of water in summer, it is a dilatory navigation; so that frequently the passage
                    from America to London occupies less time than from Leachlade to that city. The
                    scarcity of fuel was severely experienced till within these last few years; but
                    the completion of a canal which connects the city of Oxford with the collieries
                    of Staffordshire has removed the evil, and proved highly profitable to the
                    proprietors of that important work.</p>
                <p>The city of Oxford, the glory of this county and of the kingdom, has already been
                    described.</p>
                <p>The antiquities of this county have been accurately described, and are deserving
                    of the closest inspection. Amongst them are traces of the various roads formed
                    by the Romans, whose principal station was at Dorchester; besides many funereal
                    mounds, and the Vallum, called the Devil’s Ditch. The Priory of Godstow, and the
                    ruins of many other religious houses, exhibit the architecture of different and
                    remote ages.</p>
                <p>The population of this county, according to the returns at the four decennial
                    enumerations, has been as follows, viz. in 1801, 109,620; in 1811, 119,191; in
                    1821, 136,971; and in 1831, 152,100.</p>
                <p>The occupiers of land employing labourers were 2054</p>
                <p>Occupiers of land not employing labourers ...458 Labourers employed in
                    agriculture 15,998</p>
                <p>Labourers employed in manufactures 711</p>
                <p>Labourers employed in retail trade or han dicraft 11,110</p>
                <p>Capitalists, bankers, &amp;c 2,254</p>
                <p>Labourers not agricultural 3,049</p>
                <p>Other males under twenty years of age 2,547</p>
                <p>Male servants 1,223</p>
                <p>Female servants 5,571</p>
                <p>The towns within this county which contain more than 1000 inhabitants are the
                    following:</p>
                <p>Oxford 20,640 inhabitants.</p>
                <p>Banbury 5,906</p>
                <p>Witney 5,336</p>
                <p>Henley-on-Thames 3,618</p>
                <p>Bicester 2,868</p>
                <p>Thame 2,885</p>
                <p>Chipping Norton 2,637</p>
                <p>Burford 1,866</p>
                <p>Watlington 1,833</p>
                <p>Bampton 1,605</p>
                <p>Deddington 1,590</p>
                <p>Woodstock 1,380</p>
                <p>The whole county is in the diocese of its chief city. The members returned to the
                    House of Commons under the new law are, three for the county, who are polled for
                    at Oxford, Witney, Deddington, and Nettlebed; two each for the city and for the
                    university <hi rend="italic">of</hi> Oxford; and one each for the boroughs of
                    Banbury and Woodstock.</p>
                <p>The most distinguished residences are, Blenheim Cas tle, Duke of Marlborough;
                    Blandford House, Duke of Beaufort; Brightwell, W. Lowndes Stowe, Esq.;
                    Cud-desdon Palace, Bishop of Oxford; Crowsley Park, John Atkins Wright, Esq.;
                    Ditchley Park, Lord Dillon; Grey’s Court, Lady Stapleton; Heythorp, Earl of
                    Shrewsbury; Kirtlington Park, Sir H. W. Dashwood; Middleton Stoney, Earl of
                    Jersey; Mongewell, Bishop of Durham; Mapledurham, Michael Blount, Esq.; Nuneham
                    Park, Lord Vernon; Ry cot Park, Earl of Abingdon; Shiplake, Lord Mark Kerr;
                    Shelswell, Harrison,</p>
                <p>Esq.; Shirburn Castle, Earl of Macclesfield; Thane Park, Miss Wykham; Wroxton,
                    Earl of Guildford; Waterstock, W. H. Ashhurst, Esq.; Wormsley, John Fane, Esq.;
                    Wheatfield, Lord Churchill.</p>
                <p>(See the <hi rend="italic">Agricultural</hi><hi rend="italic">State of
                    Oxfordshire,</hi> by Arthur Young; Pott’s <hi rend="italic">Oxfordshire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> and Brewer’s Account of Oxfordshire, in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Beauties of England and Wales.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
