<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-3612-0519-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ORDEAL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 519</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40p0wv7t">Paganism</term>
                    <term n="25" ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dp26">Ordeals</term>
                    <term n="25" ref="lcsh1910:b40r9mb0h">Ordeal</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="25" ref="fasttopic:1047347">Ordeal</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:925173">Fire</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194563612" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ORDEAL</label>, an ancient form of trial. It consisted in an
                    appeal to the immediate interposition of divine power, being particularly
                    distinguished by the appellation of <hi rend="italic">judicium Deiς</hi> and was
                    sometimes called <hi rend="italic">purgatio vulgaris,</hi> to distinguish it
                    from the canonical purgation, which was by the oath of the party. Two kinds of
                    this trial were more common than the rest, at least in Europe; viz. fire-ordeal
                    and water-ordeal. The former was confined to persons of high rank, the latter to
                    the common people. Both these might be performed by deputy; but the principal
                    was bound to answer for the success of the trial, the deputy only venturing some
                    corporal pain, for hire, or perhaps for friendship.</p>
                <p>That the purgation by ordeal, of some kind or other, is very aneient, admits not
                    of a doubt; and that it was universal in the times of superstitious ignorance,
                    seems to be equally certain. It appears even to have been known to the ancient
                    Greeks; for, in the <hi rend="italic">Antigone</hi> of Sophocles, a person
                    suspected by Creon of a misdemeanour, declares himself ready “to handle hot iron
                    and to walk over fire,” in order to manifest his innocence, which, the scholiast
                    tells us, was then an usual mode of purgation. And Grotius gives many instances
                    of water-ordeal in Bithynia, Sardinia, and other places. It seems, however, to
                    have been carried to a greater height amongst the Hindus than ever it had been
                    in any nation or amongst any people, however rude or barbarous; for in a paper
                    in the Asiatic Researches, communicated by Mr Hastings, we find that the trial
                    by ordeal amongst that people is conducted in nine different ways: firstly, by
                    the balance; secondly, by fire; thirdly, by^water; fourthly, by poison; fifthly,
                    by the <hi rend="italic">cosha,</hi> or the water in which an idol has been
                    washed; sixthly, by rice; seventhly, by boiling oil; eighthly, by red-hot iron;
                    and ninthly, by images.</p>
                <p>1. Ordeal by the balance is thus performed. The beam having been previously
                    adjusted, the cord fixed, and both scales made perfectly equiponderant, the
                    person accused and a pundit fast a whole day; then, after the accused has been
                    bathed in sacred water, the <hi rend="italic">homa</hi> or oblation presented to
                    fire, and the deities worshipped, he is carefully weighed; and when he is taken
                    out of the scale, the pundits prostrate themselves before it, pronounce a
                    certain <hi rend="italic">mentra</hi> or incantation, agreeably to the Shastras,
                    and, having written the substance of the accusation upon a piece of paper, bind
                    it on his head. Six minutes afterwards they place him again in the scale, and if
                    he weigh more than before, he is held guilty; if less, innocent; if exactly the
                    same, he must be weighed a third time, when, as it is written in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Mitacshera,</hi> there will certainly be a difference in his
                    weight. Should the balance, though well fixed, break down, this would be
                    considered as a proof of his guilt.</p>
                <p>2. For the fire-ordeal, an excavation, nine hands in length, two spans in
                    breadth, and one span in depth, is made in the ground, and filled with a fire of
                    pippal-wood. Into this the person accused must walk barefooted; and, if his foot
                    be unhurt, they hold him blameless; but if it be burned, he is held guilty.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In Europe, fire-ordeal was
                    performed either by taking up in the hand, unhurt, a piece of red-hot iron, of
                    one, two, or three pounds eight; or else by walking, barefooted and blindfold,
                    over nine red-hot ploughshares, laid lengthwise at unequal distances; and if the
                    arty escaped unhurt, he was adjudged innocent; but if it happened otherwise, as
                    without collusion it usually did, he was then )ndemned as guilty. However, by
                    this latter method, Queen Emma, the mother of Edward the Confessor, is mentioned
                    to have cared her character, when suspected of familiarity with Alwyn, bishop of
                    Winchester. The first account which we have of Christians )pealing to the
                    fire-ordeal, as a proof of their innocence, is that of Simplicius, bishop of
                    Autun, who lived in the fourth century. This relate, as the story is related,
                    before his promotion to the episcopal order, had married a wife, who loved him
                    tenderly, and who, □willing to quit him after his advancement, continued to
                    sleep in the same chamber with him. The sanctity of Simplicius suffered,; least
                    in the voice of fame, by the constancy of his wife’s affection; and it was
                    rumoured about that the holy man, though a bishop, irsisted, in opposition to
                    the ecclesiastical canons, to taste the sweets of matrimony; upon which his
                    wife, in the presence of a great ∣ncourse of people, took up a considerable
                    quantity of burning coals, which she held in her clothes, and applied to her
                    breasts, withI it the least hurt to her person or her garments, as the legend
                    says; and her example being followed by her husband with similar I ιccess, the
                    credulous multitude admired the miracle, and proclaimed the innocence of the
                    loving pair. A similar trick was played ∣' St Brice, in the fifth century.
                    (Mosheim, <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiast. Hist.</hi> vol. ii.)</p></note></p>
                <p>3. Water-ordeal is performed by causing the person <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194563625" xml:id="kp-eb0716-3625-0520"/>accused to stand in a depth
                    of water, either flowing or stagnant, sufficient to reach his navel; but care
                    should be taken that no ravenous animal be in it, and that it be not moved by
                    much air. A Brahmin is then directed to go into the water, holding a staff in
                    his hand; and a soldier shoots three arrows upon dry ground from a bow of cane.
                    A man is next despatched to bring the arrow which has been shot farthest; and,
                    after he has taken it up, another is ordered to run from the edge of the water;
                    at which instant the person accused is told to grasp the foot or the staff of
                    the Brahmin, who stands near him in the water, and immediately to dive into it.
                    He must remain under water till the two men who went to fetch the arrows have
                    returned; for, if he raise his head or body above the surface before the arrows
                    are brought back, his guilt is considered as fully proved. In the villages near
                    Benares, it is the practice for the person who is to be tried by this kind of
                    ordeal to stand in water up to his navel, and then, holding the foot of a
                    Brahmin, to dive under it as long as a man can walk fifty paces very gently; if,
                    before the man has walked thus far, the accused rise above the water, he is
                    condemned; but if not, he is acquitted.</p>
                <p>4. There are two sorts of trial by poison. Firstly, the pundits having performed
                    their homa, and the person accused his ablution, two <hi rend="italic"
                    >rettis</hi> and a half, or seven barley-corns of <hi rend="italic"
                    >vishanaga,</hi> a poisonous root, or of <hi rend="italic">saudhya,</hi> that
                    is, white arsenic, are mixed in eight <hi rend="italic">mashas,</hi> or
                    sixty-four <hi rend="italic">rettis, of</hi> clarified butter, which the accused
                    must eat from the hand of a Brahmin. If the poison produce no visible effect, he
                    is absolved; but if otherwise, he is condemned. Secondly, the hooded snake,
                    called <hi rend="italic">nagga,</hi> is thrown into a deep earthen pot, into
                    which is dropped a ring, a seal, or a coin. This the person accused is ordered
                    to take out with his hand; and, if the serpent bite him, he is pronounced
                    guilty; but if not, he is declared innocent.</p>
                <p>5. Trial by the cosha is as follows. The accused is made to drink three draughts
                    of the water in which the images of the sun, of Devi, and other deities, have
                    been washed for that purpose; and if, within fourteen days, he has any sickness
                    or indisposition, his crime is considered as proved.</p>
                <p>6. When several persons are suspected of theft, some dry rice is weighed with the
                    sacred stone called <hi rend="italic">salgrarn,</hi> or certain <hi
                    rend="italic">slocas</hi> are read over it; after which the suspected persons
                    are severally ordered to chew a quantity of it. As soon as they have chewed it,
                    they are to throw on it some leaves of <hi rend="italic">pippal,</hi> or, if
                    none be at hand, some <hi rend="italic">l&gt;hurja</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >patra,</hi> or bark of a tree from Nepaul or Cashmere. The man'from whose mouth
                    the rice comes dry or stained with blood is held guilty; the rest are
                    acquitted.</p>
                <p>7. The ordeal by hot oil is exceedingly simple. When it is heated sufficiently,
                    the accused thrusts his hand into it; and, if he be not burned, he is held
                    innocent.</p>
                <p>8. In the same manner they make an iron ball, or the head of a lance, red hot,
                    and place it in the hands of the person accused, who, if it burn him not, is
                    judged guiltless.</p>
                <p>9. To perform the ordeal by <hi rend="italic">dharmach,</hi> which is the name of
                    the <hi rend="italic">sloca</hi> appropriated to this mode of trial, either an
                    image, named <hi rend="italic">dharma,</hi> or the genius of justice, is made of
                    silver, and another, called <hi rend="italic">adharma,</hi> of clay or iron,
                    both of which are thrown into a large earthen jar; and the accused having thrust
                    his hand into it, is acquitted if he bring out the silver image, but condemned
                    if he draw forth the iron. Or, one figure of a deity is painted on white cloth,
                    and another on black; the first of which they name <hi rend="italic"
                    >dharma,</hi> and the second <hi rend="italic">adharma.</hi> These are severally
                    rolled up in cow-dung, and thrown into a large jar, without having ever been
                    shown to the accused, who must put his hand into the jar, and is acquitted or
                    convicted according as he draws out the figure on white or on black cloth.</p>
                <p>The superstitious weakness of mankind, when left to themselves, is astonishing.
                    There is indeed nothing so absurd that they may not be made most firmly to
                    believe, nothing so impious that they will not do. Nor can a more notorious
                    instance of the truth of this assertion be possibly given than that of the trial
                    by ordeal. The gross absurdity as well as impiety of pronouncing a man guilty
                    unless he was cleared by a miracle, and of expecting that all the powers of
                    nature should be suspended by an immediate interposition of Providence to save
                    the innocent, when it was even presumptuously required, is self-evident. Yet the
                    origin of this mode of trial may be traced to necessity as well as to
                    superstition. At the time in which it originated in England, as well as in other
                    countries of Europe, it was no easy matter for an innocent person, when accused
                    of guilt, to get himself cleared by the then established mode of trial. It was
                    therefore natural for superstition to fly to Heaven for those testimonies of
                    innocence which the absurdity of human laws often prevented men from obtaining
                    in the ordinary course of affairs. In this way, doubtless, did the trial by
                    ordeal commence; and being thus begun by necessitous superstition, it was
                    fostered by impious priestcraft and unjust power. During all the processes there
                    was great room for collusion and deceit, and there can be no question but it was
                    often practised; it could not, therefore, on any account, or in any case, be a
                    sign of innocence or of guilt.</p>
                <p>Besides the particular methods of trial which we have already mentioned, there
                    were some few more common in European countries; as the judicial combat, the
                    ordeal of the cross, and the ordeal of the corsned.</p>
                <p>The judicial combat was well suited to the genius and spirit of fierce and
                    warlike nations, and, as we might reasonably expect, formed one of the most
                    ancient and universal modes of trial. We know that it was exceedingly common in
                    Germany in very remote ages. It was also used in some countries on the Continent
                    at a pretty early period; but it is not mentioned in any of the Anglo-Saxon
                    laws, and it does not appear to have been much used in England until after the
                    Conquest. It was so much the custom in the middle ages of Christianity to
                    respect the cross even to superstition, that it would indeed have been wonderful
                    if the same ignorant bigotry had not converted it into an ordeal; and
                    accordingly we find it used for this purpose in so many different ways as almost
                    to preclude description. In criminal trials, the judgment of the cross was
                    commonly conducted in this manner. When the prisoner had declared his innocence
                    upon oath, and appealed to the judgment of the cross, two sticks were prepared
                    exactly like one another; the figure of the cross was cut on one of these
                    sticks, and nothing on the other; each of them was then wrapped up in a quantity
                    of fine white wool, and laid on the altar, or on the relics of the saints; after
                    which a solemn prayer was offered up to God, that he would be pleased to
                    discover, by evident signs, whether the prisoner was innocent or guilty. These
                    solemnities being finished, a priest approached the altar, and took up one of
                    the sticks, which was uncovered with much anxiety. If it was the stick marked
                    with the cross, the prisoner was pronounced innocent; but if it was the other,
                    he was declared guilty. When the judgment of the cross was appealed to in civil
                    causes, the trial was usually conducted in this manner. The judges, parties, and
                    all concerned, being assembled in a church, each of the parties chose a priest,
                    the youngest and stoutest whom he could find, to be his representative in the
                    trial. These representatives were then placed one on each side of some famous
                    crucifix; and, at a signal given, they both at once stretched their arms at full
                    length, so as to form a cross with their body. In this painful posture they
                    continued to stand whilst divine service was performing; and the party whose
                    representative dropped his arms first lost his cause.</p>
                <p>The corsned, or the consecrated bread and cheese, was <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194563638" xml:id="kp-eb0716-3638-0521"/>the ordeal to which the
                    clergy commonly appealed when they were accused of any crimes; and in this they
                    acted a very prudent part, as it was attended with no danger or inconvenience.
                    This ordeal was performed in this manner. A piece of barley bread and a piece of
                    cheese were laid upon the altar, over which a priest pronounced certain
                    conjurations, and prayed with great fervency, that if the person accused was
                    guilty, God would send his angel Gabriel to stop his throat, that he might not
                    be able to swallow that bread and cheese. These prayers being ended, the culprit
                    approached the altar, took up the bread and cheese, and began to eat it. If he
                    swallowed freely, he was declared innocent; but if it stuck in his throat, and
                    he could not swallow, which we may presume seldom or never happened, he was
                    pronounced guilty.</p>
                <p>Besides these, there were a variety of other ordeals practised in Christian
                    countries, many of which retain the same names which were used amongst Pagans,
                    and differ only as to the mode in which they were performed. In all nations of
                    Christians where these trials were used, we find the clergy engaged in them.
                    Indeed, in England, as late as the time of King John, we find grants to the
                    bishops and clergy to use the <hi rend="italic">judicium</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ferri,</hi><hi rend="italic">aquae,</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ignis</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and, both in England and
                    Sweden, the clergy presided at this trial, and it was only performed in the
                    churches, or in other consecrated ground. “Non defuit illis operae et laboris
                    pretium,” says Stiernhook; “semper enim ab ejusmodi judicio aliquid lucri
                    sacerdotibus obveniebat.” But, to give the canon law its due praise, we find it
                    at a very early period declaring against trial by ordeal, or <hi rend="italic"
                    >vulgaris</hi><hi rend="italic">purgatio,</hi> as being the work of the devil,
                    “cum sit contra praeceptum Domini, <hi rend="italic">Non tentabis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Dominum Deum</hi><hi rend="italic">tuum.'</hi> ’ Upon this
                    authority, though the canons themselves were of no validity in England, it was
                    thought proper (as had been done in Denmark above a century before) to disuse
                    and abolish this trial entirely in our courts of justice, by an act of
                    parliament 3 Henry III. according to Sir Edward Coke, or rather by an order of
                    the king in council.</p>
                <p>It may still perhaps be a postulate with some in what manner the effects of these
                    trials were evaded, and how it was possible to appear to do that which we know
                    could not be really done without material injury to the persons concerned. On
                    this subject Dr Henry observes, in reference to the ordeals in ancient Britain,
                    that, if we suppose few or none escaped conviction who exposed themselves to
                    those fiery trials, we shall be very much mistaken. “For the histories of those
                    times contain innumerable examples of persons plunging their naked arms into
                    boiling water, handling red-hot balls of iron, and walking upon burning
                    ploughshares, without receiving the least injury. Many learned men have been
                    much puzzled to account for this, and disposed to think that Providence
                    graciously interposed, in a miraculous manner, for the preservation of injured
                    innocence. But if we examine every circumstance of those fiery ordeals with due
                    attention, we shall see sufficient reason to suspect that the whole was a gross
                    imposition on the credulity of mankind. The accused person was committed wholly
                    to the priest who was to perform the ceremony, three days before the trial, in
                    which he had time enough to bargain with him for his deliverance, and give him
                    instructions how to act his part. On the day of trial, no person was permitted
                    to enter the church but the priest and the accused till after the iron was
                    heated, when twelve friends of the accuser, and twelve of the accused, and no
                    more, were admitted, and ranged along the wallon each side of the church, at a
                    respectful distance. After the iron was taken out of the fire, several prayers
                    were said;, the accused drank a cup of holy water, and sprinkled his hand with
                    it, which might take a considerable time if the priest was indulgent. The space
                    of nine feet was measured by the accused himself with his own feet, and he would
                    probably give but scanty measure. He was obliged only to touch one of the marks
                    with the toe of his right foot, and allowed to stretch the other foot as far
                    towards the other mark as he could, so that the conveyance was almost
                    instantaneous. His hand was not immediately examined, but wrapped in a cloth
                    prepared for that purpose three days. May we not, then, from all these
                    precautions, suspect that those priests were in possession of some secret that
                    secured the hand from the impressions of such a momentary touch of hot iron, or
                    removed all appearance of these impressions in three days; and that they made
                    use of this secret whenever they saw reason? What greatly strengthens these
                    suspicions is, that we meet with no example of any champion of the church who
                    suffered the least injury from the touch of hot iron in this ordeal; but when
                    any one was so fool-hardy as to appeal to it, or to that of hot water, with a
                    view to deprive the church of any of her possessions, he never failed to burn
                    his fingers, and lose his cause.”</p>
                <p>To this we may add what the learned Beckmann<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>‘ Vol. iii. 297∙</p></note> has stated concerning the
                    imposition which was probably practised in the ordeal by fire. “I am not
                    acquainted with every thing that concerns the trial by ordeal, when persons
                    accused were obliged to prove their innocence by holding in their hands red-hot
                    iron; but 1 am almost convinced that this was also a juggling trick of the
                    popes, which they employed as might best suit their views. It is well known that
                    this mode of exculpation was allowed only to weak persons, who were unfit to
                    wield arms, and particularly to monks and ecclesiastics, to whom, for the sake
                    of their security, that by single combat was forbidden. The trial itself took
                    place in the church, entirely under the inspection of the clergy; mass was
                    celebrated at the same time; the defendant and the iron were consecrated, by
                    being sprinkled with holy water; the clergy made the iron hot themselves; and
                    they used all these preparatives, <hi rend="superscript"> as</hi> jugglers do
                    many motions, only to divert the attention of the spectators. It was necessary
                    that the accused person should remain at least three days and three nights under
                    their immediate care, and continue as long after. They covered his hands both
                    before and after the proof, sealed and unsealed the covering; the former, as
                    they pretended, to prevent the hands from being prepared any how by art; the
                    latter, to see if they were burned.</p>
                <p>“Some artificial preparation was therefore known, else no precautions would have
                    been necessary. It is highly probable, that during the first three days the
                    preventive was applied to those persons whom they wished to appear innocent; and
                    that the three days after the trial were requisite to let the hands resume their
                    natural state. The sacred sealing secured them from the examination of
                    presumptuous unbelievers; for, to determine whether the hands were burned, the
                    last three days were certainly not wanted. When the ordeal was abolished, and
                    this art rendered useless, the clergy no longer kept it a secret. In the
                    thirteenth century, an account of it was published by Albertus Magnus, a
                    Dominican monk.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In his
                    work <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Mirabilibus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Mundi,</hi> at the enel of his book <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Secretis Mulierum,</hi> Amsterdam, 1702, 12mo, p. 100.
                    “Experimentum mirabile quod facit hominem ire in ignem sine laesione, vel
                    portare ignem vel ferrum ignitum sine laesione in manu. Recipe succum
                    bistnalvae, et albumen ovi, et semen psylli et calcem, et pulveriza, et confice
                    cum illo albumine ovi succum raphani; commisce; ex hac confectione illineas
                    corpus tuum vel manum, et dimitte siccari, et postea iterum illineas, et post
                    hoc poteris audacter ιustincre ignem sine nocumento.”</p></note> If his receipt
                    be <pb break="no" facs="nls:194563651" xml:id="kp-eb0716-3651-0522"/>genuine, it
                    seems to have consisted rather in covering the hands with a kind of paste than
                    in hardening them. The sap of the <hi rend="italic">althaea</hi> (marshmallow),
                    the slimy seeds of the flea-bane, which is still used for stiffening by the
                    hatmakers and silk-weavers, together with the white of an egg, were employed to
                    make the paste adhere. And by these means the hands were as safe as if they had
                    been secured by gloves.</p>
                <p>“The use of this juggling trick is very old, and may be traced back to a Pagan
                    origin. In the <hi rend="italic">Antigone</hi> of Sophocles, the guards placed
                    over the body of Polynices, which had been buried contrary to the orders of
                    Creon, offered, in order to prove their innocence, to submit to any trial. We
                    will, said they, take up red-hot iron in our hands, or walk through fire.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
