<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0716-5707-0680-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">OVIEDO</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 680</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86t6p">Mining</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950478">Haitians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1086604">Racing</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1086436">Race</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1179191">Wood</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205135">Haiti</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194565707" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">OVIEDO</label>, a city of Spain, in the province of Asturias,
                    of which it is the capital. It is situated between the rivers Nalon and Nora, on
                    a hill of granite, and enjoys a serene atmosphere, although generally rather
                    rainy. Its fields are fertile, and yield abundance of fruits and horticultural
                    vegetables; and near it there are good meadows, where cattle are depastured, and
                    hay made for the winter consumption of stock. The city contains a population of
                    6000 inhabitants, amongst whom there are some of the most distinguished families
                    of the province, who unfortunately prefer a residence in cities to living on
                    their own estates. It is not a place of trade, but rather the resort of lawyers
                    and clergy. It has a very magnificent cathedral in the Gothic style, with a
                    remarkable lofty tower, an university, a well-endowed hospital, and a beautiful
                    public walk. It is supplied with water by a fine aqueduct, which conveys it from
                    two fountains in the neighbouring hills. Long. 5. 56. 22. W. Lat. 43. 21. 55.
                    N.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Oviedo,</hi><hi rend="italic">John Gonsales,</hi> in
                    Spanish, Gonçalo Herman-dez de Oviedo y Valdez, a celebrated historian, was born
                    at Madrid about the year 1478, and educated amongst the pages of Ferdinand and
                    Isabella. Oviedo had attained the age of fifteen when Christopher Columbus
                    returned from his first voyage; and being seized with a strong desire to learn
                    the details relating to the great discovery of the illustrious<pb break="no" facs="nls:194565720" xml:id="kp-eb0716-5720-0681"/> navigator, he
                    soon made himself acquainted with all that had passed in this wonderful
                    expedition. Having embraced the profession of arms, he distinguished himself in
                    the war of Naples, where he rendered important service to Spain; and it was in
                    recompense of his talents and bravery that Ferdinand appointed him director of
                    the gold and silver mines in the island of Haïti, which Columbus named first <hi rend="italic">Espanola·,</hi> and then <hi rend="italic">San-Domingo.</hi>
                    Oviedo proceeded to his destination in 1513; and employed in working the mines,
                    which were poor compared with those afterwards discovered in the continent of
                    America, the natives of the island, a good and gentle race, naturally indolent,
                    and by no means robust, with constitutions already enfeebled by the ravages of
                    syphilis, a disease previously unknown in the old world. This unfortunate
                    people, who had received the companions of Columbus with so much cordiality,
                    Oviedo treated worse than beasts of burden; compelling them to labour without
                    intermission, and exercising the greatest cruelties to enforce submission to his
                    commands on the part of a race which had previously lived in idleness,
                    subsisting on the abundant natural productions of the climate, and on fish,
                    which they caught without difficulty, as an amusement rather than an occupation.
                    The abominable tyranny to which the natives were thus subjected soon caused a
                    considerable diminution of their number; and Oviedo, in order to justify himself
                    for the oppression and cruelty which he exercised, had the bad faith to allege,
                    in his writings, that the Haitians were dissolute, unprincipled, and in every
                    respect deserving of extermination. Nor was this all. Not content with
                    calumniating the people he had so cruelly treated, he added the ridiculous
                    falsehood, that amongst them syphilis was the result of debauchery; whereas,
                    according to the testimony of all impartial historians, it had been ascertained
                    by Columbus that the Haitian people were comparatively indifferent to sexual
                    pleasure, a circumstance by no means common in a burning climate, and which can
                    only be explained by the weak physical organization of these islanders, or by a
                    deficiency of vital power. A residence of nearly twelve years in Haïti enabled
                    Oviedo to study the natural history <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the island in all
                    its parts, to observe syphilis in all its types, and to ascertain the remedies
                    which the natives employed in their treatment of the disease. The principal of
                    these was the gaiae, which is still classed amongst die number of the
                    antisyphilitics. On his return to Spain in 1525, Oviedo published a journal of
                    his researches under the title of <hi rend="italic">Summario</hi><hi rend="italic">de la</hi><hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">General</hi><hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">Natural de las
                    Indias</hi><hi rend="italic">Occidentales,</hi> Toledo, one vol. folio,
                    dedicated to Charles V. At a later period, however, the author recast this
                    production, to which he added numerous facts connected with the natural history
                    of Haiti, and, in 1535, he published the first twenty books of his great work
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">La</hi><hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">General</hi><hi rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">Natural de
                    las Indias</hi><hi rend="italic">Occidentales;</hi> but the entire work, which
                    is divided into fifty books, did not appear till 1783, when it came out under
                    the auspices of the Marquis of Truxillo. Oviedo affirms, in his narrative, that
                    the syphilis is an endemic malady in the island of Haïti, and that having been
                    contracted there by the Spaniards belonging to the expedition of Columbus, it
                    was by them communicated to the Neapolitans belonging to the expedition of
                    Gonealvo de Cordova; and, in point of fact, the syphilis appeared at Naples
                    immediately after the return of the squadron of Gonçalvo. Several writers, who
                    pretend that syphilis existed in Europe anterior to the discovery of the new
                    world, have attempted to prove this hy-ιothetical assertion from the writings of
                    Oviedo himself; ĭut these, so far from countenancing any sueb notion,
                    con-ainineontestible proof of the error into which those persons ιave fallen who
                    ascribe the origin of this fearful scourge to he old continent. Some authors
                    assure us that Oviedo, having been infected by syphilis during his sojourn at
                    Naples about the year 1513, came to the conclusion that if had been imported
                    from Haïti; and conceiving that there must exist in that island a remedy for the
                    disease, solicited the employment which led him thither, and in fact discovered
                    that the wood of gaiac was the infallible antidote employed by the natives, and
                    by which also he effected his own cure. It is added that, on his return to
                    Spain, Oviedo commenced physician for syphilitic maladies, in the treatment of
                    which he made use of the wood of gaïac, with a success which considerably
                    augmented the fortune he had acquired in working the mines of Haiti, at the
                    expense of the lives of a great number of the natives. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>