<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0716-5798-0687-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">OXUS</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 687</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:966505">Ice</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194565798" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">OXUS</label>, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Ammu.</hi> This great
                    river of Central Asia has its source in the high lands of Pamer, a branch of the
                    main ridge of the Hindu Coosh Mountains, which, extending northward, forms the
                    boundary between Thibet and Great Bukharia. It issues from a glacier in a narrow
                    valley 200 or 300 yards broad, which is enclosed on three sides by the high
                    snowy mountain called Pooshtikhur. The stream is seen flowing from under the
                    ice, which is stated to be at least forty spears in depth. The spring itself is
                    buried under the great mass of ice whence it issues, and cannot be seen; but
                    there is no doubt of its issuing from this spot, as there is no other open or
                    break from which it could issue at any more distant point. The small but
                    swelling stream is carried north in this narrow valley for five coss or ten
                    miles; at eight miles it is twenty yards broad, and breast deep; and on leaving
                    the valley, after being joined by many other springs from the same hill, it is
                    fifty yards broad, and about four feet deep. It is joined by the Shiber about
                    sixty miles from its source, which is sixty yards broad. The Oxus, however, is
                    much broader, having been joined by seven or eight streams from knee to middle
                    deep, and from ten to thirty yards broad. It flows in a south-west direction for
                    120 miles, and then meets a high ridge of mountains running from west-north-west
                    to east-south-east. From this point it takes a west-south-west course through
                    the wild and mountainous regions which separate the country of Balkh from
                    Independent Tartary, until it breaks through the ridge in its progress
                    southward, and meets some of the ridges which diverge from the main ridge of
                    Hindu Coosh. In this part of its upper course, being a distance of more than 300
                    miles, it is confined between the mountains, and is joined by numerous streams,
                    from two to four of which are crossed in each day’s journey along its left or
                    southern bank, besides two very considerable rivers, namely, the Soorkhab or
                    Kurategeen River, and the Kok-cha or Budukshan River. It also receives the
                    tribute of many streams from the north, the names of which are unknown in
                    Europe. Its course is now west-north-west; and it passes the far-famed city of
                    Samarcand, which, however, is not situated on its banks, but on a river flowing
                    into it. To Bukharia, which is situated on one of its tributary streams, it has
                    a northerly course of 250 miles, being forced off in this direction by the high
                    land of Hindu Coosh, which extends north of the ridge a considerable distance,
                    and runs over a flat country, sandy, and little better than a desert. From this
                    point to Ourgunge is a distance of 400 miles, over a desert of at least 300
                    miles, with only a few habitations of horse-breeders along the banks. On the
                    left bank is a forest the greater part of the way, through which those who pass
                    are obliged to carry their provisions for eight or ten days at a time. Mr
                    Elphinstone has thus traced <pb break="no" facs="nls:194565811" xml:id="kp-eb0716-5811-0688"/>its course for 900 miles; and other travellers in
                    the East have gleaned scanty information respecting its lower course till it
                    terminates in the Sea of Aral after a course of 1200 miles. Frazer mentions, on
                    the authority of a native traveller or merchant, that after passing the town of
                    Ourgunge, it makes a turn to the east, and is joined by the Seer or Sihon (the
                    Jaxartes), when both spread out into a large lake, which has no outlet, its
                    waters being absorbed by the sand of which the surrounding country is composed.
                    Frazer seems to think that this account corresponds so well with that of the
                    Arabian and the Persian geographers, that there is no denying credit to it. But
                    the accounts of native travellers are proverbially so erroneous, that no
                    reliance can be placed upon them. They generally travel for the purposes of
                    trade, and pay little attention to thegeography of the country, or other
                    details; and this, joined to their known careless-nessof truth, renders their
                    testimony of little value. Colonel Kinneir mentions, that Sir John Malcolm
                    conversed with a native, who assured him that the termination of the river was
                    in the Caspian Sea. This opinion is, however, strongly combated by Mr Frazer,
                    who affirms that there is nothing like evidence to prove that the Oxus ever
                    reached the Caspian Sea; that this notion rests on vague tradition, founded on
                    ignorance; and that all the native authorities who speak directly to this point
                    constantly say that the Jeyhoon or Ammu falls into the lake of Khaurezm. The
                    ancient geographers were ignorant that there were two distinct lakes in Asia,
                    namely, the Caspian Sea, and that of Aral. They supposed that both formed one
                    lake; and hence their error was extremely natural, in giving a termination to
                    the Oxus in the Caspian, the only outlet which they knew to exist in the
                    direction of its stream. But we know for certain that no river falls into the
                    Caspian to the south of the bay of Mangulshuck; for the caravans that pass and
                    repass from Astrabad to Khyvah, and from thence to Mangulshuck, do not cross a
                    single stream, or meet with a drop of running fresh water, after crossing the
                    river Attruck near Astrabad. It is equally certain, from the same evidence, that
                    no branch of the Oxus falls into the Caspian to the northward of Mangulshuck. Mr
                    Frazer, in answer to his inquiries concerning the rise of the Oxus or Ammu, was
                    informed by a traveller who saw it in the summer season near Balkh, that it was
                    as large as the Jumna in its fullest season, and perfectly navigable for boats,
                    which are in common use for crossing the stream, and for the conveyance both of
                    goods and passengers from Balkh and from Bukharia to Ourgunge and Khyvah. At
                    Bukharia it is a very large river, the stream being at no time less than a
                    thousand yards wide; and in summer, when the snow melts, it sometimes spreads to
                    the breadth of four miles. It is deep, and navigable for boats, by which means
                    an active intercourse is maintained in most parts of its course. <hi rend="smallcaps">(f.)</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>