<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-7713-0646-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BIRD (7th edition, volume 4, page 646)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1036179">Nests</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998853">Limes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998827">Lime</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1036191">Nets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10z9f">Nests</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z7110r">Lime</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cf8t">Nets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n87332f">Netting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193197713?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BIRD</label>. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ornithology.</hi> For
                    the method of preserving birds see <hi rend="smallcaps">Taxidermy.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">EiRD~Call,</hi> a little stick, cleft at one end, in which is put
                    a leaf of some plant, wherewith to counterfeit the cry or call of several birds,
                    and bring them to the net, or snare, or lime-twig, to be taken. A laurel leaf
                    fitted on the bird-call counterfeits the voice of lapwings; a leek that of
                    nightingales, &amp;c.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Bird-</hi><hi rend="italic">Catching,</hi> the art
                    of taking birds or wild-fowl, whether for food, for the pleasure of their song,
                    or for their destruction as pernicious to the husbandman and horticulturist.</p>
                <p>Song-birds, in a state of nature, <hi rend="italic">fly,</hi> as the
                    bird-catchers term it, chiefly during the month of October, and part of
                    September and November; as the flight in March is much less considerable than
                    that of Michaelmas. It is to be noted, also, that the several species of birds
                    of <hi rend="italic">flight</hi> do not make their appearance precisely at the
                    same time, during the months of September, October, and November. The
                    pippet-lark, for example, begins to fly about Michaelmas, and is succeeded by
                    the wood-lark, linnet, goldfinch, chaffinch, greenfinch, and other kinds. These
                    birds, during the Michaelmas and March flights, are chiefly on the wing from
                    day-break to noon, though there is afterwards a small flight from two till
                    night; but this is so inconsiderable that the bird-catchers usually take up
                    their nets at noon.</p>
                <p>It may also be observed that they always fly against the wind; and hence there is
                    great contention amongst the bird-catchers who shall gain the leeward point. A
                    gentle wind to the south-west produces the best sport. The bird-catcher
                    generally carries with him five or six linnets (of which more are caught than of
                    any other singing bird), two goldfinches, two greenfinches, one wood-lark, one
                    redpoll, a yellow-hammer, titlark, and aberdavine or siskin, and perhaps a
                    bullfinch; these are placed at small distances from the nets, in little cages.
                    He is moreover provided with what are called <hi rend="italic">flur-birds,</hi>
                    which are placed within the nets, and are raised upon the flur, or gently
                    lowered, as the wild birds are seen to approach them. The tìur is a movable
                    perch, to which the tame bird is secured, and which, by means of a long cord,
                    the bird-catcher ean raise or depress at pleasure. The flur-birds generally
                    consist of the linnet, the goldfinch, and the greenfinch, whieh are secured to
                    the flur by what is called a <hi rend="italic">brace.</hi><note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">A sort of bandage, formed
                    of a slender silken string that is fastened round the bird’s body, and under the
                    wings.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>It having been found that there is a difference between bird and bird, from the
                    one being more in song than the other, the bird-catchers contrive that their
                    call-birds should moult before the usual time. They therefore, in June or July,
                    put them into a close box under two or three folds of blankets, in which state
                    they continue about a month. The birds frequently die under this operation; and
                    for this reason the value of a stopped bird rises greatly. When the bird has
                    thus prematurely moulted, lie is in song whilst the wild birds are out of song,
                    and his note is louder and more piercing than theirs; his plumage also is said
                    to be equally improved. The black and yellow in the wings of the goldfinch, for
                    example, become deeper and more vivid, and exhibit a beautiful gloss. In short,
                    according to the bird-fanciers, there is as much difference between a wild and a
                    stopped bird, as there is between a horse which is kept in body-clothes and one
                    at grass.</p>
                <p>WΙιen the bird-catcher has laid his nets, he disposes of his call-birds at proper
                    intervals. Their sight and hearing infinitely excel that of the bird-catcher;
                    and the instant that the wild birds are perceived, notice is given by one of the
                    call-birds, which seem to anticipate with pleasure the expected capture of their
                    fellows. The call-birds, while the wild ones are at a distance, do not sing as
                    birds do in a chamber; they invite them by what the bird-catchers eall <hi
                    rend="italic">shortjerhs,</hi> which, when the birds are good, maybe heard at a
                    great distance. The power of this inviting call is so great, that the wild bird
                    is stopped in its course of flight; and, if not already acquainted with the
                    nets,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic"
                    >A bird acquainted with the nets is by the bird-catchers termed a</hi> sharper;
                    <hi rend="italic">and this they endeavour to drive away, as they can have no
                    sport whilst it continues near them.</hi></p></note> lights boldly within twenty
                    yards of perhaps three or four bird-catchers, on a spot which otherwise it would
                    not have taken the least notice of. Nay, it frequently happens, that if half a
                    flock only are caught, the remaining half will immediately afterwards light in
                    the nets and share the same fate; and should only one bird escape, that bird
                    will suffer itself to be pulled at till it is caught, such a fascinating power
                    have the call-birds.</p>
                <p>Bird-catchers frequently lay considerable wagers on the jerking capacities of
                    their call-birds. They place them opposite to each other, by an inch of candle;
                    and the bird who jerks the oftenest before the candle is burnt out wins the
                    wager. We have been informed that there have been instances of a bird’s giving
                    170 jerks in a quarter of an hour; and we have known a linnet, in such a trial,
                    persevere in its emulation till it swooned from the perch; thus, as Pliny says
                    of the nightingale, <hi rend="italic">victa morte flnit saepe vitam, spiritu
                    prius deficiente quam cantu.</hi></p>
                <p>The females of the different species are usually killed, as incapable of song,
                    and inferior in the beauty of their plumage. They are sold for threepence or
                    fourpence a <pb break="no" facs="nls:193197726?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0704-7726-0647"/> dozen. These small birds are so good, that we are
                    surprised the luxury of the age neglects so delicate an acquisition to the
                    table. The modern Italians are fond of small birds, which they eat under the
                    common name of <hi rend="italic">heccaficos;</hi> and the extravagant price paid
                    by a Roman tragedian for one dish of singing birds is well known.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">AEsop, the
                    actor, is said to have expended a sum equal to L.800 sterling on a single dish
                    of singing birds.</hi></p></note> Another particular we learned, in conversation
                    with a London bird-catcher, was the vast price that is sometimes given even for
                    song-birds which have not learned to whistle tunes. The greatest sum we heard of
                    was five guineas for a chaffinch that had a particular and uncommon note, under
                    which it was intended to train others; and we also heard of five pounds ten
                    shillings being given for a call-bird linnet. The male birds usually fly by
                    themselves, and in that case their flight precedes that of the female. When the
                    titlarks are caught in the beginning of the season, it frequently happens that
                    forty are taken and not one female among them; and probably the same would be
                    observed with regard to other birds (as has been done with relation to the
                    wheatear), if they were attended to. An experienced and intelligent bird-catcher
                    informed us, that such birds as breed twice a year generally have in their first
                    brood a majority of males, and in their second of females, which may in part
                    account for the circumstance above mentioned. It has been observed with regard
                    to the bullfinch, that the female answers the purpose of a call-bird as well as
                    the male.</p>
                <p>The nightingale is not a bird of flight, in the sense in which the bird-catchers
                    use this term. Like the red-breast, wren, and many other singing birds, it only
                    moves from hedge to hedge, and does not take the periodical flights in October
                    and March. The persons who catch these birds make use of small trap-nets,
                    without call-birds; and they are considered as inferior in dignity to other
                    bird-catchers, who will not rank with them. The arrival of the nightingale is
                    expected by the trappers in the neighbourhood of London during the first week of
                    April: at the beginning, none but cocks are taken; but in a few days the hens
                    make their appearance, generally by themselves, though sometimes a few males
                    come along with them. The latter are distinguished from the females not only by
                    their superior size, but by a great swelling of their vent, which commences on
                    the first arrival of the hens. They are caught in a net-trap, the bottom of
                    which is surrounded with an iron ring; the net itself is rather larger than a
                    cabbage net. When the trappers hear or see them, they strew some fresh mould
                    under the place, and bait the trap with a mealworm from the baker’s shop. Ten or
                    a dozen nightingales have been thus caught in a day.</p>
                <p>Γhe common way of taking larks, of which so many are used at our’tables, is in
                    the night, with nets called <hi rend="italic">trammels.</hi> These are usually
                    made of thirty-six yards in length, and about six yards over, with six ribs of
                    pack-thread, which at the ends are put upon two poles of about sixteen feet
                    long, and made lesser at each end. The net is to be drawn over the ground by two
                    men, and every five or six steps it is made to touch the ground, otherwise it
                    will pass over the birds without touching them, and they yill escape. When they
                    are felt to fly up against the net, <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> r</hi> l <hi rend="superscript"> ls</hi> clapped down, and
                    then all are safe that are under it. The darkest nights are most proper for this
                    sport; and the net will not only take larks, but all other birds that roost on
                    the ground; among which are woodcocks, snipes, parh'idges, quails, and several
                    others. In the depth of winter people sometimes take great numbers of larks by
                    nooses of horse-hair. The method is this: Take 100 or 200 yards <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 01</hi> pack-thread; fasten at every six inches a noose,
                    made of double horse-hair; at every twenty yards the line is to be pegged down
                    to the ground, and so left ready to take them. The time to use this is when the
                    ground is covered with snow, and the larks are to be allured to it by some white
                    oats scattered all the way among the nooses. They must be taken away as soon as
                    three or four are hung, otherwise the rest will be frightened; but though the
                    others are scared away just where the sportsman comes, they will be feeding at
                    the other end of the line, and the sport may be thus continued for a long time.
                    Those caught in the day are taken in clap-nets, of fifteen yards in length and
                    two and a half in breadth; and are enticed within the reach by means of bits of
                    looking-glass, fixed in a piece of wood, and placed in the middle of the nets,
                    which are put in a quick whirling motion by a string which the larker commands;
                    he also makes use of a decoy lark. These nets are used only till the 14th
                    November; for the larks will not <hi rend="italic">dare</hi> to frolic in the
                    air, except in fine sunny weather, and of course cannot be inveigled into the
                    snare. When the weather grows gloomy, the larker changes his engine, and makes
                    use of a trammel-net, twenty-seven or twenty-eight feet long, and five broad,
                    which is put on two poles, eighteen feet long, and carried by men under each
                    arm, who pass over the fields and quarter the ground as a setting dog. When they
                    hear or feel a lark hit the net, they drop it down, and so the birds are
                    taken.</p>
                <p>A singular species of bird-catching is practised on the holm of Noss, a vast rock
                    severed from the Isle of Noss by some unknown convulsion, and only about sixteen
                    fathoms distant. It is of the same stupendous height as the opposite precipice,
                    with a raging sea between. An adventurous climber reaches the rock in a boat,
                    gains the height, and fastens several stakes on the small portion of earth which
                    is to be found on the top; corresponding stakes are also placed on the edge of·
                    the opposite cliffs. A rope is fixed to the stakes on both sides, along which a
                    machine, called a cradle, is contrived to slide; and, by the help of a small
                    parallel cord fastened in like manner, the adventurer pulls himself over, and
                    returns with his booty.</p>
                <p>The manner of bird-catching in the Feroe Islands is also extremely hazardous. The
                    cliffs which contain the objects of their search are often two hundred fathoms
                    in height, and are attempted both from above and below. In the first case, the
                    fowlers provide themselves with a rope eighty or a hundred fathoms in length.
                    The fowler fastens one end about his’waist and between his legs, recommends
                    himself to the protection of the Almighty, and is lowered down by six others,
                    who place a piece of timber on the margin of the rock, to preserve the rope from
                    wearing against the sharp edge. They have, besides, a small line fastened to the
                    body of the adventurer, by which he gives signals that they may lower or raise
                    him, or shift him from place to place. The last operation is attended with great
                    danger, by the loosening of the stones, which often fall on his head, and would
                    infallibly destroy him, were he not protected by a strong thick cap; but even
                    that is found unequal to save him against the weight of the larger fragments of
                    rock. The dexterity of the fowlers is amazing; they will place their feet
                    against the front of the precipice, and dart themselves some fathoms from it,
                    with a cool eye survey the places where the birds nestle, and again shoot into
                    their haunts. In some places the birds lodge in deep recesses. The fowler will
                    alight there, disengage himself from the rope, fix it to a stone, and at his
                    leisure collect the booty, fasten it to his girdle, and resume his pendulous
                    seat. At times he will again <pb break="no" facs="nls:193197739?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0704-7739-0648"/> spring from the rock, and in that attitude, with
                    a fowling-net placed at the end of a staff, catch the old birds which are flying
                    to and from their retreats. When he has finished his dreadful employ, he gives a
                    signal to his friends above, who pull him up, and share the hard-earned spoils.
                    The feathers are preserved for exportation: the flesh is partly eaten fresh, but
                    the greater portion is dried for winter’s provision.</p>
                <p>The fowling from below has its share of danger. The party goes on the expedition
                    in a boat; and when it has attained the base of the precipice, one of the most
                    daring, having fastened a rope about his waist, and furnished himself with a
                    long pole with an iron hook at one cnd, either climbs, or is thrust up by his
                    companions, who place a.pole under his breech, to the first station. He, by
                    means of the rope, brings up one of the boat’s crew; the rest are drawn up in
                    the same manner, and each is furnished with his rope and fowling staff. They
                    then continue their progress upwards in the same manner, till they arrive at the
                    region of birds; and wander about the face of the cliff in search of them. They
                    then act in pairs; one fastens himself to the end of his associate’s rope, and
                    in places where birds have nestled beneath his footing, he permits himself to be
                    lowered down, depending for his security on the strength of his companion, who
                    has to haul him up again; but it sometimes happens that the person above is
                    overpowered by the weight, and both inevitably perish. They fling the fowl into
                    the boat, which attends their motions, and receives the booty. They often pass
                    seven or eight days in this tremendous employ, and lodge in the crannies which
                    they find in the face of the precipice.</p>
                <p>In some remote parts of Russia there is practised a singular invention for taking
                    great quantities of gelinottes, which are a species of grouse. They choose the
                    most open places in the birch woods; and there they plant long forks in the
                    earth, opposite to the larger trees. On these forks is laid a horizontal stick,
                    gallows-wisc, to which are tied small bundles of ears of corn. At a short
                    distance from this part of the contrivance is a kind of large funnel or inverted
                    cone, made with long birch-twigs, thin and flexible, the lower extremities of
                    which are stuck in the earth, very near to one another, but, by spreading
                    towards the top, form there an opening of above a yard in diameter. In this
                    opening is placed a wheel made of two circles that intersect each other, and are
                    surrounded with straw and ears of corn. This wheel turns on an axis fastened to
                    the side of the funnel in such a manner that there is room enough between the
                    sticks of the cone and the circles to admit of the wheel’s turning freely about.
                    The birds first perch upon the transverse stick near the tree; and when they
                    have a mind to fall upon the corn tied to the wheel, they must necessarily stand
                    upon one of the projecting parts of the circles of which it is composed. At that
                    instant the wheel turns, and the gelinotte falls, head foremost, to the bottom
                    of the trap, which is there so contracted that he cannot get out. By these means
                    the fowler sometimes finds the machine half-full of gelinottes.</p>
                <p>The following method of netting or catching wild pigeons is eagerly pursued as a
                    diversion in different parts of Italy, particularly by the inhabitants of Cava,
                    and is thus described by Mr Swinburne. The people “assemble in parties; and if
                    any stranger chances to stray to their rendezvous, they give him a most cordial
                    welcome. I am not in the least surprised,” says Mr Swinburne, “at their
                    passionate fondness for this sport, as* I found it extremely bewitching, keeping
                    the attention constantly alive, and the springs of the mind pleasingly agitated
                    by expectation; the situations where the toils are spread are incomparably
                    beautiful, the air is pure and balsamic, and every thing around breathes health
                    and satisfaction. When the' periodical flights of stock-doves return from the
                    northern and western parts of Europe to gain warmer regions for their winter
                    abode, the fowler repairs to the mountain and spreads his nets across the
                    intermediate hollows, the passes through which the birds direct their course, to
                    avoid unnecessary elevation in their flight. These nets are hung upon a row of
                    large trees planted for the purpose. The branches being very thick and close at
                    top, and the pole lofty and bare, a greät opening is left below for the toils,
                    which reach to the ground, and, by means of pulleys, fall in a heap with the
                    least effort. Sometimes they are extended upon poles that exceed the height of
                    the trees. At a small distance is a lofty circular turret, like a column with a
                    little capital or cap, upon which a man is stationed to watch the approach of
                    the game. As he commands a free view over all the country, and practice has made
                    his sight as acute as that of the lynx, he descries the birds at a wonderful
                    distance. The doves advance with great velocity; but the alert watchman is
                    prepared for them; and just as they approach his post, hurls a stone above them
                    with a sling. Upon this the whole flock, whose fears have birds of prey for
                    their great object, supposing the stone to be an enemy of that kind ready to
                    pounce them, dart down like lightning to avoid the blow by passing under the
                    trees; but there they rush into the jaws of death, by dashing against the net,
                    which instantly drops, and so entangles them thatnot one of them can escape the
                    active hands of the fowler. These birds are sometimes taken by dozens at one
                    fall, and are accounted fine eating. The dexterity with which the slingers
                    manage their weapon is very remarkable; they throw the stone to a great height
                    without any violent effort, and even without whirling the sling round before
                    they discharge the pellet. In the Pyrenncan mountains, where the same diversion
                    is followed, the watchmen use a bow and arrow, trimmed with the feathers of a
                    hawk.”</p>
                <p>The methods employed for the capture of <hi rend="italic">water-fowl</hi> will be
                    found described under the word <hi rend="smallcaps">Decoy.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >EiRD-Lime,</hi> a viscid substance, prepared in different ways. The most common
                    bird-lime is made from hollybark, boiled ten or twelve hours; when the green
                    coat being separated from the other, it is covered up for a fortnight in a moist
                    place; then pounded into a tough paste, so that no fibres of the wood are
                    discernible, and washed in a running stream till no motes appear. It is next put
                    up to ferment for four or five days, and skimmed as often as any thing rises to
                    the surface. To prepare it for use, a third part of nut-oil, or thin grease,
                    must be incorporated with it over the fire.</p>
                <p>The juice of holly-bark is a very peculiar substance. But if trials were made, it
                    seems probable that many other juices would be found to have the same clammy
                    nature. The misletoc affords a juice even superior to that of the holly; and if
                    a young shoot of the common alder be cut through there will issue a stringy
                    juice capable of being drawn out into threads, and which will follow the knife
                    like bird-lime or the juice of the holly. In this tree it seems to be lodged,
                    not in the bark, but in certain vessels just within the circle of the wood. The
                    roots of all the hyacintl also afford a tough and stringy juice of the same
                    kind; and so does the asphodel, the narcissus, and the black bryony root, in a
                    surprising quantity <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi>.</p>
                <p>When twigs, smeared with bird-lime, are to be pul in places subject to wet, the
                    common bird-lime is apt tθ have its force soon taken away. It is necessary,
                    therefore, to have recourse to a particular sort, which, from its property of
                    bearing water unhurt, is called <hi rend="italic">water bird-ln∣^</hi> and is
                    prepared thus: Take a pound of strong and goo bird-lime; wash it thoroughly in
                    spring-water, till <hi rend="superscript"> tιe</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193197752?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-7752-0649"/> hardness is
                    all removed; and then beat it well, that the water may be separated. When it is
                    dry put it into an earthen pot, and add to it as much capon’s grease as will
                    make it run. Then add two spoonfuls of strong vinegar, one spoonful of oil, and
                    a small quantity of Venice turpentine. Let the whole boil for some minutes over
                    a moderate fire, stirring it all the time. Whenever it is required for use it
                    ought to be warmed again. This is the best sort <hi rend="italic">of</hi>
                    bird-lime for snipes and other birds that love wet places.</p>
                <p>The most successful method of using the common birdlime is this: Cut down the
                    main branch or bough of any bushy tree whose twigs are thick, straight, long,
                    and smooth, and have neither knots nor prickles. The willow and the birch-tree
                    afford the best of this kind. Let all the superfluous shoots be trimmed off, and
                    the twigs all made neat and clean; they must all be well covered with the
                    bird-lime, within four inches of the bottom; but the main bough from which they
                    grow must not be touched with the lime. No part of the bark where the lime
                    should come must be left bare; but it is a nice matter to lay it on properly;
                    for if it be too thick it will give the birds a distaste, and they will not come
                    near it; and if there be too little of it, it will not hold them when they are
                    there. When the bush is thus prepared, it may be set up wherever birds have been
                    observed to congregate. If it be used in summer, it may be placed in the midst
                    of a quickset hedge, or in groves, bushes, or white thorn trees, near fields of
                    corn, hemp, flax, and the like; and in the winter the proper places are about
                    stacks of corn, cottages, barns, and such situations. When the lime-bush is thus
                    planted, the sportsman must stand as near it as he can without being discovered;
                    and if he can imitate the natural calls of different species, his chances of
                    success will be so much the greater. When one bird is thus enticed to the bush,
                    and hung fast, the business of the sportsman is not to run up to take it, but to
                    be patient; for it will hang itself more fast by its struggling to get away; and
                    its fluttering will bring more to the bush, so that several maybe taken
                    together. The best time of the day for this sport is from sunrise to ten
                    o’clock, and from one to sunset. Another very good method of bringing the birds
                    together is by a stale: a bat makes a very good stale; but it must be fastened
                    so as to be in sight at a distance. An owl is a still better stale; for this
                    bird never goes abroad but it is followed by all the small birds in the
                    neighbourhood. They will gather together in great numbers about it; and having
                    no convenient place to sit on but the lime-bush, will be taken in great numbers.
                    If a living owl or bat is not to be had, a stuffed or preserved skin will serve
                    the purpose. Some have even used the image of an owl carved in wood, and painted
                    in the natural colours.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Birds,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Heraldry,</hi> according to
                    their several kinds, represent either the contemplative or active life. They are
                    the emblems of liberty, expedition, readiness, swiftness, and the like, and are
                    therefore more honourable bearings than fishes. Birds must be borne in
                    cóat-armour, as is ⅛&gt; <hi rend="superscript"> es</hi> t fitting the propriety
                    of their natural actions. Such as are either whole-footed, or have their feet
                    divided, and yet have no talons, are said to be <hi rend="italic">membered;</hi>
                    but the cock, and all birds of prey with sharp and hooked beaks and talons for
                    encounter or defence, are said to be <hi rend="italic">armed.</hi> In the
                    blazoning of birds, if their wings be not displayed, they are said to be borne
                    close.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">BiRDs∙Nests, mCommerce,</hi> the nests of a small Indian swal-θ
                    <hi rend="superscript"> w</hi>) of delicate taste, and frequently mixed among
                    soups. In the sea-coasts of China, at certain seasons of the year, there are
                    seen vast numbers of these birds. They leave he inland country at their breeding
                    time, come to build <hi rend="superscript"> ln</hi> the rocks, and fashion their
                    nests out of a matter which they find on the shore, washed thither by the waves.
                    The nature of this substance is scarcely yet ascertained. According to Kempfer,
                    it is molluscae or sea-worms; according to M. le Poivre, fish-spawn; according
                    to Dalrymple, sea-weeds; and according to Linnaeus, it is the animal substance
                    frequently found on the beach, which fishermen call <hi rend="italic"
                    >blubbers</hi> or <hi rend="italic">jellies.</hi> The nests are of a
                    hemispherical figure, and of the size of a goose’s <hi rend="italic">egg,</hi>
                    and in substance much resemble ichthyocolla or <hi rend="italic">isinglass.</hi>
                    The Chinese gather these nests, and sell them to all parts of the world; they
                    dissolve in broths, and make a kind of jelly of a very agreeable flavour.</p>
                <p>These nests, Mr Marsden informs us, are found in great abundance in the island of
                    Sumatra, particularly about Croe, near the south end of the island. Four miles
                    up the river of that name is a large cave, where the birds build in vast
                    numbers. The nests are distinguished into white and black; but of these the
                    former are more scarce and valuable, being found in the proportion of only one
                    to twenty-five. “The white sort,” says Mr Marsden, “sells in China at the rate
                    of 1000 to 1500 Spanish dollars the pecul; the black is usually disposed of at
                    Batavia for about twenty dollars the same weight, where it is chiefly converted
                    into glue, of which it makes a very superior kind. The difference between the
                    two has by some been supposed to be owing to the mixture of the feathers of the
                    birds with the viscous substance of which the nests are formed; and this they
                    deduce from the experiment of steeping the black nests for a short time in hot
                    water, when they are said to become in a great degree white. Among the natives I
                    have heard a few assert that they are the work of a different species of bird.
                    It was suggested to me that the white might probably be the recent nests in
                    which they were taken; and the black, such as have been used for a number of
                    years successively. This opinion appearing plausible, I was particular in my
                    inquiries as to that point, and learned what seemed much to corroborate it. When
                    the natives prepare to take the nests, they enter the caves with torches, and
                    forming ladders, according to the usual mode, of a single bamboo notched, they
                    ascend and pull down the nests, which adhere in numbers together, from the side
                    and top of the rock. They informed me that the more frequently and regularly the
                    cave is stripped, the greater proportion of white nests they are sure to find,
                    and that on this experience they often make a practice of beating down and
                    destroying the old nests in larger quantities than they trouble themselves to
                    carry away, in order that they may find white nests the next season in their
                    room. The birds during the building time are seen in large flocks on the beach,
                    collecting in their bills the foam which is thrown up by the surf, of which
                    there is little doubt but they construct their nests, after it has undergone
                    perhaps a preparation, from a commixture with their saliva, or other secretion
                    with which nature has provided them for that purpose.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
