<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0473-0443-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TYTLER, William (7th edition, volume 21, page
                    443)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=473" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TYTLER, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>, one of the
                    most strenuous defenders of the immaculate purity of Queen Mary, was born at
                    Edinburgh on the 12th of October 171). He was the son of Mr Alexander Tytler. a
                    writer or attorney in Edinburgh, by Jane the daughter of Mr William Leslie,
                    merchant in Aberdeen, and granddaughter of Sir Patrick Leslie of Iden, provost
                    of that city. He received his education at the High School and the university of
                    his native city, and distinguished himself by an early proficiency in those
                    classical studies which, to the latest period of his life, were the occupation
                    of his leisure hours, and a principal source of his mental enjoyments. At the
                    age of thirty-one he was admitted into the society of writers to the signet, and
                    till the time of his death he continued the practice of his profession with very
                    good success, and with equal respect from his clients and the public. In
                    September 1745, he marri&lt;d Anre Craig, daughter of Mr James Craig of Dalnair,
                    writer to the signet, by whom he left two sons and a daughter. In 1759 he
                    published his “Inquiry, Historical and Critical, into the Evidence against Mary
                    Queen of Scots, and an Examination of the Histories of Dr Robertson and Mr Hume,
                    with respect to that Evidence.” Here he warmly espoused the cause of that
                    unfortunate princess, and attacked with severity the conduct of her enemies. On
                    this subject, most of his opinions have already become obsolete. On its first
                    appearance, the book was much read in Britain, and was translated into French.
                    He afterwards published the “Poetical Remains of James the First, King of
                    Scotland.” Edinb. 1783, 8vo. This volume includes a dissertation on the life and
                    writings of the royal author, and a “Dissertation on the Scottish Music.” He
                    contributed several papers to the first volume of the Transactions of the
                    Society of Antiquaries of Scotland. In the Lounger he wrote a single paper, No.
                    16. Mr Tytler died on the 12th of September 1792. In domestic life his character
                    was particularly amiable; and he is said to have been one of the kindest of
                    husbands, and most affectionate of fathers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Tytler,</hi><hi rend="italic">Alexander Fraser,</hi> the
                    eldest son of William Tytler, noticed in the prcecding article, was born at
                    Edinburgh on the 15th of October 1747. In his eighth year, he was sent to the
                    High School, where he became dux of the rector’s class. In 1763, he was placed
                    under the care of Mr Elphinston, who then kept an academy at Kensington. Here he
                    enlarged his stock of classical knowledge, and cultivated his talent for Latin
                    versification. One of his poems was communicated to Dr Jortin, an excellent
                    judge, who encouraged the youthful writer by his commendation, and presented him
                    with a copy of his own <pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=474" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0474-0444"/>
                    Latin poems. After a residence of two years he quitted Kensington, and in 1763
                    entered the university of Edinburgh, where he had the advantage of prosecuting
                    bis studies under Dr Ferguson and Dr Blair. His range of enquiry was
                    sufficiently ample, but his chief efforts were directed to literature and
                    jurisprudence. He continued to increase his familiarity with the Greek and Latin
                    writers, nor did he neglect the study of modern languages. Music and drawing
                    were added to his other accomplishments. Natural history became, and long
                    continued to be, one of his favourite recreations.</p>
                <p>He was called to the bar in 1770; and in the spring of the ensuing year, he
                    accompanied his relation Mr Kerr of Blackshiels on a tour to Paris, from which
                    they returned by Flanders and Holland. At the age of twenty-four he published
                    “Piscatory Eclogues, with other Poetical Miscellanies, by Phineas Fletcher:
                    illustrated with notes, critical and explanatory.” Edinb. 1771, 8vo. In 1776 he
                    married Anne, the eldest daughter of William Fraser, Esq. of Balnain. When the
                    Works of John Gregory, M.D. were published in 1778, he contributed the
                    preliminary account of the author’s life and writings. During the same year, he
                    published a folio volume, supplementary to Lord Kames’s Dictionary of Decisions.
                    Although he never rose to high practice at the bar, he did not neglect the
                    learning of his profession; but soon after this period he sought and obtained an
                    academical office. In 1780 he was appointed conjunct professor with Mr Pringle,
                    and in 1786 he became sole professor of civil history. From his first
                    appointment till the year 1800, he devoted his attention almost exclusively to
                    the duties of his professorship; and ten years of assiduous study were employed
                    in the composition and improvement of the course of lectures which he annually
                    read in the university. His lectures were considered as valuable, and they
                    continued to attract a very respectable auditory. For the use of his students,
                    he printed a “Plan and Outlines of a Course of Lectures on Universal History,
                    Ancient and Modern.” Edinb. 1782, 8vo. This compendium was afterwards enlarged,
                    and published under the title of “Elements of General History, Ancient and
                    Modern.” Edinb. 1801, 2 vols. 8vo. In 1822 a supplementary volume was added by
                    Dr Nares, professor of modern history at Oxford. Mr Tytler’s next, and,
                    according to our judgment, his best work, bears the title of an “Essay on the
                    Principles of Translation.” Lond. 1791, 8vo. The third edition, with large
                    additions, appeared at Edinburgh in 1813. This essay, originally published
                    without the author’s name, experienced a very favourable reception, and still
                    continues to be regarded as a judicious and learned work.</p>
                <p>In 1790 he was appointed judge-advocate of Scotland. On the death of his father
                    in 1792, he succeeded to the estate of Woodhouselee near Edinburgh; and on the
                    death of his father-in-law, he had previously succeeded to that of Balnain in
                    the county of Inverness. In 1795 he was seized with a dangerous fever, which was
                    of long continuance, and was accompanied with delirium. When he was sufficiently
                    recovered, he resumed his favourite pursuits, and occupied himself with
                    preparing an edition of Dr Derham’s Physico-theology, including an account of
                    the life and writings of the author, and a short dissertation on final causes,
                    together with notes. This edition was printed in 1790. During the same year he
                    wrote a pamphlet, which was published at Dublin under the title of “Ireland
                    profiting by Example; or the Question considered, whether Scotland has gained or
                    lost by the Union.” Of this well-timed tract, three thousand copies were sold on
                    the day of its publication. His next production was “An Essay on Military Law,
                    and the Practice of Courts Martial.” Edinb. 1800, 8vo. A second edition was
                    printed at London in 1800. He contributed the critical remarks, inserted without
                    his name in an edition of the Poems of Allan Ramsay. Lend. 1800, 2 vols. 8vo.
                    The biographical account of the poet was contributed by a writer greatly
                    inferior to Mr Tytler.</p>
                <p>The literary, professional, and, we may add, political merits, of the learned
                    professor, were too conspicuous to be overlooked. On the second of February 1802
                    he took his seat in the Court of Session, with the title of Lord Woodhouselee.
                    To the duties of his new station he devoted himself with scrupulous assiduity;
                    but the long vacations left him abundant leisure for his literary pursuits. He
                    devised several projects which he did not live to execute. One of these was a
                    life of George Buchanan; “in which,” as we are informed, “he proposed to tlo
                    ample justice to his genius as a poet, and his merits as a historian, but to
                    examine, with firmness and accuracy, his conduct as a man and as a politician.”
                    It is easy to conjecture that Buchanan’s politics could not be very highly
                    approved by Lord Woodhouselee. He however found another subject for his
                    biographical labours, and published a very copious work, under the title of
                    “Memoirs of the Life and Writings of the Hon. Henry Home of Kames.” Edinb. 1807,
                    2 vols. 4to. This work, which was reprinted in octavo, contains an ample store
                    of historical and literary information, and in various respects is very
                    creditable to the author. Like all other works, however, it is not without its
                    defects. The author’s manner of writing is too diffuse; his muster-roll of great
                    men is much too great; and not a few subjects and characters seem to be viewed
                    through the dim and narrow expanse of political prejudice. In this modern judge,
                    the conduct of Sir George Mackenzie found a zealous defender. His lordship, we
                    are inclined to think, was more laudably employed in preparing for the press “An
                    Historical and Critical Essay on the Life and Character of Petrarch: with a
                    Translation of a few of his Sonnets.” Edinb. 1810, 8vo. The greater part of this
                    work had appeared in two separate publications; the one a small pamphlet,
                    printed with a similar title twenty-five years before; the other a dissertation
                    or an historical hypothesis of the Abbé de Sade, printed in the fourth volume of
                    the Transactions of the Royal Society of Edinburgh. In the year 1811, he was
                    appointed a judge of the Court of Justiciary. This new preferment he did not
                    long enjoy. For some time he laboured under a disease which he himself
                    contemplated as fatal, but the termination of his earthly career was very
                    sudden. He died at his house in Prince’s-street, on the 5th of January 1813, in
                    the sixty-sixth year of his age.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Transactions of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, vol. viii.
                    p. 515.</p></note></p>
                <p>Lord Woodhouselee appears to have been an amiable as well as an accomplished man.
                    He was gentle and polished in his manners. At every period of his life, he was
                    distinguished by his love of elegant literature. He had cultivated classical
                    learning with perseverance and success; and even during his advanced years he
                    continued to seek a change of tasteful recreation in the composition of Latin
                    verses. Some specimens have been printed. In the Mirror and the Lounger he wrote
                    various papers, and he was likewise a contributor to the Transactions of the
                    Royal Society. He left a widow, with four sons and two daughters. The eldest son
                    succeeded to the estate of Balnain, and the second to that of Woodhouselee.
                    Another son, Alexander, published a work entitled “Considerations on the present
                    Political State of India.” Loud. 1815, 2 vols. 8vo. His youngest son is the
                    author of the History of Scotland, and other performances well known to the
                    public.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
