<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0620-0599-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">POTSDAM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 19, page 599</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1115719">Shells</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r753">Lying</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65f63">Soldiers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn8c">Mark</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n620/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">POTSDAM</label>, the seat of government for the Prussian
                    province of Brandenburg, and the summer residence of the emperor of Germany,
                    lies 16 miles to the south-west of</p>
                <p>Berlin, on the river Havel, which here expands into a series of small lakes. The
                    town is handsomely built, though with a monotonous regularity that betrays its
                    artificial origin, and is situated amid the prettiest scenery of the Mark of
                    Brandenburg, consisting of an oasis of wood and hill and lake in the centre of a
                    sandy and unattractive plain. Except during the summer months, when its streets
                    are enlivened by endless streams of excursionists from Berlin, Potsdam usually
                    presents a somewhat dull and deserted scene, relieved only by the soldiers of
                    its extensive garrison. The greater part of the town lies on the right bank of
                    the Havel and is connected with the Teltow suburb on the opposite bank by a long
                    bridge. At the north end of this bridge rises the royal palace, a large
                    quadrangular building of the 17 th century, with a colonnade, chiefly
                    interesting for the numerous relics it contains of Frederick the Great, who made
                    it his favourite residence. It also contains reminiscences of Voltaire, who also
                    resided here for several years. The principal churches are the Nicolaikirche, a
                    handsome edifice with a dome; the garrison church, containing the remains of
                    Frederick the Great and his father; and the Friedenskirche or church of peace,
                    erected by Frederick William IV. as a “positive and Christian counterpart to the
                    worldly negative of Sans Souci.” Among other conspicuous buildings are the large
                    barracks, orphanages, and other military establishments; the town-house; the
                    district courts; the theatre; and the Brandenburg gate, in the style of a Roman
                    triumphal arch. The Lustgarten, Wilhelmsplatz, and Plantage are open spaces laid
                    out as pleasure-grounds and adorned with statues and busts. In spite of its
                    somewhat sleepy appearance, Potsdam is the seat of a varied if not very
                    extensive industry, of which sugar, cotton and woollen goods, chocolate, and
                    tobacco are the chief products. Market-gardening affords occupation to many of
                    the inhabitants, and the cultivation of winter violets is important enough to be
                    mentioned as a specialty. The Havel is well stocked with fish. In 1880 Potsdam
                    contained 48,447 inhabitants, mainly Protestant. The garrison consists of about
                    7000 men.</p>
                <p>Potsdam is almost entirely surrounded by a fringe of royal palaces, parks, and
                    pleasure-grounds, which fairly substantiate its claim to the title of a “German
                    Versailles.” Immediately to the west is the park of Sans Souci, laid out by
                    Frederick the Great, and largely extended by Frederick William IV. It is in the
                    formal French style of the period, and is profusely embellished with primly-cut
                    hedges and alleys, terraces, fountains, statuary, and artificial ruins. Adjacent
                    to the palace is the famous windmill (now royal property) which its owner
                    refused to sell to the king, meeting threatened violence by an appeal to the
                    judges of Berlin; the whole story, however, is now doubted. A little farther on
                    is the so-called Orangery, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n621/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0621-0600"/> an extensive edifice in the Italian style,
                    containing numerous pictures and other works of art. The park also includes the
                    Charlottenhof, a reproduction of a Pompeian villa. At the west end of the park
                    stands the New Palace, a huge brick edifice 375 feet in length, erected by
                    Frederick the Great at enormous expense in 1763-69, ’ and now occupied by the
                    crown prince of Germany. It contains other reminiscences of Frederick and
                    Voltaire, a few pictures by ancient masters, a theatre, and a large hall
                    gorgeously decorated with shells and minerals. The spacious buildings at the
                    back are devoted to the “Lehrbataillon,” a battalion of infantry composed of
                    draughts from different regiments trained here to ensure uniformity of drill
                    throughout the army. To the north of Potsdam lies a small Russian village,
                    established in 1826 to accommodate the Russian singers attached to the Prussian
                    guards. A little to the east of it is the New Garden, containing the Marble
                    Palace. The list of Potsdam palaces may be closed with two situated on the left
                    bank of the Havel—one at Glienicke and the other on the hill of Babelsberg. The
                    latter, a picturesque building in the English Gothic style, in the midst of a
                    park also in the English taste, is the summer residence of the present emperor
                    of Germany.</p>
                <p>Potsdam was originally a Slavonic fishing-village named Potsdu-pimi, and is first
                    mentioned in a document of 993. It did not, however, attain any importance until
                    the Great Elector established a park and palace here about 1660; and even at the
                    close of his reign it only contained 3000 inhabitants. Frederick William I.
                    (1688-1740) greatly enlarged Potsdam, and hisstiff military tastes are reflected
                    in the monotonous uniformity of the streets. Frederick the Great willingly
                    continued his father’s work, and is the real creator of the modern splendour of
                    the town, of which his memory may be said to form the predominant interest. His
                    successors have each contributed his quota towards the embellishment and
                    extension of the town.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
