<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0919-0674-0651-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PRAED, Winthrop Mackworth (9th edition, volume 19, page
                    651)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:879476">Cornish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pv6b75c">Rowing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086358z">Medals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n674/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PRAED, <hi rend="smallcaps">Winthrop Mackworth</hi></label>
                    (1802-1839), one of the most illustrious English writers of <hi rend="italic"
                        >vers de société,</hi> was the third and youngest son of William Mackworth
                    Praed, serjeant at law. The name of his father’s family had been originally
                    Mackworth, and the circumstances under which the additional title of Praed was
                    adopted are set out in the <hi rend="italic">Parochial History of Cornwall</hi>
                    (iii. 101). Winthrop, a cognomen famous across the Atlantic as borne by the
                    governor of Massachusetts, was his mother’s maiden name, and the union of these
                    three consonantal names in the person of Winthrop Mackworth Praed formed the
                    combination over which Miss Mitford expressed righteous indignation. He was born
                    at 35 John Street, Bedford Row, London, 26th July 1802, and almost as soon as he
                    could read was taught by his father to “lisp in numbers.” His <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n675/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0675-0652"/> mother died in 1809, whereupon the child was
                    sent to the preparatory school of Langley Broom near Coinbrook, where he
                    remained until he was removed (28th March 1814) to Eton. Towards the close of
                    his schoolboy days he started a manuscript periodical called <hi rend="italic"
                        >Apis</hi><hi rend="italic">Matina.</hi> This was succeeded in October 1820
                    by the <hi rend="italic">Etonian,</hi> a paper projected and edited by Praed and
                    Walter Blunt, which appeared every month until July 1821, when the chief editor
                    left the “glade” of Eton and the paper died. Henry Nelson Coleridge, William
                    Sidney Walker, and John Moultrie were the three best known of his coadjutors in
                    this periodical, which was published by Charles Knight, and of which many
                    interesting particulars are set out in Knight’s <hi rend="italic">A
                        utobiography</hi> and in Maxwell Lyte’s <hi rend="italic">Eton College.</hi>
                    Before Praed left school he succeeded in establishing over a shop at Eton a
                    “boy’s library” for the use of the higher Etonians, the books of which are now
                    amalgamated in the official “boy’s library” in the new buildings. His career at
                    Cambridge, where he matriculated at Trinity College, October 1821, was marked by
                    exceptional brilliancy. Thrice he gained the Browne medal and twice the
                    chancellor’s medal for English verse. He was bracketed third in the classical
                    tripos in 1825, won a fellowship at his college in 1827, and three years later
                    carried off the Seatonian prizes. At the Union his speeches attracted the
                    admiration of his fellow-undergraduates; he struggled, and not unequally, with
                    Macaulay and Austin. The character of Praed during his university life is
                    described by Bulwer Lytton in the first volume of his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Life</hi> (pp. 227-239, 244-246). At Cambridge, as at Eton, the poet was
                    drawn by Charles Knight into the pleasures of magazine-writing. <hi
                        rend="italic">Knight’s Quarterly Magazine</hi> was started in 1822 with
                    Praed as one of the principal contributors, and, after languishing for some
                    time, it expired when three octavo volumes had been issued. For two years
                    (1825-27) he resided at Eton as private tutor to Lord Ernest Bruce, a younger
                    son of the marquis of Ailesbury. During part of this time he was occupied in
                    preparing himself for the profession of the law’, and on 29 th May 1829 he was
                    called to the bar at the Middle Temple. He travelled on the Norfolk circuit,
                    where his prospects of advancement were bright, but the bias of his feelings
                    inclined him towards politics, and after a year or two he devoted himself
                    entirely to political life. Whilst at Cambridge he leaned to Whiggism, and even
                    to the autumn of 1829 his feelings were bent towards the same side, but with the
                    dawning of the Reform Bill he passed into the opposite ranks, and when he was
                    returned to parliament for St Germans (17th December 1830) his election was due
                    to the kindness of Mr Herries, a zealous member of the Tory party. He sat for
                    that borough until December 1832, and on its extinction contested the borough of
                    St Ives, within the limits of which the Cornish estates of the Praeds are
                    situated. The squibs which he wrote on this occasion were collected in a volume
                    printed at Penzance in 1833 and entitled <hi rend="italic">Trash, dedicated
                        without respect to James Haise, Esq. M.P.,</hi> his successful competitor.
                    Praed subsequently sat for Great Yarmouth from 1835 to 1837 and for Aylesbury
                    from the latter year until his death. During the progress of the Reform Bill he
                    advocated the creation of three-cornered constituencies, in which each voter
                    should have the power of giving two votes only, and maintained that freeholds
                    within boroughs should confer votes for the boroughs and not for the county.
                    Neither of these suggestions was then adopted, but the former ultimately formed
                    part of the Reform Bill of 1866. Praed was for a few months (December 1834 to
                    April 1835) secretary to the Board of Control, and he was much gratified at
                    receiving the appointment of deputy high steward of his beloved university of
                    Cambridge. The last years of his life were racked by the pains of phthisis,
                    though all that sympathy and devotion could effect to alleviate his sufferings
                    was accomplished by his wife, Helen, daughter of Mr George Bogle, whom he had
                    married in 1835. He died at Chester Square, London, on 15th July 1839, and was
                    buried at Kensal Green on 23d July.</p>
                <p>Praed’s lighter poetry was the perfection of ease. It abounded in allusions to
                    the characters and follies of the day and passed with playful touch from puns to
                    politics. In his humorous effusions he was the chief of a school which in these
                    latter days has found numerous imitators. Many of his poems were marked by much
                    pathetic feeling, for his talents were by no means limited to puns and jests.
                    Several American issues of his works appeared before the comprehensive English
                    edition of his <hi rend="italic">Poems,</hi> “with a memoir by Rev. Derwent
                    Coleridge,” was published in 1864. At a later date a selection from his poems by
                    Sir George Young was given to the world.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
