<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0919-0184-0175-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PLANCK, Gottlieb Jakob (9th edition, volume 19, page
                    175)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f766g40">Sovereigns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sf3s">Charters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150446">Thrones</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852538">Charters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n184/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PLANCK, <hi rend="smallcaps">Gottlieb Jakob</hi></label>
                    (1751-1833), theologian and church historian, was born at Nürtingen in
                    Wiirteinberg, where his father was a notary, on November 15, 1751. He was
                    educated for the Protestant ministry at Blaubeuren, Bebenhausen, and Tübingen,
                    and from 1774 to 1784 held successive appointments as repetent, preacher, and
                    professor in Tübingen and Stuttgart. In 1781 he published anonymously the first
                    volume of his <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Protestantischen
                        Lehrbegriffs</hi>; the second, also anonymous, appeared in 1783; and in 1784
                    he was chosen to succeed Walch at Göttingen. Here in the course of a long and
                    useful professional career he enjoyed a large number of academical and
                    ecclesiastical honours. His death took place on August 31, 1833.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Protestantischen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Lehrl·cgriffs</hi> was completed in 6 vols, in 1800. It was followed by an
                    extensive <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Kirchenverfassung,</hi> in 5 vols.
                    (1803-1809). Both are works of considerable importance, and are characterized by
                    abundant learning and acuteness, the most conspicuous fault in the eyes of his
                    least favourable critics being a tendency, which cannot be wholly denied, to
                    “subjective pragmatism.”</p>
                <p>. PLANTAGENET. This surname, distinctive of a line of kings who ruled in England
                    for more than three hundred years, was first adopted by Geoffrey, count of
                    Anjou, in reference to a sprig of broom <hi rend="italic">(planta genistae)</hi>
                    which he is said to have worn in his bonnet. He is described by early writers as
                    a very handsome man, but there was certainly nothing very striking in his
                    character. He was the son of Fulk, count of Anjou, king of Jerusalem, who,
                    before his departure for the Holy Land, placed him in possession of the counties
                    of Anjou and Maine. This made him in the eyes of Henry I. of England, who was
                    anxious to protect Normandy, an eligible husband for his widowed daughter, the
                    empress Maud, whom he proposed to make his heiress, both in England and beyond
                    sea. It was a purely political marriage, and the couple immediately afterwards
                    had violent quarrels. Nor was either of them popular in England, where a female
                    sovereign would at that time have been an innovation, and Geoffrey was disliked
                    as a foreigner—although the same objection might have seemed to apply to Stephen
                    of Blois, whose superior activity gained possession of the throne before Maud
                    could make good her pretensions. In a long war with the usurper, though
                    recognized as “lady of England” and virtual sovereign by one part of the
                    country, she was only able in the end to secure the succession for her son.
                    Stephen ended his days in peace, and the house of Plantagenet succeeded to the
                    throne in the person of Henry II. by virtue of a compact.</p>
                <p>Henry, the son of Geoffrey of Anjou and the empress Maud, was born at Le Mans in
                    the year 1133, and was just twenty-one years of age when he attained the crown.
                    But his youth had been well spent in preparation for it. When eight years old he
                    was brought to England to be trained in arms. At sixteen he was knighted by his
                    great-uncle David of Scotland. In 1151 his father put him in possession of
                    Normandy, and, dying soon after, left him also the succession to Anjou. These
                    advantages he improved next year by his marriage with Eleanor of Aquitaine,
                    which, by adding Poitou and Guienne to his dominions, gave him the lordship over
                    the whole western side of France from north to south, with the exception of
                    Britanny, which also some time afterwards came under his power.</p>
                <p>Having thus, even before he was twenty, become master of so many fair provinces,
                    he then sailed to England, and, though he did not dethrone Stephen, compelled
                    him to acknowledge him as his successor. Next year he was king It is a new era
                    in the history of England as well as in the fortunes of his house. The country,
                    which was lately so impatient of the rule of a foreigner—fearing, doubtless,
                    that English interests would be sacrificed to those of Anjou —now yields an easy
                    submission to the ruler of all western France from Picardy to the Pyrenees. And,
                    though Henry is in fact one of the greatest of Continental potentates, greater
                    really than his feudal superior the king of France, there is no great cause for
                    anxiety. Henry devotes himself to the interests of his island kingdom, takes
                    steps to secure the succession there to his issue, causing his eldest son even
                    to be crowned king during his own lifetime, and is much more intent on the
                    subjugation of Wales and Ireland and the recognition of his feudal superiority
                    over Scotland than upon any extension of his responsibilities abroad. Personally
                    a man of fiery temperament and strong passions, his patience as a politician is
                    remarkable. Bit by bit he is building up a strong empire, and even keeping the
                    pretensions of the church within definite and reasonable bounds. But a single
                    angry word undoes the work of years. He is responsible for Becket’s murder. He
                    must do penance and make his peace with the church. He must humiliate himself
                    before Becket’s grave.</p>
                <p>His dynastic policy seemed almost an equal failure, but was productive of wide
                    and far-reaching consequences. His ungrateful sons rebelled against him, and
                    when he heard that even John had joined the confederacy he felt that he had
                    nothing more to live for. The eldest, Henry, whom he had been so anxious to make
                    a king during his own life, sickened and died in France after flagrant acts of
                    ingratitude and impiety. Geoffrey, to whom he had secured the duchy of Britanny,
                    soon followed his brother; and there remained but Richard and John, besides
                    three daughters, who were all disposed of in marriage to Continental princes. As
                    Richard, though he came to the crown, also died without legitimate issue, the
                    male line was continued in the two sons of John, Henry III. and Richard, king of
                    the Romans, and the issue of the latter became extinct in the next
                    generation.</p>
                <p>It is remarkable how the prosperity of England seemed to keep pace with the
                    stability of the succession. The short reigns of Richard I. and John were times
                    of peculiar misery, which was only brought to a climax by the war of the Great
                    Charter and by the dauphin being called in to enforce it. Matters improved under
                    Henry HL, even during the minority; but he, too, had a war with his barons in
                    the latter part of his reign. He, too, like his father, had but two sons who
                    grew up to manhood; and, while the elder, Edward I., succeeded him on the throne
                    and was the ancestor of all the following kings, the younger, Edmund Crouchback,
                    became progenitor of the house of Lancaster by the marriage of his great
                    granddaughter Blanche to John of Gaunt, fourth son of Edward III. Edward I. had
                    three sons who came to man’s estate; Edward II. only two, or more properly only
                    one, for the second, John of Eltham, died in Scotland at the age of nineteen.
                    Finally the time of Edward III. with his great family was the climax in the
                    fortunes of the house of Plantagenet. Nor need we pursue the family history
                    further, as the story of its descent after the days of Edward III. will be found
                    sufficiently treated elsewhere (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Lancaster, House
                        of,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">York, House of).</hi></p>
                <p>Of the alliances of this great dynasty the most important after the days of Henry
                    II. were those of the house of Lancaster. Henry III. married his daughter
                    Margaret to Alexander III. of Scotland, and another daughter to the <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n185/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0185-0176"/> duke of Britanny. Edward I. had for his
                    sons-in-law Gilbert de Clare, earl of Gloucester, the duke of Brabant, and the
                    earl of Holland. A daughter of Edward II. married a duke of Gueldres. But “the
                    aspiring blood of Lancaster” spread itself over Europe by alliances with Castile
                    and Portugal, Navarre and Denmark, Bavaria and other foreign states. It has
                    reigned in Portugal to the present day, and it continued to reign in Spain till
                    the end of the 17th century. (j. GA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
