<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0919-0846-0823-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PROSELYTE (9th edition, volume 19, page 823)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:862898">Civilization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827229">Baptism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102941">Sabbath</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46m3337r">Civilization</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35664">Baptism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tk26">Sabbath</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n846/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PROSELYTE</label><hi rend="italic">(πpoσηλvτo&lt;i)</hi> is
                    the term most frequently adopted by the Septuagint, especially in legal
                    passages, to represent the Hebrew ηj. The <hi rend="italic">ger,</hi> or more
                    fully <hi rend="italic">ger</hi><hi rend="italic">vftöshäb,</hi> is not any
                    “stranger” but a stranger dwelling in a Hebrew community and enjoying a certain
                    measure of protection. In old time at least the position of such a stranger was
                    no doubt very insecure, for he had no strong kinsmen to take his part, and so,
                    like the widow and orphan, with whom many passages of the Old Testament
                    associate him, he was liable to oppression. The law as well as the prophets
                    commend him to the humane regard of his neighbours, but it would have been quite
                    foreign to antique ideas to grant him equal rights (see Lev. xxv. 45; Deut,
                    xxiii. 20). Like the Arabic <hi rend="italic">jar,</hi> therefore (whose name is
                    at bottom the same), he must have generally sought to attach himself as a client
                    to some individual or community able to protect him, and so we must understand
                    the metaphor in passages like Ps. xv. 1, xxxix. 12.</p>
                <p>In the old Hebrew kingdom the word <hi rend="italic">gër</hi> had a civil not a
                    religious significance, and it would almost seem that a poor Israelite without
                    inheritance might sink to this position, which indeed is scarcely
                    distinguishable from that of the Le vite in Jud. xvii. 8, who went forth to
                    sojourn <hi rend="italic">(gur)</hi> where he might find a place. The exile and
                    the restoration made a change in this as in all other aspects of Hebrew society.
                    On the one hand Ezekiel xlvii. 22 and Isa. xiv. 1 contemplate that the restored
                    nation shall be recruited by strangers who are received on equal terms; but, as
                    the Jews returned not as an independent nation but as a distinct religious
                    community, this implies especially that the sons of the stranger, by joining
                    Israel, observing the Sabbath, and holding fast to Jehovah’s covenant, may gain
                    admission to all the privileges of the temple and its worship. So it is put in
                    Isa. Ivi. 6, 7 in marked contrast to the restrictions laid down in Deut, xxiii.
                    3, 7 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> That the views of the prophets had practical
                    issue cannot be doubted; even the foreign Nethinim in the second temple were
                    rapidly transformed not merely into good Israelites but into Levites. The
                    condition of admission to the full privileges of an Israelite, in particular to
                    the passover, is, according to the Priestly Code (Exod. xii. 48; Numb. ix. 14),
                    circumcision,—to which the later Jewish usage adds lustration by immersion in
                    water (baptism, <hi rend="italic">t</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">blla)</hi> and the
                    presentation of a sacrifice <hi rend="italic">(korbän).</hi> The immersion,
                    about which there has been a good deal of controversy, some maintaining that it
                    came into use later than Christian baptism, was really a necessary act for one
                    who had been previously unclean, and may be held to be involved in the general
                    Pentateuchal law of ceremonial washings. The later technical name for a heathen
                    who thus joined the theocracy was pηχ∏ *1J, “proselyte of righteousness.”</p>
                <p>The free admission of foreigners to the Jewish church is a mark of the
                    universalistic tendency which, in spite of all the narrownesses of Judaism under
                    the law, accompanied the break-up of the old national system. On the other hand
                    the so-called Law of Holiness (later than Ezekiel but earlier than the Priestly
                    Code), which is contained in Lev. xvii. <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> presents a
                    different line of transition from the purely civil to the religious meaning of
                        <hi rend="italic">gêr.</hi> In these laws, which proceed throughout on the
                    principle that Israel, and all that has to do with Israel, must be regulated by
                    regard to formal holiness, it is demanded that certain rules shall be enforced
                    not only on Israelites proper but on strangers sojourning in their land. They
                    are not to eat blood (xvii. 10), commit incest (xviii. 26), sacrifice to Moloch
                    (xx. 2), or blaspheme Jehovah (xxiv. 16); and for murder and other crimes they
                    are to be answerable to the Hebrew authorities according to Hebrew law (xxiv.
                    22). These rules are in substance—the third being extended to a prohibition of
                    idolatry generally—-the “Noachic laws” to which in later usage a man or woman
                    might promise to conform and thereby, without becoming a regular member of the
                    theocracy, be recognized as a “proselyte of the gate,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >i.e.,</hi> “within the gates of Israel.” What the Law of Holiness proposed
                    to enforce became in fact—the theocracy not possessing political power over
                    strangers— a voluntary obligation assumed by those “who worshipped God” <hi
                        rend="italic">(σeβ0gevoL τbv θeov,</hi> Acts xiii. 50, xvi. 14, xvii. 4, 17,
                    xviii. 7—in E.V. often rendered “devout”).</p>
                <p>The proselytizing zeal of the Jews is spoken of in Mat. xxiii. 15, and by many
                    Greek and Latin writers. Up to the time of Hadrian it was facilitated by the
                    favour generally extended to the Jews by the Roman emperors; and not only on
                    Semitic soil, as at Damascus, where Josephus tells us that most of the women
                    were proselytes, but <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n847/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0847-0824"/> throughout the Roman world many converts were
                    made, especially among women. The most noted conversion was that of the royal
                    house of Adiabene (Josephus, <hi rend="italic">Ant.,</hi> xx. 2), of which the
                    splendid tomb of Queen Helena, a little way outside of Jerusalem, still remains
                    a monument.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
