<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0919-0742-0719-05" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PRÉVOST D’EXILLES, Antoine (9th edition, volume 19,
                    page 719)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b6k">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pt4b">Novels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:835564">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:875388">Conquerors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039784">Novelle</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1002769">Love</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n742/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PRÉVOST D’EXILLES, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Antoine</hi></label><hi rend="smallcaps">François</hi> (1697- 1763), more
                    commonly called the abbé Prévost, one of the most important French novelists of
                    the 18th century, was born at Hesdin in Artois on 1st April 1697. His father was
                    of good family, and held legal employments of some importance. Prévost was
                    educated by the Jesuits, first at Hesdin and then at Paris. At the age of
                    sixteen he left the Collège d’Harcourt and enlisted. This was, however, at the
                    close of the War of the Spanish Succession, and he soon returned to the Jesuits,
                    and was almost persuaded to enter the order. According to some accounts he
                    actually did so, but a truant disposition once more came on him and he again
                    joined the army, apparently obtaining some commission. It is, however, not easy
                    to make his statement that he passed five or six years thus tally with the
                    positive assertion that in 1719 he once more sought the cloister, this time
                    joining the famous learned community of the Benedictines of St Maur. He took the
                    vows finally in 1720, and it would appear that for some seven years he devoted
                    himself without repining to study at various houses of the order, preaching,
                    teaching, and writing some part of the <hi rend="italic">Gallia Christiana.</hi>
                    In 1727, however, or thereabouts (for the details of Prévost’s life, though
                    unusually interesting, are most vaguely and insufficiently recorded) he once
                    more broke bounds and fled to Holland. It is said that the immediate occasion
                    was nothing more than a wish which he had formed to be transferred to Cluny, and
                    which made him commit some technical misdemeanour. However this may be, he was
                    for six years an exile in Holland and England, and one story even asserts that
                    he contracted a regular or rather irregular marriage during this period. He
                    certainly published the first of his remarkable novels, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mémoires</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">un Homme</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de Qualité,</hi> in 1728, and continued them for some years.
                    Besides this he produced much miscellaneous work— <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cléve-</hi><hi rend="italic">land,</hi> another novel <hi rend="italic">;
                        Manon</hi><hi rend="italic">Lescaut,</hi> his masterpiece (which is a kind
                    of appendix to his first book); and a periodical publication, partly in the
                    style of the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> and partly in that of a literary
                    review, called <hi rend="italic">Le Pour et le Contre.</hi> All these were begun
                    and most of them were finished before 1735, when he was back in France and
                    produced his last novel of importance, the <hi rend="italic">Doyen</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de Killérine,</hi> in which, as in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cléveland,</hi> he made much use of his English sojourn. He returned to
                    France openly and with the royal permission, being allowed to wear the dress of
                    the secular priesthood. Among his patrons the cardinal de Bissy and the prince
                    de Conti are named; the latter made him his chaplain. He lived for nearly thirty
                    years longer, composing, though not for bread, an extraordinary number of books,
                    some of them original, some compilations. Amongst them were an <hi rend="italic"
                        >Histoire Générale</hi><hi rend="italic">des Voyages,</hi> historical
                    compilations on William the Conqueror and Margaret of Anjou, letters, moral
                    essays, semi-scientific works, translations (including <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pamela</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Clarissa),</hi> and some original pieces.
                    Of all these the novel called <hi rend="italic">Histoire d'une Grecque
                        Moderne</hi> (1741) has alone attracted some attention in modern times.
                    Prévost was a facile writer and a fair critic, but except for his first three
                    novels, and especially for <hi rend="italic">Manon Lescaut,</hi> he would hardly
                    be remembered save as a man of a curiously eventful and very imperfectly
                    recorded life. His death itself has a kind of legendary character, and some of
                    the circumstances are, it may be hoped, fictitious. He lived in a small cottage
                    (for, despite his immense literary work on subjects which for the most part
                    occupy only writers for money, he seems to have written <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n743/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0743-0720"/> purely for love) at Chantilly, and it was his
                    custom to walk much in the woods there. What is agreed is that he was struck
                    with apoplexy during one of these walks, on 23d November 1763, and was found
                    senseless. The legend adds the hideous particular that he was not dead, and that
                    a clumsy village surgeon, heedlessly beginning what he supposed to be a <hi
                        rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination, at once recalled his patient to
                    life and killed him. Even without this detail there is sufficient romantic
                    interest (without other stories, some of them demonstrably fictitious, such as
                    that he was accidentally the cause of his father’s death) about this life of a
                    man who is at the same time uniformly represented as an indefatigable student
                    and one of a quiet and easygoing temperament.</p>
                <p>Prevost’s three chief romances, the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Cleveland,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Doyen</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de Killérine,</hi> are not unremarkable, because they hold a
                    kind of middle place between the incident-romance of Le Sage and Defoe and the
                    sentiment - romance of Marivaux and Richardson; but they all have the defect of
                    intolerable length and of an indefinite fluency. <hi rend="italic">Manon</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Lescaut,</hi> his one masterpiece, and one of the greatest
                    novels of the century, is in both these respects so different that it might seem
                    impossible that the same man should have written it. It is very short, it is
                    entirely free from improbable incident, it is penetrated by the truest and the
                    most cunningly managed feeling, and almost every one of its characters is a
                    triumph of that analytic portraiture which is the secret of the modern novel.
                    The chevalier des Grieux, the hero, is probably the most perfect example of the
                    carrying out of the sentiment “All for love and the world well lost” that exists
                    in fiction (it is curious that Prévost translated Dryden’s play of the name), at
                    least where the circumstances are those of ordinary and probable life. Tiberge,
                    his friend, is hardly inferior in the difficult part of mentor and reasonable
                    man. Lescaut, the heroine’s brother, has vigorous touches as a bully and
                    Bohemian; but the triumph of the book is Manon herself. Animated by a real
                    affection for her lover, and false to him only because her incurable love of
                    splendour, comfort, and luxury prevents her from welcoming privation with him or
                    for him, though in effect she prefers him to all others, perfectly natural and
                    even amiable in her degradation, and yet showing the moral of that degradation
                    more .vividly than a hundred characters drawn with a less complacent pencil
                    could have done, Manon is one of the most remarkable heroines in all fiction.
                    She had no literary ancestress; she seems to have sprung entirely from the
                    imagination, or perhaps the sympathetic observation, of the wandering scholar
                    who drew her. Only the <hi rend="italic">Princesse de Clèves</hi> can challenge
                    comparison with her before or near to her own date, and in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Manon</hi><hi rend="italic">Lescaut</hi> the plot is much more complete and
                    interesting, the sentiments less artificial, and the whole story nearer to
                    actual life than in Madame de la Fayette’s masterpiece. It is not easy to name a
                    novel on the same scale which is more directly and naturally affecting at a
                    first reading, and which on subsequent study approves itself more thoroughly as
                    a work of art, than <hi rend="italic">Manon</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Lescaut.</hi></p>
                <p>There is no complete edition of Prévost’s works. Oeuvres Choisies were published
                    in 1783, and again in 1806. Of Manon Lescaut the editions are very numerous.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
