<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0761-0738-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PRINCE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 19, page 738</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1076505">Princesses</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1750257">Heirs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888134">Daughters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1212489">Bulgaria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1692600">Montenegro</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v18f">Princesses</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4sn01992">Monarchs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4610w100">Rulers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm13z3g">Heirs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n761/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PRINCE</label>. “Prince” and “princess” are names or
                    descriptions implying either political authority or social rank in the persons
                    to whom they relate or are accorded. We have in “prince” the English and French
                    form of the Latin <hi rend="italic">princeps,</hi> which with more or less
                    modification has been adopted into nearly every language of modern Europe, and
                    of which the original and common use was to indicate priority or pre-eminence of
                    any sort. In an honorary sense it was, to begin with, applied by the Romans to
                    the first or most distinguished members of the senate and the equestrian order
                    respectively, and their appellations of <hi rend="italic">princeps senatus</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">princeps juventutis</hi><hi rend="italic">^WQτe</hi>
                    afterwards appropriated to the emperors themselves and to their adopted heirs
                    and successors in the empire. Hence the attribute <hi rend="italic"
                    >princeps</hi> became definitely associated with the notions of sovereignty and
                    dominion, and its derivatives have been always and everywhere employed as titles
                    of dignity and expressions of awe or respect.</p>
                <p>In English the word “prince” may be used in certain connexions in the original
                    wide sense of the Latin word. More definitely it is applicable to supreme rulers
                    of both sexes and almost all kinds. Thus the emperor of Russia, the queen of
                    England, and the king of the Belgians are equally princes or monarchs, and the
                    consorts of emperors and kings are princesses. But the presidents of republics
                    are neither princes nor monarchs. Prince, however, unlike monarch, applies to
                    rulers who are subordinate as well as to rulers who are supreme, to such minor
                    potentates as the electors of the old German empire or the feudal peers of
                    France once were, and the reigning grand-dukes or dukes of Germany now are.
                    Again, all the children and many of the descendants and other relations of
                    monarchs and princes of every class and grade are themselves princes or
                    princesses, although it often happens that they have also some special name or
                    personal dignity by which they are ordinarily known. The eldest son of the
                    emperor of Russia, for instance, is called the “cesarewich,” as the eldest son
                    and next brother of the king of France under the <hi rend="italic"
                    >ancien</hi><hi rend="italic">regime</hi> were called the “dauphin” and
                    “monsieur.” In England for several centuries the younger sons of the sovereign
                    have had dukedoms conferred on them, as in the cases of the dukes of Edinburgh,
                    Connaught, and Albany, and from the reign of Edward IV. until the reign of
                    Victoria the dukedom of York was always given to the second son and the dukedom
                    of Gloucester to the third, unless it was already appropriated. The princes and
                    princesses of Russia are “grand-dukes” and “grandduchesses,” of Austria
                    “archdukes” and “archduchesses,” and of Spain “infants” and “infantas.” Some of
                    the eldest sons of kings are “dukes,” as the duke of Brabant in Belgium and the
                    duke of Sparta in Greece. But, when they are not dukes, or princes with a
                    territorial title, as the prince of Wales or the princes of Naples in Italy and
                    Orange in Holland, they are described as “princes” with the additions of
                    “imperial,” “crown,” “royal,” or “hereditary,” as the case may be, and the name
                    of the dominions to which they are the heirs-apparent. The eldest sons of
                    reigning grand-dukes or dukes, however, are called “hereditary grand-dukes” or
                    “hereditary dukes,” their younger brothers and their sisters being all the same
                    princes and princesses. The Prussian fashion of calling the eldest daughter of
                    the sovereign the “princess royal” was introduced into England by George II. It
                    was not the custom, however, for the daughters of English monarchs to be
                    entitled “princesses” at all until the reign of Charles I. The two daughters of
                    Henry VIII. were the Lady Mary and the Lady Elizabeth until they ascended the
                    throne, for, although there is a tradition that they were both made princess of
                    Wales successively, there is no evidence whatever to support it. As late as the
                    reign of Charles II. the granddaughters of Charles I., daughters of James, duke
                    of York, the heir-presumptive to the crown, were called the Lady Mary and the
                    Lady Anne until they became princesses by marriage, the one as the wife of
                    William, prince of Orange, and the other as the wife of Prince George of
                    Denmark. It is difficult to say when the younger sons of English sovereigns were
                    originally called “princes.” But the practice of so calling them probably began
                    as early as the reign of Henry VII., although there was no opportunity of
                    observing it again before the reign of James I., when it was certainly
                    established.</p>
                <p>In France before the Revolution the designation of “princes du sang,” or “princes
                    of the blood,” was common from generation to generation to all the male
                    descendants of the French kings, and they had precedence according to their
                    proximity to the crown of all dignitaries and nobles. It was not, however, until
                    the reign of Charles VII. or Louis XI. that they were called “princes,” their
                    earlier appellation having been “seigneurs du sang” or “seigneurs du lignage du
                    roi.” In France, too, the natural children of the king were, when formally
                    acknowledged, termed “princes légitimés,” at any rate from the reign of Louis
                    XIV., and although they were excluded from the line of succession to the throne
                    they were ranked immediately after the princes du sang. The princely character
                    of all the male descendants of the imperial, royal, and other reigning families
                    of the Continent, when neither illegitimate nor the issue of a morganatic
                    marriage, is perpetual and indelible. Moreover, the families which were formerly
                    reigning within the boundaries of the old German or existing Austrian empires,
                    despite that they have now ceased to reign, are in this respect still in the
                    full possession of their earlier privileges. But in England, on the contrary, it
                    was considered necessary only about a quarter of a century ago to make express
                    provision by royal authority that the titles of “prince” and “princess” should
                    be enjoyed by the children of the sons as well as by the sons and daughters of
                    any sovereign of the United Kingdom. It may therefore be concluded that they had
                    no previous claim to the attributes of prince and princess, and that they will
                    not transmit them to their posterity.</p>
                <p>Besides the more or less general uses of the words “prince’’and “princess” which
                    we have already noticed, there are the particular applications of them, first to
                    a distinct class of rulers, and secondly to a particular order of nobility.
                    Princes regarded as the political chiefs of states are inferior to emperors and
                    kings, and not necessarily superior to reigning grand-dukes or dukes. Very few
                    examples of them at present exist,—those of Waldeck and Pyrmont, Montenegro,
                    Bulgaria, and Monaco alone occurring to us. None of the great feudatories of the
                    Middle Ages, whether in Germany, France, or Spain, were formally described as
                    princes, and of the mediatized families still extant who once supplied members
                    to the imperial diet, many of them from a remote period, not one had the
                    designation of “prince” before the commencement of the 17th century, while not
                    more than five or six had it before the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n762/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0762-0739"/></p>
                <p>commencement of the 18th century. The old Italian and Welsh princes and the more
                    modern princes of Orange are in fact nearly the only reigning princes who are
                    remembered in history. As a name of dignity, neither of dominion on the one hand
                    nor of courtesy on the other, “prince” is common enough among the nobility of
                    the Continent. But in England it is never conferred on anybody except the
                    heir-apparent to the crown, and his principality is a peerage. Since the reign
                    of Edward III. the eldest sons of the kings and queens of England have always
                    been dukes of Cornwall by birth, and, with a few exceptions, princes of Wales by
                    creation. Before that Edward I. had conferred the principality on his eldest
                    son, afterwards Edward II., who was summoned to and sat in parliament as prince
                    of Wales. But Edward the Black Prince was the original grantee of the
                    principality as well as of the dukedom, under the special limitations which have
                    continued in force to the present day. The entail of the former was “to him and
                    his heirs the kings of England” and of the latter “to him and his heirs the
                    first-begotten sons of the kings of England.” Hence when a prince of Wales and
                    duke of Cornwall succeeds to the throne the principality in all cases merges at
                    once in the crown, and can have no separate existence again except under a fresh
                    creation, while the dukedom, if he has a son, descends immediately to him, or
                    remains in abeyance until he has a son if one is not already born. If, however,
                    a prince of Wales and duke of Cornwall should die in the lifetime of the
                    sovereign, leaving a son and heir, both dignities are extinguished, because his
                    son, although he is his heir, is neither a king of England nor the
                    first-begotten son of a king of England. But, if instead of a son he should
                    leave a brother his heir, then— as was decided in the reign of James I. on the
                    death of Henry, prince of Wales, whose heir was his brother Charles, duke of
                    York—the dukedom of Cornwall would pass to him as the first-begotten son of the
                    king of England then alive, the principality of Wales alone becoming merged in
                    the crown. It has thus occasionally happened that the dukes of Cornwall have not
                    been princes of Wales, as Henry VI. and Edward VI., and that the princes of
                    Wales have not been dukes of Cornwall, as Richard II. and George III. It was in
                    direct imitation of these dignities that the principality of the Asturias and
                    the dukedom of Rothesay were created by John I. of Castile and Robert III. of
                    Scotland in favour of their eldest sons and the eldest sons of their successors.
                    In the new kingdoms of Holland and Italy the principalities of Orange and Naples
                    have been appropriated to the eldest sons of the sovereigns. Under the monarchy
                    in France princes invariably yielded precedence to dukes, unless of course they
                    were “princes du sang” or “princes légitimés,” as the princes of Condé, of
                    Conti, or of Lamballe. Several of the French dukes numbered principalities among
                    their inferior titles, as the duke of La Rochefoucauld also prince of Marçillac,
                    and the duke of Gramont also prince of Bidache, while several of the French
                    princes were the heads merely of junior branches of ducal families, as the
                    princes of Léon and of Soubise of the Rohan family, and the princes of Tingry
                    and of Robecq of the Montmorency family. When Napoleon established the empire
                    and reintroduced titles into France, princes were made the first and dukes the
                    second order of the new nobility. But only a few princes were
                    created—Talleyrand, prince of Bénévent; Bernadotte, prince of Ponte Corvo;
                    Berthier, prince of Wagram; Davoust, prince of Eckmühl; Masséna, prince of
                    Essling; and Ney, prince of Moskowa, nearly if not quite exhausting the list. In
                    Germany and Austria the title of “prince” is represented by “Prinz” when it
                    appertains to the members of imperial and royal families, as Kronprinz von
                    Oesterreich or Prinz Wilhelm von Preussen, and by “Fürst” when it appertains to
                    the members of mediatized or noble families, as Fürst von Salm-Salm or von
                    Hohenlohe-Langenburg, and Fürst von Metternich-Winneburg or von
                    Bismarck-Schönhausen. According to its identification with “Prinz” or “Fürst” it
                    is a higher or lower dignity than “Herzog” (duke). In the old empire, however,
                    the Churfürsten or electors were always next to the emperor and the king of the
                    Romans. In Italy, as well as in Belgium and Holland, princes are inferior to
                    dukes as members of a particular order of nobility. In Spain and Portugal we are
                    not aware that the title of “prince” has ever been conferred on a subject
                    outside of the royal family except in the well-known case of Godoy, Prince of
                    the Peace. Among the Russian nobility there are neither dukes nor marquesses,
                    the orders being princes, counts, and barons. It is to be observed, however,
                    that in no part of the Continent does precedence depend exclusively as in the
                    United Kingdom on the apparent rank of titular distinctions or the relative
                    positions which they nominally occupy in formal classification. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(f. db.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
