<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0812-0789-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PROCOPIUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 19, page 789</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j97c33">Ostrogoths</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4wp9tb5s">Historians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1750271">Ostrogoths</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:957686">Historians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1085685">Questioning</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n812/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PROCOPIUS</label>, the most eminent historian of the Eastern
                    Roman empire, was born at Caesarea in Palestine, then one of the chief cities of
                    the Roman East, towards the end of the 5th century, probably between 485 and 495
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> Of his family and earlier life nothing is known,
                    but it has been plausibly conjectured from the aristocratic sympathies he
                    manifests that he belonged to one of the better families of his city, and from
                    the place of his birth that he was educated at the great law school of Berytus
                    (Beirut). He became a lawyer, probably at Constantinople, and was in 526
                    appointed <hi rend="italic">συp,βoυλoς</hi> to Belisarius, who was proceeding to
                    command the imperial army in the war against the Persians (Proc., <hi
                    rend="italic">Pers.,</hi> i. 12). The chief duties of this office, which is also
                    described as that of παp∈δpoς or σ∙υγκα0cδpos, seem to have been the giving of
                    legal advice to the generaζ <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n813/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0813-0790"/> who had a measure of judicial as well as
                    administrative power, and have been well compared by Air Hodgkin <hi
                    rend="italic">(Italy and Her Invaders,</hi> vol. iii. p. 638) to those of an
                    English judge advocate. When the Persian War was suspended Procopius probably
                    returned with his general to Constantinople; and when Belisarius was despatched
                    against the Vandals of Africa in 533 Procopius again accompanied him, as he
                    subsequently did in the war against the Ostrogoths of Italy which began in 536.
                    Whether he held the same position of legal assessor through these campaigns or
                    was merely a member of the large personal following which Belisarius had we do
                    not know. Suidas calls him the secretary (υτroγpαφcυς) of Belisarius, but this
                    may be merely a reference to his original appointment as <hi rend="italic"
                    >σύμβουλος</hi> in the Persian campaign. He was evidently much valued by
                    Belisarius, who twice employed him on difficult and important missions—once in
                    533 to obtain from Syracuse provisions for the Roman fleet and information as to
                    the preparations of the Vandals, and again in 537, when the historian was
                    despatched from Rome, which Belisarius was holding against the Goths, to collect
                    troops and corn in Campania and bring them in a fleet to Ostia. On both
                    occasions Procopius acquitted himself with skill and success. He passes lightly
                    over his own performances, and nowhere strikes us as eager for an opportunity of
                    singing his own praises.</p>
                <p>After the capture of Ravenna in 539 Procopius would seem to have returned to
                    Constantinople, where he was in 542, the year of the great plague, which he has
                    minutely described <hi rend="italic">(Pers.,</hi> ii. 22). It does not appear
                    whether he was with the Roman armies in the later stages of the Gothic War, when
                    Belisarius and afterwards Narses fought against Totila in Italy, though his
                    narrative of these years is so much less full and minute than that of the
                    earlier warfare that probably he was not an eye-witness of these campaigns. Of
                    his subsequent fortunes we know nothing, except that he was living in 559. He
                    was an advocate by profession (Agathias, Evagrius, and other Byzantine writers
                    call him <hi rend="italic">pητωp),</hi> but whether he practised law after his
                    return from the Italian wars may be doubted, for he must have been then occupied
                    with the composition of his histories, and his books show that he spent a good
                    deal of time in travel. He seldom refers to legal matters, and shows little
                    interest in them, mentioning only in the most cursory way the legislation and
                    codification of Justinian. Whether he was the Procopius who was prefect of
                    Constantinople in 562 (Theophanes, <hi rend="italic">Chronographia,</hi> 201,
                    202) and was removed from office in the year following cannot be determined.
                    Little can be founded on the name, for it was a common one in that age, and had
                    this Procopius been our historian one might have expected some of the subsequent
                    writers who refer to the latter to have mentioned this fact about him. On the
                    other hand the historian was evidently a person of note, who had obtained the
                    rank of <hi rend="italic">Illustris</hi> (Suidas calls him <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ίλλούστριος),</hi> and a passage in the <hi rend="italic">Anecdota</hi> looks
                    as if he had risen to be a senator <hi rend="italic">(Anecd.,</hi> c. 12), so
                    that there is no improbability in his having been raised to the high office of
                    prefect.</p>
                <p>There has been some controversy as to his religion. So far as external profession
                    went, he must have been a Christian; for paganism, persecuted by Justinian,
                    would hardly have been tolerated in so conspicuous a person; nor is there any
                    evidence for his being a heathen other than the cool indifference with which
                    (except in the <hi rend="italic">De Aedi-</hi><hi rend="italic">faιis)</hi> he
                    speaks about Christian beliefs and practices. He seems to have been so far a
                    Christian as to have believed in a God and have held Christ to be a supernatural
                    being, but he frequently expresses himself in sceptical language, talks of God
                    and Fate as if practically synonymous, and entertained great contempt for the
                    theological controversies which raged so hotly in his own time.</p>
                <p>Procopius’s writings fall into three divisions—the <hi rend="italic">His</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">tories</hi> (Persian, Vandal, and Gothic Wars) in eight books, the
                    treatise on the <hi rend="italic">Buildings of Justinian</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(De Aedificiis)</hi> in six books, and the <hi rend="italic">Unpublished
                    Memoirs</hi> (τα ’Ανέκδοτα, <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Arcana),</hi> here cited as the <hi rend="italic">Anecdota.</hi></p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Histories</hi> are called by the author himself the <hi
                    rend="italic">Boohs about the</hi> IPαrs (oi <hi rend="italic">υπep τωv
                    7roλeμωv</hi><hi rend="italic">λόγοι).</hi> They consist of—(1) the Persian
                    Wars, in two books, giving a narrative of the long struggle of the emperors
                    Justin and Justinian against the Persian kings Kobad and Chosroes Anushirvan
                    down to 550 <hi rend="italic">; (2)</hi> the Vandal War, in two books,
                    describing the conquest of the Vandal kingdom in Africa and the subsequent
                    events there from 532 down to 546 (with a few words on later occurrences); (3)
                    the Gothic War, in four books, narrating the war against the Ostrogoths in
                    Sicily and Italy from 536 till 552. These three treatises were written
                    continuously to form one connected history; but, as the arrangement of events is
                    geographical, not chronological, they overlap in time, the Persian War carrying
                    its narrative over a large part of the period embraced in the Vandal War and the
                    Gothic War. The fourth and last of the four books of the Gothic War is really a
                    general history of the empire, designed to continue the Persian War as well as
                    the Gothic. It was written after the year in which the preceding seven books had
                    been published, and was itself published apparently in 554 or 555. These eight
                    books of <hi rend="italic">Histories,</hi> although mainly occupied with
                    military matters, contain notices of some of the more important domestic events,
                    such as the Nika insurrection at Constantinople in 532, the plague in 542, the
                    conspiracy of Artabanes in 548. They tell us, however, comparatively little
                    about the civil administration of the empire, and nothing about legislation. On
                    the other hand they are rich in geographical and ethnographical information,
                    often of the highest value for our knowledge of the barbarian and particularly
                    of the Teutonic tribes who lived on the borders of the empire and were either
                    its enemies or the material of its armies.</p>
                <p>As an historian, Procopius would have deserved honour in any age, and is of quite
                    unusual merit when one considers the generally low literary level of the age
                    which produced him. From the 4th to the 15th century the Eastern empire has no
                    lay writer of gifts approaching his. He is industrious in collecting facts,
                    careful and impartial in stating them; his judgment is sound, his reflexions
                    generally acute, his conceptions of the general march and movement of things not
                    unworthy of the great events he has recorded. His descriptions, particularly of
                    military operations, are clear, and his especial fondness for this part of the
                    subject seldom leads him into unnecessary minuteness. The style, although marked
                    by mannerisms, by occasional affectations and rhetorical devices, is on the
                    whole direct and businesslike, nor is the Greek bad, when one considers the
                    time. Thucydides and Herodotus are the two models whom he keeps always before
                    his eyes: he imitates the former in the maxims <hi rend="italic">(γvωμai)</hi>
                    he throws in, and the speeches which he puts into the mouth of the chief actors;
                    the latter in his frequent geographical digressions, in the personal anecdotes,
                    in the tendency to collect and attach some credence to marvellous tales. It need
                    hardly be said that he falls far short of the vigour and profundity of the
                    Attic, as well as of the genial richness, the grace, the simplicity, the moral
                    elevation, the poetical feeling of the Ionic historian. The speeches are
                    obviously composed by Procopius himself, rarely showing any dramatic variety in
                    their language, but they seem sometimes to convey the substance of what was
                    said, and even when this is not the case they frequently serve to bring out the
                    points of a critical situation. The geographical and ethnological notices are
                    precious. Procopius is almost as much a geo- <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n814/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0814-0791"/></p>
                <p>grapher as an historian—it is one of his merits to have perceived the importance
                    of each science to the other—and his descriptions of the peoples and places he
                    himself visited are generally careful and thorough. Although a warmly patriotic
                    Roman, he does full justice to the merits of the barbarian enemies of the
                    empire, and particularly of the Ostrogoths; although the subject of a despotic
                    prince, he criticizes the civil and military administration of Justinian and his
                    dealings with foreign peoples with a freedom which gives a favourable impression
                    of the tolerance of the emperor. His chief defects are a somewhat pretentious
                    and at the same time monotonous style, and a want of sympathy and intensity,
                    which prevents him from giving full life and reality to the personages who
                    figure in his narrative, or raising it to a level worthy of the great and
                    terrible scenes which he has sometimes to describe.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">De Aedificiis,</hi> or treatise on the Buildings of
                    Justinian, contains an account of the chief public works executed during the
                    reign of the emperor down to 558, in which year it seems to have been composed,
                    particularly -churches, palaces, hospitals, fortresses, roads, bridges and other
                    river works. All these are of course ascribed to the personal action of the
                    monarch. The treatise is a little longer than the average length of one single
                    book of the eight books of the <hi rend="italic">Histories.</hi> Its arrangement
                    is geographical; beginning from Constantinople, it describes works executed in
                    the Mesopotamian provinces, in Armenia and the Caucasian countries, in Thrace
                    and Macedonia, in Asia Minor and Syria, in Egypt and Africa as far as the
                    Pillars of Hercules. If not written at the command of Justinian (as some have
                    supposed), it is at any rate semiofficial, being evidently grounded on official
                    information, and is full of gross flattery of the emperor and of the (then
                    deceased) empress. In point of style it is greatly inferior to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Histories</hi> —florid, pompous, and affected, and at the same
                    time tedious. Its chief value lies in the geographical notices which it
                    contains.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Anecdota,</hi> or Secret History, in length almost equal to
                    the <hi rend="italic">De Aedificiis,</hi> and somewhat shorter than the average
                    length of a book of the <hi rend="italic">Histories,</hi> purports to be a
                    supplement to these, containing explanations and additions which the author
                    could not place in the <hi rend="italic">Histories</hi> for fear of Justinian
                    and Theodora. It is a furious invective against these sovereigns, their
                    characters, personal conduct, and government, with attacks on Belisarius and his
                    wife Antonina, and on other official persons of note in the civil and military
                    services of the empire—attacks whose effect is weakened by the passion the
                    author betrays. Frequent references to the <hi rend="italic">Histories</hi> are
                    interspersed, but the events of the wars are seldom referred to, the main topic
                    being the personal and official misdeeds of the rulers as shown in domestic
                    affairs. The ferocity and brutality - <hi rend="italic">1</hi> this scandalous
                    chronicle astonish us, for modern writings of the same order have usually been
                    the work of vulgar and anonymous scribblers, not of an able, accomplished, and
                    highly placed man such as Procopius was. Hence its authenticity has been often
                    called in question, and a few words are needed both on that question and on the
                    further question of the credibility of its contents.</p>
                <p>It was unknown to Agathias and Evagrius, younger contemporaries of Procopius who
                    frequently mention his <hi rend="italic">Histories,</hi> and is first referred
                    to by Suidas (writing in the 10th century), who ascribes it to Procopius. Two
                    MSS. (since lost) are mentioned as having been brought to Italy in the days of
                    the Renaissance, but the first publication was made by Nicholas Alemanni, an
                    official of the Vatican, who found a MS. in that library and edited it with
                    copious and learned notes and a Latin translation (Lyons, 1623). Since his day
                    several jurists (led thereto by jealousy for Justinian’s reputation) and other
                    scholars have denied it to be the work of Procopius, among whom it is sufficient
                    to refer to the latest, J. H. Reinkens.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Anecdota sintne</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >scripta</hi><hi rend="italic">a Procopio</hi><hi rend="italic">Caesariensi
                    inquiritur,</hi> Breslau, 1858.</p></note> The external argument against its
                    genuineness, drawn from its not being mentioned till four centuries after the
                    death of Procopius, appears weak when we recollect that it was obviously not
                    written to be published at the time, and may well have remained concealed for
                    generations. The internal argument from the difference between the view of
                    Justinian it presents and that given in the <hi rend="italic">De Aedificiis</hi>
                    will impress no one who has observed the almost patent insincerity of the latter
                    book, and the censure, severe though carefully guarded, which the <hi
                    rend="italic">Histories</hi> frequently bestow on Justinian’s policy. On the
                    other hand the agreement in many points of fact between the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histories</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Anecdota,</hi> and the exactness of
                    the references from the latter to the former, point to unity of authorship;
                    while the similarity of opinions, ideas, beliefs, prejudices, and still more the
                    similarities of literary manner, style, and language, supply an overwhelming
                    body of evidence that the <hi rend="italic">Anecdota</hi> are a genuine, and so
                    far as his deep-seated feelings go the most genuine, work of Procopius. The
                    question, which ought never to have been deemed doubtful, has been set at rest
                    by the careful comparison of the use of words and phrases in the acknowledged
                    works of Procopius and in the <hi rend="italic">Anecdota,</hi> which we owe to
                    the industry of Dr Felix Dahn, and which is set forth in his excellent book
                    mentioned at the close of this article. It is less easy to pronounce on the
                    credibility of the picture which the <hi rend="italic">Anecdota</hi> give of the
                    court and government of Justinian. Plainly there are many exaggerations and some
                    absurdities; yet, when we find some of the severest statements of the book
                    confirmed by other annalists and others substantially tallying with or
                    explaining those made by Procopius himself in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histories,</hi> we are led to conclude that there is a substantial basis of
                    fact for the charges it brings. It is of course often difficult, sometimes
                    impossible, to say what deductions must be made from the form these charges
                    take; but after studying the book closely one becomes rather less than more
                    sceptical.</p>
                <p>In point of style, the <hi rend="italic">Anecdota</hi> are inferior to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Histories,</hi> and have the air of being u: iff fished or at
                    least unrevised. Their merit lies in the furious earnestness with which they are
                    written, and which gives them a force and reality sometimes wanting in the more
                    elaborate books written for publication.</p>
                <p>The character of a man who could revenge himself for having been obliged to
                    bestow gross flattery on his sovereign by ferocious invective meant to be
                    launched after his death inspires little respect. Otherwise Procopius is a
                    favourable specimen of his age. He is patriotic, with a strong feeling for the
                    greatness of the empire, its dignity, the preservation of its ancient order. He
                    is a worshipper of the past, whose ideal is such a government as that of Trajan
                    or Hadrian. His ethical standard is scarcely affected by Christianity, but is tL
                    t of a Greek of classical times, with too great a tolerance of deceit when
                    practised against barbarian enemies, and doubtless also with a deficient sense
                    of honour and personal independence.. Yet his patriotism does not prevent him
                    from doing justice to the valour of the Persians, or the still finer qualities
                    of the Goths as he had learnt to know them in Italy. He is, however, frigid in
                    sentiment as well as in style, and throws little geniality into his narratives
                    and descriptions. In his attitude towards the unseen world he is at once
                    sceptical and superstitious—sceptical in that he speaks with equal hesitation
                    about the practices <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n815/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0815-0792"/> and doctrines of different faiths, and declares
                    his persuasion that nothing more can be known about God than that He is all-wise
                    and all-powerful; superstitious in his readiness to accept all kinds of marvels,
                    omens, prophecies, apparitions, and to find in the sudden changes of human
                    affairs the action of a spiteful fortune which delights to startle men and
                    confound their schemes. Procopius has little philosophy in his history; he is a
                    vague and inconsistent thinker, and is strongest when he is describing events or
                    facts, or drawing such direct inferences from them as strike an acute man of the
                    world.</p>
                <p>The best edition of Procopius is that by Dindorf in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Corpus</hi><hi rend="italic">Scriptorum</hi><hi rend="italic">Historiae
                    Byzantines,</hi> 3 vols., Bonn, 1833-38. The best criticisms and examinations of
                    his writings are those by W. S. Teuffel, in his <hi rend="italic">Studien und
                    Charakteristiken zur Literaturgeschichte,</hi> Leipsic, 1871; and F. Dahn, <hi
                    rend="italic">Prokopius von Cäsarea,</hi> Berlin, 1865. (J. BR.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
