<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0010-0001-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PHYSICAL SCIENCES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 19, page 1</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52ff6p">Heat</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hr3b">Heating</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r31v">Lighting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:954023">Heating</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:953778">Heat</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:998642">Lighting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n10/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PHYSICAL SCIENCES</label>.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The paper of the late Professor J. Clerk
                    Maxwell which is presented to the reader under this head was prepared at the
                    time when the ninth edition of the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia
                    Britannica</hi> was being planned, and bore in his MS. the title “Remarks on the
                    Classification of the Physical Sciences.”</p></note> According to the original
                    meaning of the word, physical science would be that knowledge which is
                    conversant with the order of nature— that is, with the regular succession of
                    events whether mechanical or vital—in so far as it has been reduced to a
                    scientific form. The Greek word “physical” would thus be the exact equivalent of
                    the Latin word “natural.” In the actual development, however, of modern science
                    and its terminology these two words have come to be restricted each to one of
                    the two great branches into which the knowledge of nature is divided according
                    to its subject-matter. Natural science is now understood to refer to the study
                    of organized bodies and their development, while physical science investigates
                    those phenomena primarily which are observed in things without life, though it
                    does not give up its claim to pursue this investigation when the same phenomena
                    take place in the body of a living being. In forming a classification of
                    sciences the aim must be to determine the best arrangement of them in the state
                    in which they now exist. We therefore make no attempt to map out a scheme for
                    the science of future ages. We can no more lay down beforehand the plan
                    according to which science will be developed by our successors than we can
                    anticipate the particular discoveries which they will make. Still less can we
                    found our classification on the order in time according to which different
                    sciences have been developed. This would be no more scientific than the
                    classification of the properties of matter according to the senses by which we
                    have become acquainted with their existence.</p>
                <p>It is manifest that there are some sciences, of which we may take arithmetic as
                    the type, in which the subjectmatter is abstract, capable of exact definition,
                    and incapable of any variation arising from causes unknown to us which would in
                    the slightest degree alter its properties. Thus in arithmetic the properties of
                    numbers depend entirely on the definitions of these numbers, and these
                    definitions may be perfectly understood by any person who will attend to them.
                    The same is true of theoretical geometry, though, as this science is associated
                    in our minds with practical geometry, it is difficult to avoid thinking of the
                    probability of error arising from unknown causes affecting the actual
                    measurement of the quantities. There are other sciences, again, of which we may
                    take biology as the type, in which the subject-matter is concrete, not capable
                    of exact definition, and subject to the influence of many causes quite unknown
                    to us. Thus in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n11/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0011-0002"/> biology many abstract words such as “species,”
                    “generation,” &lt;fcc., may be employed, but the only thing which we can define
                    is the concrete individual, and the ideas which the most accomplished biologist
                    attaches to such words as “species” or “generation” have a very different degree
                    of exactness from those which mathematicians associate, say, with the class or
                    order of a surface, or with the umbilical generation of conicoids. Sciences of
                    this kind are rich in facts, and will be well occupied for ages to come in the
                    co-ordination of these facts, though their cultivators may be cheered in the
                    meantime by the hope of the discovery of laws like those of the more abstract
                    sciences, and may indulge their fancy in the contemplation of a state of
                    scientific knowledge when maxims cast in the same mould as those which apply to
                    our present ideas of dead matter will regulate all our thoughts about living
                    things.</p>
                <p>What is commonly called “physical science” occupies a position intermediate
                    between the abstract sciences of arithmetic, algebra, and geometry and the
                    morphological and biological sciences. The principal physical sciences are as
                    follows.</p>
                <p>A. <hi rend="italic">The Fundamental Science of Dynamics, or the doctrine of the
                    motion of bodies as affected by force.—</hi> The divisions of dynamics are the
                    following. (1) Kinematics, or the investigation of the kinds of motion of which
                    a body or system of bodies is capable, without reference to the cause of these
                    motions. This science differs from ordinary geometry only in introducing the
                    idea of motion,—that is, change of position going on continuously in space and
                    time. Kinematics includes, of course, geometry, but in every existing system of
                    geometry the idea of motion is freely introduced to explain the tracing of
                    lines, the sweeping out of surfaces, and the generation of solids. (2) Statics,
                    or the investigation of the equilibrium of forces, —that is to say, the
                    conditions under which a system of forces may exist without producing motion of
                    the body to which they are applied. Statics includes the discussion of systems
                    of forces which are equivalent to each other. (3) Kinetics, or the relations
                    between the motions of material bodies and the forces which act on them. Here
                    the idea of matter as something capable of being set in motion by force, and
                    requiring a certain force to generate a given motion, is first introduced into
                    physical science. (4) Energetics, or the investigation of the force which acts
                    between two bodies or parts of a body, as dependent on the conditions under
                    which action takes place between one body or part of a body and another so as to
                    transfer energy from one to the other.</p>
                <p>The science of dynamics may be divided in a different manner with respect to the
                    nature of the body whose motion is studied. This forms a cross division. (1)
                    Dynamics of a particle; including its kinematics or the theory of the tracing of
                    curves, its statics or the doctrine of forces acting at a point, its kinetics or
                    the elementary equations of motion of a particle, and its energetics, including,
                    as examples, the theory of collision and that of central forces. (2) Dynamics of
                    a connected system, including the same subdivisions. This is the most important
                    section in the whole of physical science, as every dynamical theory of natural
                    phenomena must be founded on it. The subdivisions of this, again, are— <hi
                    rend="italic">a.</hi> dynamics of a rigid system, or a body of invariable form;
                    <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> dynamics of a fluid, including the discussion (a) of
                    its possible motion, <hi rend="italic">(β)</hi> of the conditions of its
                    equilibrium (hydrostatics), (γ) of the action of force in producing motion
                    (hydrodynamics, not so unsatisfactory since Helmholtz, Stokes, and Thomson’s
                    investigations), and (δ) of the forces called into play by change of volume; <hi
                    rend="italic">c.</hi> dynamics of an elastic body; <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>
                    dynamics of a viscous body.</p>
                <p>B. <hi rend="italic">The Secondary Physical Sciences.—</hi> Each of these
                    sciences consists of two divisions or stages. In the elementary stage it is
                    occupied in deducing from the observed phenomena certain general laws, and then
                    employing these laws in the calculation of all varieties of the phenomena. In
                    the dynamical stage the general laws already discovered are analysed and shown
                    to be equivalent to certain forms of the dynamical relations of a connected
                    system (A, 2), and the attempt is made to discover the nature of the dynamical
                    system of which the observed phenomena are the motions. This dynamical stage
                    includes, of course, several other stages rising one above the other; for we may
                    successfully account for a certain phenomenon, say the turning of a weathercock
                    towards the direction of the wind, by assuming the existence of a force having a
                    particular direction and tending to turn the tail of the cock in that direction.
                    In this way we may account not only for the setting of the weathercock but for
                    its oscillations about its final position. This, therefore, is entitled to rank
                    as a dynamical theory. But we may go on and discover a new fact, that the air
                    exerts a pressure and that there is a greater pressure on that side of the cock
                    on which the wind blows. This is a further development of the theory, as it
                    tends to account for the force already discovered. We may go on and explain the
                    dynamical connexion between this inequality of pressure and the motion of the
                    air regarded as a fluid. Finally, we may explain the pressure of the air on the
                    hypothesis that the air consists of molecules in motion, which strike against
                    each other and against the surface of any body exposed to the air.</p>
                <p>The dynamical theories of the different physical sciences are in very different
                    stages of development, and in almost all of them a sound knowledge of the
                    subject is best acquired by adopting, at least at first, the method which we
                    have called “elementary,”—that is to say, the study of the connexion of the
                    phenomena peculiar to the science without reference to any dynamical
                    explanations or hypotheses. Thus we have—</p>
                <p>(1) Theory of gravitation, with discussion of the weight and motion of bodies
                    near the earth, of the whole of physical astronomy, and of the figure of the
                    earth. There is a great deal of dynamics here, but we can hardly say that there
                    is even a beginning of a dynamical theory of the method by which bodies
                    gravitate towards each other.</p>
                <p>(2) Theory of the action of pressure and heat in changing the dimensions and
                    state of bodies. This is a very large subject and might be divided into two
                    parts, one treating of the action of pressure and the other of heat. But it is
                    much more instructive to study the action of both causes together, because they
                    produce effects of the same kind, and therefore mutually influence each other.
                    Hence the term “thermodynamics” might be extended to the whole subject were it
                    not that it is already restricted to a very important department relating to the
                    transformation of energy from the thermal to the mechanical form and the
                    reverse. The divisions of the subject are seven, (a) Physical states of a
                    substance,—gaseous, liquid, and solid; elasticity of volume in all three states;
                    elasticity of figure in the solid state; viscosity in all three states;
                    plasticity in the solid state; surface-tension, or capillarity; tenacity of
                    solids; cohesion of liquids; adhesion of gases to liquids and solids, (δ)
                    Effects of heat in raising temperature, altering size and form, changing
                    physical state, (c) Thermometry. (&lt;Z) Calorimetry, (e) Thermodynamics, or the
                    mutual convertibility of heat and work. (∕) Dissipation of energy by diffusion
                    of matter by mixture, diffusion of motion by internal friction of fluids,
                    diffusion of heat by conduction. <hi rend="italic">Iff)</hi> Theory of
                    propagation of sound, vibrations of strings, rods, and other bodies.</p>
                <p>(3) Theory of radiance. (a) Geometrical optics; theory of conjugate foci and of
                    instruments, (ά) Velocity <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n12/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0012-0003"/> of light in different media, (c) Prismatic
                    analysis of light,—spectroscopy, radiant heat, visible radiance, ultra-violet
                    rays, calorescence, &lt;fcc., fluorescence, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">(d)</hi>
                    Colours of thin plates, diffraction, &amp;c. (cΓ) Proof of the existence of
                    wave-lengths and wave-periods (preparation for dynamical theory), (e) Polarized
                    light, radiant heat, &amp;c. (e') The disturbance is transverse to the ray. (∕)
                    Quantity of energy in the total radiation from a hot body; Prévost’s theory of
                    exchanges, &amp;c. (y) Theory of three primary colours.</p>
                <p>(4) Electricity and magnetism, (a) Electrostatics, or distribution and effects of
                    electricity in equilibrium, (δ) Electrokinematics, or distribution of currents
                    in conductors, (c) Magnetism and magnetic induction (diamagnetism, &lt;fcc.).
                    <hi rend="italic">(d)</hi> Electromagnetism, or the effects of an electric
                    current at a distance. Under (δ) we may discuss electrochemistry, or the theory
                    of electrolysis; under (c) terrestrial magnetism and ship’s magnetism; and after
                    (cZ) comes electrokinetics, or electromagnetic phenomena considered with
                    reference to the fundamental science of dynamics. There is also Faraday’s
                    discovery of the effect of magnetism on light and the electromagnetic theory of
                    light.</p>
                <p>Chemistry is not included in this list, because, though dynamical science is
                    continually reclaiming large tracts of good ground from the one side of
                    chemistry, chemistry is extending with still greater rapidity on the other side
                    into regions where the dynamics of the present day must put her hand upon her
                    mouth. Chemistry, however, is a physical science, and a physical science which
                    occupies a very high rank. (j. c. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
