<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0919-0282-0273-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">POGGENDORFF, Johann Christian (9th edition, volume 19,
                    page 273)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:902475">Editors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095153">Research</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950757">Hamburgers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16x10">Plans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n282/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">POGGENDORFF, <hi rend="smallcaps">Johann
                        Christian</hi></label> (1796-1877), physicist, and editor for more than half
                    a century of the well-known scientific journal called after him <hi
                        rend="italic">Poggendorff's</hi><hi rend="italic">Annalen,</hi> was born in
                    Hamburg on the 29th December 1796. His father, a wealthy manufacturer of that
                    town, was all but ruined by the French siege. His son Christian, after receiving
                    his education at Hamburg and Schiffbeck, had therefore, when only sixteen, to
                    apprentice himself to an apothecary in Hamburg, and when twenty-two began to
                    earn his living as an apothecary’s assistant at Itzehoe. Ambition and a strong
                    inclination towards a scientific career led him to throw up his business and
                    remove to Berlin, where he entered the university in 1820. Here his abilities
                    were speedily recognized, and in 1823 he was appointed meteorological observer
                    to the Academy of Sciences with a small salary, which was important to him,
                    inasmuch as the expenses of his university career had nearly exhausted his
                    slender patrimony. Even at this early period he had conceived the idea of
                    founding a physical and chemical scientific journal. The realization of this
                    plan was hastened by the sudden death of Gilbert, the editor of <hi
                        rend="italic">Gilbert's</hi><hi rend="italic">Annalen der Physik,</hi> in
                    1824. Poggendorff immediately put himself in communication with the publisher,
                    Barth of Leipsic, with the result that he was installed as editor of a
                    scientific journal which was to be a continuation of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gilbert's</hi><hi rend="italic">Annalen</hi> on a somewhat extended plan,
                    indicated by its title <hi rend="italic">Annalen der Physik und Chemie.</hi>
                    Poggendorff was admirably qualified for the post which he thus attained. He had
                    an extraordinary memory, well-stored with scientific knowledge, both moderr and
                    historical, which served him in good stead in the critical part of his editorial
                    duty. He had a cool and impartial judgment, with a strong preference for facts
                    as against theory of the speculative kind at least, and was able to throw
                    himself into the spirit of modern experimental science, represented in the early
                    part of his editorial career by such great names as Berzelius, Faraday,
                    Brewster, Fresnel, Régnault. He also possessed in more than German measure the
                    German virtue of orderliness in the arrangement of knowledge and in the conduct
                    of business. To this he added an engaging geniality of manner and much tact in
                    dealing with men; so marked in fact was this part of his character that,
                    notwithstanding his somewhat trying position, he never during his long life was
                    involved in anything that could be fairly called a literary quarrel. These
                    qualities of its editor soon made <hi rend="italic">Poggendorff's</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Annalen</hi> the foremost scientific journal in Europe. He
                    collected around him all the eminent seien-tific<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n283/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0283-0274"/> men of his own country, and he managed,
                    either through original contributions or by translations of memoirs of approved
                    value already printed, to secure for many years an adequate representation of
                    the scientific work of other lands. So true is this that, for years after the
                    beginning of Poggendorff’s editorship, the tables of contents of his annual
                    volumes read like an index of the history of physical science.</p>
                <p>In the course of his fifty-two years’ editorship of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Annalen</hi> Poggendorfi could not fail to acquire an unusual acquaintance
                    with the labours of modern men of science. This knowledge, joined to what he had
                    gathered by historical reading of equally unusual extent, he carefully digested
                    and gave to the world in his <hi rend="italic">Biographisch-literarisches
                        Handbuch zur Geschichte der Exacten Wissenschaften,</hi> containing notices
                    of the lives and labours of mathematicians, astronomers, physicists, chemists,
                    mineralogists, geologists, &lt;fcc., of all peoples and all ages. The two
                    volumes of this work contain an astounding collection of facts invaluable to the
                    scientific biographer and historian; they form in fact the basis of the yet
                    unwritten history of physical science. We possess a small fragment of such a
                    history in the form of lectures delivered by Poggendorfi himself at Berlin; and
                    probably he had contemplated at one time writing a continuous narrative; but
                    even his long life was too short for the double task of collecting and using the
                    material.</p>
                <p>Poggendorfi was a physicist of high although not of the very highest rank. He wàs
                    wanting in mathematical ability, and never displayed in any remarkable degree
                    the still more important power of scientific generalization, which, whether
                    accompanied by mathematical skill or not, never fails to mark the highest genius
                    in physical science. He was, however, an able and conscientious experimenter. He
                    was very fertile and ingenious in devising physical apparatus, and contributed
                    greatly in the earlier part of his life to enrich the resources of experimental
                    science. Contemporaneously with Schweigger, he succeeded in greatly increasing
                    the sensitiveness of the galvanometer by introducing the multiplying coil, and
                    he made important improvements on that particular type of this instrument which
                    is usually called the sine galvanometer. To him (according to Wiedemann) we owe
                    the use of binding screws in most of their various forms. He invented the
                    “Inversor” for rapidly alternating the direction of a voltaic current, and the
                    “Wippe” for throwing a number of voltaic or electrolytic cells suddenly into
                    “series” or into “multiple arc”; and to him is due the suggestion of the
                    telescope and mirror method for reading galvanometers and other physical
                    instruments, a device which has proved very valuable in all branches of physical
                    science.</p>
                <p>Poggendorff’s contributions to physics were published for the most part in his
                    own journal. They form an important part of the scientific work of the 19th
                    century; but it would be difficult in a few words to characterize them inasmuch
                    as they do not constitute a single coherent group or even a few coherent groups
                    of connected researches. By far the greater and more important part of his work
                    related to electricity and magnetism. As specimens we may mention his
                    investigations into the working of Holtz’s machines, and his variations on their
                    construction; his researches on the resistance and electromotive force of
                    electrolytic cells, along with which ought to be noticed his admirable method of
                    comparing electromotive forces by “compensation”; and finally his researches on
                    magnetism and diamagnetism.</p>
                <p>Poggendorff’s literary and scientific reputation speedily brought him honourable
                    recognition. In 1830 he was made royal professor and in 1834 Hon. Ph.D. and
                    extraordinary professor in the university of Berlin, and in 1839 member of the
                    Berlin Academy of Sciences. He ultimately became a member of many foreign
                    societies, and received more than the usual share of the orders bestowed by
                    Continental nations for scientific merit. During his lifetime many offers of
                    ordinary professorships were made to him, but he declined them all, devoting
                    himself to his duties as editor of the <hi rend="italic">Annalen,</hi> and to
                    the pursuit of his scientific researches. He died at Berlin on January 24,
                    1877.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
