<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0919-0177-0168-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PLAIN SONG, or Plain Chant (9th edition, volume 19,
                    page 168)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852158">Chants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126120">Songs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nb7p">Chanting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z99h">Age</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n177/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PLAIN SONG, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Plain
                        Chant</hi></label><hi rend="italic">(Gregorian Music;</hi> Lat. <hi
                        rend="italic">Cantus planus</hi>; Ital. <hi rend="italic">Canto
                        Gregoriano;</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">Plain Chant),</hi> a style of music,
                    easily recognizable by certain strongly-marked characteristics, some very
                    ancient fragments of which are believed to have been in use under the Jewish
                    dispensation from a remote period, and to have been thence transferred to the
                    ritual of the Christian church.</p>
                <p>The theories advanced as to the origin of this solemn form of ecclesiastical
                    music are innumerable. The most widely-spread opinion is that the older portion
                    of it originated with the Psalms themselves, or at least sprang from the later
                    synagogue music. Another theory traces the origin of plain song to the early
                    Greeks; and the supporters of this view lay much stress on the fact that the
                    scales in which its melodies are composed are named after the old Greek “modes.”
                    But, beyond the name, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n178/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0178-0169"/> no connexion whatever exists between the two
                    tonalities, which bear not the remotest resemblance to each other. Less
                    reasonable hypotheses attribute the origin of plain song to the Phoenicians, to
                    the Egyptians, to the early Christian converts, and to the musicians of the
                    Middle Ages. These divergent views, however, though entirely hypothetical, are
                    defended by arguments so voluminous that for the elucidation of the subject we
                    must content ourselves with referring the reader to the works of Gerbert, P.
                    Martini, P. Kircher, Mersennus, P. Lambil-lotte, the Abbé Raillard, Coussemaker,
                    Kiesewetter, Jakob, Ambros, and other authors, who have treated it at great
                    length.</p>
                <p>The earliest important fact upon which we can rest with absolute confidence is
                    that towards the close of the 4th century Ambrose of Milan, fearing the loss or
                    corruption of the venerable melodies which up to that time had been preserved to
                    the church by means of oral tradition only, endeavoured to restore them as
                    nearly as possible to their primitive purity, and at the same time to teach the
                    clergy to sing them with greater precision than had previously been attempted. A
                    still more extensive work of the same nature was undertaken, two centuries
                    later, by Pope Gregory the Great. And thus arose two schools of ecclesiastical
                    music, still known as the “Ambrosian” and the “Gregorian chant,”—the first of
                    which is now practised only in the diocese of Milan, while the latter is
                    universally accepted as the authorized “Roman use.” In order to explain the
                    essential differences existing between these two schools, we must here describe
                    in detail some of the peculiar characteristics of plain song to which allusion
                    has been made.</p>
                <p>The melodies which collectively form the <hi rend="italic">repertoire</hi> of
                    plain chant are not written in modern major and minor scales, but in certain
                    tonalities bearing names analogous to those of the early Greek “modes,” though
                    constructed on very different principles. Of these “modes,” fourteen exist in
                    theory, though twelve only are in practical use. The intervals of each “mode”
                    are derived from a fundamental sound, called its “final.”<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Analogous to the tonic or key-note of the
                            modern scale.</p></note> The compass of each mode comprises eight
                    sounds,—that of the first, third, fifth, seventh, ninth, eleventh, and
                    thirteenth “modes,” extending to the octave above the “final,” and that of the
                    second, fourth, sixth, eighth, tenth, twelfth, and fourteenth, extending from
                    the fourth note below the final to the fifth note above it. Consequently, the
                    “finals” of the first series, called the “authentic modes,” occupy the lowest
                    place in each system of sounds, and those of the second series, called the
                    “plagal modes,” the middle place,—the same “final” being common to one
                    “authentic” and one “plagal mode.” The following table exhibits the entire
                    system, expressed in the alphabetical notation peculiar to modern English
                    music,—the “final” being indicated in each case by an asterisk, and the position
                    of the semitones, from which each mode derives its distinctive character, by
                    brackets.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">Authentic Modes.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">Plagal Modes.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1. Dorian,*D, fζF&gt; G, A, iÇc, D.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2. Hypodorhιn, A, B, C, *D, E, F, G, A.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>3. Phrygian, *E, F, G, A, ïÇc, D, E.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4. Hypophrygian, B, C, D, *E, F,G, A, B.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>5. Lydian, *F, G, A, B, C, D, E?F.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6. Hypolydian, C, D, jζ*F, G, A, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >b7c.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>7. Mlxolydian <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> *G, A, iÇc, D, EJ∙',
                                G.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8. Hypomixolydian, D, ⅞F,*G, A.B^C, D.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>9. Aeolian, *A, B^C, D, E, F, G, A.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10. Hypoaeolian, F√F, G, *A, lζ^C, D, E.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>11. <hi rend="italic">Locrian, *J⅛C,</hi><hi rend="italic">D, E,
                                    F,</hi><hi rend="italic">0, A, B.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12. <hi rend="italic">Hypolocrian,</hi><hi rend="italic">F,</hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">G, A, *ffc, D, E,~F</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>13. Ionian, *C, D, E, F, G, A, B, C.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>14. Hypoionian, G, A, B,*C, D, E, F, G.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Nos. 11 and 12 in this series are rejected, for technical reasons into which we
                    have not space to enter; they are practically useless<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For fuller information on the subject see
                            the article “Modes, the Ecclesiastical,” in Sir G. Grove’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Dictionary of Music.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>Of these modes Ambrose used four only—the first four</p>
                <p>“authentic modes,” now numbered 1, 3, 5, and 7 Gregory acknowledged, and is said
                    by some historians of credit to have invented, the first four “plagal
                    modes,”—Nos 2, 4, 6, and 8. The use of the remaining “modes,” except perhaps the
                    ninth, was not formally authorized until the reign of Charlemagne, who published
                    an official decision upon the subject. In one or other of the twelve “modes”
                    recognized by this decision, every plain-chant melody is composed. The number of
                    such melodies preserved to us the genuineness of which is undoubted is immensely
                    large; and the collection is divided into several distinct classes, the most
                    important of which are the melodies proper to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Psalm-Tones</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Antiphons</hi>; the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ordinarium</hi><hi rend="italic">Missae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Introite,</hi><hi rend="italic">Graduais,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Offertoria</hi>; the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Praefationes,</hi><hi rend="italic">Versiculi,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Responsoria·,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Hymns</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sequences;</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Lamentationes,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Exult</hi><hi rend="italic">et,</hi> and other music used in
                    Holy Week.</p>
                <p>Of these classes the most interesting by far is that which includes the
                    psalm-tones, or psalm-tunes, called by modern English historians, the “Gregorian
                    tones.” The oldest of these are tones 1, 3, 5, and 7, as sung by Ambrose. The
                    antiquity of tones 2, 4, 6, and 8 is less firmly established, though there is no
                    doubt that Gregory the Great sanctioned their use on strong traditional
                    evidence. In addition to these, a peculiarly beautiful melody in mode 9, known
                    as the <hi rend="italic">Tonus</hi><hi rend="italic">peregrinus,</hi> has been
                    sung from time immemorial only to the psalm <hi rend="italic">In</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">exitu</hi><hi rend="italic">Israel.</hi> The oldest version of
                    this melody now extant is undoubtedly to a certain extent impure; but tradition
                    imputes to it a very high antiquity, and even our doubts as to the authenticity
                    of the now generally accepted reading extend only to one single note. A
                    widely-accepted tradition points out this melody as the tune sung to <hi
                        rend="italic">In</hi><hi rend="italic">exitu</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Israel,</hi> as part of the Great Hallel (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Psalms),</hi> which is generally (but hardly rightly) identified with the
                    hymn sung by our Lord and His apostles immediately after the institution of the
                    Last Supper.</p>
                <p>One very powerful argument in favour of the Jewish origin of the psalm-tones lies
                    in the peculiarity of their construction. We are not aware that this argument
                    has ever been previously brought forward; but it is impossible to subject the
                    venerable melodies to minute examination without observing their perfect
                    adaptation to the laws of Hebrew poetry, as opposed to those which governed
                    Greek and Latin verse. The division of the tune in every case, without
                    exception, into two distinct strains, exactly balancing each other, points
                    assuredly to the intention of singing it to the two contrasted phrases which,
                    inseparable from the constitution of a Hebrew verse, find no place in any later
                    form of poetry. And it is very remarkable that this constructional peculiarity
                    was never imitated, either in the earliest hymns or antiphons we possess or in
                    those of the Middle Ages,—evidently because it was found impossible to adapt it
                    to any mediaeval form of verse—even to the <hi rend="italic">Te</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Deum,</hi> which, though a manifest reproduction of the Hebrew
                    psalm, was adapted by Ambrose to a melody of very different formation, and
                    naturally so since so many of its phrases consist of a single clause only,
                    balanced in the following verse. This peculiarity now passes for the most part
                    unnoticed; and the <hi rend="italic">Te Deum</hi> is constantly sung to a
                    psalm-tone, very much to the detriment of both. But in the Middle Ages this
                    abuse was unknown; and so it came to pass that, until the “School of the
                    Restoration” gave birth, in England, to the single chant, avowedly built upon
                    the lines of its Gregorian predecessor, and a somewhat later period to the
                    double one, so constructed as to weld two verses of the psalm into one, often
                    with utter disregard to the sense of the words, the venerable psalm-tones stood
                    quite alone— the only melodies in existence to which the psalms could <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n179/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0179-0170"/> be chanted. And so intimate is the adaptation
                    of these plain-chant melodies to the rhythm as well as to the sense of the
                    sacred text, even after its translation into more modern languages, so strongly
                    do they swing with the one and emphasize the other, that it is difficult to
                    believe that the composition of the music was not coeval with that of the
                    poetry.</p>
                <p>Next in antiquity to the psalm-tones are the melodies adapted to the antiphons,
                    the offertoria, the graduais, and the introits, sung at high mass. Those proper
                    to the <hi rend="italic">Ordinarium</hi><hi rend="italic">Missse</hi> are
                    probably of later date. Those belonging to hymns and sequences are of all ages.
                    Among the latest we possess—perhaps the very latest of any great importance—is
                    that of <hi rend="italic">Lauda Sion,—</hi> a very fine one, in modes 7 and 8,
                    adapted to the celebrated sequence written by Thomas Aquinas about 1261.</p>
                <p>To the melodies adapted to the <hi rend="italic">Lamentationes</hi> and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Exultet,</hi> as sung in the Church of Rome during Holy Week,
                    it is absolutely impossible to assign any date at all. All we know is that they
                    are of extreme antiquity, and beautiful beyond all description. The melody of
                        <hi rend="italic">Exultet</hi> is, indeed, very frequently cited as the
                    finest example of plain song in existence.</p>
                <p>To assert that melodies so old as these have been handed down to us in their
                    original purity would be absurd. But the presence of corruption rarely passes
                    undetected by the initiated; and vigorous efforts have been made from time to
                    time to purify the received text by reference to the oldest and most trustworthy
                    MSS. attainable. Such an effort was made on a very extensive scale by the
                    “Congregation of Rites,” at the instigation of Pope Pius IX., in the year 1868;
                    and the labours of that learned body, still in active progress, are doing all
                    that can now be done towards the restoration of plain chant to the highest state
                    of purity possible in the present stage of its existence. (w. s. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">r.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
