<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0919-0460-0441-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">POMEGRANATE (9th edition, volume 19, page 441)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:847816">Carpel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927866">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1158581">Tubes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:935548">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:819237">Assyrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1062222">Phrygians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kw6x">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68d53">Tubes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pv6b75c">Rowing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205406">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n460/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">POMEGRANATE</label>. The pomegranate <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Punica Granatum)</hi> is of exceptional interest by reason of its
                    structure, its history, and its utility. It forms a tree of small stature, or a
                    bush with opposite, shining, lance-shaped leaves, from the axils of some of
                    which proceed the brilliant scarlet flowers. These are raised on a short stalk,
                    and consist of a thick fleshy cylindrical or bell-shaped calyx tube, with five
                    to seven short lobes at the top. From the throat of the calyx proceed five to
                    seven roundish, crumpled, scarlet or crimson petals, and below them very
                    numerous slender stamens. The pistil consists of two rows of carpels placed one
                    above another, both rows embedded in, and partially inseparate from, the inner
                    surface of the calyx tube. The styles are confluent into one filiform thread.
                    The fruit, which usually attains the size of a large orange, consists of a hard
                    leathery rind, which is the enlarged calyx tube, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n461/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0461-0442"/> enclosing a quantity of pulp derived from the
                    coats of the numerous seeds. This pulp, filled as it is with refreshing acid
                    juice, constitutes the chief value of the tree. The more highly cultivated forms
                    contain more of it than the wild or half-wild varieties. The great structural
                    peculiarity consists in the presence of the two rows of carpels one above
                    another (a state of things which occurs exceptionally in apples and oranges),
                    and in the fact that, while in the lower series (fig. 1 ) the seeds are attached
                    to the inner border or lower angle of the cavity, they occupy the outer side in
                    the upper series (fig. 2), as if, during growth, the upper whorl had become
                    completely bent over.</p>
                <p>By Bentham and Hooker the genus <hi rend="italic">Punica</hi> is included under
                        <hi rend="italic">Lythraceae</hi>; others consider it more nearly allied to
                    the myrtles; while its peculiarities are so great as, in the opinion of many
                    botanists, to justify its inclusion in a separate order. Not only is the fruit
                    valuable in hot countries for the sake of its pulp, but the rind and the bark
                    and the outer part of the root are valuable as astringentsowing to the large
                    quantity of tannin that they contain. The bark of the root is likewise valued in
                    cases of tape-worm.</p>
                <p>The tree is without doubt wild in Afghanistan, north-western India, and the
                    districts south and south-west of the Caspian, but it has been so long
                    cultivated that it is difficult to say whether it is really native in Palestine
                    and the Mediterranean region. It has been cited as wild in northern Africa, but
                    this appears to be a mistake. Recently, however, Prof. Bayley Balfour met with a
                    wild species, heretofore unknown, in the island of Socotra, the flowers of which
                    have only a single row of carpels, which suggests the inference that it may have
                    been the source of the cultivated varieties. But, on the other hand, in
                    Afghanistan, where Aitchison met with the tree truly wild, a double row of
                    carpels was present as usual. The antiquity of the tree as a cultivated plant is
                    evidenced by the Sanskrit name <hi rend="italic">Dâdimba,</hi> and by the
                    references to the fruit in the Old Testament, and in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Odyssey,</hi> where it is spoken of as cultivated in the gardens of the
                    kings of Phaeaeia and Phrygia. The fruit is frequently represented on ancient
                    Assyrian and Egyptian sculptures, and had a religious significance in connexion
                    with several Oriental cults, especially the Phrygian cult of Cybele (Arnob., v.
                    5 <hi rend="italic">sq.∙,</hi> see also Baudissin, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Studien,</hi> ii. 207 <hi rend="italic">sq.).</hi> It was well known to the
                    Greeks and Romans, who were acquainted with its medicinal properties an'd its
                    use as a tanning material. The name given by the Romans, <hi rend="italic">malum
                        punicum,</hi> indicates that they received it from Carthage, as indeed is
                    expressly stated by Pliny; and this circumstance has given rise to the notion
                    that the tree was indigenous in northern Africa. On a review of the whole
                    evidence, botanical, literary, and linguistic, Alphonse de Candolle <hi
                        rend="italic">(Origine</hi><hi rend="italic">des Plantes</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Cultivées)</hi> pronounces against its African origin, and
                    decides in favour of its source in Persia and the neighbouring countries.
                    According to Saporta the pomegranate existed in a fossil state in beds of the
                    Pliocene epoch near Meximieux in Burgundy. The pomegranate is sometimes met with
                    in cultivation against a wall in England, but it is too tender to withstand a
                    severe winter. The double-flowered varieties are specially desirable for the
                    beauty and long duration of their flowers.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
