<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0850-0827-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PROTEUS ANGUINUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 19, page 827</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:878299">Cope</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1157225">Tritone</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1164079">Vans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1163796">Valentines</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1003744">Lungs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:813061">Arches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:835916">Bone</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1120222">Skull</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tm5k">Valentines</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96091f">Arches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n17f">Skull</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41z41s56">Batrachia</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b56d52v">Bones</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4fx73z68">Bone</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n850/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PROTEUS ANGUINUS</label>, a blind, newt-like
                    perennibranchiate Amphibian, about a foot long, found in the Adelsberg,
                    Maddalena, and other limestone caverns of Carinthia and Carniola. The creature
                    is white or flesh-coloured, and the transparent gills appear blood red; the skin
                    passes uninterruptedly over the rudimentary eyes. The animal’s body is
                    cylindrical; the snout is long and blunt; the fore-feet have three toes, and the
                    hind (which are set very far back) two. There are three gill-arches and two
                    gill-slits on each side. The absence of the fourth branchial arch is a feature
                    that <hi rend="italic">Proleus</hi> has in common with <hi rend="italic"
                    >Menobranchus</hi> and also with <hi rend="italic">Spelerpes.</hi> The skull is
                    of an elongated form, and presents several remarkable characters. The trabeculae
                    cranii are persistent, as in the snake. The membrane bones are singularly few,
                    the maxillae being rudimentary and the nasals and supraoccipital absent. In the
                    lower jaw the splenial is said to be absent, but a mento-Meckelian cartilage
                    element is present, as in <hi rend="italic">Batrachia.</hi> The palatines have a
                    row of teeth, and are ankylosed with the pterygoids; the premaxillae, dentaries,
                    and vomers carry teeth. The absence of a cartilage roof to the nasal cavity is
                    one of the many characters in which <hi rend="italic">Proteus</hi> agrees with
                    <hi rend="italic">Menobranchus,</hi> but differs from <hi rend="italic"
                    >Siren</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Menopoma.</hi> The suspensorium has only a
                    simple pedicle, as in <hi rend="italic">Batrachia,</hi> and the hyoid arch is
                    remarkable for the enormous hyo-mandibular element, which is larger even than in
                    many sharks. The notochord is scarcely constricted by the amphicoelous
                    vertebrae, and the intervertebral cartilages are at a minimum of development.
                    There are twenty-nine trunk vertebrae, one sacral, and twenty-eight caudal. The
                    pectoral arch contains a long thin ossified scapula, a suprascapula, and a long
                    precoracoid separated by a deep notch from the main coracoid; a fissure exists
                    in the glenoid region. There is no sternum. The pectoral girdle is almost
                    identical with that of <hi rend="italic">Menobranchus.</hi> The pelvis has a
                    narrow tapering ischial region, well-marked prepubes, and (?) a pointed
                    epipubis; this girdle also is extremely like that of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Menobranchus,</hi> but notably different from that of the Axolotl, which is
                    only a pseudo-perennibranchiate, and whose real affinities are with <hi
                    rend="italic">Salamander</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Triton.</hi> The bones of
                    the fore-arm and leg are unankylosed. There are three unossified carpal and
                    tarsal elements, which Gegenbaur identifies as a radiale, ulnare, and a fused
                    distal row; such a carpus has no resemblance to either the embryonic or adult
                    stage of any other amphibian. In the heart the auricular septum is incomplete;
                    the truncus arteriosus bifurcates into two trunks: each divides into two, and
                    the posterior of these again into two, thus forming the three aortic arches on
                    each side. The pulmonary vein sends part only of its blood into the heart, and
                    part into the systemic veins. The blood-corpuscles are the largest known among
                    vertebrates, and are comparable to the exceedingly large corpuscles of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Dipnoi.</hi> The brain is very small, straight, and embryonic in
                    character. The gut is straight, and the stomach is a scarcely perceptible
                    dilatation. The thyroid (alone among amphibians) is unpaired. The lungs are long
                    simple sacs, expanded distally, as in <hi rend="italic">Menobranchus</hi>; the
                    trachea is excessively short, and the two cartilages which bound the glottis are
                    continued into long processes which pass to the base of the lungs. As in <hi
                    rend="italic">Siren, Siredon,</hi> and others, the lateral branch of the vagus
                    nerve is connected with a series of sense-organs forming a “lateral line.” These
                    characters together indicate the exceedingly low position of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Proteus</hi> among <hi rend="italic">Amphibia</hi>; it and its close relative
                    the American <hi rend="italic">Menobranchus</hi> are the lowest of living <hi
                    rend="italic">Amphibia.</hi> The creature seems to be abundant within its
                    limited habitat; it feeds on worms and small fishes, which in spite of its
                    blindness it catches dexterously. It has bred in captivity, and lays round,
                    isolated eggs, about a third of an inch in diameter. It changes colour slightly
                    in the breeding season, and two rows of reddish spots make their appearance on
                    the hinder part of the body. Such a change seems to indicate that the creature
                    has not always lived in the absolute darkness in which it now spends its life.
                    Individuals differ in some minor characters, and Cope <hi rend="italic">(Journ.
                    Acad. Philadelphia,</hi> v. p. 103, 1866) has based four new species on Hyrtl’s
                    specimens <hi rend="italic">(P. zoisii,</hi><hi rend="italic">carrarae,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">xanthostichus,</hi><hi rend="italic">sehr eiter</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">sit).</hi> Merrem altered the name of the genus to <hi
                    rend="italic">Hypochthon (Gesch.</hi><hi rend="italic">der Amphibien,</hi>
                    1790-1820).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—Proteus</hi> was first described by Laurenti in
                    lιis <hi rend="italic">Synopsis</hi><hi rend="italic">Reptilium</hi> (Vienna,
                    1768, p. 37); his locality, Lake Zirknitz, was erroneous. It was next mentioned
                    by Scopoli <hi rend="italic">(Annus V. Hist. Nat.,</hi> 1772). A full
                    description, with plates, is given by Configliachi and Rusconi <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Delproteo</hi><hi rend="italic">anguino</hi><hi rend="italic">di</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Laurenti,</hi> 4 to, Pavia, 1819). The brain has been described by
                    Treviranus <hi rend="italic">(P. anguini</hi><hi rend="italic">encephalon,</hi>
                    4to, Göttingen, 1820), the spinal cord by Klaussner <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Rückenmark</hi><hi rend="italic">des P.,</hi> 4to, Munich, 1883), the skull by
                    Parker <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Trans.,</hi> clxvii. pp. 568-573, 1877), the
                    pectoral arch by Parker <hi rend="italic">(Shoulder-girdle,</hi> p. 58, pl. iv.
                    ), the pelvis by Hofiinann <hi rend="italic">(Nedcrl. Arch.,</hi> iii. p. 144,
                    1877), the vertebral column by Mivart <hi rend="italic">(P.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Z. S.,</hi> 1870), the lateral line, &amp;c., by Bugnion <hi
                    rend="italic">(Bull. Soc. Vaud.,</hi> xii. pp. 259-316, 1873), the eye by
                    Desfosses <hi rend="italic">(Comptes rendus,</hi> xciv. p. 1729, 1882), the
                    kidney by Solger <hi rend="italic">(Abh. Ges. Halle,</hi> xv. p. 405, 1882), the
                    reproduction by Schultze <hi rend="italic">(Zeits. f. wiss. Zool.,</hi> xxvi. ρ.
                    350, 1876) and Μ. V. Chauvin <hi rend="italic">(Zeits. f. wiss. Zool.,</hi>
                    xxxviii. 671- 685,1883), and the affinities with <hi rend="italic"
                    >Menobranchus</hi> by Van d. Hoeven <hi rend="italic">(Arch. Neerl.,</hi> i. p.
                    305, 1866; <hi rend="italic">Ann. and Mag. N. H.,</hi> xviii. p. 363, 1866). See
                    also anatomical details by Valentin <hi rend="italic">(Repert. f. Anat.,</hi> i.
                    p. 282, 1837, vi. p. 353, 1841), and many smaller papers.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
