<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0789-0766-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PRIZE, or Prize of War</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 19, page 766</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45717p75">Prizes</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sc8g">Money</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="27" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1077716">Prizes</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="fasttopic:1025265">Money</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="27" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n789/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PRIZE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Prize of War</hi></label>,
                    denotes the ship or goods of an enemy, or <hi rend="italic">in transitu</hi> to
                    an enemy, captured at sea. Goods captured on land are not prize, but booty of
                    war. To be good prize the capture must be on the high seas or in the territorial
                    waters of one of the belligerents, and must be by an armed vessel duly
                    commissioned by the sovereign of the captor. A capture made in neutral waters is
                    a violation of neutrality, and may be restored at the discretion of the neutral
                    power. Most nations have municipal regulations upon the subject. Thus prize
                    captured in breach of the neutrality of Great Britain may be restored by the
                    High Court of Justice (Admiralty Division) under the powers of the Foreign
                    Enlistment Act, 1870, 33 &amp; 34 Vict. c. 90, § 14. Capture may be actual or
                    constructive. Constructive or joint captors are those who have assisted the
                    actual captors by conveying encouragement to them or intimidation to the enemy.
                    All public ships of war within signalling distance are usually held entitled to
                    share in the proceeds of the capture. This rule is incorporated in the United
                    States code of prize law, the Act of Congress of June 30, 1864. It is not all
                    nemy’s property that is good prize. The conflicting interests of neutrals have
                    led to modifications of the general belligerent right of seizing enemy’s
                    property wherever found, a right which had become established as part of the
                    general maritime law as early as the <hi rend="italic">Consolato</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">del Mare</hi> (see vol. vi. p. 317, and <hi rend="smallcaps">Sea
                    Laws).</hi> By the rules laid down in the <hi rend="italic">Consolato</hi>
                    neutral vessels or neutral goods were to be restored to the owners without
                    compensation for the loss of time and other inconveniences attending capture.
                    This may be said to have been the general law of the sea down to 1856. At the
                    same time it is to be noticed that two doctrines inconsistent with the original
                    rule had met with the sanction of certain nations, <hi rend="italic">viz.,</hi>
                    (1) the French doctrine of hostile infection, by which neutral property on an
                    enemy’s ship or a neutral ship carrying enemy’s property was good prize; (2) the
                    Dutch doctrine, by which the character of the ship alone was regarded—free ship
                    made free goods, enemy ship enemy goods (see Twiss, <hi rend="italic">Law of
                    Nations,</hi> vol. ii. ch. v.). In 1856 the Declaration of Paris adopted an
                    intermediate system. To this Declaration most nations have acceded (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Privateer).</hi> By article 2 of the Declaration, “the neutral
                    flag covers enemy’s goods, with the exception of contraband of war.” By article
                    3, “neutral goods, with the exception of contraband of war, are not liable to
                    capture under an enemy’s flag.” Contraband of war, speaking generally, includes
                    all articles, such as provisions and munitions of war, likely to add to the
                    military or naval resources of the enemy (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Contraband).</hi> After the capture has been made, the next proceeding is the
                    determination of its legality. It is now an understood rule of international law
                    that the question of prize or no prize must be determined by a qualified prize
                    court (see below). Captors should send their capture to a convenient port, if
                    possible a port of their own nation or an allied-power, for adjudication. They
                    may forfeit their rights by misconduct in this respect. The property in the
                    prize vests in the sovereign, in accordance with the old maxim of law <hi
                    rend="italic">Parta bello cedunt</hi><hi rend="italic">reipublicae.</hi> This
                    right attaches both in cases of capture and recapture, subject in the latter
                    case to what is called the√ωs <hi rend="italic">postliminii,</hi> that is, the
                    right of the owner of property recaptured from the enemy to have it
                    returned—formerly if the recapture has taken place before the property had been
                    taken within the enemy’s territory <hi rend="italic">(infra</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">praesidia),</hi> at present if less than twenty-four hours has
                    elapsed between the capture and recapture. The right of the recaptors to salvage
                    on recapture is regulated by the municipal law of different nations. By English
                    law one-eighth of the value is the sum usually awarded, but this may be
                    increased to one-fourth under special circumstances. The right does not exist at
                    all if the vessel has been fitted out as a vessel of war by the enemy, 27 &amp;
                    28 Vict. c. 25, § 40. One-eighth is awarded for recapture from pirates, 13 &amp;
                    14 Vict. c. 26, § 5. In the United States, by the Prize Act of June 30, 1864,
                    salvage on recapture is allowed according to the circumstances of the case.
                    There is no sum fixed as in England. Although the prize vests in the sovereign,
                    it has been held in England that the captors have an insurable interest in the
                    prize immediately after capture and before condemnation on the ground that under
                    the Prize Act the captors have a certain expectation of profit upon the safe
                    arrival of the prize in port, and that they are liable to condemnation in
                    damages and costs if the capture be unjustifiable. By the general maritime law a
                    prize may be released upon ransom; but it has been the general policy of
                    European nations to discountenance ransom as less beneficial to the state than
                    the detention of a prize. Thus an Act of 1782, and subsequent Acts, avoided
                    ransom bills given by British s abjects, and subjected a commander giving one to
                    an enemy to penalties, unless in either case the circumstances were such as to
                    justify the giving or taking of the bill. The Naval Prize Act, 1864, is less
                    strict in its terms. It enacts that the queen in council may from time to time
                    in relation to any war make such orders as are expedient as to contracts for the
                    ransoming of a ship or goods; contravention of the orders makes the contract
                    void and renders the offender liable to a penalty not exceeding £500, 27 &amp;
                    28 Vict. c. 25, § 45. By the Naval Discipline Act, 1866, a commanding officer
                    making an unlawful agreement for ransom is liable to be dismissed from the
                    service, 29 &amp; 30 Vict. c. 109, § 41. The <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n790/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0790-0767"/></p>
                <p>United States have never prohibited ransom bills. The rights of the sovereign to
                    prize may be waived, as was formerly done by the crown of Great Britain in the
                    case of privateers (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Privateer).</hi></p>
                <p>Many statutes dealing with prize have been enacted at different times in England.
                    The first general Prize Act was 6 Anne c. 13. The Act that now regulates prize
                    is the Naval Prize Act, 1864, already referred to. Various offences in relation
                    to prize are dealt with by the Naval Prize Act and the Naval Discipline Act.
                    Such are false swearing in a prize cause or appeal, taking money, &amp;c., out
                    of a ship before condemnation, ill-using persons on board the prize, &amp;c., or
                    breaking bulk with a view to embezzlement. Prize is subject to the usual customs
                    regulations. The United States Prize Act is the Act of June 30, 1864, just seven
                    days later in date than the British Prize Act. The two Acts are similar in
                    character, but the United States Act is more full and definite than the British,
                    as it deals with some matters which in Great Britain are left to the discretion
                    of the executive.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Prize Court.—</hi> This is a court sitting by the commission of
                    the the sovereign of the captor for the determination of prize causes. A capture
                    does not become good prize until condemnation by a prize court. As a general
                    rule the court must be commissioned by the sovereign, must sit in the country of
                    the captor, and must be in possession of the prize. In the case of allied
                    powers, it is usually agreed (as it was between Great Britain and France in
                    1854) that the decision shall be made by a court of the country to which the
                    officer in command belongs. A prize court may sit in the territory of an ally,
                    though this is irregular; but it is a violation of neutrality to constitute a
                    prize court within the limits of a neutral power. A prize may, however, in case
                    of necessity be brought into a neutral port and sold there under the decree of a
                    prize court, subject to objection on the part of the neutral Government. The
                    sentence of a prize court is, where the jurisdiction is well-founded, a judgment
                    <hi rend="italic">in rem</hi> and entitled to universal respect. In the British
                    dominions the prize courts are such courts as the crown or parliament invests
                    with authority in prize matters. In practice these are the High Court of Justice
                    (Admiralty Division) and the Vice-Admiralty Courts abroad. By the Naval Prize
                    Act, 1864, the High Court of Admiralty of England (now represented by the
                    Admiralty Division) has jurisdiction as a prize court throughout the British
                    dominions. It is to be noticed that this jurisdiction is entirely derivative;
                    the court has no original prize jurisdiction as it has original instance
                    jurisdiction. The prize jurisdiction of Scotch courts was vested in the High
                    Court of Admiralty of England by 6 Geo. IV. c. 120, § 57. In the United States
                    (in accordance with Art. III. § 2 of the constitution, “The judicial power shall
                    extend to all cases of admiralty and maritime jurisdiction”)</p>
                <p>the prize courts are the district courts, the State courts having no
                    jurisdiction. The procedure of a prize court is simple in its character. In
                    Great Britain and the United States standing interrogatories are administered to
                    the captors. The case is heard upon the depositions of the witnesses in answer
                    to the interrogatories, and upon the ship’s papers, which it is the duty of the
                    captor to forward to a port of his country for deposit in the court. The flag is
                    regarded <hi rend="italic">prima</hi><hi rend="italic">facie</hi> evidence of
                    the nationality of a captured vessel. The pleadings are not technical. A libel
                    is filed, followed by a monition to parties interested. If the cause be not
                    prosecuted, the court will issue a monition to the captors to proceed. A prize
                    court has power to order matters incidental to the cause, such as unlivery and
                    appraisement and sale. It also distributes prize money in some cases (see
                    below). The procedure of prize courts in the British dominions may be regulated
                    by order in council under the powers of the Naval Prize Act, 1864; in the United
                    States it depends upon the Prize Act of June 30, 1864. An appeal lies in England
                    from the Admiralty Division to the Court of Appeal and thence to the House of
                    Lords, from the Vice-Admiralty Courts abroad to the Judicial Committee of the
                    Privy Council. In the United States it lies to the supreme court where the
                    matter in dispute exceeds 2000 dollars, or involves a question of general
                    importance. In addition to prize proper, prize courts have had jurisdiction in
                    some analogous matters conferred on them by statute. Thus a prize court in the
                    British dominions has jurisdiction over (1) enemy’s property captured in a
                    conjunct expedition of land and naval forces, 2 &amp; 3 Will. IV. c. 53, § 30,
                    or captured on land by a naval or naval and military force acting either alone
                    or with allied forces, 27 &amp; 28 Vict. c. 25, §§ 34, 35; (2) petitions of
                    right where the subject-matter of a petition arises out of the exercise of any
                    belligerent right by the crown, or would be cognizable in a prize court if the
                    same were a matter in dispute between private persons, § 52. Questions of booty
                    of war may be referred to the Admiralty Division as a prize court, 3 &amp; 4
                    Viet, c. 65, § 22. The United States prize courts have by the Act of 1854
                    jurisdiction over property captured in an insurrection.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For the procedure of prize courts see Story,
                    On Prize Courts; Phi∏imore, International Law, vol. iii. pt. xi.; Lushington,
                    Manual of Naval Prize Law.</p></note><hi rend="italic">Prize Money.—</hi> The
                    term prize money is used in a wider sense than the term prize. It extends to any
                    reward granted by the state for the capture of enemy’s property whether by land
                    or sea. (1) The Act consolidating the right to and distribution of army prize
                    money is the Army Prize Act, 1832, 2 &amp; 3 Will. IV. c. 53. The right and
                    interest of troops to prize money and bounty money is at the discretion of the
                    crown, and is to be distributed in such proportions as the crown may direct. It
                    is to be noticed that capture by troops of an enemy’s ship in a road, river,
                    haven, or creek of the enemy gives a right to prize money in this sense, though
                    it is not prize proper, not having been captured at sea by an armed ship.
                    Deserters are not entitled to prize money. Shares not claimed within six years
                    are forfeited. A list of persons entitled is transmitted to Chelsea Hospital,
                    the treasurer of which distributes the money either to such persons or their
                    assignees, or to the regimental agent, according to the rules laid down in the
                    Act. Prize money may be assigned subject to certain conditions. In the case of
                    officers the assignment must express the consideration money actually paid for
                    the assignment; in the case of non-commissioned officers or seamen the
                    assignment is only valid where there is no regimental agent. In conjunct
                    expeditions of land and naval forces, the share of the land forces is to be paid
                    to the treasurer of Chelsea Hospital. By 27 &amp; 28 Vict. c. 36, § 3, prize
                    money not exceeding £50 may be paid without probate or letters of
                    administration. By 39 Vict. c. 14, the accounts are to be laid before
                    parliament. In the United States provision was made by several Acts of Congress
                    that officers and soldiers who had served in certain wars should be entitled to
                    warrants for bounty-lands as a reward for their services. (2) For the right to
                    prize money where the captor at sea is not a public ship of war, see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Privateer.</hi> Where the captor is a public snip of war of
                    Great Britain, the officers and crew have only such interest in the proceeds of
                    prize as the crown may from time to time grant them. This interest is subject to
                    forfeiture for misconduct in relation to the prize, 27 &amp; 28 Vict. c. 25, §§
                    36, 55. In the United States, by the Prize Act of 1864, the whole proceeds go to
                    the captor where the prize is of superior or equal force, one-half to the captor
                    and one-half to the United States where the prize is of inferior force. The
                    prize money accruing to the United States forms part of the fund for pensions.
                    Besides a share of the prize, prize bounty is generally given. By the Naval
                    Prize Act, 1864, this is at the rate of £5 for each person on board the enemy’s
                    ship, if a ship of war, 27 &amp; 28 Vict. c. 25, § 42. By the United States Act
                    of 1864, the rate is 200 dollars if the prize is of superior or equal force, 100
                    if of inferior force. The distribution of prize money and prize bounty in Great
                    Britain is regulated by the Naval Agency and Distribution Act, 1864, 27 &amp; 28
                    Vict. c. 24. The money is distributed under the direction of the lords of the
                    Admiralty in the proportions specified in a royal proclamation or order in
                    council. The proportions are graduated according to rank (see vol. xvii. p.
                    298). Assignment of a share by a petty officer or seaman or a non-commissioned
                    officer of marines or marine is void unless in accordance with orders in
                    council. All forfeited and unclaimed shares, and a percentage of 5 per cent, out
                    of the proceeds and grants, are carried to the account of the naval prize cash
                    balance. The Admiralty Division has the sole right of determining disputes as to
                    distribution or investment. In the United States the distribution is regulated
                    by the Act of 1864. The distribution is by the district court; it is a judicial
                    act, not, as in Great Britain, the act of a Government department. The
                    proportions too are fixed by statute—not left, as in Great Britain, to the
                    discretion of the executive. The commanding officer of a fleet or squadron has
                    one-twentieth allotted to him, of a division one-fiftieth, a fleet captain
                    one-hundredth, the commander of a single vessel one-tenth of the amount awarded
                    to the vessel; the residue share in proportion to their pay. Prize money is paid
                    into the treasury of the United States to be distributed according to the decree
                    of the court. Ransom money, salvage, bounty, and proceeds of condemned property
                    are distributable as prize money. Assignments of prize money must be attested by
                    the commanding officer and the paymaster. There are certain cases where money is
                    granted to the officers and crew of vessels making captures which are not prize
                    in the strict sense of the word. Under this head may be classed the salvage on
                    recapture already mentioned, besides the cases provided for in the following
                    enactments. By 22 &amp; 23 Car. II. c. 11, § 10, 2 per cent, of the value of the
                    ship defended may be awarded to those wounded and the representatives of those
                    slain in the defence of a merchant ship against pirates. By the Customs Act,
                    1876, 39 &amp; 40 Vict. c. 36, §§ 210-216, rewards may be granted to officers of
                    the customs out of the penalties for goods seized. By the Slave Trade Act, 1873,
                    36 &amp; 37 Vict. c. 88, §§ 11, 12, a bounty of £5 per slave or of £4 per ton is
                    payable to the officers and crew of one of Her Majesty’s ships upon capture of a
                    slave ship. Where the capture is not by a ship of war, the bounty is one-third
                    of the value of the ship seized, and a bounty of £5 for each slave. By an Act of
                    Congress of March 3, 1819, a bounty of 25 dollars is given for each slave
                    captured, and the proceeds of condemned slave ships are divided between the
                    United States and the captors, half to each. (J. W+.) <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n791/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0791-0768"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
