<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0919-0247-0238-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PLYMOUTH BRETHREN (9th edition, volume 19, page
                    238)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892p9k">Spiritism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:875214">Congregationalists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166896">Views</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n247/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PLYMOUTH BRETHREN</label><hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >(Brethren,</hi></hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Christian Brethren)</hi>
                    are a sect of Christians who received the name in 1830 when the Rev. J. N. Darby
                    induced many of the inhabitants of Plymouth to associate themselves with him for
                    the promulgation of opinions which they held in common. Although small Christian
                    communities existed in Ireland and elsewhere calling themselves <hi
                        rend="italic">Brethren</hi> and holding similar views, the accession to the
                    ranks of Mr Darby so increased their numbers and influence that he is usually
                    reckoned the founder of Plymouthism. Darby (born in Nov. 1800, in London;
                    graduated at Trinity College, Dublin, in 1819; died April 29, 1882 at
                    Bournemouth) was a curate in the Episcopalian Church of Ireland until 1827, when
                    he felt himself constrained to leave the Established Church; betaking himself to
                    Dublin, he became associated with several devout people who refused all
                    ecclesiastical fellowship, met statedly for public worship, and called
                    themselves the Brethren. In 1830 Darby at Plymouth won over a large number of
                    people to his way of thinking, among whom were the Rev. Benjamin Wills Newton,
                    who had been a clergyman of the Established Church of England; the Rev. James L.
                    Harris, a Plymouth clergyman; and the well known Biblical scholar Dr Samuel
                    Prideaux Tregelles. ' The Brethren started a newspaper, <hi rend="italic">The,
                        Christian Witness,</hi> continued under the names <hi rend="italic">The
                        Present Testimony</hi> (1849) and <hi rend="italic">The Bible Treasury</hi>
                    (1856), with Harris as editor and Darby as the most important contributor.
                    During the next eight years the progress of the sect was rapid, and communities
                    of the brethren were to be found in many of the principal towns in England.</p>
                <p>In 1838 Darby, after a short stay in Paris, went to reside in French Switzerland,
                    and found many disciples. Congregations were formed in Geneva, at Lausanne,
                    where most of the Methodist and other dissenters joined the Brethren, at Vevey,
                    and elsewhere in Vaud. His opinions also found their way into Germany, German
                    Switzerland, Italy, and France; but French Switzerland has always remained the
                    stronghold of Plymouthism on the Continent, and for his followers there Mr Darby
                    wrote two of his most important tracts, <hi rend="italic">Le Ministère considéré
                        dans sa Nature</hi> and <hi rend="italic">De la</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Presence</hi><hi rend="italic">et de VAction du S. Esprit dans
                        VÉglise.</hi> The revolution in the canton Vaud, instigated by the Jesuits
                    in 1845, brought persecution to the Brethren in the canton and in other parts of
                    French Switzerland, and Darby felt his own life insecure there.</p>
                <p>He returned to England, and his reappearance was accompanied by divisions among
                    the Brethren at home. These divisions began at Plymouth. Mr B. Wills Newton, at
                    the head of the community there, was accused of departing from the testimony of
                    the Brethren against an official ministry, and of reintroducing the spirit of
                    clericalism. Unable to detach the congregation from the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n248/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0248-0239"/> preacher, Darby began a rival and separate
                    assembly. The majority of the Brethren out of Plymouth supported Darby, but a
                    minority kept by Newton. The separation became wider in 1847 on the discovery of
                    supposed heretical teaching by Newton. In 1848 another division took place. The
                    Bethesda congregation at Bristol, where Mr George Müller was the most
                    influential member, received into communion several of Newton’s followers and
                    justified their action. A large number of communities approved of their conduct;
                    others were strongly opposed to it. Out of this came the separation into Neutral
                    Brethren led by Müller, and Exclusive Brethren or Darbyites, who refused to hold
                    communion with the followers of Newton or Müller. The exclusives, who were the
                    more numerous, suffered further divisions. An Irish clergyman named Cluff had
                    adopted the views of Mr Pearsall Smith, and when these were repudiated seceded
                    with his followers. The most important division among the exclusives came to a
                    crisis in 1881, when Mr William Kelly and Mr Darby became the recognized leaders
                    of two sections who separated on some point of discipline. There are therefore
                    at least five official divisions or sects of Plymouthists :—(1) the followers of
                    Mr B. Wills Newton; (2) the Neutrals, who incline to the Congregationalist idea
                    that each assembly should judge for itself in matters of discipline, headed by
                    Mr George Müller; (3) the Darbyite Exclusives; (4) the Exclusives who follow Mr
                    Kelly; and (5) the followers of Mr Cluff. The fundamental principle of the
                    Exclusives, “Separation from evil God’s principle of unity,” has led to many
                    unimportant excommunications and separations besides those mentioned.</p>
                <p>The theological views of the Brethren do not differ greatly from those held by
                    evangelical Protestants (for a list of divergences, see Reid, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Plymouth Brethrenism Unveiled and Refuted)·,</hi> they make the baptism of
                    infants an open question and celebrate the Lord’s Supper weekly. Their
                    distinctive doctrines are ecclesiastical. They hold that all official ministry,
                    anything like a clergy, whether on Episcopalian, Presbyterian, or
                    Congregationalist theories, is a denial of the spiritual priesthood of all
                    believers, and a striving against the Holy Spirit. Hence it is a point of
                    conscience to have no communion with any church which possesses a regular
                    ministry. The gradual growth of this opinion, and perhaps the reasons for
                    holding it, may be traced in Mr Darby’s earlier writings. While a curate in the
                    Church of Ireland he was indignant with Archbishop Magee for stopping the
                    progress of mission work among Roman Catholics by imposing on all who joined the
                    church the oath of supremacy. This led Darby to the idea that established
                    churches are as foreign to the spirit of Christianity as the papacy is
                    (“Considerations addressed to the Archbishop of Dublin, &amp;c.,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Coll. Works,</hi> vol. i. 1). The parochial system, when
                    enforced to the extent of prohibiting the preaching of the gospel within a
                    parish where the incumbent was opposed to it, led him to consider the whole
                    system a hindrance to the proper work of the church and therefore anti-Christian
                    (“Thoughts on the present position of the Home Mission,” <hi rend="italic">Coll.
                        Works,</hi> i. 78). And the waste of power implied in the refusal to
                    sanction lay-preaching seemed to him to lead to the conclusion that an official
                    ministry was a refusal of the gifts of the Spirit to the church (“On Lay
                    Preaching,” <hi rend="italic">Coll. Works,</hi> p. 200). These three ideas seem
                    to have led in the end to Plymouthism; and the movement, if it has had small
                    results in the formation of a sect, has at least set churches to consider how
                    they might make their machinery more elastic. Perhaps one of the reasons of the
                    comparatively small number of Brethren may be found in their idea that their
                    mission is not to the heathen but to “the awakened in the ehurches.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.</hi> —Darby, <hi rend="italic">Collected
                        Works,</hi> 32 vols., edited by Kelly; Reid, <hi rend="italic">Plymouth
                        Brethrenism Unveiled and Refuted,</hi> 3d ed., 1880, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >History and Literature of the so-called Plymouth Brethren,</hi> 2d ed.,
                    1876; Miller, <hi rend="italic">The Brethren, their Rise, Progress, and
                        Testimony,</hi> 1879; Teulon, <hi rend="italic">History and Doctrines of the
                        Plymouth Brethren,</hi> 1888. (τ. Μ. L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
