<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0671-0648-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">POUSHKIN, Alexander</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 19, page 648</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1043867">Odes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933357">Fountains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46688q84">Odes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vq1n">Fountains</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4804xp4n">Polishes</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n671/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">POUSHKIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Alexander</hi></label>
                    (1799-1837), the most celebrated of Russian poets, was born at Moscow, 7th June
                    1799. He belonged to an ancient family of boyars, and in a clever poem, many of
                    the sallies of which were too trenchant to pass the censorship, he has sketched
                    some of the more important of his progenitors. A strange ancestor was his
                    maternal great-grandfather, a favourite Negro ennobled by Peter the Great, who
                    bequeathed to him the curly hair of his race and a somewhat darker complexion
                    than falls to the lot of the ordinary Russian.</p>
                <p>In 1811 the poet entered the newly-founded lyceum of Tzarskoe Selo, situated near
                    St Petersburg. To his stay in this college Poushkin has alluded in many of his
                    poems. On quitting the lyceum in 1817 he was attached to the ministry of foreign
                    affairs, and in this year he began the composition of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ruslan and Ly'udτm,ila,</hi> a poem which was completed in 1820. The scene is
                    laid at Kieff, in the time of Vladimir, the “bright sun” of the old Russian
                    legends. Meanwhile Poushkin mixed in all the gayest society of the capital, and
                    it seemed as if he would turn out a mere man of fashion instead of a poet. But
                    an event occurred which, however disastrous it might appear to him at first
                    sight, was fraught with the happiest consequences to his muse. A very daring <hi
                    rend="italic">Ode to Liberty</hi> written by him had been circulated in
                    manuscript in St Petersburg. This production having been brought to the notice
                    of the governor, the young author only escaped a journey to Siberia by accepting
                    an official position at Kishineff in Bessarabia, in southern Russia. Here he
                    found himself surrounded by a world of new associations. If we follow the
                    chronological order of his poems, we can trace with what enthusiasm he greeted
                    the ever-changing prospects of the sea and the regions of the Danube and the
                    Crimea. In some elegant lines he sang the <hi rend="italic">Fountain of
                    Bakhchisarai,</hi> the old palace of the khans near Simpheropol. This fountain
                    and the legend connected with it he afterwards made the subject of a longer
                    poem.</p>
                <p>At this time Poushkin was, or affected to be, overpowered by the Byronic
                    “Weltschmerz.” Having visited the baths of the Caucasus for the re-establishment
                    of his health in 1822, he felt the inspiration of its magnificent scenery, and
                    composed his next production of any considerable length, <hi rend="italic">The
                    Prisoner of the Caucasus,</hi> narrating the story of the love of a Circassian
                    girl for a youthful Russian officer who has been taken prisoner. This was
                    followed by the <hi rend="italic">Fountain of Bakhchisarai,</hi> which tells of
                    the detention of a young Polish captive, a Countess Potocka, in the palace of
                    the khans of the Crimea. About the same time he composed some interesting lines
                    on Ovid, whose place of banishment, Tomi, was not far distant. To this period
                    belongs also the <hi rend="italic">Ode to Napoleon,</hi> which is far inferior
                    to the fine poems of Byron and Manzoni, or indeed of Lermontoff, on the same
                    subject. In the <hi rend="italic">Lay concerning the Wise Oleg</hi> we see how
                    the influence of Karamzin’s <hi rend="italic">History</hi> had led the Russians
                    to take a greater interest in the early records of their country. The next long
                    poem was the <hi rend="italic">Gipsies</hi> (Tzuigani), an Oriental tale of love
                    and vengeance, in which Poushkin has admirably delineated these nomads, whose
                    strange mode of life fascinated him. During his stay in southern Russia he
                    allowed himself to get mixed up with the secret societies then rife throughout
                    the country. He also became embroiled with his chief, Count Vorontzoff, who sent
                    him to report upon the damages which had been committed by locusts in the
                    southern part of Bessarabia. Poushkin took this as a premeditated insult, and
                    sent in his resignation; and Count Vorontzoff in his official report requested
                    the Government to remove the poet, “as he was surrounded by a society of
                    political and literary fanatics, whose praises might turn his head and make him
                    believe that he was a great writer, whereas he λvas only a feeble imitator of
                    Lord Byron, an original not much to be commended.” The poet quitted Odessa in
                    1824, and on leaving wrote a fine <hi rend="italic">Ode to the Sea.</hi> Before
                    the close of the year he had returned to his father’s seat at Mikhailovskoe,
                    near Pskoff, where he soon became embroiled with his relatives, but grew more at
                    ease when the veteran, who led the life of reckless expenditure of the
                    old-fashioned Russian boyar, betook himself to the capital. The father survived
                    his celebrated son, and it was to him that Zhukovski addressed a pathetic
                    letter, giving him an account of his death. His mother died a year before her
                    son; and Poushkin, when choosing a burial-place for her, marked out a spot for
                    himself and expressed a presentiment that he had not long to live. He had now
                    involved himself in trouble on all sides <hi rend="italic">; for so</hi>
                    obnoxious had he become to the authorities even during his retreat in the
                    country that he was put under the supervision of the governor, the marshal of
                    the nobility, and the archimandrite of the neighbouring monastery of
                    Svyatogorski. In his retirement he devoted a great deal of time to the study of
                    the old Russian popular poetry, the <hi rend="italic">builinas,</hi> of which he
                    became a great admirer. Recollections of Byron and André Chenier gave the
                    inspiration to some fine lines consecrated to the latter, in which Poushkin
                    appeared more conservative than was his wont, and wrote in a spirit antagonistic
                    to the French Revolution. In 1825 he published his tragedy <hi rend="italic"
                    >Boris Godunoff,</hi> a bold effort to imitate the style of Shakespeare. Up to
                    this time the traditions of the Russian stage, such as it was, had been French.
                    Plays of all kinds had appeared,—translations of Molière, Corneille, and Racine,
                    or adaptations of them, and even glimpses of Shakespeare conveyed through the
                    medium of the paltry versions of Ducis.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n672/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0672-0649"/>
                <p>In 1825 the unfortunate conspiracy of the Dekabrists broke out, the ostensible
                    aim of which was to defend the claims of the grand-duke Constantine against his
                    brother Nicholas, but the real purpose was to set up a republican form of
                    government in Russia, for which the country was not by any means prepared. Many
                    of the conspirators were personal friends of Poushkin, especially Küchelbecker
                    and Pustchin. The poet himself was to a certain extent compromised, but he
                    succeeded in getting to his house at Mikhailovskoe and burning all the papers
                    which might have been prejudicial to him. He had resolved to go to St
                    Petersburg, possibly to throw in his lot with his friends there, but was stopped
                    by what are considered portents by the Russian people. As soon as he had left
                    the gates of his house he met a priest, and he had not gone a verst before three
                    hares crossed his path. These were such bad omens that there was nothing for him
                    to do, as a genuine Russian and at all times a superstitious man, but to return
                    home at once. Through influential friends he succeeded in making his peace with
                    the emperor, to whom he was presented at Moscow soon after his coronation. The
                    story goes that Nicholas said to Count Bludoff on the same evening, “I have just
                    been conversing with the most witty man in Russia.” In 1828 appeared <hi
                    rend="italic">Poltava,</hi> a spirited narrative poem, in which the expedition
                    of Charles XII. against Peter and the treachery of the hetman Mazeppa were
                    described. The best part of the poem is the picture of the battle itself, where
                    the colours are laid on very boldly. In 1829 Poushkin again visited the
                    Caucasus, on this occasion accompanying the expedition of Prince Paskewitch. He
                    wrote a pleasing account of the tour; many of the short lyrical pieces suggested
                    by the scenery and associations of his visit are delightful, especially the
                    lines on the Don and the Caucasus. In 1831 Poushkin married Mademoiselle Natalia
                    Goncharoff, and in the following year was again attached to the ministry of
                    foreign affairs, with a salary of 5000 roubles. He now busied himself with an
                    historical work, an account of the revolt of the Cossack Pugacheff, who almost
                    overthrew the empire of Catherine and was executed at Moscow in the latter part
                    of the 18th century. While engaged upon this he wrote <hi rend="italic">The
                    Captain’s Daughter,</hi> one of the best of his prose works. In 1832 was
                    completed the poem <hi rend="italic">Eugene Cnyegin,</hi> in which the author
                    attempted a completely new style, moulding his production upon the lighter
                    sketches of Byron in the Italian manner. The poem is, on the whole, very
                    successful. The metre is graceful and sprightlyand well adapted for serio-comic
                    verse. The characters of Lenski, Onyegin, Tatiana, and Olga are drawn with a
                    vigorous hand, and each is a type. No one can accuse Poushkin of want of
                    nationalism in this poem: it is Russian in every fibre.</p>
                <p>In 1837 the poet, who had been long growing in literary reputation, fell mortally
                    wounded in a duel with Baron George Heckeren d’Anthès, the adopted son of the
                    Dutch minister then resident at the court of St Petersburg. D’Anthès, a vain and
                    frivolous young man, had married a sister of the poet’s wife. Notwithstanding
                    this he aroused Poushkin’s jealousy by some attentions which he paid Natalia;
                    but the grounds for the poet’s anger, it must be confessed, do not appear very
                    great. Poushkin died, after two days’ suffering, on the afternoon of Friday,
                    10th February. D’Anthès was tried by court-martial and expelled the country. In
                    the year 1880 a statue of the poet was erected at the Tver Barrier at Moscow,
                    and fêtes were held in his honour, on which occasion many interesting memorials
                    of him were exhibited to his admiring countrymen and a few foreigners who had
                    congregated for the festivities. The poet left four children; his widow was
                    afterwards married to an officer in the army named Lanskoi; she died in
                    1863.</p>
                <p>Poushkin remains as yet the greatest poet whom Russia has produced. The most
                    celebrated names before him were those of Lomonosoff and Derzhavin; the former
                    was a composer of merely scholastic verses, and the latter, in spite of great
                    merits, was too much wedded to the pedantries of the classical school. Since
                    Poushkin’s death, Lermontoff and Nekrasoff have appeared, both distinctly
                    writers of genius, but they are confessedly inferior to him. His poetical tales
                    are spirited and full of dramatic power. The influence of Byron is undoubtedly
                    seen in them, but they are not imitations, still less is anything in them
                    plagiarized. <hi rend="italic">Boris Godunoff</hi> is a fine tragedy; on the
                    whole <hi rend="italic">Eugene Onyegin</hi> must be considered Poushkin’s
                    masterpiece. Here we have a great variety of styles— satire, pathos, and humour
                    mixed together. The character-painting is good, and the descriptions of scenery
                    introduced faithful to nature. The poem in many places reminds us of Byron, who
                    himself in his mixture of the pathetic and the humorous was a disciple of the
                    Italian school. Poushkin also wrote a great many lyrical pieces. Interspersed
                    among the poet’s minor works will be found many epigrams, but some of the best
                    composed by him were not so fortunate as to pass the censorship, and must be
                    read in a supplementary volume published at Berlin. As a prose writer Poushkin
                    has considerable merits. Besides his <hi rend="italic">History of the Revolt of
                    Pugacheff,</hi> which is perhaps too much of a compilation, he published a small
                    volume of tales under the <hi rend="italic">nom</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    plume</hi> of Ivan Byelkin. These all show considerable dramatic power; the best
                    are <hi rend="italic">The Captain’s Daughter,</hi> a tale of the times of
                    Catherine II., <hi rend="italic">The Undertaker,</hi> a very ghostly story,
                    which will remind the English reader of some of the tales of Edgar Poe; <hi
                    rend="italic">The Pistol Shot</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">The Queen of
                    Spades.</hi> Of the letters of Poushkin, which originally were to be found
                    scattered over many magazines and literary journals, a fairly complete
                    collection was published in the new edition of his works which appeared at
                    Moscow under the editorship of Μ. Yefrimoff. (W. R. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
