<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0125-0116-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PIRACY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 19, page 116</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:955173">Hens</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gw8z">Treason</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8br9k">Hens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n125/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PIRACY</label>. Sir Edward Coke <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Instit.</hi> iii. 113) describes a pirate (Latin <hi rend="italic"
                    >pirata,</hi> from Greek <hi rend="italic">πeψaτη&lt;i)</hi> as <hi
                    rend="italic">hostis humani</hi><hi rend="italic">generis,</hi> and as a rover
                    and robber upon the sea. Piracy may be defined in law as an offence which
                    consists in the commission of those acts of pillage and violence upon the high
                    seas which on land would amount to felony. By the ancient common law of England
                    piracy, if committed by a subject, was deemed to be a species of treason, being
                    contrary to his natural allegiance, and by an alien to be felony; but since the
                    Statute of Treasons, 25 Edw. III. c. 2 (1351^52), piracy has been held to be
                    felony only. Formerly this offence was only cognizable by the Admiralty courts,
                    whose proceedings were based upon the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n126/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0126-0117"/> civil law, but by the statute 28 Hen. VIII. c. 15
                    (1536) a new jurisdiction proceeding according to the common law was set up
                    which, modified and regulated by subsequent enactments, such as 39 Geo. III. c.
                    37 (1798-99), 4 &amp; 5 Will. IV. c. 36 (1834), and 7 &amp; 8 Vict. c. 2 (1844),
                    continues to be the tribunal by which offenders of this description are
                    tried.</p>
                <p>Piracy, being a crime not against any particular state but against all mankind,
                    may be punished in the competent court of any country where the offender may be
                    found or into which he may be carried. But, whilst the law of nations gives to
                    every one the right to pursue and exterminate pirates without any previous
                    declaration of war (pirates holding no commission or delegated authority from
                    any sovereign or state), it is not allowed to kill them without trial except in
                    battle. Those who surrender or are taken prisoners must be brought before the
                    proper tribunal and dealt with according to law.</p>
                <p>The earliest of all sea-rovers were perhaps the Phoenicians. During the heroic
                    age of Greece piracy was universally practised. In the Homeric poems frequent
                    mention is made of piracy, which indeed was held in honourable estimation,—the
                    vocation of a pirate being recognized, so that a host, when he asked his guest
                    what was the purpose of his voyage, would enumerate enrichment by indiscriminate
                    maritime plunder as among those projects which might naturally enter into his
                    contemplation. So late as the time of Solon the Phoceans, on account of the
                    sterility of their soil, were forced to roam the seas as pirates. That
                    legislator tolerated whilst he regulated the association of sea-rovers which he
                    found established by inveterate usage. The prevalence of the piratical spirit in
                    Greece in the early ages may perhaps be explained by the number of small
                    independent states into which the country was divided, and the violent animosity
                    subsisting among them. In this way predatory habits were diffused and kept
                    alive. As a more regular system of government grew up, and a few states such as
                    Athens and Corinth had become naval powers, piracy was made a capital offence.
                    It was, however, never entirely put down. Cilicia was at all times the great
                    stronghold of the pirates of antiquity, and in consequence of the decline of the
                    maritime forces which had kept them in check they increased so much in numbers
                    and audacity as to insult the majesty of Rome itself, so that it became
                    necessary to send Pompey against them with a large fleet and army and more
                    extensive powers than had ever previously been conferred on any Roman general.
                    The Etruscans were notorious sea-rovers who infested the Mediterranean; and
                    Polybius relates that the Romans imposed upon the Carthaginians as a condition
                    of peace the stipulation that they should not sail beyond Cape Faro, either for
                    the purposes of trade or piracy.</p>
                <p>Hallam <hi rend="italic">{Middle Ages,</hi> iii. 336) says that in the 13th and
                    14th centuries a rich vessel was never secure from attack, and neither
                    restitution nor punishment of the criminals was to be obtained from Governments.
                    Hugh Despenser seized a Genoese vessel valued at 14,300 marks, for which no
                    restitution was ever made. The famous Hanseatic League was formed in the middle
                    <hi rend="subscript"> rf</hi> of the 13th century in northern Germany chiefly
                    for the purpose of protecting the ships of the confederated cities from the
                    attacks of the pirates by which the Baltic was then infested.</p>
                <p>A graphic account of piracy as it existed at the end of the 16 th century in
                    European waters, especially on the English, French, and Dutch coasts, will be
                    found in Motley, <hi rend="italic">Hist. United Netherlands</hi> (vols. iii. and
                    iv.). The nuisance was not abated in Europe until the feudal system had been
                    subverted and the ascendency of the law finally secured. In more modern times
                    some of the smaller West India Islands became a great resort of pirates, from
                    which, however, they have for many years been driven; for continued acts of
                    piracy the city of Algiers was successfully bombarded by the British fleet under
                    Lord Exmouth as lately as August 1816; and pirates are still not unfrequently
                    met with in the Indian and Chinese seas, but piracy in its original form is no
                    longer in vogue. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Buccaneebs</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(q.v.)</hi> were cruel piratical adventurers of a later date who commenced
                    their depredations on the Spaniards soon after they had taken possession of the
                    American continent and the West Indies, although there was a time when the
                    spirit of buccaneering approached in some degree to the spirit of chivalry in
                    point of adventure. Scaliger observes in a strain of doubtful compliment, “Nulli
                    melius piraticam exercent quam Angli.” The first levy of ship money in England
                    in 1635 was to defray the expense of chastising these pirates. The buccaneering
                    confederacy was broken up through the peace of Ryswick in 1697.</p>
                <p>At a very early period of English history the law provided for the restitution of
                    property taken by pirates, if found within the realm, whether belonging to
                    strangers or Englishmen; but any foreigner suing for the recovery of his goods
                    was required to prove that at the time of the capture his own sovereign and the
                    sovereign of the captor were in mutual amity, for it was held that piracy could
                    not be committed by the subjects of states at war with each other, In England
                    the crown is, generally speaking, entitled to all <hi rend="italic">bona
                    piratorum∙,</hi> but if any person can establish a title to the goods the claim
                    of the crown thereto ceases. By 13 &amp; 14 Vict. c. 26 (1850), ships and
                    effects captured from pirates are to be restored on the payment of one-eighth of
                    their value (by way of salvage), which is to be distributed among the
                    recaptors.</p>
                <p>Cowel <hi rend="italic">(Law Diet.,</hi> 1727) states that in former times the
                    word pirate was used in a better sense than that of a sea-robber, being
                    attributed to persons to whose care the mole or pier of a haven was entrusted,
                    and, quoting the learned Spelman, he adds, sometimes to a sea soldier:
                    “Robertasvero Comes (Normaniae) attemptavit venire in Angliam cum magno
                    exercitu, sed a piratis Regis qui curam maris a Rege (Willielmo) susceperant
                    repulsus est” <hi rend="italic">(Glossarium,</hi> 1687, p. 460). (J. C. W.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
