<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0264-0255-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">POE, Edgar Allan</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 19, page 255</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1090401">Ravens</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w26p">Murder</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc3p">Appeal</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204597">Virginia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n264/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">POE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Edgar Allan</hi></label>
                    (1809-1849), is the most interesting figure in American literature, and his life
                    furnishes the most extraordinary instance on record of systematic
                    misrepresentation on the part of a biographer. The greater part of his short
                    working life was passed in intense and unremitting literary toil, and no poems
                    or romances were ever produced at greater expense of brain and spirit than his.
                    Yet, till lately, when Mr J. H. Ingram, the careful editor of Poe’s works,
                    undertook to collect the plain facts of the poet’s life, the current statement
                    and belief were that his strange tales and poems were flung off from a
                    distempered imagination in the intervals of degraded debauchery. This myth was
                    studiously floated by his first biographer, Griswold, and found readier
                    acceptance with the public owing to the weird and horrible character of much of
                    his imaginative work. Griswold’s story of a life wayward and irregular from
                    hapless beginning to disgraceful close was just what people were prepared to
                    believe about a genius so eccentric and with such a turn for dark mysteries,
                    horrible crimes, inhuman doings and sufferings. That the author of such works
                    should have been expelled from the university and from the army, and from
                    situation after situation when he tried to make a living by literature, all
                    owing to the gross irregularity of his habits, and should finally have died in a
                    hospital in a fit of intoxication, seemed credible enough when affirmed by a
                    selfconstituted biographer. Many of Griswold’s allegations were denied at the
                    time, but the denials were local and isolated, and the truth had no chance
                    against the systematic libel, repeated as it was in many editions, till Mr
                    Ingram prepared a regular and authoritative memoir.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See his <hi rend="italic">Works of Edgar
                    Allan Poe, 4</hi> vols., 1874-75.</p></note></p>
                <p>There was a sufficient mixture of truth with falsehood to make Griswold’s story
                    plausible. It was not quite correct to describe Poe as the son of strolling
                    players, but his father, a man of good family, had married an actress and taken
                    to the stage as a profession. Their son was born in Baltimore, February 19,
                    1809; and father and mother died in 1811 when he was a child. The orphan was
                    adopted by his godfather, Mr Allan, a wealthy merchant, and from his eighth till
                    his thirteenth year (1816— 1821) was placed at school in England. Thence he was
                    transferred to an academy at Richmond, Virginia, and thence at the age of
                    seventeen to the university of Virginia at Charlottesville. Mr Allan was
                    childless, and apparently treated his adopted son as his own child. Why Poe left
                    the university after one session is not clearly explained, but it has bcm
                    ascertained that he was not expelled, but on the contrary was honourably
                    distinguished as a student, although it is admitted that he had contracted debts
                    and had “an ungovernable passion for card-playing.” These debts may have been
                    sufficient cause for a quarrel with Mr Allan. Poe disappeared for two years,
                    setting out for Europe to join the Greeks in their fight for independence.
                    Reappearing at Richmond in 1829, he stayed at home for a year, and then was
                    entered as a military cadet at West Point. But all his ambitions by this time
                    were towards literature; he neglected his duties, disobeyed orders, and was
                    dismissed from the service of the United States. What he did for two years after
                    is not ascertained, but in 1833 he reappeared as the successful competitor for a
                    prize offered by a Baltimore newspaper for a prose story. From that time he
                    subsisted by literature. Mr Allan had married again, and died soon afterwards,
                    leaving an heir by his second wife, and “not a mill,” as Griswold puts it, to
                    Poe.</p>
                <p>It is chiefly in his account of Poe’s literary career that Griswold has been
                    guilty of slandering the subject of his biography, representing him as rendered
                    incapable of permanent employment by his intemperate habits. There would seem to
                    be not the slightest foundation for this coarse slander. During the fifteen
                    years of his literary life Poe was connected with various newspapers and
                    magazines in Richmond, New York, and Philadelphia, and there is unanimous
                    testimony that, so far from being an irregular contributor, he was a model of
                    punctuality and thoroughness, and took a pride in these homely virtues. His
                    connexion was not in any one case “severed by his irregularities.” He wrote
                    first for the <hi rend="italic">Southern Literary Messenger</hi> in Richmond,
                    and edited it for some time; then, in 1837, he removed to New York, and wrote
                    criticisms and did editorial work for the <hi rend="italic">New York Quarterly
                    Review;</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n265/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0265-0256"/> then, after a year, with a prospect of more
                    lucrative employment, he removed to Philadelphia, and for four years was the
                    mainstay of <hi rend="italic">Graham's Magazine.</hi> His literary work was
                    poorly paid for, though some of his most powerful tales— <hi rend="italic">Hans
                    Pfaal, Arthur Gordon Pym, Ligeia, The House of Usher, The Murders in the Rue
                    Morgue, Marie</hi><hi rend="italic">Roget,</hi><hi rend="italic">The Descent
                    into the Maelstrom—</hi> were among Poe’s contributions to these periodicals.
                    Not unnaturally he conceived the idea of starting a magazine of his own as the
                    most hopeful way of living by his work, but he had no capital, and was obliged
                    to abandon the project, and return to New York and miscellaneous journalism. To
                    add to his troubles his wife, a cousin of his own, whom he had married in 1836,
                    and to whom he was passionately attached, was in very delicate health, and
                    during a lingering illness of eight years gave him constant anxiety. We have
                    only to look at the character of Poe’s work, and the condition of such
                    literature commercially, to see why it was that the most popular writer of his
                    generation in America had to struggle so hard for a bare subsistence. His short
                    stories were an easy prey for the newspaper pirate, and when thousands were
                    reading them the author received nothing but the few dollars paid him by the
                    publication in which they first appeared. The <hi rend="italic">Raven</hi> was
                    published first in 1845, and in a few months was being read and recited and
                    parodied wherever the English language was spoken; but the half-starved poet,
                    who had to live by his genius, received only two pounds for the production. And,
                    fertile and active as his imagination was, these short works of his, which
                    served for the passing sensation of the newspaper reader, were far from being
                    extempore effusions. His <hi rend="italic">Philosophy of Composition</hi> is
                    sometimes, indeed génerally, regarded as half-serious half a jest in the
                    author’s peculiar way of mystification. But to any one who examines Poe’s work
                    closely by the light of this essay it is obvious that the disclosure of his
                    method is only too seriously true. It would have been well for his own powers of
                    endurance if he had composed on a less exacting and exhausting system. The most
                    fantastic of Poe’s creations are not the product of the imagination abandoned to
                    the impulses of a dominant mood; the effects are deliberately calculated, as he
                    says they were, step by step and point by point to a prearranged culmination. A
                    man writing on such a system, with the wolf at the door and affections daily on
                    the rack, could hardly have endured the strain if he had had a constitution of
                    iron. It was no wonder that Poe’s health became distempered, or that, during the
                    last years of his wife’s illness and the two remaining years through which he
                    survived her, he had recourse to the dangerous help of stimulants. Not only did
                    he subject his imagination to exhausting conditions, but he wasted his force in
                    doing with superfluous thoroughness what a ready journalist would have dismissed
                    with a few easy sentences of commonplace. When we read his criticisms, which are
                    full of insight and suggestion, we see that in reviewing a book or a poem he was
                    never satisfied till he had thought out what could be done with the subject. His
                    famous feat in anticipating the plot of <hi rend="italic">Barnaby Rudge</hi>
                    from the opening chapters was only a sample of the thoroughness with which he
                    threw himself into whatever he undertook. Poe failed to make a living by
                    literature, not because he was an irregular profligate in the vulgar sense, but
                    because he did ten times as much work as he was paid to do—a species of
                    profligacy, perhaps, but not quite the same in kind as that with which he was
                    charged by his malignant biographer.</p>
                <p>The current story about his breaking off his engagement with Mrs Whitman by
                    presenting himself at her house in a state of violent drunkenness has been
                    proved to be a fabrication, and many other stories about him have been exploded
                    by Mr Ingram. His wife died in 1847, and he followed her in 1849, dying under
                    painful circumstances at Baltimore. For a critical estimate of Poe’s writings
                    the reader may be referred to Professor Nichol’s <hi rend="italic">American
                    Literature.</hi> There are few English writers of this century whose fame is
                    likely to be more enduring. The feelings to which he appeals are simple but
                    universal, and he appeals to them with a force that has never been surpassed.
                    (w. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
