<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0919-0091-0082-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PIERO (9th edition, volume 19, page 82)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093581">Relationism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834457">Blinds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827285">Baptists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010895">Martinis</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884187">Crosses</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp2k">Cross</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wp9t89t">Frescoes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n91/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PIERO</label> (or PIETRO) DE’ FRANCESCHI (1415- 1492), a
                    leading painter of the Umbrian school. This master is generally named Piero
                    della Francesca (Peter, son of Frances), the tradition being that his father, a
                    woollendraper named Benedetto, had died before his birth. This is not correct,
                    for the mother’s name was Romana, and the father continued living during many
                    years of Piero’s career. The painter is also named Piero Borghese, from his
                    birthplace, Borgo San Sepolcro, in Umbria. The true family name was, as above
                    stated, Franceschi, and the family still exists under the name of
                    Martini-Franceschi.</p>
                <p>Piero first received a scientific education, and became an adept in mathematics
                    and geometry. This early bent of mind and course of study influenced to a large
                    extent his development as a painter. He had more science than either Paolo
                    Uccello or Mantegna, both of them his contemporaries, the former older and the
                    latter younger. Skilful in linear perspective, he fixed rectangular planes in
                    perfect order and measured them, and thus got his figures in true proportional
                    height. He preceded and excelled Domenico Ghirlandajo in projecting shadows, and
                    rendered with considerable truth atmosphere, the harmony of colours, and the
                    relief of objects. He was naturally therefore excellent in architectural
                    painting, and, in point of technique, he advanced the practice of oil-colouring
                    in Italy.</p>
                <p>The earliest trace that we find of Piero as a painter is in 1439, when he was an
                    apprentice of Domenico Veneziano, and assisted him in painting the chapel of S.
                    Egidio, in S. Maria Novella of Florence. Towards. 1450 he is said to have been
                    with the same artist in Loreto; nothing of his, however, can now be identified
                    in that locality. In 1451 he was by himself, painting in Rimini, where a fresco
                    still remains. Prior to this he had executed some extensive frescos in the
                    Vatican; but these were destroyed when Raphael undertook on the same walls the
                    Liberation of St Peter and other paintings. His most extensive extant series of
                    frescos is in the choir of S. Francesco in Arezzo,—the History of the Cross,
                    beginning with legendary subjects of the death and burial of Adam, and going on
                    to the entry of Heraclius into Jerusalem after the overthrow of Chosroes. This
                    series is, in relation to its period, remarkable for effect, movement, and
                    mastery of the nude. The subject of the Vision of Constantine is particularly
                    vigorous in chiaroscuro; and a preparatory design of the same composition was so
                    highly effective that it used to be ascribed to Giorgione, and might even
                    (according to one authority) have passed for the handiwork of Correggio or of
                    Rembrandt. A noted fresco in Borgo San Sepolcro, the Resurrection, may be later
                    than this series; it is preserved in the Palazzo de’ Conservatori. An important
                    painting of the Flagellation of Christ, in the cathedral of Urbino, is later
                    still, probably towards 1470. Piero appears to have been much in his native town
                    of Borgo San Sepolcro from about 1445, and more especially after 1454, when he
                    finished the series in Arezzo. He grew rich there, and there he died, and in
                    October 1492 was buried.</p>
                <p>Two statements made by Vasari regarding “Piero della Francesca” <hi rend="italic"
                        >are</hi> open to much controversy. He says that Piero became blind at the
                    age of sixty, which cannot be true, as he continued painting some years later;
                    but scepticism need perhaps hardly go to the extent of inferring that he was
                    never blind at all. Vasari also says that Fra Luca Pacioli, a disciple of Piero
                    in scientific matters, defrauded his memory by appropriating his researches
                    without acknowledgment. This is hard upon the friar, who constantly shows a
                    great reverence for his master in the sciences. One of Pacioli’s books was
                    published in 1509, and speaks of Piero as still living. Hence it has been
                    propounded that Piero lived to the patriarchal age of ninety-four or upwards;
                    but, as it is now stated that he was buried in 1492, we must infer that there is
                    some mistake in relation to Pacioli’s remark—perhaps the date of writing was
                    several years earlier than that of publication. Piero was known to have left a
                    manuscript of his own on perspective; this remained undiscovered till a recent
                    date, when it was found by E. Harzen in the Ambrosian Library of Milan, ascribed
                    to some supposititious “Pietro, Pittore di Bruges.” The treatise shows a
                    knowledge of perspective as dependent on the point of distance.</p>
                <p>In the London National Gallery are four paintings attributed to Piero de’
                    Franceschi. One of them, a profile of Isotta da Rimini, may safely be rejected.
                    The Baptism of Christ, which used to be the altarpiece of the Priory of the
                    Baptist in Borgo San Sapolcro, is an important example; and still more so the
                    Nativity, with the Virgin kneeling, and five angels singing to musical
                    instruments. This is a very interesting and characteristic specimen, and has
                    indeed been praised somewhat beyond its deservings on aesthetic grounds.</p>
                <p>Piero’s earlier style was energetic but unrefined, and to the last he lacked
                    selectness of form and feature. The types of his visages are peculiar, and the
                    costumes (as especially in the Arezzo series) <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n92/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0092-0083"/> singular. He used to work assiduously from
                    clay models swathed in real drapery. Luca Signorelli was his pupil, and probably
                    to some extent Perugino; and his own influence, furthered by that of Signorelli,
                    was potent over all Italy. Belonging as he does to the Umbrian school, he united
                    with that style something of the Sienese and more of the Florentine mode.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
