<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0919-0676-0653-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PRAeMUNIRE (9th edition, volume 19, page 653)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1181694">Writs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:866909">Coke</term>
                    <term ref="fast:893284">Diet</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rv0d79g">Riches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6vd1b">Writs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s296">Coke</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46w96878">Diet</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n676/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PRAeMUNIRE</label>, the name given to a writ originating in
                    the 14th century in the attempt to put restraint on the action of the papal
                    authority in regard to the disposal of ecclesiastical benefices in England
                    before the same became vacant, and subsequently, to the prejudice of the
                    rightful patron, and also in the encouragement of resort to the Roman curia
                    rather than to the courts of the country, in disregard of the authority of the
                    crown, leading thereby to the creation of an <hi rend="italic">imperium
                        in</hi><hi rend="italic">imperio</hi> and the paying that obedience to papal
                    process which constitutionally belonged to the king alone. The λvord
                        “praemunire”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Praemunire is a corruption of the Latin <hi rend="italic"
                                >praemonere,</hi> to pre-admonish or forewarn, and is taken from the
                            words of the writ itself, which runs “Praemunire facias” A. B., &amp;c.,
                                <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> cause A. B. to be forewarned that he
                            appear to answer the contempt wherewith he stands charged.</p></note> is
                    applied also to the offence for which the writ is granted, and furthermore to
                    the penalty it incurs. The range and description of offences made liable to the
                    penalties of praemunire became greatly widened subsequently to the Reformation,
                    so that acts of a very miscellaneous character were from time to time brought
                    within the scope of enactments passed for a very different purpose. The offence
                    is of a nature highly criminal, though not capital, and more immediately affects
                    the crown and Government. The statute 16 Rich. II. c. 5 (1392) is usually
                    designated the Statute of Praemunire; it is, however, but one only of numerous
                    stringent measures (many of which are still unrepealed) resulting from the
                    enactment of the Statute of Provisors (35 Edw. I. c. 1), passed in a previous
                    reign, which according to Coke <hi rend="italic">(Instit.)</hi> was the
                    foundation of all the subsequent statutes of praemunire. Cowel <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Laιo Diet.)</hi> describes a provisor as one who sued to the court of Rome
                    for a provision which was called <hi rend="italic">gratia expectiυa.</hi></p>
                <p>The penalties of praemunire involved the loss of all civil rights, forfeiture of
                    lands, goods, and chattels, and imprisonment during the royal pleasure. In the
                    Habeas Corpus Act (31 Car. II. c. 2, 1679) the committing of any man to prison
                    out of the realm was made praemunire unpardonable even by the king. It thus
                    appears that, whilst the crown by its prerogative might at any time remit the
                    whole or any part of the punishment incurred by a praemunire, an exception was
                    made in transgressions of the Statute of Habeas Corpus. The Royal Marriage Act
                    (12 Geo. III. c. 11) of 1772 is the last statute which subjects any one to the
                    penalties of a praemunire as ordained by 16 Rich. II.</p>
                <p>It cannot be doubted that the legislation exemplified in the Statutes of
                    Praemunire and Provisors was felt by the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n677/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0677-0654"/> popes to be a great check on their freedom of
                    action. In the hands of Henry VIII. praemunire became eventually a lever for the
                    overthrow of papal supremacy. The last ancient statute concerning praemunire,
                    until the Reformation, was the 2 Hen. IV. c. 3 (1400), by which all persons who
                    accepted any provision from the pope to be exempt from canonical obedience to
                    their proper ordinary were subjected to the penalties prescribed. Bishop
                        Stubbs,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                                rend="italic">Constit. Hist, of Eng.</hi> (1880), iii. 356 <hi
                                rend="italic">sg.</hi></p></note> in summing up his account of the
                    various statutes of praemunire, succinctly says of them that they were intended
                    to prevent encroachments on and usurpations of jurisdiction on the part of the
                    pope, and he adds that the more important statute was that of 16 Rich. II. c.
                        <hi rend="italic">5</hi> (1392), which he describes as one of the strongest
                    defensive measures taken during the Middle Ages against Rome, and which was
                    called for in consequence of the conduct of the pope, who had forbidden the
                    bishops to execute the sentences of the royal courts in suits connected with
                    ecclesiastical patronage. Tomlins <hi rend="italic">{Law Diet.)</hi> states that
                    there is only one instance of a prosecution on a praemunire to be found in the
                    state trials, in which case the penalties were inflicted upon some persons for
                    refusing to take the oath of allegiance to Charles II. It may be added that on
                    an indictment for praemunire a peer might not be tried by his peers.</p>
                <p>See Coke, <hi rend="italic">Instit.</hi>; Collier, <hi rend="italic">Eccl.
                        Hist.,</hi> 1708; Hallam, <hi rend="italic">Middle Ages,</hi> 1868; Stephen,
                        <hi rend="italic">Comm.,</hi> 1853, and <hi rend="italic">Hist. Crim.
                        Law;</hi> and Stubbs, <hi rend="italic">Constit. Hist.,</hi> 1880.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
