<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0138-0129-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PISIDIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 19, page 129</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1023088">Minorities</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1023465">Minors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h12vb7j">Frontiers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k931f29">Ruins</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n138/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PISIDIA</label>, in ancient geography, was the name given to
                    a country in the south of Asia Minor, immediately north of Pamphylia, by which
                    it was separated from the Mediterranean, while it was bounded on the north by
                    Phrygia, on the east by Isauria, Lycaonia, and Cilicia, and on the west and
                    south-west by Lycia and a part of Phrygia (see vol. xv. Pl. II.). It was a
                    rugged and mountainous district, comprising some of the loftiest portions of the
                    great range of Mount Taurus, together with the offshoots of the same chain
                    towards the central tableland of Phrygia. Such a region was naturally occupied
                    from a very early period by wild and lawless races of mountaineers, who were
                    very imperfectly reduced to subjection by the powers that successively
                    established their dominion in Asia Minor. The Pisidians are not mentioned by
                    Herodotus, either among the nations that were subdued by Croesus, or among those
                    that furnished contingents to the army of Xerxes, and the first mention of them
                    in history occurs in the <hi rend="italic">Anabasis</hi> of Xenophon, when they
                    furnished a pretext to the younger Cyrus for levying the army with which he
                    designed to subvert his brother’s throne, while he pretended only to put down
                    the Pisidians who were continually harassing the neighbouring nations by their
                    lawless forays <hi rend="italic">{Anab.</hi> i. 1, 11; ii. 1, 4, &amp;c.). They
                    are afterwards mentioned by Ephorus among the inland nations of Asia Minor, and
                    assume a morè prominent part in the history of Alexander the Great, to whose
                    march through their country they opposed a determined resistance. In Strabo’s
                    time they had passed tranquilly under the Roman dominion, though still governed
                    by their own petty chiefs and retaining to a considerable extent their predatory
                    habits.</p>
                <p>The boundaries of Pisidia, like those of most of the inland provinces or regions
                    of Asia Minor, were not clearly defined, and appear to have fluctuated at
                    different times. This was especially the case on the side of Lycia, where the
                    upland district of Milyas was sometimes included in Pisidia, at other times
                    assigned to Lycia. Some <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n139/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0139-0130"/> writers, indeed, considered the Pisidians as the
                    same people with the Milyans, while others regarded them as descendants of the
                    Solymi, but Strabo speaks of the language of the Pisidians as distinct from that
                    of the Solymi, as well as from that of the Lydians. The whole of Pisidia is an
                    elevated region of tablelands or upland valleys in the midst of the ranges of
                    Mount Taurus which descends abruptly on the side of Pamphylia. It contains
                    several small lakes, but the only one of any importance is that now called the
                    Egerdin Göl, of which the ancient name has not been preserved. It is a
                    fresh-water lake of about 30 miles in length, situated in the north of Pisidia
                    on the frontier of Phrygia, at an elevation of 2800 feet above the sea. The only
                    rivers of any importance are the Cestrus and the Eurymedon, both of which take
                    their rise in the highest ranges of Mount Taurus, and flow down through deep and
                    narrow valleys to the plain of Pamphylia, which they traverse on their way to
                    the sea.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding its rugged and mountainous character, Pisidia contained in
                    ancient times several considerable towns, the ruins of which have been brought
                    to light by the researches of recent travellers (Arundell, Hamilton, Daniell),
                    and show them to have attained under the Roman empire to a degree of opulence
                    and prosperity far beyond what we should have looked for in a country of
                    predatory mountaineers. The most important of them are Termessus, near the
                    frontier of Lycia, a strong fortress in a position of great natural strength and
                    commanding one of the principal passes into Pamphylia; Cremna, another mountain
                    fortress, north of the preceding, impending over the valley of the Cestrus;
                    Sagalassus, a little farther north, a large town in a strong position, the ruins
                    of which are among the most remarkable in Asia Minor; Selge, on the right bank
                    of the Eurymedon, surrounded by rugged mountains, notwithstanding which it was
                    in Strabo’s time a large and opulent city; and Antioch, known for distinction’s
                    sake as Antioch in Pisidia, and celebrated for the visit of St Paul. This was
                    situated in the extreme north-east of the district immediately on the frontier
                    of Phrygia, between Lake Egerdin and the range of the Sultan Dagh. Besides these
                    there were situated in the rugged mountain tract west of the Cestrus Cretopolis,
                    Olba or Olbasa, Pogla, Isinda, Etenna, and Conana. Pednelissus was in the upper
                    valley of the Eurymedon above Selge. The only place in the district at the
                    present day deserving to be called a town is Isbarta, the residence of a pasha;
                    it stands at the northern foot of Mount Taurus, looking over the great plain
                    which extends from thence into Phrygia. North of this and immediately on the
                    borders of Phrygia stood Apollonia, called also Mor-diaeum. Several other towns
                    are assigned to Pisidia by Strabo, Pliny, and Ptolemy, of which the sites have
                    not yet been determined.</p>
                <p>We have ho clue to the ethnic character and relations of the Pisidians, except
                    that we learn from Strabo that they were distinct from the neighbouring Solymi,
                    who were probably a Semitic race, but we find mention at an early period in
                    these mountain districts of various other tribes, as the Cabali, Milyans,
                    &amp;c., of all which, as well as the neighbouring Isaurians and Lycaonians, the
                    origin is wholly unknown, and in the absence of monuments of their language
                    must, in all probability, ever remain so.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
