<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0919-0323-0312-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">POLARITY and (9th edition, volume 19, page 312)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1028682">Muffs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795828">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884667">Crystals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884644">Crystallization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100524">Roses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1164079">Vans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1919447">Pasteurization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s24m">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s42j">Crystallization</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x51x">Atoms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42805584">Atomism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n323/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">POLARITY <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi></label>
                    ENANTIOMORPHISM. Any figure, such as a solid of revolution, which has one line
                    in it in reference to which the figure is symmetrical may be said to have an
                    axis, and the points at which the axis cuts the surface of the figure are poles.
                    But the term polarity when applied to material figures or substances is usually
                    confined to cases where there are not only a definite axis and poles, but where
                    the two poles have distinct characters which enable us to recognize them and say
                    which is which. It is in this sense that the word is used here.</p>
                <p>Two figures or two portions of matter are said to be <hi rend="italic"
                        >enantiomorph</hi> to each other when these forms are not superposable, <hi
                        rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> the one will not fit into a mould which fits the
                    other, but the one is identical in form with the mirror image of the other.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Polarity.</hi> — As examples of polarity we may take an awn of
                    barley or a cat’s tail, in which we recognize the distinction between the two
                    poles or ends, which we may call A and B by finding that it is easy to stroke
                    from say A to B but not in the opposite direction. As an example of
                    enantiomorphism we may take our two hands, which will not fit the same mould or
                    glove, but the one of which resembles in figure the mirror image of the
                    other.</p>
                <p>It will be seen by and by that there is a close relation between polarity and
                    enantiomorphism.</p>
                <p>In the examples of polarity just given the condition occurs because the parts of
                    the body are arranged in the direction of the axis in a particular order which
                    is different when read backwards. The simplest expression for such a state of
                    matters will be found in the case of a substance composed of equal numbers of
                    three different kinds of particles, these particles being arranged along the
                    axis in the order</p>
                <p>A I <hi rend="italic">abcabc dbc</hi> ∣ B, where A and B are poles and <hi
                        rend="italic">a, b, c</hi> particles of three different kinds. Of course the
                    same may occur with a more complicated constitution, the condition being that
                    the cyclical order read from A to B is different from that read from B to A.
                    Even with particles all of the same kind we can imagine this sort of polarity
                    produced by such an arrangement as</p>
                <p>A I αα <hi rend="italic">a a a aa a a a aa a a</hi> a∣B, where the density varies
                    periodically as we pass along the axis, but so that the order of variation is
                    different in passing from A to B and from B to A. There is another sort of
                    polarity produced also by an arrangement such as that described above, but here
                    not along the axis but about it. As we took a cat’s tail as an example of the
                    one, so we may take a sable muff as an example of the other. As we stroke the
                    tail in one direction along the axis, so we stroke the muff in one sense about
                    the axis. This arrangement also produces polarity, for there is a real
                    difference between the two ends of the muff. The one is that into which we put
                    our right hand, the other that into which we put our left hand if the fur is to
                    lie downwards in front. If we reverse the ends we find the fur sticking up in
                    front, and we have thus as little difficulty in distinguishing the two poles
                    from one another in this as in the former sort of polarity.</p>
                <p>We can easily imagine the particles of a compound substance to be arranged so as
                    to produce this polarity. To take a simple case,—the molecules of the substance
                    may be formed of three atoms <hi rend="italic">a, b,</hi> and c, arranged <hi
                        rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 0</hi> with <hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi> the planes of the molecules all at right angles to the
                    axis, so that on turning the substance about the axis in one sense the atoms in
                    every molecule follow each other in the order <hi rend="italic">abc,</hi> and of
                    course in the opposite order when the rotation is reversed.</p>
                <p>In these examples the polarity is due to an arrangement of the matter at rest,
                    but both kinds of polarity may be produced by motion. Thus a rotating body has
                    polarity of the second kind; the axis is the axis of rotation, and the two poles
                    differ from each other as the two ends of a muff do. A wire along which a
                    current of electricity is passing has polarity of the first kind; and a magnet,
                    in which currents of electricity may be supposed to circulate about the axis,
                    has polarity of the second kind.</p>
                <p>There is an important difference between these two kinds of polarity. We have
                    seen that they depend on two different conditions—the one on an arrangement of
                    matter or motion along the axis, the other on a similar arrangement about the
                    axis. This gives rise to a difference in their relation to their mirror
                    image.</p>
                <p>If we hang up a cat’s tail by one end, say the A end, in front of a mirror, we
                    see in the mirror the image of a cat’s tail hanging by its A end. But if we hang
                    up a muff by one end, say the right-hand end, before a mirror, we see in the
                    mirror the image of a muff hanging by its left-hand end. If we put our hands
                    into the muff in the usual way and stand before the mirror we see a person with
                    his hands in a muff in the usual way. But his right and left hands correspond to
                    our left and right hands respectively, and the right and left ends of the muff
                    in the mirror are the images of the left and right ends respectively of the real
                    muff. Thus the mirror image of a body having polarity of the second kind has its
                    polarity reversed.</p>
                <p>But the muff and its image are not truly enantiomorph. They differ in position
                    but in nothing else. Turn the one round and it will fit the other.</p>
                <p>Magnetic and electric polarity having been already discussed under <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Electricity</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Magnetism,</hi>
                    we shall here consider some cases of crystalline polarity.</p>
                <p>Both kinds of polarity occur in crystals.</p>
                <p>We have no direct means of ascertaining how the ultimate particles of a crystal
                    are arranged, but it seems reasonable to suppose that there is a relation
                    between the form of the crystal and the structure of its smallest parts; and,
                    when we find the crystals of particular substances always showing polarity of
                    the one or the other kind, we naturally suspect that this is the external
                    indication of such an arrangement of the particles as has been shown above to be
                    capable of producing structural polarity. Of crystalline polarity of the first
                    kind the most striking instances are tourmaline and electric calamine (hydrated
                    silicate of zinc), forms of which are shown in figs. 1 and 2, in which it will
                    be seen that the crystals are not similarly terminated at the two ends. It is
                    this kind of crystalline polarity (often called “hemimorphism”) which (as was
                    first observed by Haiiy and more fully investigated by <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n324/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0324-0313"/> Gustav Rose and by Hankel) is associated with
                    pyroelectricity (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mineralogy,</hi> vol. xvi. p. 376). It
                    is worthy of note that the crystalline polarity and the physical (electric)
                    polarity occurring in the same substances are both of the kind not inverted by
                    reflexion in a mirror.</p>
                <p>As an instance of the same kind of crystalline polarity of a somewhat more
                    complicated character, also associated with pyroelectricity, we may take
                    boracite. The crystals of this mineral exhibit combinations of the cube, the
                    rhombic dodecahedron, and the tetrahedron, as shown in fig. 3. If four lines are
                    drawn corresponding to the four diagonals of the cube, it will be observed that
                    at the two ends of each of these axes the crystal is differently developed. (In
                    the figure one of these axes is indicated by the dotted line.) These axes,
                    therefore, resemble the single axis in tourmaline and electric calamine, and are
                    also axes of pyroelectricity, the end at which the tetrahedral face is situated
                    being the antilogous pole.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Upon some crystals of boracite the faces of both tetrahedra occur.
                            They can, however, be easily distinguished from one another. The faces
                            of the tetrahedron represented in the figure are smooth and shining,
                            while those of the opposite tetrahedron are rough and usually much
                            smaller. It has been suggested that boracite is only apparently regular,
                            and that each crystal is really a group of eight pyramids with their
                            apices in the centre of the group. For a full discussion of the relation
                            between pyroelectricity and crystalline form the reader is referred to a
                            series of papers by Professor Hankel in <hi rend="italic">Trans. R.
                                Saxon Soc. of Sciences.</hi> 1857-79.</p></note></p>
                <p>Scheelite, apatite, ilmenite, and fergusonite are examples of crystalline
                    polarity of the second kind. Figs. 4, 5, and 6 are representations of forms of
                    ilmeni te, apatite, and fergusonite.</p>
                <p>Crystalline polarity of both kinds no doubt depends on the arrangement of the
                    molecules and on their structure; it manifests itself by the occurrence of
                    hemihedral or hemimorphic forms. A crystal may have a polar structure although
                    these external marks of polarity are absent, just as the faces parallel to
                    planes of cleavage do not appear on every crystal.</p>
                <p>Another kind of contrast between the two complementary hemihedral forms of the
                    same substance may be mentioned here.</p>
                <p>Marbach observed that different specimens of iron pyrites (and also of cobalt
                    glance) have very different thermoelectric characters, differing indeed from one
                    another more than bismuth and antimony. Gustav Rose showed that these
                    thermoelectrically opposite kinds are also crystallographically opposite. There
                    is indeed no geometrical difference between two opposite hemihedral forms in the
                    regular system, but Rose detected a difference in the lustre and striation of
                    the faces of the two kinds, and by examining the rare cases in which the two
                    opposite pentagonal dodecahedra or tetragonal icositetrahedra occur on the same
                    crystal proved that the one surface character belongs to the one, the other
                    surface character to the other of the two complementary hemihedra.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Enantiomorphism..—</hi> A figure having polarity of the first
                    kind gives a mirror image resembling itself in form and in position; a figure
                    having polarity of the second kind gives a mirror image resembling itself in
                    form but not in position—the poles being inverted. A figure the axis of which
                    has both kinds of polarity will therefore give a mirror image not superposable
                    to the figure itself, because the polarity of the second kind is reversed while
                    that of the first kind remains unchanged. The figure and its mirror image are
                    enantiomorph, as well as polar. We can construct a figure which is enantiomorph
                    to its mirror image but not polar. Imagine a muff so made that in one half the
                    fur lies the one way, and the opposite way in the other half (fig. 7, where the
                    arrow-heads indicate the lie of the fur). In whichever way we put our hands into
                    this muff one end will be wrong; the muff in the figure has, in fact, two
                    righthand ends. It has therefore no polarity; the two ends are exactly alike.
                    But there are two ways in which such a non-polar muff could be made—with two
                    right-hand ends as in the figure, or with two left-hand ends, and these two
                    forms are enantiomorph. A helix or screw has similar properties (compare fig. 8
                    with fig. 7); if uniform it is non-polar, but is either rightor left-handed.
                    Hence the property which each of two enantiomorph bodies possesses has been
                    called by Sir William Thomson “hélicoïdal asymmetry.”</p>
                <p>As we have crystals exhibiting polarity of both kinds, so we have also
                    enantiomorph crystals, indeed the word enantiomorph was first used by Naumann to
                    express the relation between such crystals. The crystallographic theory of
                    enantiomorph crystals has been very fully worked out. We may divide them into
                    two groups— (1) those in which the hélicoïdal asymmetry depends on the presence
                    of tetartohedral forms of the regular or of the hexagonal system, and (*2) those
                    in which it depends on the presence of hemihedral forms of the rhombic system or
                    hemimorphic forms of the monoclinic system.</p>
                <p>In the first group the asymmetry seems to be produced by the manner in which the
                    molecules, themselves symmetrical, are arranged in the crystal. In the second
                    group the molecules themselves appear to have hélicoïdal asymmetry. This is
                    shown by the action of these substances on polarized light. We shall take
                    examples from each group. If we allow a solution of sodium chlorate to
                    crystallize we find that the crystals, which belong to the regular system, are
                    of two kinds enantiomorph to each other. These are represented in fig. 9. The
                    enantiomorphism depends on the combination of the tetrahedron <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n325/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0325-0314"/> and the pentagonal dodecahedron.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This combination is
                            regarded as tetartohedral because the tetrahedron and the pentagonal
                            dodecahedron belong to two different classes of hennhedral
                        forme.</p></note> Now when a ray of plane polarized light is passed through
                    one of these crystals the plane of polarization is rotated, the amount of
                    rotation being proportional to the length of the path in the crystal. The
                    crystals having the form <hi rend="italic">a</hi> rotate to the right, those
                    having the form <hi rend="italic">b</hi> to the left. They are therefore
                    optically as well as crystallographically enantiomorph. But a solution of sodium
                    chlorate is without action on the plane of polarization, even if the solution be
                    made by dissolving only right-handed or only left-handed crystals, and if a
                    crystal be fused the fused mass is optically inactive, so that it would seem
                    that the optical activity depends on the arrangement of the molecules in the
                    crystal and not on any enantiomorphism in the molecules. The enantiomorphism of
                    quartz crystals is indicated by the presence of faces of a tetartohedral form
                    (vol. xvi. p. 389). The two kinds of crystals rotate the plane of polarization
                    equally, but in opposite senses, when a plane polarized ray is passed through a
                    section cut at right angles to the axis of the crystal. Here also the optical
                    activity ceases when crystalline structure is destroyed by fusion or
                    solution.</p>
                <p>Right-handed and left-handed tartaric acids crystallize in enantiomorph forms
                    (fig. 10). Their solutions are optic ally active, the amount of the rotation for
                    the same strength of solution and the same length of path in it being the same
                    in both acids, but the sense of the rotation is right-handed in the one and
                    left-handed in the other. It iε clear that here we have to do with enantiomorph
                    molecules. In ordinary physical properties such as density, solubility,
                    refracting power—in short, in everything <hi rend="italic">not involving rightor
                        left-handedness—</hi> the acids are identical. When mixed in equal
                    proportions they unite and form racemic acid which is optically inactive, and
                    from racemic acid we can by various means recover unchanged the right and
                    left-handed tartaric acids. We now know a considerable number of cases where, as
                    in that of the two tartaric acids, both enantiomorphs have been discovered, and
                    many where only one has as yet been found.</p>
                <p>It is natural that we should ask what peculiarity of constitution can give a
                    molecule this hélicoïdal asymmetry? Λ very ingenious answer to this question was
                    given simultaneously and independently by the French chemist Le Bel and the
                    Dutch chemist Van ’ t Hoff. We shall give a short statement of the essential
                    points of this interesting theory.</p>
                <p>All the known substances which are optically active in solution are compounds of
                    carbon, and may be regarded as derived from marsh gas, a compound of one atom of
                    carbon and four of hydrogen, by the replacement of hydrogen by other elements or
                    compound radicals. Now we do not know how the atoms of hydrogen are actually
                    arranged relatively to each other and to the atom of carbon in the molecule of
                    marsh gas, but, if we may make a supposition on the subject, the most simple is
                    to imagine the four hydrogen atoms at the apices of a regular tetrahedron in the
                    centre of which is the carbon atom as in the diagrams (fig. 11), where C
                    represents the position of the carbon atom and α, <hi rend="italic">β,</hi> γ, δ
                    that of the four atoms of hydrogen.</p>
                <p>If these hydrogen atoms are replaced by atoms of other elements or by compound
                    radicals we should expect a change of form of the tetrahedron. If two or more of
                    the atoms or radicals united to the carbon atom are similar there is only one
                    way of arranging them, but if they are all different there are two ways in which
                    they may be arranged, as indicated in the figures. It will be seen that these
                    two arrangements are enantiomorph. In the figures the tetrahedron is represented
                    as regular, but if the distance from C depends on the nature of the atom, the
                    tetrahedron, when <hi rend="italic">a, β,</hi> γ, and δ are all different, will
                    not be symmetrical, but its two forms will be enantiomorph. A carbon atom
                    combined with four different atoms or compound radicals may therefore be called
                    an asymmetric carbon atom.</p>
                <p>Now all substances of ascertained constitution, the solutions of which are
                    optically active, contain an asymmetric carbon atom, and their molecules should
                    therefore, on the above hypothesis, have hélicoïdal asymmetry.</p>
                <p>The converse is not generally true. Many substances contain an asymmetric carbon
                    atom but are optically inactive. It is easy to reconcile this with the theory;
                    indeed, a little consideration will show that it is a necessary consequence of
                    it.</p>
                <p>Let us suppose that we have the symmetrical combination of C with <hi
                        rend="italic">a, a, β,</hi> γ and that we treat the substance in such a way
                    that one <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is replaced by δ. The new arrangement is
                    asymmetrical, and will be right or left as the one or the other α is replaced.
                    But the chances for the two are equal, and therefore, as the number of molecules
                    in any quantity we can deal with is very great, the ratio of the number of
                    right-handed molecules in the new substance to the number of left-handed ones
                    will be sensibly that of unity. It is therefore evident that by ordinary
                    chemical processes we cannot expect to produce optically active from optically
                    inactive substances; all that we can get is an inactive mixture of equal
                    quantities of the two oppositely active substances.</p>
                <p>As these two substances have identical properties in every respect where rightor
                    left-handedness is not involved, the problem of separating them is a difficult
                    one. We may note three distinct ways in which the separation can be
                    effected.</p>
                <p>(1) By crystallization. For example, the right and left double tartrates of soda
                    and ammonia crystallize in enantiomorph forms (fig. 12) and are less soluble in
                    water than the double racemate formed by their union. If therefore racemic acid
                    (the optically inactive compound of equal quantities of right and left tartaric
                    acids) is half neutralized<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n330/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0330-0315"/> with soda and half with ammonia, we obtain an
                    optically inactive solution containing a mixture of the two double salts. If
                    this solution is allowed to crystallize each salt crystallizes independently,
                    and the crystals can be separated by picking them out. Further, a supersaturated
                    solution of the one double salt is not made to crystallize by contact with a
                    crystal of the other, so that if we make a supersaturated solution of the
                    inactive mixture and drop into the vessel, at different places, two crystals one
                    of the right the other of the left salt, crystallization occurs at each place,
                    at the one of the one kind and at the other of the other.</p>
                <p>(2) By the action of another optically active substance. While the salts of the
                    two opposite tartaric acids with an inactive base are precisely alike in
                    solubility, density, and other physical characters, and, if they crystallize,
                    crystallize in the same form (or in enantiomorph forms), it is not at all so
                    when the base is optically active; thus right tartaric acid forms a crystalline
                    salt with left asparagine, while with the same base left tartaric acid gives an
                    uncrystallizable compound.</p>
                <p>(3) By the action of living ferments. The minute fungi which act as ferments do
                    not show any rightor left-handedness as far as their obvious anatomical
                    structure is concerned, but Pasteur has shown that some of them are, if we may
                    use the expression, physiologically asymmetrical. As an example we may give the
                    very interesting case of mandelic acid. This acid, which stands to benzoic
                    aldehyde (bitter almond oil) in the same relation as lactic acid does to common
                    aldehyde, contains one asymmetric carbon atom in its molecule. It is optically
                    inactive, and therefore, if Le Bel and Van ’ t Hoff’s theory is true, it must be
                    a mixture of two oppositely active acids. Now Lewko-witsch found that when <hi
                        rend="italic">Penicilium,</hi><hi rend="italic">glaucum,</hi> is cultivated
                    in a solution of mandelic acid fermentation takes place. This goes on until
                    exactly half of the acid is decomposed, and what remains has all the properties
                    of mandelic acid, but is optically active; it is the right-handed component of
                    the mixture, the growing fungus having consumed the other.</p>
                <p>There is an interesting peculiarity of tartaric acid discovered by Pasteur (to
                    whom we owe nearly all our knowledge of the relations between optical activity
                    and crystalline form in tartaric acid) which is of importance in connexion with
                    the theory we have just been explaining.</p>
                <p>We have not only right and left tartaric acid and racemic acid, the inactive
                    compound of the two, but also a kind of tartaric acid which is inactive but
                    incapable of being separated into the two oppositely active acids.</p>
                <p>Now the chemical formula of tartaric acid is</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Ο Η Η O</p><p>II 1 1 II</p><p>c—c*-c*-c Illi 0 0 0 0 1 1 1
                                1</p><p>H H H H</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>It will be observed that the carbon atoms marked * are asymmetric, and that they
                    occupy precisely similar positions in the molecule. Each of them is combined
                    with H, OH, COOH and CH(OH)COOH. If in both of them these four things are
                    arranged in the same order there is hélicoïdal asymmetry—the one order giving
                    the one, the other the other enantiomorph form. But if the one has one order and
                    the other the opposite, then there is in the whole molecule no hélicoïdal
                    asymmetry, as the two halves exactly balance one another. There is not, as in
                    racemic acid, a compound of one molecule of each of the two opposite active
                    acids, but rather a compound of half a molecule of each, and we should not
                    expect such a compound to be easily separable. Jungfleisch has shown that if any
                    one of the four tartaric acids (right, left, racemic, and inactive) is mixed
                    with a little water and kept for some time at a temperature of about 200° C., it
                    is converted into a mixture of racemic and inactive tartaric acids, so that, as
                    racemic acid can be divided into right and left tartaric acids, it is possible
                    to prepare any one of the four from any other. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. c.
                        b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
