<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0919-0233-0224-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PLINY, the Naturalist (9th edition, volume 19, page
                    224)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vs35">Naturalists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n233/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PLINY, <hi rend="smallcaps">the Naturalist</hi></label>
                    (23-79 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.).</hi> Caius Plinius Secundus, commonly
                    distinguished as the elder Pliny, the author of the <hi rend="italic">Natural
                        History,</hi> is believed to have been born (23 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >a.d.)</hi> at Novum Comum (Como). In the first sentence of his preface he
                    calls Catullus, born at Verona, “conterraneum meum,” meaning, perhaps, a native
                    of Gallia Cisalpina, though it may be that Verona was the actual birthplace of
                        both.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>But, as has
                            been shrewdly remarked by Mr Long, “this somewhat barbarous word is much
                            better adapted to intimate that Catullus was a fellow-countryman of
                            Pliny than that he was a fellow-townsman.”</p></note> At Comum, however,
                    was the family estate which the younger Pliny inherited from his uncle. Like his
                    nephew, the elder Pliny had seen military service, having joined the campaign in
                    Germany under L. Pomponius Secundus;<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>“De Vita Pomponi Secundi duo (libri)” are enumerated
                            among his uncle’s works by the younger Pliny, <hi rend="italic">Ep.</hi>
                            iii. 5, § 3, who adds, “a quo singulariter amatus hoc memoriae amici
                            quasi debitum munus exsolvit.”</p></note> like him also, he had been a
                    pleader in the law-courts, and a diligent student of Greek and Roman literature.
                    Much of his literary work was done, he tells us himself, in the hours stolen
                    from sleep. Of his many works the <hi rend="italic">Naturalis Historia</hi> in
                    thirty-seven books has alone been preserved, and in a nearly complete state.
                    This voluminous treatise professes to be an encyclopaedia of Roman knowledge,
                    mainly based on the researches and speculations of the Greeks. What A. von
                    Humboldt accomplished in our own times, in his great work <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cosmos,</hi> Pliny had essayed to carry out on similar principles,—but, of
                    course, without the scientific knowledge, and also without the comprehensive
                    view of the universe which is the inheritance of the present age. Pliny, we must
                    admit, was an industrious compiler, but he was not, like Aristotle, a man of
                    original research.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>He
                            claims for himself “ingenium perquam mediocre,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Praef.</hi> § 12. His nephew (iii. 5, § 8) calls it “acre
                            ingenium,” which may mean active and energetic.</p></note></p>
                <p>In his first book, which contains a summary of the whole work, he names the
                    authors, both Greek and Latin, from which the matter of each book was
                        derived.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Hence he
                            reckons the number of books at 36, the subject beginning with Book ii.
                            The matter of these, he says, comprising 20,000 points worthy of
                            attention, he has collected from the perusal of about 2000 books, and
                            from 100 Roman authors of special note (ex exquisitis auctoribus
                            centum), <hi rend="italic">Praef.</hi> § 17. The first book the author
                            regards as an appendix to the dedicatory letter or preface, “Quia
                            occupationibus tuis publico bono parcendum erat, quid singulis
                            contineretur libris huic epistulae subjunxi,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Praef.</hi> § 33.</p></note> The list indeed is a surprising one,
                    and of comparatively few have we any remains. Among Roman authors he most
                    frequently cites Cato the censor, Μ. Varro, Celsus, Cornelius Nepos, Pomponius
                    Mela, Columella; among the Greeks, Aristotle, Theophrastus, Democritus, more
                    than one Apollodorus, Apollonius of Pergamum, and Hippocrates. The Latin writers
                    he calls simply “auctores;” the Greeks, of whom the list is considerably longer,
                    are “externi.”</p>
                <p>The preface, written in a rather inflated and by no means clear style, very
                    inferior to the Latini ty of the younger Pliny, is a dedication of the work in a
                    strain of extravagant adulation to Titus, who was then, as Caesar, joint emperor
                    with his father Vespasian. Pliny apologizes for dedicating to such a man a work
                    of such commonplace and hackneyed subject-matter, but he pleads the novelty of
                    the undertaking, and boasts of being the first who had attempted so
                    comprehensive a theme.</p>
                <p>The work itself commences with a pantheistic definition of the universe, <hi
                        rend="italic">Mundus,</hi><hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> world and sky, and
                    the sun and stars in space. This, he says, is reasonably regarded as a
                    divinity—eternal, boundless, uncreated, and indestructible. Nature, he adds, and
                    Nature’s work are one, and to suppose there is more than one universe is to
                    believe there can be more than one Nature,—which he calls “furor.” His theology
                    is “agnostic,” or Epicurean; if there is any God, he says, it is vain to inquire
                    His form and shape; He is entirely a Being of feeling and sentiment and
                    intelligence, not of tangible existence. He believes in the “religion of
                    humanity,” according to a rather recent definition of the idea. God is what
                    Nature is; God cannot do what Nature cannot do; He cannot kill Himself, nor make
                    mortals immortal, nor raise the dead to life, nor cause one who has lived never
                    to have lived at all, or make twice ten anything else than twenty. The last
                    sentence of his work is remarkable, and is characteristic of a pagan piety which
                    takes Nature alone for its God :— “Salve, parens rerum omnium Natura, teque
                    nobis Quiritium solis celebratum esse numeris omnibus tuis fave” (xxxvii.
                    205).</p>
                <p>But, although he regarded nature as one whole, of the great doctrine of the unity
                    of nature and the tendency of all its operations to one definite end Pliny had
                    no correct idea. He had a great store of ill-digested knowledge, not only
                    imperfect in itself, but put together on no consistent plan. His style too is
                    forced and somewhat pedantic, so that to read through and understand even a
                    single book is by no means a light task.</p>
                <p>To give an outline sketch of the <hi rend="italic">Natural History,</hi> it may
                    be said that book ii. treats of earth, stars, meteorics, and terrestrial
                    phenomena, such as earthquakes, elevation of islands, &amp;c. Books iii. to vi.
                    inclusive are devoted to a geographical account of the known <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n234/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0919-0234-0225"/> world, in giving which the author makes no
                    mention of Strabo. Book vii. contains a physical treatise on man, his form, the
                    laws of his birth, age, mental qualities, &amp;c. Book viii. treats of the
                    larger beasts, as elephants, lions, tigers, camels, descending to i nakes,
                    crocodiles, and the smaller and domesticated animals. Book ix. includes marine
                    animals of all kinds, fishes, shells, crustaceans, sponges, &amp;c. Book x. is
                    on birds, xi. on insects,—the latter half being devoted to an anatomical
                    description of animals generally. Book xii. is on trees; xiii. on their
                    products, fruit, gums, perfumes, &amp;c.; xiv. on the grape and the making of
                    wine; xv. on the olive, fig, apple, and other luscious fruits; xvi. on forest
                    trees, canes, and reeds, kinds of timber, and different ages of trees. Book
                    xvii. treats chiefly of the culture of trees, their diseases, and the arts of
                    pruning, manuring, training, &amp;c. Book xviii. is on farming and cereal crops;
                    xix. on other kinds of produce, including horticulture; XX. on the medicinal
                    properties of plants; xxi. on flowers, bees, honey, and on botanical
                    distinctions as to leaves, thorns, and times of flowering. Book xxii. treats of
                    all kinds of herbs used in medicine and in cookery; xxiii. the medicinal
                    properties of cultivated trees; xxiv. the same of forest trees, and their useful
                    products generally. (These two books are chiefly derived from Greek authorities,
                    and include the names and properties of a vast number of species.) Books XXV. to
                    xxvii. inclusive treat of the properties of plants, and these books also are
                    chiefly from Greek sources,—Cornelius Celsus being the principal Roman
                    authority. Books xxviii. to xxx. discuss the medicinal properties residing in
                    animals; xxxi. and xxxii. those in fishes. These books are full of the most
                    extraordinary and nonsensical superstitions, including discussions on magic in
                    book XXX. Book xxxiii. is on the nature and use of the precious metals; xxxiv.
                    on the different kinds of bronze, on lead, iron, and the oxides generally. Book
                    xxxv. is on the origin and practice of painting; xxxvi. on the different kinds
                    of stone and marble, including lime, sand, and gypsum; xxxvii. on precious
                    stones.</p>
                <p>It will be observed that, though there is no scientific classification in this
                    long work, a kind of sequence, not altogether unphilosophical, is observed. The
                    amount of matter and the number of subjects treated of in each book are always
                    recorded at the end of the epitome (book i.), just before the list of authors,
                    in the formula, “Summa: reset historiae et observationes <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >mdcvi.”</hi> &amp;c.; but in the medical books, in place of <hi
                        rend="italic">res,</hi> “subjects,” <hi rend="italic">medicinae,</hi>
                    “prescriptions,” is used. By <hi rend="italic">historiae</hi> he means
                    “inquiries,” or “the results of inquiries,” as distinguished from <hi
                        rend="italic">observationes,</hi> “remarks.”</p>
                <p>With all its faults, inevitable to the infant state of science, Pliny’s work is
                    an astounding monument of industry. It is believed to have been published about
                    two years before his death. He wrote, besides several other treatises,<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Three books, in six
                            volumes, were entitled “Studiosus,” and eight books bore the title
                            “Dubius Sermo.” To this last he probably refers, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Praef.</hi> § 28, “audio—Epicureos quoque parturire adversus
                            libellos quos de grammatica edidi.”</p></note> a history of the wars
                    from the first in Germany,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Bellorum Germaniae viginti (libri), quibus <hi rend="italic"
                                >omnia</hi> quae cum Germanis gessimus bella collegit (Pliny, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ep.</hi> iii. 5, § 4). A treatise on throwing the
                            lance from horseback, “De jaculatione equestri,” is mentioned here as
                            his first work, written when he was in command of a squadron of cavalry
                            (praefectus alae).</p></note> in twenty books, and a continuation of the
                    history of Aufidius Bassus down to his own times, in thirty-one books —all now
                    lost.</p>
                <p>He is said to have been a great student, an early riser, abstemious and temperate
                    in his meals.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Pliny, <hi
                                rend="italic">Bp.</hi> iii. 5, § 16; see <hi rend="italic"
                                >ibid.</hi> §§ 8-10.</p></note> In his later days he appears to have
                    grown somewhat unwieldy and asthmatic, for Pliny the younger, in describing his
                    uncle’s death by suffocation from the fumes in the eruption of Vesuvius, 79 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> says that his breathing “propter amplitudinem
                    corporis gravior et sonantior erat.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Eρist.</hi> vi. 16, § 13,</p></note>
                    Pliny’s intimate friendship with Vespasian may be inferred from his custom of
                    attending the morning levée; he seems to have first known him in the German wars
                    in the time of Claudius.</p>
                <p>Besides his published works, the elder Pliny left, as his nephew tells us, one
                    hundred and sixty note-books of extracts (electorum commentarios clx.), written
                    in a very small hand on both sides of the page. So valuable were these volumes
                    considered that Pliny assured his nephew he could have sold them in Spain for
                    £3500, even before the full number had been made up. He acted as procu rator in
                    Spain in 71, and was recalled to Rome by the death of his brother-in-law Caius
                    Caecilius, who by will appointed him guardian of the younger Pliny. At the time
                    of his death, the elder Pliny had the command of the Roman fleet at Misenum. He
                    fell a victim to his imprudent curiosity in advancing within the range of the
                    thickly-falling ashes during the eruption of Vesuvius in 79 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >a.d.</hi></p>
                <p>Pliny’s influence on the nomenclature and the popular ideas about common objects
                    long continued to be very extensive, and survived till the dawn of the age of
                    more exact science. The knowledge he gives us of the writings and opinions of so
                    large a number of lost authors opens a view of the whole cycle of the science of
                    the period.</p>
                <p>The best editions of the <hi rend="italic">Natural History</hi> are those by
                    Julius Sillig (Leipsic, 1831-36, in 5 vols. 12mo), and by Louis Janus (Teubner,
                    Leipsic, 1854-59, in 6 vols.), which is virtually a revised reprint of it, the
                    whole of the last volume being occupied with copious and accurate indices of
                    authors and subjects. These may be called critical editions; two French editions
                    with scientific commentaries had preceded,—by Hardouin (1685 and 1723), and by
                    Panckoucke (1829-33), in twenty volumes with a French translation. (F. A.
                    P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
