<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0248-0239-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PNEUMATIC DESPATCH</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 19, page 239</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:847939">Carriers</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1163601">Vacuum</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:802066">Air</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1158581">Tubes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1154445">Training</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:850806">Centrales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q64k">Carriers</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68d53">Tubes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm20">Pipe</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n248/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PNEUMATIC DESPATCH</label>. The transport of written
                    despatches through long narrow tubes by the agency of air-pressure was
                    introduced in 1853, by Mr Latimer Clark, between the Central and Stock Exchange
                    stations of the Electric and International Telegraph Company in London. The
                    stations were connected by a tube 1∣ inches in diameter and 220 yards long.
                    Carriers containing batches of telegrams, and fitting piston-wise in .the tube,
                    were sucked through it (in one direction only) by the production of a partial
                    vacuum at one end. In 1858 Mr C. F. Varley improved the system by using
                    compressed air to force the carriers in one direction, a partial vacuum being
                    still used to draw them in the other direction. This improvement enables single
                    radiating lines of pipe to be used both for sending and for receiving telegrams
                    between a central station supplied with pumping machinery and outlying stations
                    not so supplied. In the hands of Messrs Culley and Sabine this radial system of
                    pneumatic despatch has been brought to great perfection in connexion with the
                    telegraphic department of the British post office. Another method of working,
                    extensively used in Paris and other Continental cities, is the circuit system,
                    in Λvhich stations are grouped on circular or loop lines, round which carriers
                    travel in one direction only. In one form of circuit system —that of Messrs
                    Siemens—a continuous current of air is kept up in the tube, and rocking switches
                    are provided by which carriers can be quickly introduced or removed at any one
                    of the stations on the line without interfering with the movement of other
                    carriers in other parts of the circuit. More usually, however, the circuit
                    system is worked by despatching carriers, or trains of carriers, at relatively
                    long intervals, the pressure or vacuum which gives motive power being applied
                    only while such trains are on the line. On long circuits means are provided at
                    several stations for putting on pressure or vacuum, so that the action may be
                    limited to that section of the line on which the carriers are travelling at any
                    time.</p>
                <p>The following particulars refer to the radial system of pneumatic despatch as
                    used in the British post office. In London most of the lines connect the central
                    office with district offices for the purpose of collecting and distributing
                    telegrams. Iron tubes were used in some of the earliest lines, but now the tubes
                    are always made of lead, with soldered joints, and are enclosed in outer pipes
                    of iron for the sake of mechanical protection. The bore, which is very smooth
                    and uniform, is normally 2∣ inches, though in a few cases it is as much as 3
                    inches, and in some only 1⅜ inches. The greatest single length of any of the
                    existing London lines is 3873 yards, but a more usual length is from 1000 to
                    2000 yards. In most cases a single tube serves both to send and to receive, but
                    where the traffic is heavy a pair of tubes are used, one to send by pressure and
                    the other to receive by vacuum. The pumps, which supply pressure and vacuum to
                    two mains, are situated in the central office. At the outlying stations the
                    tubes terminate in a glass box, open to the atmosphere. At the central station
                    the end of each tube is a short vertical length, facing downwards, and provided
                    with a double valve, consisting of two sluices, one at the end and the other a
                    little way above the end, the distance between the sluices being somewhat longer
                    than the length of a carrier. The sluices are geared together in such a manner
                    that a single movement of a handle closes one and opens the other, or <hi
                    rend="italic">vice versa.</hi> To send a carrier from the central station, the
                    carrier is introduced into the tube, the lower sluice being open; a single
                    movement of the handle then successively (1) closes the lower sluice, (2) opens
                    the upper sluice, and (3) opens a valve which admits air behind the carrier from
                    the compressed-air main. As soon as the arrival of the carrier is signalled
                    (electrically) from the out-station, the handle is pushed back, thus (1) cutting
                    off the compressed air, (2) closing the upper sluice, and (3) opening the lower
                    sluice. The tube is then ready for the sending of another carrier. When an
                    electric signal arrives from an out-station that a carrier is inserted there for
                    transmission to the central station the handle is pulled forward<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n249/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0249-0240"/> far enough to close the lower and open the upper
                    sluice, but not far enough to put on the air-pressure. The vacuum main is then
                    put in connexion with the tube by a separate stop-cock. When the carrier arrives
                    the vacuum is shut off and the lower sluice opened to allow it to drop out. This
                    arrangement of double sluices admits of the insertion or removal of a carrier
                    while other carriers are travelling in the same tube, and without sensible
                    disturbance of their motion. But great caution requires to be exercised in
                    allowing two or more carriers to follow one another on a single section of line,
                    especially on lines worked by pressure, since no two carriers travel at
                    precisely the same speed. When the same tube is used alternately for sending and
                    receiving the upper sluice is dispensed with. On some lines there are
                    intermediate stations, and the sections are then worked by a block system like
                    that used on railways. The carriers are cylindrical cases of gutta-percha
                    covered with felt, which is allowed to project loosely at the back, so that the
                    pressure makes it expand and fit the pipe closely. In front the carrier is
                    closed by a buffer or piston composed of disks of felt of the diameter of the
                    pipe. The despatches are held in by an elastic band at the back. Λn ordinary
                    carrier weighs 2∣ oz., and holds about a dozen despatches. During business hours
                    carriers are passing through the London tubes almost incessantly. With a
                    pressure of 10 lb per square inch, or a vacuum of 7 lb, the time of transit, if
                    through a 2∣ inch tube, is 1 minute for a length of nearly 1000 yards, and 5⅛
                    minutes for a length of 3000 yards.</p>
                <p>The following statistics show the growth of the pneumatic despatch in the post
                    office during ten years (the figures for 1875 are taken from a paper by Messrs
                    Culley and Sabine, cited below, and those for 1885 have been furnished by Mr W.
                    H. Preece): —</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>-</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>January 1875.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>January 1885.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>No. of Tubes.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total Length.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>No. of Tubes.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total Length.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Miles. Yards.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Miles. Yards.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>London</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>25</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>17 1160</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>82 <hi rend="superscript">
                            1</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>33 635</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Liverpool</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 1237</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2 39</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Glasgow</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>242</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 1142</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Dublin</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>940</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 954</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Manchester...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 266</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 294</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Birmingham..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>917</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1235</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Newcastle</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>460</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>41</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>21 1242</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>108</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>40 1239</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>
                            Including</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>; 29 short “house” tubes.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In Paris large areas of the city have been covered by pneumatic circuits made up
                    of iron pipes round which omnibus trains of carriers are sent at intervals of
                    fifteen minutes. The trains consist of several carriers much heavier than the
                    English type, linked to one another and to a leading piston. The trains are
                    stopped at the successive stations to take up and deposit despatches. The
                    pneumatic despatch took root in Paris in 1866, and has been developed there in a
                    way which differs greatly in mechanical details from the English system. An
                    arrangement like that used in Paris has been followed in Vienna and in Berlin,
                    where the Siemens system has also been used. In New York the English system is
                    adopted, but with brass instead of lead tubes. «</p>
                <p>Interruptions occurring in the pipes can be localized by firing a pistol at one
                    end and registering by a chronograph the interval of time between the explosion
                    and the arrival of the air-wave reflected from the obstacle.</p>
                <p>In addition to its use for postal and telegraphic purposes the pneumatic despatch
                    is occasionally employed for internal communication in offices, hotels, &amp;c.,
                    and also in shops for the transport of money and bills between the cashier’s
                    desk and the counters.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">References.—</hi> The system as now used in the United Kingdom
                    is fully described in a paper by Messrs Culley and Sabine <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Min. Proc. Inst. Civ. Eng.,</hi> vol. xliii.). The same volume contains a
                    description of the pneumatic telegraphs of Paris and of experiments on them by
                    Μ. Bontemps, and also a discussion of the theory of pneumatic transmission by
                    Prof. W. C. Unwin. Reference should also be made to a paper by C. Siemens <hi
                    rend="italic">(Min.</hi><hi rend="italic">Proc. Inst. Civ. Eng.,</hi> vol.
                    xxxiii.) describing the Siemens circuit system; and to <hi rend="italic"
                    >Les</hi><hi rend="italic">Télégraphes,</hi> by Μ. A. L. Ternant (Paris, 1881).
                    (J. A. E.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
