<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0919-0092-0083-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">PIETISM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 19, page 83</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms0f">Pulpits</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v41r">Heart</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f8z">Faith</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s33k">Creeds</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bv7b36b">Reformers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1063905">Pietism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1083880">Pulpits</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:953493">Heart</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198492">Faith</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n92/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PIETISM</label>. Pietism is the name of an exceedingly
                    influential, instructive, and interesting movement in the Lutheran Church which
                    arose towards the end of the 17th and continued during the first half of the
                    following century. The name of Pietists was given to the adherents of the
                    movement by its enemies, as a term of ridicule, like that of “Methodists”
                    somewhat later in England. The origin and nature of the movement itself may be
                    both traced to defects in the Lutheran Church of the time and to isolated
                    efforts to correct them. That church had in the 17th century become a
                    creed-bound theological and sacramentarian institution, which orthodox
                    theologians ruled with almost the absolutism of the papacy. Correctness of creed
                    had taken the place of deep religious feeling and purity of life. Christian
                    faith had been dismissed from its seat in the heart, where Luther had placed it,
                    to the cold regions of the intellect. The dogmatic formularies of the Lutheran
                    Church had usurped the position which Luther himself had assigned to the Bible
                    alone, and as a consequence they only were studied and preached, while the Bible
                    was neglected in the family, the study, the pulpit, and the university. Instead
                    of advocating the priesthood of all believers, so powerfully proclaimed by
                    Luther, the Lutheran pastors had made themselves a despotic hierarchy, while
                    they neglected the practical pastoral work of caring for the moral and spiritual
                    welfare of their flocks. One of the consequences, as the Pietists believed, of
                    all this was that immorality, irréligion, and heathenish ignorance of
                    Christianity abounded in the land, and cried to heaven against an unfaithful
                    church. As forerunners of the Pietists in the strict sense, not a few earnest
                    and powerful voices had been heard bewailing the shortcomings of the church and
                    advocating a revival of practical and devout Christianity. Amongst them were
                    Jacob Boehme (Bemen), the theosophic mystic; Johann Arndt, whose principal
                    devotional work on <hi rend="italic">True Christianity</hi> is universally known
                    and appreciated; Heinrich Müller, who described the font, the pulpit, the
                    confessional, and the altar as the four dumb idols of the Lutheran Church; the
                    theologian Johann Valentin Andrea, the court chaplain of the landgrave of Hesse;
                    Schuppius, who sought to restore to the Bible its place in the pulpit; and
                    Theophilus Grossgebauer of Rostock, who from his pulpit and by his writings
                    raised “the alarm cry of a watchman in Sion.” The direct originator of the
                    movement was Philip Jacob Spener. Born in Alsace January 13, 1635, as a child
                    trained in piety under the influence of a devout godmother and books of devotion
                    recommended by her, particularly Arndt’s <hi rend="italic">True
                    Christianity,</hi> accustomed to hear the sermons of a pastor who preached the
                    Bible more than the Lutheran creeds, he was early convinced of the necessity of
                    a moral and religious reformation of the German church. He studied theology,
                    with a view to the Christian ministry, at Strasburg, where the professors at the
                    time were more inclined to practical Christianity than to theological
                    disputation. He afterwards spent a year in Geneva, and was powerfully influenced
                    by the strict moral life and rigid ecclesiastical discipline prevalent there,
                    and also by the preaching and the piety of the Waldensian professor Antoine
                    Leger and the converted Jesuit preacher Jean de Labadie. During a stay in
                    Tübingen he read Grossgebauer’s <hi rend="italic">Alarm Cry,</hi> and in 1666 he
                    entered upon his first pastoral charge at Frankfort-on-the-Main, profoundly
                    impressed with a sense of the danger of the Christian life being sacrificed to
                    zeal for rigid orthodoxy. Pietism, as a distinct movement in the German church,
                    was then originated by Spener by religious meetings at his house <hi
                    rend="italic">(collegia</hi><hi rend="italic">pietatis),</hi> at which he
                    repeated his sermons, expounded passages of the New Testament, and induced those
                    present to join in conversation on religious questions that arose. These
                    meetings were largely attended, produced a great sensation, and were soon
                    imitated elsewhere. They gave rise to the name “Pietists.” In 1675 Spener
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Pia Desideria,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Earnest
                    Desires for a Reform of the True Evangelical Church,</hi> the public literary
                    exposition and defence of his position and aims. In this publication Spener made
                    six proposals as the best means of restoring the life of the church :—(1) the
                    earnest cultivation of a more general and thorough familiarity with the Holy
                    Scriptures by means of private meetings, <hi rend="italic">ecclesiolae</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">ecclesia·,</hi> (2) a practical carrying
                    out of the principle of the universality of the Christian priesthood by a
                    participation of the laity in the spiritual government of the church and by the
                    holding of family worship; (3) a serious laying to heart of the fact that a
                    knowledge of Christianity must be attended by the practice of it as its
                    indispensable sign and supplement; (4) the conversion of the habit of making
                    merely didactic, and often bitter, attacks on the heterodox and unbelievers into
                    a treatment of them instigated by genuine affection and animated by the simple
                    desire of doing them good; (5) a reorganization of the theological training of
                    the universities, in such a way that young divines should be urged not only to
                    diligence in their studies but above all to lead devout lives; and (6) a
                    different style of preaching, namely, in the place of pleasing rhetoric, the
                    implanting of Christianity in the inner or new man, the sold of which is faith,
                    and its effects the fruits of life. This work produced a great impression
                    throughout Germany. Although large numbers of the orthodox Lutheran theologians
                    and pastors were deeply offended by it, its complaint and its demands were both
                    too well justified to admit of their being pointblank denied. A large number of
                    pastors at once practically adopted Spener’s proposals. In 1686 Spener accepted
                    an appointment to the court-chaplaincy at Dresden, which opened to him a wider
                    though more difficult sphere of labour. He succeeded in reviving the
                    catechetical instruction of the young in religious truth in Saxony. In Leipsic,
                    where Scriptural exegesis had almost wholly disappeared, a society of young
                    theologians was formed under his influence, for the learned study and devout
                    application of the Bible. Three <hi rend="italic">magistri</hi> belonging to
                    that society, one of whom was August Hermann Francke, subsequently the founder
                    of one of the noblest works of Pietism—the orphanage at Halle—commenced courses
                    of expository lectures on the Scriptures of a practical and devotional character
                    and in the German language, which were zealously frequented by both students and
                    townsmen. The lectures aroused, however, the ill-will of the other theologians
                    and pastors of Leipsic, and their promoters, charged with having slighted the
                    established worship of the land as well as true learning, were ordered to
                    discontinue them. Francke and his friends left the city, and with the aid of
                    Christian Thomasius and Spener founded the new university of Halle, which became
                    the chief home of the Pietists, and the object of the jealousy and unsparing
                    attacks of the older universities of Wittenberg and Leipsic. The theological
                    chairs in the new university were filled in complete conformity with Spener’s
                    proposals. The main difference between the new Pietistic school and the orthodox
                    Lutherans was not one affecting doctrine directly, inasmuch as Spener adhered in
                    every point to the Lutheran faith. The difference arose from his conception of
                    Christianity as chiefly consisting in a change of heart and consequent holiness
                    of life, while the orthodox Lutherans <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit19newyrich/page/n93/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0919-0093-0084"/> of the time made it to consist mainly in
                    correctness of doctrine. At the same time, the greater importance which he
                    attached to the religious life and to practical godliness than to correctness of
                    belief, and his restoration of the Bible to its place of superiority over the
                    creeds, involved numerous possible departures from and advances beyond the
                    Lutheranism of the 17th century. Again, the earnestness with which he had
                    insisted on the necessity of a new birth, and on a separation of Christians from
                    the world, led to exaggeration and fanaticism among followers less distinguished
                    than himself for wisdom and moderation. Many Pietists soon maintained that the
                    new birth must always be preceded by agonies of repentance, and that only a
                    regenerated theologian could teach theology, while the whole school shunned all
                    common worldly amusements, such as dancing, the theatre, and public games, and
                    affected a severe austerity with regard to dress, meals, and conversation.
                    Through these extravagances a reactionary movement arose at the beginning of the
                    18th century, one of the most distinguished leaders of which was Loescher,
                    superintendent at Dresden. But it was only as the opponents of Pietism gradually
                    ceased their attacks that the movement lost its strength and by degrees handed
                    over its vital truths and truest work to various representatives of a new and
                    better age of the church. As a distinct movement it had run its course before
                    the middle of the 18th century. The spirit of the school of Spener long made
                    itself felt amongst the Protestants of north and south Germany, and particularly
                    at Halle. Pietism could claim to have contributed largely to the revival of
                    Biblical studies in Germany, and to have given a Biblical basis once more to
                    theology. It also made religion once more an affair of the heart and the life,
                    and not merely of the intellect, to which theologians had reduced it. It
                    likewise vindicated afresh the rights of the Christian laity in regard to their
                    own beliefs and the work of the church, against the assumptions and despotism of
                    an arrogant clergy. It thus revived eternal elements of Christianity that had
                    been long neglected, and was a distinct agent in preparing the way for modern
                    advance in religion and theology. But it sprang from a temporary necessity, and,
                    like similar phases of Christian life, lacked the philosophical and scholarly
                    depth, the human and secular breadth, and the progressive impetus of a permanent
                    and world-subduing religious movement.</p>
                <p>The two most recent German writers on the history of Pietism— Heppe and
                    Ritschl—have given a much wider meaning to the term, including under it nearly
                    all religious tendencies amongst Protestants of the last three centuries in the
                    direction of a more serious cultivation of personal piety than that prevalent in
                    the various established churches, and manifesting itself particularly in the
                    ascetic shunning of “worldly” practices. The term then embraces the Anabaptist,
                    Moravian, Metnodistic, and other kindred tendencies of the religious life, which
                    are generally regarded rather as simply related than genetically connected
                    phenomena. Ritschl, too, treats Pietism as a retrograde movement of Christian
                    life towards Catholicism. It is also customary with some German writers to speak
                    of a later or modern Pietism, characterizing thereby a party in the German
                    church which was probably at first influenced by some remains of Spener’s
                    Pietism in Westphalia, on the Rhine, in Würtemberg, and at Halle and Berlin, and
                    which at the commencement worked to some extent on the lines of the earlier
                    movement. The party was chiefly distinguished by its opposition to an
                    independent scientific study of theology, its principal theological leader being
                    Hengstenberg, and its chief literary organ the <hi rend="italic">Evangelische
                    Kirchenzeitung.</hi> The party originated at the close of the wars with Napoleon
                    I.</p>
                <p>Amongst older works on Pietism are Walch’s <hi rend="italic">Historische und
                    theologische Einleitung in die Religionstreitigkeiten der
                    Evangelisch-Lutherischen Kirche,</hi> 1730; Tholuck’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geschichte des Pietismus und des ersten Stadiums der Aufklärung,</hi> 1865; II.
                    Schmid, <hi rend="italic">Die Geschichte des Pietismus,</hi> 1863; Goebel's <hi
                    rend="italic">Geschichte des christlichen Lebens in der Rheinisch-Westfälischen
                    Kirche,</hi> 3 vols., 1849-60; and the subject is dealt with at length in
                    Domer’s and Gass’s <hi rend="italic">Histories</hi> of Protestant theology. The
                    two chief recent works which use the term in the wider sense just referred to
                    are Heppe'β <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Pietismus und der Mystik in der
                    reformirten Kirche,</hi> (1879) which is sympathetic, and RitβchΓs <hi
                    rend="italic">Geschichte des Pietismus</hi> (vol. i. only yet published, 1880),
                    which is hostile. See also Nippold's article in <hi rend="italic">Theol.
                    Stud,</hi><hi rend="italic">und Kritiken,</hi> 1882, pp. 347-392∙ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> and Riggenbach ’ s article, “Pietismus,” in Herzog's
                    <hi rend="italic">Encyklopädie,</hi> 2d ed. (J. F. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
