<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-9650-0795-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOOTH, Barton</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163799">Valentinians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:893060">Didos</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1910079">Prompters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796296">Actors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m5h">Actors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193199650?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BOOTH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Barton</hi></label>, a
                    celebrated English actor, born in Lancashire in 1681, and educated in
                    Westminster school under the celebrated Dr Bushby, where his success in the
                    Latin plays customarily performed by the scholars gave him an inclination for
                    the stage. He was intended for the church; but having run away from school to
                    Dublin, he there commenced actor. His first appearance was in the part of
                    Oroonoko, in which he obtained the most flattering testimonials of approbation
                    from the audience. From this time he continued daily improving; and after two
                    successful campaigns in Ireland, conceived thoughts <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193199663?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-9663-0796"/>of
                    returning to his native country, and making a trial of his abilities on the
                    English stage. To this end he first reconciled himself to his friends; and then,
                    as a further step towards insuring success, he obtained from Lord Fitzharding,
                    one of the lords of the bed-chamber to Prince George of Denmark, a
                    recommendation to Mr Betterton, who, with great candour and good nature, took
                    him under his care, and gave him all the assistance in his power. The first part
                    Mr Booth appeared in at London was that of Maximus in Lord Rochester’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Valentinian,</hi> his reception in which exceeded even his
                    most sanguine expectations; and soon afterwards his performance of Artaban, in
                    Rowe’s <hi rend="italic">Ambitious Stepmother,</hi> a new tragedy, established
                    his reputation as only second to his great instructor. Pyrrhus, in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Distressed Mother,</hi> was another part in which he shone
                    without a rival. But he was indebted to a happy coincidence of merit and chance
                    for that height of fame which he at length attained in the character of Cato, as
                    drawn by Mr Addison. For this play being considered as a party one, the W <hi
                        rend="superscript"> τ</hi> higs, in favour of whose principles it was
                    apparently written, thought it their duty to support it strongly; while at the
                    same time the Tories, who had too much sense to appear to consider it as a
                    reflection on their administration, were still more vehement in their
                    approbation, which they carried to such a height as even to make a collection of
                    fifty guineas in the boxes during the performance, and present it to Mr Booth,
                    with this compliment, “that it was a slight acknowledgment~for his honest
                    opposition to a perpetual dictator, and his dying so bravely in the cause of
                    liberty.” Besides this, he had a present of an equal sum from the managers, in
                    consideration of the extraordinary success of the play, which they attributed in
                    a great measure to his merit in the performance; and it is certain that no one
                    since that time has ever equalled, or even approached, his excellence in this
                    character. But these were not the only advantages which accrued to Mr Booth from
                    his success in this part; for Lord Bolingbroke, then one of the principal
                    secretaries of state, soon after procured a special license from Queen Anne,
                    recalling all the former ones, and nominating Mr Booth joint manager with
                    Wilkes, Cibber, and Dogget. None of these persons, however, was satisfied with
                    the arrangement; and the last especially took such disgust as to withdraw
                    himself from any further share in the management. In 1704 Mr Booth married a
                    daughter of Sir William Barkham, Bart, who died in 1710, without issue. But
                    being fully established in the management, he once more turned his thoughts
                    towards matrimony, and, in the year 1719, united himself to the celebrated Miss
                    Hester Santlow, a woman of a most amiable disposition, whose great merit as an
                    actress, added to the utmost discretion and prudential economy, had enabled her
                    to save a considerable fortune. During the twenty years in which Mr Booth
                    continued a manager, the theatre was in the greatest credit; and his illness and
                    death, which happened on the 10th of May 1733, contributed not a little to its
                    decline.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr Booth wrote a dramatic entertainment called <hi rend="italic">Dido
                        and AEneas;</hi> but his masterpiece was a Latin inscription to the memory
                    of Mr William Smith, a promising actor, who died while young. As an actor, his
                    excellency lay wholly in tragedy; nor was he able to endure any parts but those
                    which had strong passion to inspire him; and even in this walk, dignity rather
                    than ease, rage rather than tenderness, seemed to be his forte. Some idea of his
                    abilities may be formed from the description Mr Cibber has given of Booth in his
                    Apology, and from the character drawn of him by Aaron Hill, in a political paper
                    called the <hi rend="italic">Prompter,</hi> which may be seen at length in
                    Cibber’s <hi rend="italic">Lives of the Poets,</hi> and Chetwood’s <hi
                        rend="italic">History of the Stage·</hi> His character as á man was adorned
                    with many amiable qualities, among which goodness of heart, the basis of almost
                    every virtue, was remarkably conspicuous.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
