<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-6764-0573-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BENTINCK, William Henry Cavendish</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:933481">Foxes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836750">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1094658">Rent</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193196764?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BENTINCK, <hi rend="smallcaps">William Henry
                            Cavendish</hi></label>, third duke of Portland, was born on the 14th of
                    April 1738. Having finished his education at Christ Church, Oxford, he went on
                    his travels. Soon after his return he was elected for the borough of Weobly, in
                    the first parliament of the king’s reign. For this borough, however, he did not
                    sit long; for, on the death of his father, on the 1st of May 1762, he was called
                    up to the house of peers. He immediately joined the opposition; and, in 1763,
                    his name is found among the minority against the cider bill, and along with that
                    of the duke of Grafton in a pro’test against it. The next session he also signed
                    a protest on the motion to vote away the privilege claimed by members of
                    parliament in matters of libel. In 1765, when his friend the marquis' of
                    Rockingham came into power, he was appointed lord chamberlain, and he retired
                    when the marquis went out of office. In 1768 there was a violent contest for the
                    county of Cumberland; and as the duke warmly supported the two opposition
                    candidates, the ministry, in order to weaken his influence, and at the same time
                    to increase that of Sir James Lowther, who was one of the ministerial
                    candidates, granted to the latter Inglewood forest, an extensive and valuable
                    estate, which had been granted by King William III. to the first duke of
                    Portland, and had remained in possession of that family ever since. The new
                    grant was made in consequence of a report from the surveyor-gene··</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193196777?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-6777-0574"/>
                <p part="N">ral of erown lands, that the premises were not comprised in the original
                    grant from King W’illiam to the duke of Portland, but were still vested in the
                    erown. A letter was written from the treasury, directing the duke to prepare his
                    title, and assuring him that nothing should be deeided concerning the grant till
                    such title had been stated and maturely considered: but while his graee’s agents
                    were busily employed in their researches and inquiries, he received a seeond
                    letter, informing him that the grants were passed and the leases signed. A
                    eaveat had been entered at the exchequer to stop the progress of the grant; but
                    when Lord North was prayed to withhold affixing the exchequer seal, he replied
                    that, as chancellor of the exchequer, he was bound to obey the orders of the
                    treasury. On the 19th of November 1771 this great cause was tried before the
                    barons of the exchequer in Westminster Hall. The court reeited all the records
                    and prerogatives of the crown, from Edward I. to the lease made to Sir James
                    Lowther; when, after a full and impartial examination of the said lease, it was
                    found invalid, agreeably to the statute of the 1st of Anne, whieh expressly
                    requires that, upon every grant from the crown, there shall be a reserved rent,
                    not under the third part of the elear yearly value of the manors, lands, &amp;c.
                    as shall be contained in the grant. Sir James Lowther’s grant from the erown,
                    being only a quit-rent of 13s. 4d. for the whole of Inglewood forest, was
                    immediately determined by the eourt an inadequate third proportion, and he was
                    nonsuited aeeordingly. The. <hi rend="italic">nullum tempus</hi> bill, or the
                    aet for quieting the possessions of the subjeet against all pretenees of
                    concealment whatsoever, which was brought into parliament in 1768, and passed in
                    the following year, owed its rise to this grant of the Portland property to Sir
                    James Lowther.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1766 the duke of Portland had been bound more closely than ever to
                    the Roękingham party, in eonsequence of his marriage with Lady Dorothy
                    Cavendish, sister to the duke of Devonshire. On the resignation of Lord North he
                    was appointed lord-lieutenant of Ireland; and during his government the
                    parliament of that eountry was declared independent of the British parliament.
                    After an administration of somewhat more than three months he was recalled, when
                    Lord Shelburne eame into power. On the death of the marquis of Roękingham he was
                    recommended by the privy eouneil to the king as his successor at the Treasury;
                    but Lord Shelburne was preferred. When the coalition eame into power, however,
                    he obtained the situation of prime minister, and went out of office with them.
                    During Mr Pitt’s difficulties, when he first eame into administration, in
                    eonsequenee of the house of eommons being against him, an attempt was made to
                    form a eoalition between him and the duke of Portland; but his graee objeeted to
                    the conditions on whieh Mr Pitt eame into power, and refused his support unless
                    he would resign his plaee and come in again on equal terms with himself and his
                    friends.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1792 he was elected chancellor of the university of Oxford; and soon
                    afterwards he, as well as several other friends of Mr Fox, who differed from
                    that statesman respecting the Freneh revolution, left the opposition and joined
                    the ministry. Upon this he was appointed lord-lieutenant of the eounty of
                    Nottingham, and, in 1794, secretary of state for the home department. The
                    scareity and high priee of provisions, and the state-trials, which oeeurred soon
                    after he beeame seeretary of state, rendered his office arduous and unpleasant.
                    He discharged his duty, however, under these eircumştanees, with moderation, and
                    with acknowledged good intentions, though not always perhaps with vigour and
                    judgment. He continued seeretary of state till Mr Addington beeame prime
                    minister in 1801, when he exchanged this situation for the more easy duty of
                    president of the couneil. On the death of Mr Pitt, and the appointment of Lord
                    Grenville and Mr Fox to the ministry, in the spring of 1806, he was removed from
                    the presidentship of the eouneil; but he was again ealled into publie life, and
                    plaeed at the head of the treasury, in March 1807, when Lord Grenville’s
                    administration elosed. His Graee, however, though nominally the prime minister,
                    was too infirm to take an aetive part in the high and arduous duties of this
                    situation, which were discharged almost entirely by Mr Pereeval, the ehaneellor
                    őf the exchequer. He eontinued nominally the first lord of the treasury till a
                    very short time before his death, whieh happened on the 30th of OEtober
                    1809.</p>
                <p part="N">The abilities of his grace were certainly but moderate, and very far
                    inferior to those whieh he must have possessed had he been, as latterly there
                    has been an attempt to prove, the author of <hi rend="italic">Junius's
                        Letters;</hi> but his understanding was good, and he was by no means
                    unwilling or unable to give regular attention to official business. His
                    political integrity was never questioned, even by the party he abandoned.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
