<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-5204-0453-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BATTERY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02z952">Cannon</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs5x">Gun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ng4gw65">Gunning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838255">Breast</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925173">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193195204?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BATTERY</label>, in the military art, any place
                    where cannon or mortars are mounted, either to attack the forces of the enemy or
                    to batter a fortification; and hence batteries have various names, according to
                    the purposes which they are designed to effect.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Gun-Battery</hi> is a defence constructed of earth
                    faced with green sods or fascines, sometimes of gabiöns filled with earth. It
                    consists of a breast-work, epaulement, or parapet, about 8 feet in height, and
                    18 or 20 feet in thickness, with a ditch 12 feet broad at the bottom, 18 at the
                    top, and 7 feet in depth. The open spaces through which the muzzles of the
                    cannon are pointed are called <hi rend="italic">embrasures,</hi> and the solid
                    masses between the embrasures, <hi rend="italic">merlons.</hi> The distance from
                    the centre of one embrasure to that of another is 18 feet, and this is also the
                    distance at which the guns are placed from each other; consequently the merlons
                    are 16 feet within and 7 without. The <hi rend="italic">genouillères,</hi> or
                    those parts of the parapet which cover the carriage of the gun, are generally
                    made 2∣ feet in height from the platform to the opening of the embrasures; but
                    this height must be regulated by the semi-diameter of the wheels of the carriage
                    and the nature of the gun. The platforms are plank floors made to prevent the
                    cannon from sinking into the ground, and they are generally 18 feet in length,
                    15 feet in breadth behind, and 9 feet before, with a rise of nine or ten inches
                    from the parapet to check the recoil of the guns, and to render it more easy to
                    bring them forward again when loaded.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Mortar-Batteries</hi> differ from gun-batteries in
                    this, that the parapets have no embrasures, and the platforms have no slope, but
                    are exactly horizontal; the shells being fired quite over the parapet, commonly
                    at an elevation <hi rend="italic">of</hi> 45 degrees.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Open Battery</hi> is a number of cannon, commonly
                    field pieces, ranged in a row abreast, on some natural elevation of ground, or
                    on an artificial bank raised for the purpose.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Covered</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Masked Battery</hi>
                    is when the cannon and gunners are covered by a bank or breast-work, commonly
                    made of brushwood, faggots, and earth.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Sunk</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Buried Battery</hi> is
                    when the platform is sunk or let down into the ground, so that trenches must be
                    cut m the earth opposite the muzzles of the guns, to serve as embrasures to fire
                    through.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Cross-Batteries</hi> are two batteries which play
                    athwart each other upon the same object, forming there an angle, and battering
                    with more effect, because what one battery shakes, the other beats down.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Battery d'Eηβlade</hi> is one that sweeps or scours
                    the whole length of a straight line, or the face or flank of any work.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Battery en Echarpe</hi> is that which plays
                    obliquely.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Battery de Reverse</hi> is one which plays upon the
                    rear of the troops appointed to defend a place.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Canιeτade Battery</hi> is when several guns are
                    discharged upon one point at the same instant.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Redan Batteries</hi> are such as flank each other at
                    the sa- <hi rend="superscript"> 16</hi> p. <hi rend="superscript"> an</hi> d
                    re-entrant angles of a fortification.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Ricochet Battery,</hi> so called by its inventor M.
                    Vauban, was ffist <hi rend="superscript"> l</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript">
                        se</hi> d <hi rend="superscript"> at</hi> ^ <hi rend="superscript"> ιe</hi>
                    siege of AEth in 1697. It is a me-</p>
                <p part="N">°d of discharging cannon with a very small charge of powder, and with
                    just elevation enough to fire over the parapet. When properly managed, its
                    effects are most destructive; for the shot, rolling along the opposite rampart,
                    dismounts the cannon and disperses or destro∙ s the troops. Ricochet practice is
                    not confined to cannon alone: small mortars and howitzers may be effectually
                    employed for the same purpose.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Fascine</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gabion
                        Batteries</hi> are batteries constructed of those machines where sods are
                    scarce, and the earth very loose or sandy.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Battery,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> is the
                    unlawful beating of another. The least touching of another’s person wilfully, or
                    in anger, is a battery, for the law cannot draw the line between different
                    degrees of violence, and therefore totally prohibits the first and lowest stage
                    of it; every man’s person being sacred, and no other having a right to meddle
                    with it, in any the slightest manner. Upon a similar principle, the Cornelian
                    law <hi rend="italic">de injuriis</hi> prohibited <hi rend="italic"
                        >pulsation</hi> as well as <hi rend="italic">verbération;</hi>
                    distinguishing verberation, which was accompanied with pain, from pulsation,
                    which was attended with none. But battery is in some cases justifiable or
                    lawful; as where one having authority,a parentor master, bestows moderate
                    correction on his child, his scholar, or his apprentice. It is justifiable on
                    the principle of self-defence; for if one man strikes another, or only assaults
                    him, the latter may strike in his own defence, and if sued for it, may plead
                    that it was the plaintiff’s own original assault which occasioned it. It is
                    likewise justifiable in defence of goods or possession, and in the exercise of
                    an office, as that of church-warden or beadle; but the person pleading such
                    justification in a civil suit, or in a criminal prosecution, must be prepared to
                    instruct that he has observed the <hi rend="italic">moderamen inculpatoe
                        tuteloe.</hi> By reason of these and other grounds of justification, battery
                    is defined the unlawful beating of another; and the remedy is, as for assault,
                    by action of trespass or damages, in -which the jury will or ought to give
                    adequate compensation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
