<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-6829-0578-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BERBICE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204607">Suriname</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193196829?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BERBICE</label> is a colony belonging to the
                    British, situated on the banks of the river of the same name, in the province of
                    Guiana, in South America. The latitude of the mouth of the river Berbice is 6.
                    20. N. and its longitude 57. 11. W. from London. The plantations are situated on
                    each side of the river, and extend nearly 300 miles from its entrance.
                    Previously to the year 1799 this colony was bounded on the east by the Devil’s
                    Creek, and on the west by Abarry Creek, which separated it f <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ronl</hi> Demerary, its breadth being then 30 miles; but
                    when Surinam surrendered to the British in that year, a négociation was entered
                    into between the governors of these two colonies, by which Surinam conceded to
                    Berbιcet∏θ tract of country between the Devil’s Creek and the r∏er Courantine,
                    thus increasing its breadth to about CO miles. The sea-coast and the west bank
                    of the Courantine were immediately surveyed and laid out into regular
                    allotments· The extent of this colony was further enlarged by t British, who
                    cleared and embanked from the sea the who e line of coast between the Dcmerary
                    and the Courantmθ&gt; forming upon it a carriage-road sixty feet broad, wιth∙sι
                        <pb break="no" facs="nls:193196842?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0704-6842-0579"/>feet parapets on each side for the convenience
                    of travelling·</p>
                <p part="N">Previously to this improvement the face of the country resembled that of
                    the rest of Guiana. On the shores there was a border of low ground, between high
                    and low-water marks, covered with mangroves. When the tide flowed, this border
                    had several feet of water over it; and when it ebbed it presented an
                    inaccessible mud-bank. This is now rendered dry and productive. Behind this
                    border of mangroves, at the distance of 400 or 500 paces, commence low, level,
                    swampy savannahs, formed by the rains, which are prolonged in the direction of
                    the coast, with a depth more or less considerable, according to the distance of
                    the mountains. This part of the colony was almost entirely neglected by the
                    Dutch, who fixed their principal plantations in the more elevated and interior
                    part of the country.</p>
                <p part="N">The year is here divided into two dry and two wet seasons; light showers
                    begin to refresh the land about the middle of April; the rain increases till the
                    middle of June, when it falls in torrents; at the beginning of July these heavy
                    rains begin to decrease; and in August the long dry season begins, and continues
                    till November. December and January constitute the short rainy season, and
                    February and March the short dry season. The land winds prevail during the two
                    wet seasons, and are unhealthy; in the dry season the air is refreshed by
                    regular diurnal sea-breezes. The temperature of this colony is not so great as
                    might be expected from its latitude; the thermometer very seldom rises to 91°;
                    during May, June, and July, it generally varies between 83° and 84°; and the
                    lowest degree is about 75°. The weather always changes very gradually.</p>
                <p part="N">There are two rivers in this colony, the Berbice and the Canje. The
                    former runs from south to north, and discharges itself into the Atlantic Ocean.
                    The coast on each side of it forms a bay at its entrance, which is nearly a mile
                    in width, having a small island in the middle, called Crab Island, from the
                    number of land-crabs on it; and the entrance itself is protected by three forts,
                    but they are of little use, as Berbice must, from its situation, always follow
                    the fate of Demerary. Without the entrance of the river is a bar of sand, over
                    which at high tide there is seldom more than eighteen feet of water; but within,
                    the water is of sufficient depth, and the river is navigable for ships of burden
                    200 miles from its mouth. On account of the bar, however, few vessels rendezvous
                    here, but anchor off the port of Demerary. The river Canje is narrow, but deep,
                    running at first nearly from south to north, but afterwards diverging to the
                    west, till it falls into the Berbice about a mile from the sea. It is navigable
                    for colony schooners thirty miles up. At its head are immense falls, and about
                    forty miles below there is a creek which connects it with the Courantine. In
                    this route, and by means of this creek, dispatches are brought from Surinam to
                    Berbice by the Indians. All the water on the coast of Berbice is brackish. The
                    rain-water, which lodges in the low parts of the forests, called bush-water, is
                    collected by the Indians for the purposes of drinking and cooking. The forests
                    are extensive, and contain many very large trees. ŋ <hi rend="superscript">
                        r</hi> Pinckard describes an enormous tree of the Tonquin bean, the body of
                    which rose perpendicularly to the height θf between seventy and eighty feet
                    before it threw out a smgle branch.</p>
                <p part="N">The only towns in this colony are Old Amsterdam, and Fort Nassau or New
                    Amsterdam. The former is said by Bolingbroke to be fifty miles up the river
                    Berbice, but Dr Bancroft places it at 100 miles from the mouth. The
                    inconveniences attendant on this situation of Old Amsterdam were so numerous and
                    obvious, arising chiefly from the uncertain and intricate navigation of the
                    river, that, in the year 1766, when Dr Bancroft visited Guiana, it was resolved
                    to remove the seat of government to a point of land on the eastern shore of the
                    Berbice, about a mile from its entrance, formed between that river and the
                    Canje. So slow, however, were the Dutch in their operations, that New Amsterdam,
                    for so this town was called, was scarcely begun in the year 1796, when Berbice
                    capitulated to the English. Under the greater activity of the conquerors, New
                    Amsterdam soon assumed the size and appearance of the capital of the colony. It
                    is situated on the south side of the Canje; and the houses extend up the banks
                    of the Berbicc about a mile and a half, facing the water. The Dutch, in laying
                    out the town, paid particular attention to health and convenience. Round each
                    allotment there are trenches, which fill and empty themselves every tide, so
                    that all the filth is carried off before it stagnates and becomes unwholesome.
                    Each lot contains a quarter of an acre of land; and a free circulation of air,
                    as well as ground for a kitchen-garden, is thus secured to the inhabitants. The
                    houses are very long and narrow, and not more than a storey and a half high,
                    with galleries on each side to protect them from the sun. Those inhabited by the
                    Dutch are thatched with troolie<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p part="N">The troolies are perhaps the largest leaves
                            that have been hitherto discovered in any part of the world. Each leaf
                            is supported y a single stem, which arises immediately from the root,
                            and becomes the middle rib to the leaf, these stems are hard and strong,
                            and about three inches in circumference near the root. Each leaf is from
                            twenty to thirty feet in length, and from two to three feet <hi
                                rend="superscript"> ιn</hi> breadth. They will effectually exclude
                            the most violent rains, and last for many years.</p></note> and plantain
                    leaves, which they prefer to shingles on account of coolness; but the English
                    shingle their houses, from their dislike of the insects and vermin which the
                    troolie and plantain leaves harbour. The government-house and colonial offices
                    are built of brick, in the European style, and with considerable pretensions to
                    architectural taste and magnificence.</p>
                <p part="N">Before Berbice surrendered to the British, in 1796, almost all the
                    plantations were at a distance from the coast, considerably up the banks of the
                    Berbice and the Canje; but within a very short time after the colony came into
                    our possession, the plantations were greatly extended. The west coast was first
                    cultivated; and, in the year 1799, that to the eastward of the river Berbice, as
                    far as the Devil’s Creek, was cleared and cultivated. This part was surveyed and
                    cut into two parallel lines of estates, with a navigable canal between them for
                    the convenience of watercarriage. Behind the second row of estates runs the
                    river Canje, both the banks of which are cultivated with sugar, coffee, and
                    plantains. The estates are distinguished as follows: those on the line facing
                    the sea are the coast estates; the second line consists of the canal estates;
                    and the remainder are called the Canje estates. Besides these there are valuable
                    and extensive plantations on each side of the Berbice, stretching, as has been
                    already mentioned, nearly 300 miles from its mouth. The principal and most
                    valuable productions of the colony are sugar, coffee, cocoa, tobacco, cotton,
                    and the arnotta or roucou shrub. This last was, for a considerable time after
                    the settlement of the colony, cultivated almost exclusively by the Indians; they
                    macerated its seed in the juice of lemons, in which the gum of the manna-tree
                    had been dissolved, and thus obtained the celebrated Indian pigment, or crimson
                    paint, with which they adorned their bodies.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193196855?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-6855-0580"/>
                <p part="N">The roucou is now cultivated by the Dutch and English planters as a
                    dye-stuff. Cotton thrives best on the coast estates, and it is on these
                    therefore that it is principally cultivated. The sugar plantations are esteemed
                    the most valuable.</p>
                <p part="N">Agriculture, and all other labour in Berbice, is almost wholly performed
                    by negroes. It is estimated that, on an average, there are about 200 slaves,
                    calculated at the value of from L.50 to L.100 each, employed in producing
                    annually 140,000 cwts. of coffee, and 10,000 cwts∙ of cocoa. The Indians who
                    inhabit this part of the South American coast consist of four tribes; and from
                    these, particularly the tribe of the Arrowaucs, the inhabitants derive some
                    assistance, as a few of them reside on almost every plantation, and are employed
                    in various services, particularly in hunting and fishing. They have no animals
                    domesticated, nor any grain or roots, except the cassada, brought into
                    cultivation. A small species of deer, which somewhat resembles the hare, and the
                    armadillo, are their favourite food. They scald off the fur of the deer, cut the
                    body in pieces, and stew it in cassada juice, seasoning it very highly with
                    capsicum. The weapons they employ are the common bow and arrow, and the poisoned
                    arrow, which they blow from a tube. Their accuracy and skill in using both these
                    is surprising. With the common arrow, which is formed of a reed nearly six feet
                    long, they can hit a chicken with tolerable certainty at nearly 100 yards
                    distance. The poisoned arrow they can shoot from a tube of about seven feet in
                    length, to the distance of eight or ten yards, with great accuracy; and, at
                    twelve or fourteen feet distance, they seldom fail in striking the edge of a
                    penknife stuck on the back of a chair. The plants from which this poison is
                    extracted are not known.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr Bolingbroke states that the negro population of Berbice was doubled
                    within ten years after it came into the possession of the English; and that, in
                    1805, it amounted to about 40,000, besides 1000 free people of colour and 2500
                    whites. From the papers relative to the British West Indies, ordered by the
                    house of commons to be printed in 1815, it appears that, in October 1811, the
                    population of Berbice must have decreased very considerably, if Mr Bolingbroke’s
                    estimate be correct, since at that time it consisted of,</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Whites</p><p part="N"
                                >Coloured</p><p part="N">Blacks</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">550</p><p part="N">240</p><p
                                part="N">25,169</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Total </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 25,959 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">From 1811 to 1828 a further decrease took place. At the latter period,
                    the population, as returned from the colony, stood as follows :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Whites </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 522 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Coloured </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 960 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Blacks </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 20,588 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Total </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 22,070 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">A capitation-tax on the white and black inhabitants, an excise on every
                    fifty pounds of sugar made, a weightagetoll of about two per cent, on all
                    imports and exports, and a tonnage-duty of three florins per last on the burden
                    of ships, are the principal sources of the revenue of the colony. In October
                    1811 there was only one private dwelling hired as a church for the use of the
                    Dutch. The salary of the curate was 7000 stivers, that of the clerk and sexton
                    500 each, and that of the churchwarden 375. These sums were raised by a tax of
                    one stiver per acre, with the exception of the Courantine coast of the colony,·
                    which, in the return to parliament, is represented as consisting of eighty
                    estates, at 500 acres each.</p>
                <p part="N">The imports and exports were,—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1809 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Imports.</p><p part="N"
                                >L.193,663</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Exports.</p><p part="N"
                                >L.49,662</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1810 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 191,566 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 51,785 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">In the years ending the 5th of January there were imported into Great
                    Britain from Berbice, of rum,</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1810. 1811. 1812. 1813. 1828 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Gallons,... </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> .,.20,355.,..6193⅜....
                            1866...23,139....110 469 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">And, in the year ending 5th January 1813, there were imported of sugar
                    9084 cwts.; and in 1828, 87,971 cwts. In 1809 the exportation of cocoa from the
                    colony amounted to 17,665 cwts., and in 1810 to 22,582 cwts. In the former year
                    the exportation of cotton was 1,874,195 lbs., and in the latter year 2,656,057
                    lbs.</p>
                <p part="N">The colony of Berbice was founded in the year 1626, by a minister of
                    Flushing, to whose family, in 1678, it was granted as an hereditary fief. Three
                    fourths of it, however, were, not long afterwards, given to Van Hoorn and
                    Company, in consequence of their discharging a heavy contribution levied on the
                    colony by some French privateers. The new proprietors, being allowed by the
                    Dutch East India Company to import a certain number of negroes annually from
                    Africa, and obtaining other privileges, greatly extended the cultivation of
                    sugar, cocoa, and indigo; but they were restricted from exporting the produce of
                    their plantations to any port not within the province of Holland. In 1763 an
                    insurrection happened among the slaves of Berbice, which was quelled chiefly by
                    the assistance of the Indians and the English from Barbadoes. In 1796 the colony
                    capitulated to the British, but it was restored to the Dutch by the peace of
                    Amiens. In 1803 it was again reduced, and its possession was confirmed to
                    Britain by the peace of Paris. In consequence of the lords of the treasury
                    learning that the loss of slaves on the crown estates from the year 1803 to 1810
                    had been at the rate of 26 per cent., they appointed, in 1811, commissioners for
                    the management of these estates, who were especially directed and empowered to
                    maintain and protect the negroes, and to reward and encourage industry among
                    them.</p>
                <p part="N">By an act of the British parliament, passed in the 56tlι of George III.
                    (1816), cap. 91, Berbice is placed on the same footing in relation to the
                    regulations of trade as the British West India Islands. The subjects of the king
                    of the Netherlands, who are proprietors in Berbice, may import into it from the
                    Netherlands the usual articles of supply for their estates, but not for trade;
                    but wine imported for the use of their estates pays a duty of 10s. per tun. The
                    Dutch proprietors may export their produce, but not to Britain; both exports and
                    imports must be made in ships belonging to the Netherlands; the duties are the
                    same as those payable by British proprietors.</p>
                <p part="N">See Pinckard’s <hi rend="italic">Notes on the West Indies,</hi> 2d
                    edition, vols. i. and ii.; Bancroft’s <hi rend="italic">Essay on the Natural
                        History of Guiana;</hi> Bolingbroke’s <hi rend="italic">Voyage to
                        Demerary;</hi> Tuckeys <hi rend="italic">Maritime Geography,</hi> vol. iv.;
                    Baron Sack’s <hi rend="italic">Account of Surinam.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
