<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-6959-0588-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BERNARD, St</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1170170">Walloons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198490">Dreams</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dn40532">Walloons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193196959?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BERNARD, <hi rend="smallcaps">St</hi></label>, the
                    first abbot of Clairvaux, was born in the year 1091, in the village of Fontaine,
                    in Burgundy. He acquired so great a reputation by his zeal and abilities, that
                    all the affairs of the church appeared to rest upon his shoulders, and kings and
                    princes seemed to have chosen him as general arbitrator of their differences. It
                    was owing to him that Innocent II. was acknowledged sovereign pontiff, and that,
                    after the death of Peter Louis anti-pope, Victor, who had been named successor,
                    made a voluntary abdication of his dignity. He convicted Abelard at the council
                    of Sens, in the year 1140; he opposed the monk Raoul; he persecuted the
                    followers of Arnaud dc Bresse; and, in 1148, he caused Gilbert de la Por-vicé,
                    bishop of Poitiers, and Eonde ľEtoile, to be condemned in the council of Rheims.
                    By such zealous behaviour he verified, according to Mr Bayle, the interpretation
                    of his mother’s dream. She had dreamed, when with child of him, that she should
                    bring forth a white dog, whose barking should be very loud. Astonished at this
                    dream, which she was unable to unriddle, she consulted a monk, who said to her,
                    “Bc of good courage; you shall have a son who shall guard the house of God, and
                    bark loudly against the enemies of the faith.” But St Bernard went far beyond
                    the prediction; for he barked sometimes against chimerical enemies, and was more
                    successful in exterminating the heterodox than in putting down infidels,
                    although he attacked the latter, not only with the ordinary arms of his
                    eloquence, but also with the extraordinary weapon of prophecy. He preached up
                    the crusade under Louis the Younger, and added greatly to the troops of the
                    crusaders. But all the fine hopes with which he had flattered the people were
                    disappointed by the event; and when it was alleged that he had hurried a vast
                    number of Christians to slaughter, without sharing the dangers which he had
                    induced so many to brave, the saint defended himself by alleging that the sins
                    of the crusaders had destroyed the efficacy of his prophecies. He is said,
                    however, to have founded 160 monasteries, and to have wrought a prodigious
                    number of miracles. H <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> died on the 20th of August
                    1153, at the age of sixty-three·</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193196972?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-6972-0589"/>
                <p part="N">The best edition of his works is that of 1690 by Father Mabillon.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Bernard,</hi><hi rend="italic">Dr Edward,</hi> a
                    learned astronomer, linguist, and critic, was born at Perry St Paul, on the 2d
                    of May 1638, and educated at Merchant-Tailor’s school, and St John’s College,
                    Oxford. During his stay at school he had laid in such a fund of classical
                    learning, that, on entering the university, he was master of all the elegancies
                    of the Greek and Latin tongues, and not unacquainted with the Hebrew. On his
                    settling in the university, he applied himself to the study of history,
                    philology, and philosophy, and made himself master of the Hebrew, Syriac,
                    Arabic, and Coptic languages; after which he turned his attention to the study
                    of the mathematics under Dr Wallis. Having successively taken the degrees of
                    bachelor and master of arts, and afterwards that of bachelor of divinity, he
                    went to Leyden to consult several oriental manuscripts left to the university
                    there by Joseph Scaliger and Levi-nus Warnerus. At his return to Oxford he
                    collated and examined the most valuable manuscripts in the Bodleian library; and
                    being of a communicative disposition, he in consequence became engaged in a very
                    extensive correspondence with the learned of most countries. In the year 1669
                    the celebrated Christopher W <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi> ren, Savilian
                    professor of astronomy at Oxford, having been appointed surveyor general of his
                    majesty’s works, and obliged by this employment to spend much of his time in
                    London, obtained leave to name a deputy at Oxford, and immediately pitched upon
                    Mr Bernard; which engaged the latter in a more particular application to the
                    study of astronomy. In 1676 he was sent by the earl of Arlington to France as
                    tutor to the dukes of Grafton and Northumberland, sons of Charles II. by the
                    duchess of Cleveland, and then living with their mother at Paris; but the
                    simplicity of his manners not suiting the gaiety of the duchess’s family, he
                    returned about a year after to Oxford, and resumed his studies, in which he made
                    great proficiency, as his astronomical and critical works abundantly testify. He
                    composed tables of the longitudes, latitudes, right ascensions, and declinations
                    of the fixed stars; Observations in Latin on the Obliquity of the Ecliptic; and
                    several other pieces inserted in the Philosophical Transactions. He also wrote,
                    1. A Treatise on the Ancient Weights and Measures; 2. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Chronologiae Samaritanoe Synopsis,</hi> in two tables; 3. Testimonies of
                    the Ancients concerning the Greek Version of the Old Testament by the Seventy;
                    and several other learned works. He was a person of great piety, virtue, and
                    humanity, and died on the 12th January 1696, in the fifty-ninth year of his age,
                    leaving behind him a number of manuscripts which were considered valuable.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Bernard,</hi><hi rend="italic">James,</hi>
                    professor of philosophy and mathematics, and minister of the Walloon church at
                    Leyden, was born on the 1st September 1658, at Nions, in Dauphine. Having
                    studied at Geneva, he returned to France in 1679, and was chosen minister of
                    Venterol, a village m Dauphine, whence he was removed some time afterwards to
                    the church of Vinsobres, in the same province. But the persecution raised
                    against the Protestants in France having obliged him to abandon his native
                    country, he retired to Holland, where he was received with great civility, and
                    appointed one of the pensionary ministers of Gauda. In July 1688 he began a
                    political publication entitled <hi rend="italic">Histoire Abrégée de
                        l'Europe,</hi> which he continued monthly till December 1688. In 1692 he
                    began his <hi rend="italic">Lettres Historiques,</hi> containing an account of
                    the most important transactions in Europe, with suitable reflections; and he
                    carried on this work, which was also published monthly, till the end of the year
                    1698. It was afterwards continued by other hands, and consists of a great number
                    of volumes. Mr le Clerc having left off his <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque
                        Universelle</hi> in 1691, Mr Bernard wrote the greater part of the twentieth
                    volume, and carried on the five following volumes to the year 1693. In 1698 he
                    collected and published <hi rend="italic">Actes et Négociations de la Paix de
                        Ryszvic,</hi> in four volumes 12mo. In 1699 lie began the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nouvelles de la République des Lettres,</hi> which continued till December
                    1710. Mr Bernard having acquired great reputation by his works, as well as by
                    his sermðns at Gauda and the Hague, the congregation of the Walloon church at
                    Leyden became extremely desirous to have him as one of their ministers; and a
                    vacancy happening in 1705, he was unanimously elected to that office. About the
                    same time Mr de Valder, professor of philosophy and mathematics at Leyden,
                    having resigned his situation, Mr Bernard was appointed his successor; and the
                    university presented him with the degrees of doctor in philosophy and master of
                    arts. His public and private lectures occupied the greater part of his time; yet
                    he did not neglect his pastoral function, but composed his sermons with great
                    care, and also wrote two excellent treatises, one on a late repentance, the
                    other on the excellency of religion. In 1716 he published a supplement to
                    Moreri’s Dictionary, in two volumes folio. The same year he resumed his <hi
                        rend="italic">Nouvelles de la République des Lettres,</hi> and continued it
                    till his death, which happened on the 27th of April 1718, in the sixtieth year
                    of his age.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Bernard,</hi><hi rend="italic">St,</hi> the Great,
                    a mountain in Savoy and Switzerland, between Valais and the valley of Aoste, at
                    the source of the rivers Drance and Doria, and forming part of the Pennine Alps.
                    The top is always covered with snow, and there is a monastery situated there,
                    where the monks entertain travellers hospitably without regard to difference -of
                    religion.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
