<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-4879-0428-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BASKET</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1243607">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r47q">Cuttings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7fz12">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j0b34r">Sheriffs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154dt2t">Hottentots</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885683">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:828295">Baskets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115838">Sheriffs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193194879?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BASKET</label>, a utensil made of twigs interwoven
                    together, in order to hold fruit, earth, or other substances. The ancient
                    Britons were noted for their ingenuity in making baskets, which they exported in
                    large quantities. These baskets were of very elegant workmanship, and bore a
                    high price; and they are mentioned by Juvenal among the extravagantly expensive
                    furniture of the Roman tables in his time.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p part="N">The words of Juvenal are, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Adde et bascaudas et mille escaria,</hi> “Add <hi rend="italic"
                                >baskets,</hi> and a thousand other dishes.” That these “baskets”
                            weιe of British manufacture is evident from the following lines of
                            Martial:</p><lg part="N">
                            <l part="N"> Barbara de <hi rend="italic">pictis</hi> veni bascauda <hi
                                    rend="italic">Britannis,</hi></l>
                            <l part="N"> Sed me jam mavult dicere Roma suam. </l>
                            <l part="N"> Barbarie basket I, by Britons made, </l>
                            <l part="N"> Painted, yet skilful in the basket trade; </l>
                            <l part="N"> Rome claims me now, although a thing of twigs, </l>
                            <l part="N"> Well-pleased to tickle thus the imperial prigs. </l>
                        </lg></note><hi rend="smallcaps">Basket-making.</hi> The earlier arts among
                    mankind, in an uncivilized condition, are restricted to operations on materials
                    which undergo slight and imperceptible changes; and implements are fabricated
                    from substances almost in their natural state. The process of interweaving
                    twigs, reeds, or leaves, is seen among the rudest nations of the world; and
                    there is known even an inferior specimen of art among the natives of Van
                    Diemen’s Land, consisting of a bunch of rushes tied together at either end,
                    which, spread out in the middle, forms a basket. But the sudden alteration of
                    shape obviously renders this construction less convenient; whence the same and
                    other tribes make a basket of leaves interwoven, and that so skilfully executed,
                    that it retains either milk or water. A bundle of rushes spread out may be
                    compared to the warp of a web, and the application of others across it to the
                    woof, also an early discovery; for basket-making is literally a web of the
                    coarsest materials. By experience these materials are refined and ornamented;
                    and, in the most improved stages of manufacture, neat and useful implements and
                    utensils are produced. Scarcely any nation has been entirely ignorant of the
                    art; and our ancestors in this island made baskets which, as we have already
                    stated, were carried to Rome either for use or ornament.</p>
                <p part="N">Basket-making, however, has by no means been confined to the fabrication
                    of those simple and useful utensils from which its name is derived. Of old, the
                    shields of soldiers were fashioned of wicker-work, either plain or covered with
                    hides; and the like has been witnessed among modern savages. In Britain, the
                    wicker boats of the natives, covered with the skins of animals, attracted the
                    notice of the Romans; and Herodotus mentions boats of this kind on the Tigris
                    and Euphrates. But there was this difference, that the former seem to have been
                    of the ordinary figure of a boat, whereas the latter were round and covered with
                    bitumen. Boats of this shape, about seven feet in diameter, are used at the
                    present day on these rivers; and boats of analogous construction are employed in
                    crossing the rivers of India which have not a rapid current. At Hurrial, a town
                    on the western side of Hindostan, the river Toombudra is not fordable from June
                    to October; during which interval, round basket-boats are used to transport
                    people, goods, and cattle, to the opposite sides. They are of all sizes, from
                    three to fifteen feet in diameter, but shallow, not being above three feet in
                    depth; yet some are capable of carrying thirty men. They are of very simple
                    construction: A number of pieces of split bamboo, twenty for example, are laid
                    on the ground, crossing each other near the centre, and there fastened with
                    thongs; the ends of the bamboos are then elevated by several persons, and fixed
                    asunder at due distance by means of stakes, in which position they are bound by
                    other long slips of bamboo. The latter are introduced alternately over and under
                    the pieces first crossed, and tied at the intersections to preserve the shape.
                    This being completed, beginning from the bottom to the centre, the parts above
                    the intended height or depth of the basket-boat are cut off, and it is liberated
                    from the stakes reversed, and covered with halfdressed hides sewed together with
                    thongs. Nothing can be more expeditious or more simple than the fabrication and
                    materials of these vessels, if they merit that name. One may be made by six men
                    in as many hours. Only two substances, almost always accessible, are used,—
                    hides and bamboo. They are navigated either by paddles where the water is deep,
                    or are pushed over a shallow bottom with long poles; and the passengers within
                    are safely transported, being kept dry by planks and pieces of wood at the
                    bottom. The basket-boats on the river Krishna, in the same country, are about
                    twelve feet in diameter and four feet deep. Whole armies are thus enabled to
                    continue their march, and even heavy artillery has been conveyed in this manner
                    across rivers. Sometimes the boats are towed by bullocks fastened to them, and
                    goaded on in the proper direction. We may also observe, that in different parts
                    of the world, whole houses, cottages, fences, and gates, are formed of basket or
                    wicker work. On the Continent, a two-horse carriage, called a Holstein waggon,
                    of very considerable size; and fit to carry several persons, is composed solely
                    of basket-work. The same is done in Britain with regard to the bodies of gigs;
                    and an appendage of the stage-coaches is literally designed <hi rend="italic"
                        >the basket;</hi> besides a vast variety of works on a smaller scale.</p>
                <p part="N">In respect to the materials employed, besides those specified as
                    belonging to the ruder nations, there are many which are equally the product of
                    nature and art. Twigs, branches, straw, and whalebone, are all of the number.
                    The natives of some parts of South America make baskets simply of rushes, so
                    closely interwoven as to hold water; and tlιousands of them are annually sold in
                    the Spanish provinces. The Caffres and Hottentots are alike skilful with the
                    roots of plants. Thus it does not belong to Europeans to rival an uncivilized
                    tribe in the exercise of a simple art. But of all materials, osiers or willows
                    are in most general use.</p>
                <p part="N">Osiers employed for basket-making are either taken entire, cut from the
                    root, split asunder, or stripped of their bark, according to the work to be
                    produced; but in the latter case they are previously soaked in water. The
                    stripping is performed by drawing the willows through an iron-edged implement
                    called brakes, which removes the bark, and the willows are then cleaned, as far
                    as necessary, by manual operation with a sharp knife. Next they are exposed to
                    the sun and air, and afterwards placed in a dry situation. But it is not the
                    less necessary to preserve willows with their bark in the same manner; for
                    nothing can be more injurious than the humidity inherent in die plant; and
                    previous to use they must be soaked some days in water also. The barked or white
                    osier is then divided into bundles or faggots according to size; the larger
                    being reserved to form the strong work in the skeleton of the basket, and the
                    smaller for weaving the bottom and sides. Should the latter be applied to
                    ordinary work, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193194892?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0704-4892-0429"/>they are taken whole; but for implements of
                    slight and finer texture, each osier is divided into splits and skains; which
                    names denote the different degrees of size to which they are reduced. Splits are
                    osiers cleft into four parts, by means of a particular implement employed for
                    that purpose, consisting of two edge tools placed at right angles, whereby the
                    rod is longitudinally divided down the pith. These are next drawn through an
                    implement resembling the common spoke-shave, keeping the grain of the split next
                    the wood or stock of the shave, while the pith is presented to the edge of the
                    iron, which is sct in an oblique direction to the wood: and in order to bring
                    the split into a shape still more regular, it is passed through another
                    implement called an upright, consisting of a flat piece of stecl, each end of
                    which is fashioned into a cutting edge, like that of an ordinary chisel. The
                    flat is bent round, so that the two edges approach ćach other at a greater or
                    less interval by means of regulating screws, and the whole is fixed into a
                    handle. By passing the splits between the two edges they are reduced to skains,
                    the thickness of which is determined by the interval between tlιe edges of the
                    tool. All the implements required by a basket-maker are few and simple: they
                    consist, besides the preceding, of knives, bodkins and drills for boring, leads
                    for keeping the w ork steady while in process, and, where it is of small
                    dimensions, a heavy piece of iron called a beater, vrhich is employed to beat
                    the basket close as it is augmented. Thus a basket-maker has this great
                    advantage over many other artificers, that he can establish himself in his
                    profession at the most inconsiderable expense either for tools or materials.</p>
                <p part="N">An ordinary basket is made by preparing the requisite number of osiers,
                    and preserving their length considerably greater than that of the finished work.
                    They are ranged in pairs on the floor parallel to each other, at small
                    intervals, in the direction of the longer diameter of the basket; and this may
                    be called the woof; for, as we have said, basket work is literally a web. These
                    parallel rods are then crossed at right angles by two of the largest osiers,
                    with the thick ends towards the workman, who places his foot upon them; and
                    weaving each alternately over and under the parallel pieces first laid dowm,
                    they are by that means confined in their places. The whole now forms what is
                    technically called the slat or slate, which is the foundation or the basket.
                    Next, the long end of one of the two rods is taken and woven under and over the
                    pairs of short ends all round the bottom, until the whole be woven in. The same
                    is done with the other rod, and then additional long osiers are also woven in,
                    until the bottom be of sufficient size, and the ¼Oof be occupied by them. Thus
                    the bottom or foundation on which the superstructure is to be raised is
                    finished; and this latter part is accomplished by sharpen- <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ln</hi> S the large ends of as many long and stout
                    osiers as way be necessary to form the ribs or skeleton. These are forced or
                    plaited between the rods of the bottom from die edge towards the centre, and are
                    turned up in the direction of the sides; then other rods are woven in and out
                    between each of them, until the basket is raised to the intended height, or,
                    more correctly speaking, the depth it is to receive. The edge or brim is
                    finished by turning own the perpendicular ends of the ribs, now' protruding and
                    standing up over each other, whereby the whole is rmly and compactly united. A
                    handle is adapted to the " <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> ∣ by forcing two or
                    three osiers, sharpened at the end, <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi>. <hi
                        rend="superscript"> n</hi>. cut to the requisite length, down the weaving of
                    the ' θs, close together; and they are pinned fast, about two <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 11</hi> 1 <hi rend="superscript"> c le</hi> Ş f <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ronι</hi> the brim, in order that the handle, when comP
                        <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> θd, may be retained in its proper position.
                    The osiers * <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> then either bound or plaited in such
                    fashion as pleases d&gt;e taste of the artist.</p>
                <p part="N">This is the most simple kind of basket, from which others differ only in
                    finer materials and nicer execution; but in these there is considerable scope
                    for taste and fancy, and implements are produced of extreme neatness and
                    ingenuity in construction. Some are formed of twigs or straw entire; others of
                    sections, split of various thickness, coloured, plaited, or plain; and baskets
                    of endless variety in size, figure, and texture, are fabricated, according to
                    the artist’s inclination. The skains are frequently smoked and dyed either of
                    dull or brilliant colours, and, by intermixing them judiciously, a very good
                    effect is produced.</p>
                <p part="N">From the simplicity of this manufacture a great many individuals,
                    independent of professed basket-makers, are occupied in it; and, fortunately, it
                    affords employment to the blind in the several asylums established for their
                    reception. Not that persons suffering privation of sight are incapable of more
                    ingenious and delicate mechanical exercises, but the facility of teaching and
                    acquiring the principles of basket-making being alike obvious, is one of the
                    strongest recommendations in its favour. At Liverpool, where there is an asylum
                    of this description, the art is practised with success; and in the city of
                    Edinburgh a number of the blind find employment of the same kind in the asylum
                    established there.</p>
                <p part="N">The best materials for basket-making have been principally imported into
                    Great Britain from France and Holland; but the duration of the late war induced
                    the inhabitants of this country to endeavour to obtain a supply at home.
                    Cultivation of the osier was imperfectly understood in England, and in Scotland
                    it scarcely received any attention whatever; whence, as a suitable
                    encouragement, that patriotic society, whose notice is specially directed to the
                    improvement of arts and manufactures, offered premiums to those cultivators who
                    should raise the greatest quantity, not being less than 6000 plants on an
                    acre.</p>
                <p part="N">It became an object with such cultivators to ascertain, not only the
                    quantity that could be obtained, but the quality of the produce, which was of
                    the greater consequence, as many plants, passing under the general name of
                    osiers, and even possessing their external characters, are ill adapted for the
                    work intended. But considerable light has been thrown on the subject by Mr
                    Philipps of Ely, who was early rewarded by a premium on account of the utility
                    of his observations. He remarks that the osier is a species of salix, of which
                    there are many varieties; and that these may be comprehended under two classes,
                    the first containing nine or ten species. None, however, excepting one, the gray
                    or brindled osier, is of use. This, in common with the others, has a light
                    coloured leaf, but is distinguished by the bark being streaked with red or blood
                    colour; and it is of late introduction into Britain, having been first planted
                    in the isle of Ely, where the observer’s experiments seem to have been chiefly
                    made. It grows vigorously, is very hardy and tough, and bleaches well. All the
                    others of the same class prefer a wet soil, where they grow quickly and large,
                    flourishing even in the most barren kind of peat; but they are coarse and
                    spongy, have a thick pith, and arc extremely perishable. Nevertheless they are
                    sometimes used for coarser w orkmanship, and are profitable to those who live in
                    the vicinity of places where there is a great demand for osiers, and cheap
                    conveyance. During the interruption of continental intercourse they were much
                    resorted to by basket-makers; but their inferiority has brought the English
                    baskets into disrepute in foreign markets. The second class, according to Mr
                    Philipps, contains four or five different species. One of these, the Welsh
                    willow, is very tough and durable, but not of a favourable colour. There are two
                    varieties, red and white, the former of which is preferred, and forms part of
                    every plantation, from its particular utility in tying up the bundles<pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193194905?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-4905-0430"/>
                    of willows after they have been barked or whitened. The bitterness of this plant
                    is such as to be a protection from the depredations of cattle. Besides these
                    there are the west country Spaniard, the new willow, the French, and the red
                    Kent willow. The first has been superseded by others of superior quality; but
                    experience proves that an acre will carry 2000 plants more of them than of some
                    which are in higher repute. But the best of all is esteemed the French willow,
                    especially as being most adapted for smaller and finer work in baskets, fans,
                    hats, and other light articles. It is rather of slow growth, but extremely
                    taper, pliant, close-grained, tough, and durable. Great quantities of it are
                    always imported from the Continent, its culture being more neglected here than
                    that of the others; however, it must be distinguished from a species resembling
                    it, which is characterized by the brittleness of the leaves, which snap like
                    glass when drawn through the fingers. Plantations of the French willow have been
                    strongly recommended as forming a useful commodity, and being always in demand.
                    Having attained the requisite maturity, all willows are cut down and made up
                    into bunches in iron hoops thirty-six or forty inches in diameter, for the
                    manufacturers, and arc sold either in this way or in loads, the price being
                    subject to fluctuation according to the scarcity or abundance of the
                    commodity.</p>
                <p part="N">- In regard to the cultivation of osiers very different opinions
                    prevail; originating, it is probable, from too limited experiments, combined
                    with the diversity of soil and climate. Mr Philipps, whose opinions are entitled
                    to attention, conceives that autumn, and not spring, is the most proper season
                    for planting willows; the stagnation of the juices he considers the true
                    criterion whereby to regulate the period, but not on account of the set so much
                    as on account of the trunk; for if the shoot be severed when the sap is in
                    circulation, the parent plant bleeds to death. The osiers which he planted in
                    the first week of October he found to have struck roots about Christmas, though
                    there was no external sign of vegetation. In prosecuting this subject, Mr
                    Philipps observes, that he made a plantation in autumn, and filled up part of
                    the ground which was vacant, in the following month of March, with additional
                    sets. The latter were the further advanced in May, but in June the autumn plants
                    had the advantage, and continued growing well, while many of the others died. In
                    summer, he remarks, “when the fibres have been formed before the winter, or when
                    a tendency to form them has been observed by the swelling of the bark, and
                    particularly at the eye, the plant is enabled to charge itself with a sufficient
                    portion of the juices to answer the demand of spring.” Therefore he concludes
                    that the proper rule is to plant as early in autumn as the shoots may be cut,
                    without injuring the parent stock. The cultivator lays out the ground in beds or
                    burrows eighteen feet broad, digging ditches nine feet wide on each side. The
                    upper surface of the ditches, to the depth of fourteen inches, is thrown on the
                    beds, and the remainder of what is excavated from them is used for turf or fuel.
                    The beds, now consisting of about two feet and a half thick of solid earth above
                    the surface of the substratum of peat, are planted in the following autumn, and
                    produce good crops.</p>
                <p part="N">Experiments have been made by various cultivators respecting the
                    suitableness of different soils, after having borne different kinds of grain. Mr
                    Sheriff has related a profitable mode of culture practised by him in Scotland,
                    and also made some judicious observations on the subject in general. He remarks,
                    that the finest and most valuable twigs can be procured only from land cured of
                    chilling, weeping springs; and if the soil is not of considerable thickness, it
                    must be rendered so by manure. Moderate moisture is favourable to the production
                    of fine twigs, but water constantly stagnant is ruinous. He proposes to make the
                    cuts or shoots from fifteen to seventeen inches in length, and to allow four or
                    five inches to remain above ground, to be cut down by the surface of the soil,
                    when the heads of the stocks shall, in a series of years, have become too bushy.
                    By this operation, the vigour of the plant is renewed in the most decided
                    manner. Mr Sheriff forgets, however, that, in the time he mentions, a much
                    greater protrusion from the earth will have taken place by the simple vegetation
                    of the plant than is necessary to leave room for cutting off the head. It is
                    necessary, in his opinion, to trim and dress the stocks from decayed wood, and
                    to retain only as many buds on each as the plant may be expected to bring to
                    perfection in length and strength of shoot. Thus the superabundant stumps of old
                    wood are cut down, and the weakest shoots extirpated, in November and December,
                    or March and April; and seldom more than two buds should be left on those
                    selected to stand and produce the next summer’s growth. He considers the leading
                    errors of those who have attempted the cultivation of osiers to consist in
                    employing improper soil, peat-earth, perhaps, or poor bogs; and also in
                    defective preparation of the soil, though suitable in other respects. Failure
                    may, besides, arise from planting bad or useless species of osiers; putting too
                    few cuts in the ground; neglecting their subsequent culture, particularly during
                    the first spring and summer after plantation; and allowing the shoots to be cut
                    down after Christmas, and before the middle of March, which renders the stocks
                    liable to be much weakened by hard frosts succeeding heavy, rains, immediately
                    after the twigs have been cut, and before the wounds from the knife have healed.
                    By pursuing a system analogous to what is here exposed, he calculates the
                    profits of an acre of osiers at about L.18. 10s.; and he mentions that he
                    contracted to receive a sum between L.220 and L.250 for the produce of twelve
                    statute acres and a half. It does not appear, however, that this was an annual
                    crop, and it is rather to be inferred that willows of several years’ growth
                    formed part of it. Mr Sheriff’s experiments and observations were rewarded with
                    the gold medal of the Society for the Encouragement of Arts and Manufactures.
                    Another cultivator, Mr Wade, calculated his profits on fourteen acres, which
                    were planted with 12,000 sets each, at intervals of twenty-six inches by ten,
                    &gt; as amounting to L.10 per acre.</p>
                <p part="N">Among the experiments on the quality of soil may be. instanced a
                    plantation made in spring, of large cuttings, eighteen inches long, thrust so
                    far into the earth as to leave four or five inches protruding. Part of the
                    ground had been in wheat after summer fallow, and part, which was also planted,
                    had been sown with grass seeds. The plants made a more vigorous shoot in spring
                    than at any subsequent period, and of the whole but few failed. Those which
                    succeeded the wheat produced the best osiers, and those which were planted among
                    the grass seeds the worst. Both stood on a strong clay soil; and from the
                    difference seen here, it has been concluded, that, as the cleanest ground
                    produced the best crop, summer fallowing would be advantageous. Another example
                    is given, where, ot 350 sets planted in garden ground, the soil of which was
                    clay, 341 succeeded, producing, in the first year apparently, a bundle
                    thirty-eight inches in circumference, and some of the osiers above ten feet
                    long. They were plantet in the latter end of March, and arranged in rows,
                    between which was sown a crop of beans. Both the interval separating the plants
                    and their age are arbitrary, as is also the extent of the plantation, and we may
                    likewise add the quality of the soil; for experiments have not been made on a
                    sufficient scale to determine the fact. The most su-ŋcrficial<pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193194918?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-4918-0431"/> observer
                    cannot fail to have remarked the comparative slenderness of all plants crowded
                    together, and the superior strength of those apart from eaeh other. The sets of
                    osiers, for several reasons, should be inserted in re° ’ ular rows. Their age
                    does not appear important, and nowhere is a more vigorous erop produced than
                    from the root of the oldest tree deprived of its trunk. In general, previous
                    preparation of the ground is profitable; and plantations may thence be formed,
                    whieh are to be annually cut down for baskets and such light utensils; but the
                    shoot is allowed to grow two, or even four years, if strong rods are required
                    for larger and eoarser workmanship. The rapidity and eertainty with which this
                    plant vegetates preserves it in a manner under absolute eontrol, and peculiarly
                    adapts it for a variety of mechanieal purposes. Many cultivators recommend deep
                    insertion of the shoot into the ground; but here there is a limitation; for if
                    it be too deeply inserted, the vegetation will be less vigorous. At the same
                    time, the powerful tendency to vegetation in a willow is rather an exception to
                    ordinary rules; and although the lower part be injured, roots may spring nearer
                    the surface. But it is not to be overlooked, that if a tree be transplanted into
                    too deep a pit, the root, instead of striking out new fibres, remains inactive,
                    and the tree withers and deeays; or if seeds be deposited too deeply in the
                    earth, no vegetation will ensue; whereas, even those on the surfaee will put
                    forth a radiele, and establish themselves there. In the former ease, they either
                    lose the germinative faeulty, or are destroyed; but, if a tree be transplanted
                    into a shallow pit, the root w ill spread, and the whole will exhibit a
                    luxuriant vegetation. These are facts which demand greater attention than they
                    usually receive; and the depth at whieh the shoots of osiers are inserted should
                    be earefully observed. Nevertheless we must repeat, that it does appear that
                    deep insertion is not as noxious to them as to other plants.</p>
                <p part="N">It is commonly understood that willows flourish nowhere but with
                    abundanee of water. Undoubtedly, adequate humidity is very essential; but this
                    general position is quite erroneous, as experiment and observation daily
                    testify. Willows growing in water have almost invariably a sickly aspeet; few
                    strong cr healthy scions spring from them; and their vegetation is never so
                    vigorous as when they are at some distance from it. Every plant has a
                    predilection for a particular plaee, where the conditions of its aliment and
                    vegetation coneur. The willow requires a considerable degree of humidity, though
                    it will also be seen vigorous on drier soils; but the vieinity of water is an
                    essential quality in selecting a suitable spot for a plantation. The purposes to
                    whieh the plants are to be applied must be considered, and the eireumstanees of
                    their growth so regulated, that they may become suitable for the object in view.
                    There is little doubt that, with due notiee and consideration, this plant may
                    receive great amelioration by culture.</p>
                <p part="N">All plantations must be well feneed against cattle, as the willow, both
                    shoot and leaf, is with them a favourite kind of food; and as some particular
                    caterpillars infest the plant at certain seasons of the year, stripping it
                    totally bare and injuring its vegetation, eare should also be taken to remove
                    them as effectually as possible. <hi rend="smallcaps">(n. n.)</hi><hi
                        rend="italic smallcaps"> Baskets</hi><hi rend="italic">of Earth,</hi> ealled
                    in French <hi rend="italic">corbedles,</hi> are usually placed on the parapet of
                    a trench, to form à sort of epaulement or breast-work, and, as the name
                    indicates, are hlled with earth. They are about a foot and a half in . <hi
                        rend="superscript"> eι</hi> ght, as mueh in diameter at the top, and eight
                    or ten <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ∏ches at bottom; so that when set
                    together, the inter- <hi rend="superscript"> V</hi> ^· <hi rend="subscript">
                        1</hi><hi rend="superscript"> left at</hi> ^ <hi rend="superscript"> le
                        b</hi> °tt° <hi rend="superscript"> ms</hi> sθ <hi rend="superscript">
                        r</hi> ve as embrasures through Much the soldiers may fire without exposing
                    themselves <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> the shot of the enemy.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">BASKET-Salt,</hi> that which is made from
                    salt-springs, being purer, whiter, and composed of finer grains than the eommon
                    brine-salt.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
