<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-8688-0721-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOAR</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:835126">Boars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896265">Dogs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095872">Rest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128817">Spears</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd61">Dog</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x62g">Rest</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cr5nh9d">Wounds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p84445x">Spear</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t727k92">Nose</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193198688?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BOAR</label>, a term in the manege. A horse is said
                    to boar when he shoots out his nose as high as his ears, and tosses his nose in
                    the wind.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Boar,</hi> a male swine. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Mammalia.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">The wild boar, among huntsmen, has several names, according to his
                    different ages. The first year he is called <hi rend="italic">a P⅛t</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> o</hi><hi rend="italic">f
                        ^</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ιe</hi><hi rend="italic">saunder;</hi>
                    the second, <hi rend="italic">a hog;</hi> the third, <hi rend="italic">a
                        hogsteer;</hi> and the fourth, <hi rend="italic">a hoar.</hi> When leaving
                    the saunder, he is called a <hi rend="italic">singler</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >sangler.</hi> The boar generally lives to the age of twenty-five or thirty
                    years, if he escapes accidents. The time of rutting is in December, and lasts
                    about three weeks. Wild boars feed on all sorts of fruits, and on the roots of
                    many plants; the root of fern in particular seems a favourite with them; and
                    when they frequent places near the sea-coast, they descend to the shores, and
                    demolish the tenderer shell-fish in very great numbers. Their general places of
                    rest are among the thickest bushes that can be found; and they are not easily
                    induced to break cover, but will stand at bay a long time. In April and May they
                    sleep more soundly than at any other time of the year; and this is therefore the
                    successful time for taking them in the toils. When a boar is roused out of the
                    thicket, he always goes from it, if possible, the same way by which he entered
                    it; and when he is once up, he will never stop till he reach some place of
                    greater security. If a saunder of them be found together, when any one breaks
                    away, the rest follow in the same track. When the boar is hunted in the wood
                    where he has been bred, he can scarcely ever be brought to quit it; sometimes
                    indeed he makes towards the sides to listen to the noise of the dogs, but he
                    retires into the middle again, and usually dies or escapes there. When a boar
                    happens to run a-head, he will not be stopped or put out of his way by man or
                    beast, as long as he has any strength left. He makes no doubles or crossings
                    when chased; and, if old, utters no sound when killed, though the sows and pigs
                    will squeak when wounded. At his full strength he is one of the most resolute
                    and courageous of animals. His prevailing impulse is to close with his
                    antagonist. When fairly at bay he never shrinks from any contest, however
                    unequal; and, although mortally wounded, he will nevertheless maintain the
                    combat with the most unflinching bravery to the last.</p>
                <p part="N">The season for hunting the wild boar begins in September, and ends in
                    December, when they go to rut. If he be large, and have lain long at rest, he
                    must be hunted with a great number of dogs, and these such as will keep close to
                    him; and the huntsman, with his spear, should always be riding in among them,
                    and charging the boar as.often as he can, to discourage him; for such a boar as
                    this, with five or six couple of dogs, will make to the first convenient place
                    of shelter, and there stand at bay and attack them as they attempt to come up
                    with him. There ought also to be relays of the best and staunchest hounds in the
                    kennel; for if they are young eager dogs, they will be apt to seize him, and be
                    killed or spoiled before the rest come up. The putting collars with bells
                    about-the dogs’ necks is a great security for them; for the boar will not
                    readily strike at them when so provided, but will rather avoid them. The
                    huntsmen generally kill the boar with their swords or spears; but great caution
                    is necessary in making the blows; for he is very apt to catch them on his snout
                    or with his tusks, and if wounded and not killed, he will attack the huntsman in
                    the most furious manner. The wound with the spear should, if possible, be given
                    between the eyes in the middle of the forehead, or in the shoulder; in either
                    place a wound is almost certain to prove mortal.</p>
                <p part="N">When this creature makes at the hunter there is nothing for it but
                    courage and address. If the boar comes straight up, he is to be received at the
                    point of the spear; but if he makes doubles and windings, he is to be watched
                    very cautiously; for he will attempt getting hold of the spear in his mouth; and
                    if he does so, nothing can save the huntsman but another person attacking him
                    behind. In this case he will attack the second person; upon which the first,
                    being disengaged, must renew the onset. Two persons will thus have enough to do
                    with him; and were it not for the forks of the boar-spears that make it
                    impossible to press forward upon them, the huntsman who gives the creature his
                    death-wound would seldom escape falling a sacrifice to his revenge. The modern
                    way of boarhunting is generally to dispatch the creature by all the huntsmen
                    striking him at once; but the ancient Roman method was, for a person on foot,
                    armed with a spear, to keep the creature at bay, in which case the boar would
                    run of himself upon the spear to come at the huntsman, and push forward till the
                    weapon pierced him through.</p>
                <p part="N">The hinder claws of a boar are called <hi rend="italic">guards.</hi> In
                    the corn he is said to <hi rend="italic">feed;</hi> in the meadows or
                    fallow-fields, to <hi rend="italic">rout, worm,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >fern;</hi> in a close, to <hi rend="italic">graze.</hi> The boar is
                    farrowed with his full complement of teeth, which afterwards increase in size,
                    but not in number. Amongst these there are four called <hi rend="italic"
                        >tushes</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tusks,</hi> the two largest of which do
                    not hurt when he strikes, but serve only to whet the other two, with which the
                    beast defends himself, and frequently kills his assailant.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
