<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-4086-0367-11" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BARBOUR, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1157298">Trojans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827433">Barbering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9rd17">Trojans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4ft3d">Barbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n873131">Carthusians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z5k">Pensions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193194086?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BARBOUR, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>, the
                    contemporary and in some respects the rival of Chaucer, is the author of a poem
                    which may justly be described as a national work: it relates the exploits of a
                    very heroic monarch, whose memory is still cherished by his countrymen, and it
                    displays so conspicuous a union of talent and patriotism, that, after the lapse
                    of nearly five centuries, it has not ceased to attract an uncommon degree of
                    attention. The orthography of this poet’s name is very unsettled; it is to be
                    found under the different forms of Barber, Barbere, Barbar, Barbare, and
                    Barbour. It evidently belongs to that very numerous class of names originally
                    derived from trades or occupations; but as <hi rend="italic">Barbour</hi>
                    appears to have been the ancient orthography of the word denoting this
                    particular trade, there is sufficient propriety in adhering to the form now so
                    generally adopted, and writing the name Barbour instead of Barber. Those authors
                    who aver that he was born at Aberdeen, and educated in the abbey of
                    Aberbrothick, seem to have substituted conjecture for evidence; no document
                    which can enable us to ascertain the place of his birth or education has yet
                    been discovered. His birth has been referred to the year 1316. When he describes
                    the person of Randolph, says Lord Hailes, he seems to speak from personal
                    observation; and as Randolph died in 1331 and Barbour in 1396, the poet, if we
                    suppose him to have reached the age of eighty, would have been fifteen years old
                    at the period of that illustrious warrior’s death.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Hailes’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >Annuls of Scotland,</hi> vol. ii. p. 3.</p></note> This however is
                    but a vague calculation, resting on no solid basis; for he neither professes to
                    describe the person of Randolph from actual observation, <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193194099?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-4099-0368"/>nor is his
                    description so minute and graphic as to justify the inference-that he must have
                    acquired his knowledge in this manner. It has been suggested by Dr Jamieson,
                    that the strongest presumption of his having been born at so early a period, is
                    to be found in the circumstance of his being a dignitary of the church in the
                    year 1357. If we suppose him to have been born in 1316, he may have obtained
                    this preferment about the age of forty; and the same learned writer remarks that
                    it must have required very powerful interest to obtain it at a much earlier
                    period. We are not however sufficiently acquainted with the details of his
                    personal history, to be enabled to estimate the probability of his rapid
                    promotion; but, according to the canon law, he could be regularly appointed an
                    archdeacon at the age of twenty-five.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Decretalia Gregorii IX.</hi>
                            lib. i. tit. vi. cap. vii. §.2.</p></note> We must therefore be content
                    to leave conjectural dates as we found them, without attempting to decide
                    whether he was born in 1316, 1326, or 1330; but more authentic notices of this
                    venerable archdeacon have fortunately been preserved. On the 13th of August
                    1357, Edward HI., on the application of the Scotish king, granted Barbour a
                    safeconduct to visit the university of Oxford, accompanied by three
                        students.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N"
                            >Rymer, <hi rend="italic">Faedera,</hi> tom. vi. p. 31. <hi
                                rend="italic">Rotulì Scotice,</hi> tom. i. p· 808.</p></note> This
                    instrument expressly mentions that they are to repair thither for the purpose of
                    study, and of performing scholastic exercises; and it has been stated by a
                    distinguished ornament of the university that Barbour studied there during the
                    years 1357 and 1365.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p
                            part="N">Warton’s <hi rend="italic">Hist, of English Poetry,</hi> vol.
                            ii. p. 154. Price’s edit.</p></note> But as the safeconduct describes
                    him as archdeacon of Aberdeen, we cannot so easily admit that he comes under the
                    common denomination of an academical student, if by this term we understand a
                    person subjected to college discipline, and following a prescribed course of
                    study; nor is it unreasonable to conclude that the scholastic exercises were
                    solely to be performed by the three scholars who accompanied him. That he
                    completed his studies in this celebrated university, is however sufficiently
                    probable, though it must apparently have been at an earlier period of life. We
                    may venture to infer, that on the present occasion he repaired to Oxford, as
                    many individuals still repair to it, for the purpose of conferring with learned
                    clerks, and of consulting books which he had no opportunity of consulting at
                    home; and such a document may therefore be regarded as an honourable testimony
                    of his love of learning. Nor is it the only document of this kind. There is
                    another safeconduct, dated on the 6th of November 1364, and authorizing the
                    archdeacon of Aberdeen to visit England with four horsemen, in order to study at
                    Oxford or elsewhere, as he may judge expedient;<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Rotuli
                                Scotioe,</hi> tom. i. p. 886.</p></note> and a third, dated on the
                    30th of November 1368, authorizes him to travel through England with two
                    servants and two horses, on his way towards France for the same purpose of
                        study.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N"><hi
                                rend="italic">Rotuli Scotioe,</hi> tom. i. p. 926.</p></note> On the
                    13th of September 1357, the bishop of his diocese had nominated him one of the
                    commissioners who were to meet at Edinburgh, to deliberate concerning the ransom
                    of the captive king;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p
                            part="N">Rymer, <hi rend="italic">Foedera,</hi> tom. vi. p.
                        39.</p></note> but as he must then have received his passporťfor Oxford, it
                    is conjectured that this nomination was only intended as a compliment, and that
                    the actual duty was to devolve on a coadjutor, who is named in the same
                    instrument. On the 16th of October 1365 Edward had granted him permission to
                    travel through England, with six companions on horseback, towards St Denis and
                    other sacred places;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p
                            part="N">Rymer, tom. vi. p. 478. <hi rend="italic">Rotuli Scotioe,</hi>
                            tom. i. p. 897.</p></note> an expression which seems to indicate that
                    the object of his expedition was of a religious nature. After an interval of
                    several years, his name occurs in another authentic record; namely, in the list
                    of the auditors of exchequer, appointed on the 18th of February 1373, or,
                    according to our present computation, 1374. Here he is described as archdeacon
                    of Aberdeen, and “clericus probacionis domus domini nostri Regis and in the same
                    commission we find the name of Sir Hugh Eglintoun.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Accounts of the Great
                            Chamberlains of Scotland, <hi rend="italic">vol ii. p.
                        19.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p part="N">About this period, he was engaged in the composition of the work which
                    has transmitted his name to posterity; for it appears from his own statement
                    that in the year 1375 his work was more than half-finished.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><lg part="N">
                            <l part="N"> And in the tyme of the compiling </l>
                            <l part="N"> Off this buk, this Robert wes king, </l>
                            <l part="N"> And off his kynrik passit was </l>
                            <l part="N"> Fyve yer; and wes the yer off grace </l>
                            <l part="N"> A thousand, thre hundyr, sevynty </l>
                            <l part="N"> And fyve, and off his eld sixty. </l>
                        </lg><bibl default="false" status="draft"> ( <author> Barbour’s
                                    </author><title><hi rend="italic">Bruce,</hi></title> p. 274,
                                <editor> Jamieson’s </editor> edit.) </bibl></note> Dr Henry has
                    stated, but apparently without any competent authority, that it was undertaken
                    at the request of David IL, the son and successor of the heroic monarch whose
                    actions the author commemorates; and that a considerable pension was granted to
                    him as an encouragement to prosecute this design.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Henry’s <hi rend="italic">Hist.
                                of Great Britain,</hi> vol. iv. p. 472.</p></note> It is to be
                    recollected that David died in 1371, several years before Barbour had written
                    one half of his poem. The history of his pension was involved in much obscurity,
                    which has at length been removed by the researches of Dr Jamieson. Hume of
                    Godscroft had affirmed that his merit as the author of this poem was rewarded by
                    a pension from the exchequer during his life, that he transferred this pension
                    to the hospital of Aberdeen, and that it still continued to be paid in his own
                        lifetime.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N"
                                ><hi rend="italic">Hume’s</hi> Hist, of the Houses of Douglas and
                            Angus, <hi rend="italic">p. 31. Edinb. 1644, fol.</hi></p></note> The
                    terms of this statement are evidently at variance with each other; but the fact
                    of his having received a pension, or rather two different pensions, from the
                    crown, rests on unquestionable authority; and this fact cannot but be regarded
                    as creditable to the government of his country, nor must the extent of such
                    liberality be estimated by so fallacious a standard as the present value of
                    money. At a much later period, Hector Boyce enjoyed a revenue of forty marks, as
                    principal of King’s College, Aberdeen. Barbour’s pensions consisted of ten
                    pounds payable from the customs of Aberdeen, and twenty shillings payable from
                    the rent of the lands and fisheries which that city held of the crown.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N"><hi
                                rend="italic">Accounts of the Great Chamberlains of Scotland,</hi>
                            vol. ii. p. 128. 153—With respect to these pensions, many subsequent
                            entries occur. <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note> The first was
                    merely an annuity for his life, but the other was granted to him and his
                    assignees, with an express permission to dispose of it in mortmain; and it
                    appears from the records to have been granted by Robert II. as a reward for the
                    composition of his historical poem.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> vol. iii. p. 269.
                            Jamieson’s <hi rend="italic">Memoir of the Life of Barbour</hi> p.
                            viii.</p></note> This sum he did not bequeath to the hospital, but to
                    the dean and chapter of Aberdeen, under the condition that they <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193194112?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-4112-0369"/>should say
                    a yearly mass for the repose of his soul.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Accounts,</hi> vol. ii. p.
                            402.</p></note> His larger pension seems likewise to have been conferred
                    by the same king; and although this circumstance has not been traced in any
                    record, it was probably conferred for the same reason.</p>
                <p part="N">Although the <hi rend="italic">Pruce</hi> is the only work of Barbour
                    that is known to be extant, it is not the only work of which he was the author.
                    He appears to have written another book, doubtless in rhyme, comprising a
                    genealogical history of the kings of Scotland, and deducing their origin from
                    the Trojan colony of Brutus.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p part="N">With respect to the story of the Trojan origin
                            of another nation, “Ueber die Sage von der Trojanischen Abkunft der
                            Franken,” some curious notices may be found in W. C. Grimm’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Adtdänìsche Heldenlieder, Balladen, und Märchen,</hi>
                            S. 431. Heidelberg, 1811, 8vo.</p></note> We may venture to conclude
                    that his principal materials were drawn from very dubious sources; but although
                    the historical value of this production may not have been very conspicuous, it
                    would undoubtedly have been regarded as a curious relique of the literature of
                    the middle ages. The existence of such a work is fully established by various
                    passages in Winton’s chronicle.</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> This Nynus had a sone alsua, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Sere Dardane lord of Frygia. </l>
                    <l part="N"> Fra quham Barbere sutely </l>
                    <l part="N"> Has made a propyr Genealogy, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Tyl Robert oure secownd kyng, </l>
                    <l part="N"> That Scotland had in governyng.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                            type="authorial"><p part="N">Winton’s <hi rend="italic">Cronykil of
                                    Scotland,</hi> vol. i. p. 26.</p></note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> Of Bruttus lyneage quha wyll her, </l>
                    <l part="N"> He luk the tretis of Barbere, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Mad in-tyl a Genealogy </l>
                    <l part="N"> Rycht wele, and mare perfytly </l>
                    <l part="N"> Than I can on ony wys </l>
                    <l part="N"> Wytht all my wyt to yowe dewys.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                            type="authorial"><p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> vol. i. p.
                                54—Another early poet mentions Barbour as the author of different
                                works.</p><lg part="N">
                                <l part="N"> Master Barbour, quhilk was a worthi clerk, </l>
                                <l part="N"> He said the Bruce amang his othir werk. </l>
                            </lg><bibl default="false" status="draft"> ( <author> Henry’s
                                        </author><title><hi rend="italic">Wallace,</hi></title> p.
                                353.) </bibl></note></l>
                </lg>
                <p part="N">It is apparently the same book which the prior of Lochleven repeatedly
                    quotes under the title of the Brute; and we agree with Dr Jamieson in thinking
                    it highly probable tlιat this book is quoted by Barbour himself in the
                    subsequent passage.</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> Als Arthur, that throw chevalry </l>
                    <l part="N"> Maid Bretane maistres and lady </l>
                    <l part="N"> Off twelf kinrykis that he wan; </l>
                    <l part="N"> And alsua, as a noble man, </l>
                    <l part="N"> He wan throw bataill Fraunce all fre, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And Lucius Yber wencusyt he, </l>
                    <l part="N"> That then of Rome was emperour; </l>
                    <l part="N"> Bot yeit, for all his gret valour, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Mordreyt his systir son him slew, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And gud men als ma than inew, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Throw tresoune and throw wikkitnes; </l>
                    <l part="N"> The Broite beris thairoff wytnes.<note anchored="true"
                            place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N"><hi rend="italic"
                                    >Barbour’s</hi> Bruce, <hi rend="italic">p.
                        20.</hi></p></note></l>
                </lg>
                <p part="N">The archdeacon, as has already been hinted, died in 1396;<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Chartulary of
                            Aberaeen, <hi rend="italic">f. 115.</hi></p></note> and as he had
                    enjoyed his preferment for at least thirty-nine years, he must evidently have
                    reached an advanced period of life. His character, if we may be allowed to form
                    a conjecture from the general strain of his work, was of an amiable kind; and
                    his name has long been respected by his countrymen. The earliest edition of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Bruce</hi> which has hitherto been traced was published at
                    Edinburgh in 1616; but, as Patrick Gordon, whose poem was licensed in 1613,
                    describes it as “the old printed book,”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p part="N">Gordon's <hi rend="italic">Famous Historie of
                                the renounea and valiant Prince Robert, surnamed the Brvse, King of
                                Scotland.</hi> Dort, 1615, 4to.</p></note> there is reason to
                    believe that the first impression is of a much earlier date. Several other
                    editions appeared in the course of the seventeenth century; “and there are many
                    later editions of no value, published by different booksellers, to answer the
                    demand of the common people for this book; which, to the credit of their good
                    sense, is very great.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p
                            part="N">Pinkerton's <hi rend="italic">List of the Scotish Poets,</hi>
                            p. lxxxiii.</p></note> χV more elaborate edition was at length published
                    by Mr Pinkerton, from a manuscript in the Advocates Library; but as the
                    transcript was neither executed by himself, nor under his immediate inspection,
                    many gross inaccuracies were suffered to escape.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N"><hi rend="italic">The Bruce; or,
                                the History of Robert I. King of Scotland:</hi> written in Scottish
                            verse by John Barbour. The first genuine edition, published from a
                            manuscript dated 1489; with notes and a glossary by J. Pinkerton. Lond.
                            1790, 3 vols. 8vo.</p></note> After an interval of thirty years, another
                    edition, the best that has yet appeared, was published by Dr Jamieson from a
                    more careful collation of the same manuscript.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N"><hi rend="italic">The Bruce and
                                Wallace;</hi> published from two ancient manuscripts preserved in
                            the Library of the Faculty of Advocates: with notes, graphical sketches,
                            and a glossary. Edinb. 1820, 2 vols. 4to.</p></note> This appears from
                    the colophon to have been transcribed in 1489, by John Ramsay, who is supposed
                    to be the same person that was afterwards prior of the Carthusian monastery at
                    Perth. The transcript was executed at the request of Simon Lochmalony, vicar of
                    Moonsic; and thus every individual more immediately concerned, the poet, the
                    copyist, and his employer, belonged to the church.</p>
                <p part="N">When we endeavour to appreciate the literary merit of Barbour, we must
                    at the same time endeavour to transport ourselves to the remote and unrefined
                    age in which he lived; we must recollect the general barbarism of many preceding
                    centuries, the difficulty of acquiring liberal knowledge, the rude and grotesque
                    taste of almost all his contemporaries. When all these circumstances are duly
                    considered, his poem will be found entitled to an ample share of our
                    approbation. Fortunate in the choice of a subject, he has unfolded a series of
                    remarkable events, and has diffused over a very long narrative that lively
                    interest which an ordinary writer is incapable of exciting. Here we are not to
                    expect the blandishments of modern poetry: the author stands conspicuous amid
                    the ruins of time, and, like an undecayed Gothic tower, presents an aspect of
                    majestic simplicity. The lively strain of his narrative, the air of sincerity
                    which he always exhibits, his earnest participation in the success or sufferings
                    of his favourite characters, as well as the splendid attributes of the
                    characters themselves, cannot fail of arresting the attention of every reader
                    familiarly acquainted with the language in which he writes. The age of the great
                    King Robert was the age of Scotish chivalry, and the monarch himself presented
                    the most perfect model of a valiant knight. Whatever inconsistencies may have
                    appeared in his early conduct, the best portion of his life was undoubtedly
                    spent in the exercise of heroic valour or of political wisdom. Such a hero and
                    such a crisis were a most fortunate selection; and although the intrinsic merit
                    of the poet is very conspicuous, yet the attraction of the poem is partly to be
                    ascribed to his judicious choice of a subject.</p>
                <p part="N">Barbour was evidently skilled in such branches of knowledge as were then
                    cultivated, and his learning was so well regulated as to conduce to the real
                    improvement of his mind: the liberality of his views, and the humanity of his
                        <pb break="no" facs="nls:193194125?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0704-4125-0370"/> sentiments, appear occasionally to have been
                    unconfined by· the narrow boundaries of his own age. He has drawn various
                    illustrations from ancient history and from the stories of romance, but has
                    rarely displayed his erudition by decking his verses with the names oí ancient
                    authors: the distichs of Cato,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><lg part="N">
                            <l part="N"> And Catone sayis ws in his wryt, </l>
                            <l part="N"> That to fenyhe íbly quhile is wyt. </l>
                        </lg><bibl default="false" status="draft"> ( <author> Barbour’s
                                    </author><title><hi rend="italic">Bruce,</hi></title> p. 13.)
                            </bibl><p part="N">This passage evidently refers to the collection of
                            distichs which bears the name of Dionysius Cato, whom Chaucer likewise
                            calls Caton or Cathon; a circumstance which, as Mr Warton remarks, shews
                            that he was more familiarly known from the French translation than from
                            the Latin original.</p><lg part="N">
                            <l part="N"> Insipiens esto quum tempus postulat aut res: </l>
                            <l part="N"> Stultitiam simulare loco, prudentia summa est. </l>
                        </lg><bibl default="false" status="draft"> (Catonis <hi rend="italic"
                                >Disticha,</hi> lib. ii. 18.) </bibl><p part="N">This work of Cato
                            was held in the highest estimation during the middle ages, and it lias
                            been translated into Greek, Anglo-Saxon. German, French, and English. It
                            comprehends a series of moral lessons, which are often conveyed with a
                            considerable degree of terseness and compression. ' The author possesses
                            so much purity of diction, that Joseph Scaliger supposes he cannot have
                            flourished subsequently to the reign of Commodus or Severus; and Hen.
                            Cannegieter, who was alike conversant with philology and the civil law,
                            has employed several arguments, drawn from the history of the Roman
                            jurisprudence, to prove that this poet must at least have preceded the
                            reign of Constantine. <hi rend="italic">(Rescripta Boxhornìi đe
                                Catone,</hi> cap. xviii.) Cato, for example, speaks of divorcing a
                            wife, if she should become troublesome, “si coeperit esse molesta.”
                            (Lib. iii. 13.) But after the law of divorce had been modified by that
                            emperor, it was not competent for a husband to dismiss his. wife, merely
                            because he did not find her agreeable. <hi rend="italic">{Codex
                                Theodosianus,</hi> lib. iii. tit· <hi rend="superscript"> x</hi>.
                                <hi rend="superscript"> vι,</hi>) The most complete edition of
                            Dionysii Catonis <hi rend="italic">Disticha de Moribus ad Filium,</hi>
                            is the second published by Otto Arntzenius. Amst. 1754, 8vo. It contains
                            the notes of many learned commentators, the Greek versions of Planudes
                            and Scaliger, with the dissertation of Boxhornius, and the very copious
                            reply of Cannegieter.</p></note> and the spurious productions of Dares
                    Phrygius and Dictys Cretensis are the only profane books to which he formally
                    refers. He has borrowed more than one illustration from Statius, who was the
                    favourite classic of those times, and who likewise appears to have been the
                    favourite of Barbour; the more chaste and elegant style of Virgil and Horace was
                    not so well adapted to the prevalent taste, as the strained thoughts and
                    gorgeous diction of Statius and Claudian. The manner in which he has
                    incidentally discussed the subject of astrology and necromancy, may be specified
                    as not a little creditable to his good sense. It is well known that these
                    branches of divination were assiduously cultivated during the ages of
                    intellectual darkness. The absurdity of astrology and necromancy he has not
                    openly attempted to expose; for as the opinions of the many, however unfounded
                    in reason, must not be too rashly stigmatized, this might have been too bold and
                    decided a step. Of the possibility of predicting events he speaks with the
                    caution of a philosopher; but the following passage may be considered as a
                    sufficient indication of his deliberate sentiments:</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> And sen thai ar in sic wenyng, </l>
                    <l part="N"> For owtyue certante off witting, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Me think quha sayis he knawis thingis </l>
                    <l part="N"> To cum, he makys gret gabingis.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                            type="authorial"><p part="N">Barbour, p. 88.</p></note></l>
                </lg>
                <p part="N">To form such an estimate, required a mind capable of resisting a strong
                    torrent of prejudice; nor is it superfluous to remark, that in an age of much
                    higher refinement, Dryden suffered himself to be deluded by the prognostications
                    of judicial astrology.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p
                            part="N">Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Lives of English Poets,</hi> vol.
                            ii. p. 109.</p></note> It was not however to be expected that Barbour
                    should on every occasion evince a decided superiority to the general spirit of
                    the age to which lie belonged. His terrible imprecation on the person who
                    betrayed Sir Christopher Seton, “In hell condampnyt mot he be !” ought not to
                    have been uttered by a Christian priest. His detestation of the treacherous and
                    cruel King Edward induced him to lend a credulous ear to the report of his
                    consulting an infernal spirit. The misfortunes which attended Bruce at almost
                    every step of his early progress, he attributes to his sacrilegious act of
                    slaying Comyn at the high altar. He supposes that the women and children who
                    assisted in supplying the brave defenders of Berwick with arrows and stones,
                    were protected from injury by a miraculous interposition. Such instances of
                    superstition or uncharitable zeal are not to be viewed as marking the
                    individual: gross superstition, with its usual concomitants, was the general
                    spirit of the time; and the deviations from the ordinary track are to be traced
                    in examples of liberal feeling or enlightened judgment.</p>
                <p part="N">His encomium on political freedom is distinguished by a manly and
                    dignified strain of sentiment:</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> A! fredome is a noble thing! </l>
                    <l part="N"> Fredome mayss a man to haiff liking </l>
                    <l part="N"> Fredome all solace to man giffis: </l>
                    <l part="N"> He levys at ess that frely levys. </l>
                    <l part="N"> A noble hart may haiff’ nane ess, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Na ellys nocht that may him pless, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Gyff fredonιe failyhe; for fre liking </l>
                    <l part="N"> Is yharnyt our all othir thing. </l>
                    <l part="N"> Na he that ay hass levyt fre, </l>
                    <l part="N"> May nocht knaw weill the propyrte, </l>
                    <l part="N"> The angyr, na the wrechyt dome </l>
                    <l part="N"> That is cowplyt to foule thyrldome. </l>
                    <l part="N"> Bot gyff he had assayit it, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Than all perquer he suld it wyt, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And suld think fredome mar to pryss </l>
                    <l part="N"> Than all the gold in warld that is.<note anchored="true"
                            place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Barbour, p.
                        10.</p></note></l>
                </lg>
                <p part="N">From the satisfaction with which the poet seems to contemplate any
                    example of the gentler virtues, we may venture to draw a favourable inference
                    respecting the native benevolence of his disposition. The subsequent passage
                    cannot be passed without particular notice: the annals of heroes furnish but few
                    instances of so pleasing a nature, whether it be that heroes seldom stoop to
                    actions of mere benevolence,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p part="N">Ch yα <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> o </p><p
                            part="N">Kaκavt ∖τoιμc∣ μaλλo'j ń ivtζγtτt∣v∙ <bibl default="false"
                                status="draft"> ( <author> Menandri </author><title><hi
                                        rend="italic">Fragmenta,</hi></title> p. 158. edit. <editor>
                                    Meineke </editor> .) </bibl></p></note> or that their historians
                    do not think it of much importance to transmit such actions to posterity.</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> The king has hard a woman cry; </l>
                    <l part="N"> He askyt quhat that wės in hy. </l>
                    <l part="N"> “It is the layndar, Schyr,” said ane, </l>
                    <l part="N"> “That her child-ill rycht now has tane, </l>
                    <l part="N"> " And mon leve now behind ws her; </l>
                    <l part="N"> " Tharfor scho makys yoιιe iwill cher.” </l>
                    <l part="N"> The king said, “Certis it war pite </l>
                    <l part="N"> “That scho in that poynt left suld be; </l>
                    <l part="N"> “For certis I trow tharis na man </l>
                    <l part="N"> “That be ne will rew a woman than.” </l>
                    <l part="N"> Hiss ost all thar arestyt he, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And gert a tent sone stentit be, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And gert hyr gang in hastily, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And othyr wemen to be hyr by, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Quhill scho wes deliuer, he bad, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And syne furth on his wayis raid: </l>
                    <l part="N"> And how scho furth suld caryit be, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Or euir he furth fur, ordanyt he. </l>
                </lg>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193194138?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-4138-0371"/>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> This wes a full gret curtasy, </l>
                    <l part="N"> That swilk a king, and sa mighty, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Gert his men duell on this maner </l>
                    <l part="N"> Bot for a pouir lauender.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                            type="authorial"><p part="N">Barbour, p. 320.</p></note><hi
                            rend="superscript"> l</hi></l>
                </lg>
                <p part="N">Barbour seems to have been acquainted with those nicer springs of human
                    action which elude vulgar observation; he catches the shades of character with a
                    delicate eye, and sometimes presents us with instances of nice discrimination.
                    His work is not a mere narrative of events; it contains specimens of that minute
                    and distinct delineation which marks the hand of a skilful artist. An
                    illustration of this remark may perhaps be found in the following incident. When
                    Bruce has with his single arm defended a narrow pass against a party of two
                    hundred Gallovidians, his soldiers are represented as flocking around him with
                    the same eager curiosity as if they had never had another opportunity of seeing
                    him.</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> Syk wordis spak thai of the king, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And for his hey wndertaking </l>
                    <l part="N"> Farlyit, and yarnyt hym to se, </l>
                    <l part="N"> That with hym ay wes wont to be.<note anchored="true"
                            place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Barbour, p.
                        118.</p></note></l>
                </lg>
                <p part="N">In the opinion of an exquisite critic, Barbour has adorned the English
                    language by a strain of versification, expression, and poetical imagery, far
                    superior to the age.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p
                            part="N">Warton’s <hi rend="italic">History of English Poetry,</hi> vol.
                            ii. p. 154.</p></note> And Dr Nott remarks that he “had given his
                    countrymen a fine example of the simple energetic style, which resembled
                    Chaucer’s best manner, and wanted little to make it the genuine language of
                        poetry.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N"
                                ><hi rend="italic">Nott's</hi> Dissertation on the State of English
                            Poetry before the sixteenth Century <hi rend="italic">(p. cxc.),
                                prefixed to the Works of Surrey and Wyatt. Lond. 1815, 2 vols.
                                4to.</hi></p></note> The best method of estimating the merit of his
                    versification, will be to compare it with that of some English poet who
                    flourished about the same period; and, if placed in competition with the
                    versification of Chaucer, Gower, or Lydgate, the most celebrated English poets
                    of that era, it must certainly be admitted to appear with sufficient advantage.
                    Although a general conclusion cannot safely be drawn from a particular instance,
                    it may yet be worth while to compare the following quotations from Chaucer and
                    Barbour:</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> The byrdes that han lefft her songe, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Whyle they han suffred colde full stronge </l>
                    <l part="N"> In wethers grylle, and derke to syght, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Ben in May, for the sunne bryght, </l>
                    <l part="N"> So glad that they shewe in syngyng </l>
                    <l part="N"> That in her herte is suche lyking, </l>
                    <l part="N"> That they mote syngen and ben lyght: </l>
                    <l part="N"> Than doth the nyghtyngale her myght </l>
                    <l part="N"> To maken noyse and syngen blythe; </l>
                    <l part="N"> Than is blysfull many a sythe </l>
                    <l part="N"> The chelaunđre and the popyngay; </l>
                    <l part="N"> Than yonge folke entenden aye </l>
                    <l part="N"> For to ben gay and amarous, </l>
                    <l part="N"> The tyme is than so sauorious.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                            type="authorial"><p part="N">Chaucer's <hi rend="italic">Romaunte of the
                                    Rose:</hi> Workes, f. cxxviii. edit. Lond. 1542,
                        fol.</p></note></l>
                </lg>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> This wes in ver, quhen wynter tid, </l>
                    <l part="N"> With his blastis hidwyss to bid, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Was our drywyn, and byrdis smale, </l>
                    <l part="N"> As turturis and the nychtyngale, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Begouth rycht sariely to synge, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And for to mak in thair singyng </l>
                    <l part="N"> Swete notis, and sownys ser, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And melodys piesand to her; </l>
                    <l part="N"> And the treis begouth to ma </l>
                    <l part="N"> Burgeans, and brycht blomys alsua, </l>
                    <l part="N"> To wyn the helyng off their hewid, </l>
                    <l part="N"> That wykkyt wyntir had thaim rewid.<note anchored="true"
                            place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Barbour, p.
                        89.</p></note></l>
                </lg>
                <p part="N">Here the versification of Barbour is certainly not inferior o that of
                    Chaucer; but we have no intention to aver that the general merit of the two
                    poets is equal. Chaucer has attempted a great variety of subjects, and, for the
                    most part, with eminent success. His measures are also varied; , and, if we
                    compare his versification with that of preceding poets, or indeed with that of
                    his immediate successors, it will be found entitled to high commendation. He
                    reformed the taste and improved the language of his native country. The merit of
                    Barbour, though more circumscribed, is yet so eminent as to entitle him to a
                    very honourable place in the history of British poetry.</p>
                <p part="N">The style of this poet is distinguished by its terseness, and he often
                    exhibits a happy brevity of expression. His work contains a greater proportion
                    of French idioms than we discover in the writings of the preceding Scotish
                    poets, though their positive number is far from being considerable. Fiction is
                    not inseparably connected with verse. The historical merit of Barbour’s poem haş
                    been admitted by very competent judges; and, among others, Lord Hailes has
                    repeatedly acknowledged the general fidelity of his narrative. King Robert died
                    in 1329; and, as Barbour was employed in writing his poem within forty-six years
                    from that period, he must have enjoyed many opportunities of collecting
                    information. He might himself have conversed with warriors who fought at
                    Bannockburn; and on one occasion he quotes the authority of a valiant knight,
                    Sir Allan Cathcart, who was personally engaged in a particular exploit which he
                    is about to relate.</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> A knycht, that then wes in his rowt, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Worthi and wycht, stalwart and stout, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Curtaiss and fayr, and off gud fame, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Schyr Alane off Catkert by name, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Tauld me this taile, as I sail tell.<note anchored="true"
                            place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Barbour, p.
                        183.</p></note></l>
                </lg>
                <p part="N">Of the general merit of Barbour’s work, so favourable an estimate has
                    been formed by Mr Pinkerton, that it may not be improper here to produce his
                    testimony. “Perhaps the editor may be accused of nationality, when he says,
                    that, taking the total merits of this work together, he prefers it to the early
                    exertions of even the Italian muse, to the melancholy sublimity of Dante, and
                    the amorous quaintness of Petrarca, as much as M. Le Grand does <hi
                        rend="italic">a fabliau</hi> to a Provencal ditty. Here indeed the reader
                    will find few of the graces of fine poetry, little of the Attic dress of the
                    muse; but here are life, and spirit, and ease, and plain sense, and pictures of
                    real manners, and perpetual incident, and entertainment. The language is
                    remarkably good for the time, and far superior in neatness and elegance even to
                    that of Gawin Douglas, who wrote more than a century after. But when we consider
                    that our author is not only the first poet, but the earliest historian of
                    Scotland, who has entered into any detail, and from whom any view of the real
                    state and manners of the country can be had; and that the hero whose life he
                    paints so minutely, was a monarch equal to the greatest of modern times; let the
                    historical and poetical merits of his work be weighed together, and then opposed
                    to those of any other early poet of the present nations in Europe.”<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Pinkerton’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Preface to Barbour,</hi> p. x.</p></note> (x.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
