<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0713-0159-0672-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MADRAS (7th edition, volume 13, page 672)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp32">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sv3w">Cochineal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90257q">Servants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139321">Surfing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937852">Gardening</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937845">Gardeners</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814767">Armenians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193210159?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MADRAS</label>, a city of Hindustan, in the province of the
                    Carnatic, and the principal settlement and capital of the East India Company in
                    the southern peninsula of India. It is situated close to the margin of the sea,
                    and is a fortress of great strength. In appearance Madras differs widely from
                    Calcutta, having no European town, except a few houses, which are chiefly used
                    as warehouses in the fort. The European residents, mostly the servants of the
                    Company, live entirely in their garden-houses as they call them, which are all
                    so closely planted that the neighbouring dwelling is rarely visible. They repair
                    to the fort in the morning for the transaction of business, and return thence in
                    the afternoon. These garden-houses are very neat buildings, being mostly of one
                    story, and having a handsome balcony supported by pillars in front, with green
                    Venetian windows. The fort itself, called Fort St George, is handsome, strong,
                    and not too large; and, although not of so regular a design as Fort William,
                    yet, from the greater facility of relieving it by sea, and the natural
                    advantages of the ground, which leaves to an enemy no choice in the manner of
                    conducting his attacks, it may, on the whole, be deemed equal to it; besides
                    that it may be defended by a less numerous garrison. In the middle of the
                    present fortress stands the original one, a small square, now mostly converted
                    into government offices, and the town residences of some of the civil servants.
                    The nabob of the Carnatic has also a palace called Chepauk, situated on the
                    Chaultry Plain, at a little distance from the esplanade. The Chaultry Plain,
                    once the scene of Tippoo’s devastations, when he descended from the Ghauts, and,
                    sweeping the low country with his cavalry, carried dismay to the walls of Fort
                    St George, commences about a mile and a quarter south-west of this fort, from
                    which it is separated by two small rivers; the one the river Triplicane, winding
                    from the west, and gaining the sea about a thousand yards to the north of the
                    glacis; the other coming from the north-west, and passing round the high ground
                    of the western side of the Black Town, and continuing to the east within a
                    hundred yards of the sea, where it washes the foot of the glacis, and, running
                    for some time parallel with the beach, finally joins the Triplicane. at its
                    mouth. This plain extends two miles to the westward of the enclosures which
                    bound the St Thome road, and terminates on the other side at a large body of
                    water called the Meliapoor tank. It is now covered with the garden-houses of the
                    European settlers, who have converted a barren sand into a beautiful scene of
                    vegetation. The government-house is situated in the Chaultry Plain, on the edge
                    of the esplanade, and has the advantage of not being quite shut up, having a
                    pleasing view of the sea, and of Fort St George. The house itself is large and
                    handsome; the floors, the walls, and the pillars, are of the most beautiful
                    chunam of different colours, almost equal in splendour to marble itself. The
                    roads are a great ornament to the place, being broad, and shaded on each side by
                    a noble avenue of trees. To the southward of the fort stands the church, at the
                    back of which is the residence of the governor. To the northward of the old fort
                    stands the Exchange, on which, in 1796, a light-house was erected, the height of
                    which is ninety feet high, and it is visible from the sea at the distance of
                    seventeen miles. The botanical garden, reared at a vast expense by Dr Anderson,
                    was nearly destroyed by a violent hurricane on the 9th of December 1807, and is
                    now in a state of decay. In November 1803, a navigable canal was opened from the
                    Black Town to Ennore River, which communicates with Pullicat. It is 10,560 yards
                    in length, and thirty-five feet wide by twelve feet deep. By this channel boats
                    go to Pullicat, whence Madras is supplied with charcoal. The Black Town of
                    Madras stands to the northward of the fort, from which it is separated by a
                    spacious esplanade. It is nearly four miles in circuit, and was formerly
                    surrounded with fortifications sufficient to resist a surprise from a body of
                    horse; but, owing to the tranquillity that prevailed in the country, these have
                    long been neglected. It has some good streets and bazars; but the streets are
                    not regular, nor are the houses uniform: some of them are large brick buildings
                    with flat roofs, but the greater part are built of mud, with tiled roofs. It
                    makes a better appearance from a distance than when it is closely inspected. The
                    Black Town is the residence of the native Armenian and Portuguese merchants, and
                    also of many European settlers not the servants of the Company.</p>
                <p>In Lord Valcntia’s account of Madras, it is observed, that it would probably have
                    been difficult to find a worse place for a capital than that chosen for Madras,
                    on the extreme point of a coast where the current is most rapid, and where a
                    tremendous surf breaks even in the finest weather. But the original error of
                    fixing on this for the site of a great capital cannot now be recalled, the
                    expense of removal to a more convenient spot would be so great. Owing to the
                    exposed situation of Madras, it affords no secure anchorage <hi rend="italic"
                    >ļ</hi> and there is always a great difficulty in landing from vessels, which
                    generally moor in nine fathoms, with the flag-staff west-north-west, about two
                    miles from the shore. Any ship’s boat that should attempt to cross the surf
                    would inevitably perish; and, accordingly, the boats from ships anchor outside
                    the brokeh water, and wait for the country boats to carry the passengers safely
                    to the shore. These boats are of a particular construction, being built of soft
                    wood, with flat bottoms. They are sewed together, and have not a nail in their
                    whole construction, so that they are very light and pliable, and are borne many
                    yards through the surf without injury, as they yield to the waves like leather.
                    These boats require to be guided by seamen of experience and tried skill, and it
                    is an extremely critical operation to conduct them through the surf. When they
                    come within its influence, the cockswain stands up, and, under great agitation,
                    marks time with his voice and his foot, whilst the rowers work their oars
                    backwards until overtaken by the swell, which, curling up in its approach to the
                    shore, sweeps the boat along with fearful violence. The rowers now ply every oar
                    forward with their utmost vigour, to prevent the wave from carrying back the
                    boat with its receding swell; and by a few successive surfs the boat is at
                    length dashed high and dry on the shore. A species of floating machine called a
                    catamaran, formed of two or three light logs of wood, eight or ten feet in
                    length, lashed together with a small piece of wood inserted between them to
                    serve as a stem-piece, is employed by the fishermen and lower classes of natives
                    to carry them through the breakers. On these they go out to fish, or to carry
                    letters or small quantities of refreshments to ships when no boats can venture
                    out. They secure the letters in a pointed cap, where they cannot be damaged; and
                    when the men happen to be washed off by the surf, they regain the catamarans by
                    swimming, unless when they <pb break="no" facs="nls:193210172?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0713-0172-0673"/> are attacked by a shark. The dexterous navigators
                    of these frail vessels who distinguish themselves by saving persons in danger,
                    or by their care in conveying papers through the surf in dangerous weather, are
                    rewarded with medals.</p>
                <p>Madras, when seen from the sea, presents a striking appearance, the
                    fortifications of Fort St George being within a few yards of the shore; and, at
                    a distance, minarets and pagodas are seen mixed with trees and gardens. The
                    public offices and storehouses are fine buildings, with colonnades to the upper
                    stories, supported on arched bases, covered with beautiful shell-mortar from
                    Madras, which is hard, smooth, and polished. These being near the beach, which
                    is always crowded, form interesting objects. At a distance, the low, flat, sandy
                    shores extending to the north and south, and the small hills that are seen
                    inland, give an appearance of barrenness, which, however, improves on a closer
                    inspection. Madras is surrounded by a level country, which in general exhibits a
                    naked, brown, dusty plain, with few villages to enliven the scene, or any other
                    objects to relieve the eye, except a range of abrupt detached hills to the
                    south. The huts of the natives are covered with tiles, and are fully superior in
                    their appearance to those in Bengal; and in the inns and chaultries, also, which
                    are common on the roads, travellers experience greater attention. The soil in
                    the vicinity of Madras is very poor, and formerly provisions were scarce and
                    dear; but since the great accession of territory that has accrued to the Madras
                    presidency, they are brought from the Barramahal and other parts of the country
                    in great abundance. The soil, however, when it is cultivated, and where there is
                    abundance of water, produces a good crop of rice; and artificial irrigation
                    often makes up for natural disadvantages. The cattle that are found in the
                    neighbourhood of Madras are a small breed, such as are commonly seen in the
                    Deccan; but they are larger than those in the southern parts of Bengal.
                    Buffaloes of a small size arc generally used in carts.</p>
                <p>The manners of the Europeans at Madras, the state of society, and style of
                    living, are nearly the same as in other parts of India, except that provisions
                    are more expensive. Within doors, dinner parties, and, during the cold season,
                    monthly assemblies and balls, constitute the routine of amusements. Amongst the
                    public places of resort is the Mount Road, leading from the fort to St Thomas’s
                    Mount, which is quite smooth, and embellished on each side with banyan and
                    yellow tulip trees. Here it is customary for the fashionable parties in Madras
                    to repair, in their gayest equipages, during the cool of the evening, where they
                    drive slowly about the cenotaph which is here erected to the memory of Marquis
                    Cornwallis, and converse together. During the hottest part of the day, namely,
                    after two o’clock, which is the time when tiffin or the real dinner is eaten,
                    many retire to rest until five o’clock, when the master of the family returns
                    from the fort, and an excursion to the Mount Road, and dinner, then occupies the
                    remainder of the day, unless it be prolonged by a ball and supper in the
                    evening. The morning, from nine to eleven, is the time for visiting, when the
                    European residents call on each other, retail the news, and offer their services
                    to their friends in the city, to which they must repair for purposes of
                    business. Another tribe of visitors succeeds, and thus the forenoon passes
                    away.</p>
                <p>European passengers, when they land at Madras, being ignorant of the language,
                    manners, and customs of the country, necessarily rely on the natives for help;
                    and, accordingly, passengers landing at Madras are immediately surrounded by
                    numerous servants of all kinds, called dobashies, eager for employment They
                    undertake to transact for the Europeans all their necessary business, I to buy
                    all that is wanted, and to procure servants, tradesmen, palanquins, and the
                    like. They are of different castes, according to the nature of the duties which
                    they undertake to perform.</p>
                <p>Madras carries on a very considerable trade, not only with Europe, but with
                    China, Ceylon, Pegu, the Isle of France, New Holland, and different parts of
                    India. But, owing to the want of a navigable river, and the difficulty of
                    landing goods, it labours under great disadvantages, and its commerce is
                    inferior to that of the other two presidencies. From America the imports are
                    some inferior sorts of wines, spirits, and provisions. Rice is imported from
                    Bengal, also raw silk, canvass, piece goods, muslins, and shawls of a coarse
                    description, silk piece goods of an inferior kind, long pepper, sugar, borax,
                    saltpetre, precious stones, &amp;c. From Bombay are imported, through the
                    Persian and Arabian Gulfs, dried fruit or drugs, cotton and other goods; from
                    Ceylon, biche de mer, shark fins, ebony, &amp;c. also pearls; from China, tea,
                    sugar, nankeen, China ware, with alum, camphor, drugs, piece goods, stationery,
                    &amp;c.; from Manilla, indigo; from the Isle of France, brandy, copper, iron,
                    lead, &amp;c.; from Pegu, the staple article is timber; from the Malabar coast,
                    pepper, timber, coir, cordage, &amp;c.; from London, different articles of
                    European manufacture, in glass, iron, copper, tin, and other manufactures, also
                    supplies of wine and other necessaries; from Madeira, wine. The exports of
                    Madras consist of piece goods to America; to Batavia, piece goods of a coarse
                    coloured sort, handkerchiefs, and a proportion of southern blue cloths; to
                    Bengal, some red wood, coloured piece goods, and salt; to Bombay, chintz and
                    coloured turbans to an inconsiderable amount; to Ceylon, principally European
                    and China articles; to China, principally cotton; to Manilla, piece goods,
                    namely, cambays, handkerchiefs, &amp;c.; to the Isle of France, chiefly long
                    cloths, handkerchiefs, muslins, ginghams, &amp;c.; to Pegu, coarse
                    handkerchiefs, and copper, arrack, brandy, mace, cloves, iron, glass ware, naval
                    stores, &amp;c. which are re-exported. It does not appear that the trade of
                    Madras, which is really the trade of the coast of Coromandel, is increasing. For
                    this several causes are assigned. Amongst these are various oppressive inland
                    taxes, which obstruct the progress of improvement. Owing to the former monopoly
                    of the East India Company, the raw silks and nankeens of China, which could not
                    be exported directly to Europe, were brought to Madras, and thence re-exported.
                    They are now directly exported from Canton, and the trade is consequently lost
                    to Madras. The value of the exports and imports of Madras, in bullion and
                    merchandise, was in 1813-14 L.695,373, and in 1828-29 L.788,959, thus exhibiting
                    during this interval only the trifling increase of L.93,586.</p>
                <p>Considerable variety of coin circulates in Madras and its vicinity. Of the gold
                    coins, the principal are, star or current pagodas, value 7s. 5∣d. or 8s. The
                    gold rupee, new coinage, is worth L.l. 9s. 2d. The Arcot rupee, and the new
                    silver rupee, are worth Is. 11∣d., and Is. 11⅜d. The accounts are kept in star
                    pagodas, fanams, and cash; eighty cash make one fanam, twelve fanamsone rupee,
                    and forty-two fanaπιs a star pagoda. The natives keep their accounts at twelve
                    fanams sixty cash to a rupee, and forty-four fanams sixty cash to a pagoda. The
                    current coins consist of various sorts of pagodas, Arcot rupees, single and
                    double fanams, and copper coins of twenty, ten, five, and one cash each, called
                    dodees and half dodees.</p>
                <p>The English possessed no fixed establishment here until A. D. 1639, when they
                    received a grant from the Hindu dynasty of Bijanagur, then reigning at
                    Chandergherry, permitting the erection of a fort. In consequence of this
                    permission, Mr Day proceeded with great alacrity to the construction of a
                    fortress, which in India is soon surrounded by a town; and this town he allowed
                    to retain its Indian appellation, but the fort he named Fort George. The
                    territory granted along with it extended five miles along <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193210185?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0713-0185-0674"/> shore, and one
                    mile inland. For about a century, Madras, with the small portion of territory
                    adjoining, continued to be held by the Europeans, but rather under, or at least
                    with the consent of, the native powers, than as an independent colony. On the
                    12th of December 1687, the population of the city of Madras, Fort George, and
                    the villages within the Company’s bounds, was estimated to amount to 300,000
                    persons. In 1744 Madras was besieged by the French from the Mauritius under Μ.
                    de la Bourdonnais, at which period the native inhabitants within the Company’s
                    territory amounted to 250,000. The English in the colony did not exceed 300, and
                    of these 200 only were soldiers of the garrison. The town was taken on the 10th
                    of September, and was ransomed for L.440,000, besides plunder to the amount of
                    L.200,000 more. All the British inhabitants were afterwards compelled to abandon
                    the place. Madras was restored at the peace of Aix-la-Chapelle, and evacuated by
                    the French in August 1749, when it was found in a very improved condition, the
                    bastions and batteries having been greatly enlarged and strengthened. The
                    defences of the town were still, however, inferior to those of Fort St David,
                    where the East India Company ordered the presidency to continue. Madras was
                    again besieged in 1758, by the French under Μ. Lally. The siege commenced on the
                    17th of December 1758, and was prosecuted with vigour till the 17th of February,
                    when the French were obliged precipitately to raise it. This was the last and
                    most memorable siege which Madras ever sustained. The garrison consisted of 1758
                    European troops, 2200 sepoys, and 150 European inhabitants. The besieging force
                    consisted of 3500 Europeans, 2000 sepoys, and 2000 native and European cavalry.
                    Since this period Madras has never been assailed by an enemy, though nearly
                    approached by Hyder’s cavalry in 1781, when they descended from the mountains to
                    ravage the plains of the Carnatic. The population of the city of Madras, Fort
                    George, and the villages within the Company’s bounds, is 300,000. Long. 80. 25.
                    E. Lat. 13. 5. N. (Lord Valentia’s <hi rend="italic">Travels</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> Rennelľs <hi rend="italic">Memoir</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> Hamilton, &amp;c.)</p>
                <p>The presidency of Fort George, or of Madras, comprehends nearly the whole of
                    India south of the Krishna River, and also that large portion of the Deccan, the
                    Northern Circars. Within these boundaries there are three independent princes,
                    namely, the rajahs of Mysore, Travancore, and Cochin, who, though subject to the
                    Company in external politics, are left free to manage their own internal
                    concerns. The rest of the country is under the immediate jurisdiction of the
                    governor and council of Madras, and, for the collection of the revenue and the
                    administration of justice, is divided into the following districts,
                    namely,—∙</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1. Ganjam.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2. Vizagapatam.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Northern &lt;</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3. Rajamundry.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Circars.</p><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4. Masulipatam.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5. Guntoor, including Palnaud, which
                            is part of the Carnatic.</p><p>6. Nellore and Ongole, including part of
                            the Western Pollams or Zemindaries.</p><p>7. Northern division of Arcot,
                            including Sa-tivaid, Pullicat, Coongoody in the Barramahal, part of
                            Ballaghaut, and the Western</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Carnatic. &lt;</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Pollams or Zemindaries.</p><p>8.
                            Chingleput, or the Jaghire.</p><p>9. Southern division of Arcot,
                            including Cuddalore and Pondicherry.</p><p>10. Trichinopoly.</p><p>11.
                            Tanjore.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Mysore ∣</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12. ‘Dindigul, including Madura,
                            Manapara Pollams, Ramnad, and Shevagunga, form</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>and</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Carnatic. (</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ing part of the Southern
                            Carnatic.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Southern ì</p><p>Carnatic.
                            J</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13. Tinevelly.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15.* Cudapah } <hi rend="superscript"
                            > Bala</hi> g <hi rend="superscript"> !lílu</hi> t ceded
                            districts.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16. Seringapatam.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Mysore. &lt;</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>17. Salem and Kistnagherry.</p><p>18.
                            Coimbetoor.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>19. Canara.</p><p>20.
                            Malabar.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>21. Madras.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>A full account of these provinces, of the land revenue, the administration of
                    justice, and other details of the same nature, is given under the article <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Hindustan</hi>; also under the articles <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Canara, Malabar, Circars Northern,</hi> and the names of the districts into
                    which the presidency is divided. <hi rend="smallcaps">(f.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
