<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-0341-0391-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EUCLID of</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90c0c">Logic</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091282">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825809">Baling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:951741">Harrows</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1002014">Logic</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193750341?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">EUCLID <hi rend="smallcaps">of</hi></label><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Megara,</hi> a distinguished philosopher and logician, who
                    flourished about 400 years before Christ. The Athenians having prohibited the
                    Megareans from entering their city on pain of death, this philosopher disguised
                    himself in women’s clothes, in order to attend the lectures of Socrates. After
                    the death of Socrates, Plato and other philosophers went to Euclid at Megara, in
                    order to shelter themselves from the tyrants who then governed Athens. Euclid
                    admitted but one chief good, which he sometimes called God, sometimes Spirit,
                    and sometimes Providence.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Euclid of Alexandria,</hi> author of the most
                    ancient elements of geometry which have come down to us, and for this reason
                    justly regarded as one of the fathers of science. He has been sometimes
                    confounded with Euclid of Megara, the disciple of Socrates, and the founder of a
                    philosophic sect who pushed to an extreme the subtilties of dialectics. The
                    place of his birth is unknown. But Proclus Diadochus, one of his commentators,
                    informs us that he opened a school of mathematics in Alexandria in the reign of
                    Ptolemy the son of Lagus; and Pappus extols his kindness and affection for those
                    who laboured to advance the study of geometry. This being all that is known of
                    the life and character of Euclid, it only remains therefore to speak of his
                    works, some of which have been lost. Amongst those which we possess, however,
                    the most remarkable is that which is simply entitled <hi rend="italic"
                        >Elements,</hi> as if to indicate that it contained the entire body of
                    principles upon which the pure mathematics then rested. This work now consists
                    of fifteen books; but the last two are attributed to Hypsicles, a mathematician
                    of Alexandria who flourished at a later period. Euclid, however, neither was nor
                    could be the inventor of all that is contained in his work; for geometers more
                    ancient than he, including Hippocrates of Chio, had written Elements; but, on
                    the other hand, there can be little doubt that he added to the pre-existing
                    stock of elementary truths, improved the demonstrations in which his
                    predecessors had failed, and composed a whole which, by more severe forms of
                    reasoning, and a more exact concatenation of propositions, superseded all works
                    of the same description which had been previously written, and became the basis
                    of instruction in the mathematics. These <hi rend="italic">Elemeìits</hi> were
                    first commented on by Theon, and by Proclus; but whatever success such
                    commentaries may have had in the school of Alexandria, they remained wholly
                    unknown to the occidentals of the middle ages, who derived all their knowledge
                    of geometry, such as it was, from the works of Boe-cιus, and from a production
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Principiis Geometrice,</hi>
                    ascribed to St Augustin.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p
                            part="N">Montucla, Histoire đes Mathématiques, tom. i. p. 212 and
                            492.</p></note> It was only in the twelfth and thirteen centuries that
                    Athelard in England and Campano in Italy laboured to decipher and translate
                    Euclid from the Arabic versions, including the commentary of the Persian
                    geometer Nazir-Edđin, which was held in great estimation among the Saracens; for
                    although there <hi rend="superscript"> ls</hi> reason to believe that Boecius
                    had made a complete Latin translation of Euclid, it has not come down to our t ’
                    mes; and, in fact, it was not till long after the revival °i letters, and when
                    versions had been multiplied by means <hi rend="superscript"> 0 t</hi> 1 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> le</hi> press, that a part of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Elements</hi> of Euclid was introduced into the course of instruction in
                    the schools, <hi rend="superscript"> n 0r</hi> der to form an idea of the entire
                    work, however, it may be considered as composed of four parts. The first of
                    these parts comprehends the first six books, and may be divided into three
                    sections, viz. the demonstration of the properties of plane figures treated in
                    an absolute manner, as in books first, second, third, and fourth; the theory of
                    the proportions of quantities in general, which is the object of the fifth; and
                    the application of this theory to plane figures, as in book sixth. The second
                    part contains the seventh, eighth, and ninth books, which are denominated <hi
                        rend="italic">arithmetical,</hi> because they treat of the general
                    properties of numbers. The third part consists only of the tenth book, in which
                    the author considers in detail incommensurable quantities, and which he
                    terminates by proving that the diagonal of a square and its side cannot have a
                    common measure; a doctrine, we may add, which is much more ancient than Euclid,
                    since Plato, towards the close of his seventh book of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Laws,</hi> pronounces those who have no idea of such incommensurability as
                    sunk in almost brutish ignorance. The fourth part, which is composed of the last
                    five books, treats of planes and solids. But of all this great body of
                    geometrical doctrine, the only portions which have been considered as adapted to
                    the purposes of instruction are the first six books, together with the eleventh
                    and the twelfth; the propositions which they contain having formed the basis of
                    all the elements of geometry which, under whatever form, have from time to time
                    been given to the world. The fifth book, however, has often been omitted in such
                    publications, because the notation of our arithmetic, and still more that of our
                    algebra, have greatly simplified the theory of proportions; and, for the same
                    reason, the other arithmetical books, which it is now difficult to read, are
                    justly considered as more curious than useful. But, in borrowing their materials
                    from the work of Euclid, modern authors have frequently altered the arrangement;
                    and on this subject there have arisen two contradictory opinions, which have
                    been debated with very great warmth, yet still remain as irreconcilable as ever.
                    The concatenation established by Euclid, and even the forms which he has
                    employed in demonstrating his propositions, are regarded by some as almost the
                    last term of perfection in works of this kind; whilst others, again, have
                    considered these as mere essays, which, however excellent in themselves, leave
                    room for the introduction of a more natural order and more simple
                    demonstrations. Ramus, who declared war on the dialectics of Aristotle, accuses
                    Euclid of omissions and redundancies, and expresses his conviction that it was
                    with reference to these imperfections that Ptolemy inquired if there were not a
                    more easy method than that usually employed for learning geometry; an inquiry
                    which, as is well known, elicited from Euclid the reply, that in the mathematics
                    there was no road for kings. Antony Arnauld, and the author of the Logic of
                    Port-Royal, have also blamed the order followed by the Greek geometer, and
                    disputed some of his definitions;<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p part="N">fee Nouveaux Elements de la Géométrie, and the
                            Fourth Part of the Logique Port-RoijaL</p></note> but if Arnauld, either
                    from not being very profound in the mathematics, or by reason of the great
                    difficulty of the subject, failed, as Ramus and so many others had done, in the
                    changes which he attempted to introduce into the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Elements,</hi> his reasons for making the attempt still remain in all their
                    force. For, whatever may be said to the contrary, it is certain that they are
                    deficient in that order which, causing the propositions, as far as possible, to
                    arise out of one another, exhibits in full evidence the analogies which connect
                    them, assists the memory, and prepares the mind for the investigation of truth.
                    But whether, in the actual state of the science, it be practicable to reconcile
                        <pb break="no" facs="nls:193750354?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0709-0354-0392"/>this order with the rigour of demonstration,
                    or to obviate objections the force of which, abstractedly considered, cannot be
                    disputed, is a question which it would far exceed the limits of this notice to
                        discuss.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N"
                            >Lacroix, Essais sur l'Enseignement en général, et sur celui des
                            Mathématiques en particulier, Paris, 1805.</p></note> If it be resolved
                    affirmatively, which appears to us possible, then no reason would exist for
                    giving an absolute preference to the <hi rend="italic">Elements</hi> of Euclid.
                    As a precious relic of antiquity, and as one of those works of science which
                    time has thrown least in arrear of actual knowledge, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Elements</hi> would doubtless continue to be classed in the first rank of
                    mathematical productions; but their too arbitrary arrangement, and the style in
                    which they are written, sometimes too prolix and at other times too concise,
                    would no longer constitute the essential character of the geometric or synthetic
                    method, in opposition to the analysis of the moderns. The true difference of
                    these two methods of treating the science of quantities consists in this, that
                    the one is founded on the immediate consideration of the properties of figures,
                    whilst the other employs arbitrary signs, combined by the operations of
                    calculation. The first is geometry itself, not that of Euclid more than of any
                    other; the second is an application of algebra, which ought not to be confounded
                    with analysis, inasmuch as synthesis may be effected with algebraic signs as
                    well as with the figures of geometry. The latter, however, which may also be
                    treated analytically, presents operations equivalent to the resolution of
                    certain equations. Of this some propositions contained in^he book of <hi
                        rend="italic">Data</hi> are remarkable examples; propositions which, by a
                    natural and certain path, lead to the solution of problems otherwise
                    un-discoverable. The book of <hi rend="italic">Data</hi> was particularly
                    relished by Newton, who, persuaded that a proposition scarcely deserved to see
                    the light unless it could be demonstrated without the assistance of calculation,
                    conceived that a more profound study of this treatise would have enabled him to
                    dispense with the aid of such an instrument. But it may well be doubted, to say
                    nothing more, whether his successors, by pursuing a similar path, would have
                    ever attained those great and striking results which they have derived from the
                    new methods of calculation. Besides the <hi rend="italic">Elements</hi> and the
                        <hi rend="italic">Data·,</hi> which are the most important works of Euclid,
                    Pappus and Proclus mention the following: <hi rend="italic">Introductio</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Harmonica,</hi><hi rend="italic">Sectio Canonis,</hi> relating
                    to music; <hi rend="italic">Phoenomena,</hi> containing an exposition of the
                    appearances produced by the motion attributed to the celestial sphere, a work
                    subjoined to the book <hi rend="italic">De Sphoera</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Mobili</hi> of Autolycus; <hi rend="italic">Optica, Catoptrica,</hi>
                    concerning direct vision and mirrors; <hi rend="italic">Liber de</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Divisionibus,</hi> treating of the divisions of polygons; and
                    the lost works, entitled <hi rend="italic">Porisma-turn</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >libri, Locorum</hi><hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic">superficiem
                        libri, Fallaciarum</hi><hi rend="italic">liber,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Conicorum libri.</hi> At the end of the works of Euclid is a short
                    fragment, entitled <hi rend="italic">De Levi</hi><hi rend="italic">et
                        Ponderoso,</hi> the author of which is unknown; it is, however, of almost no
                    value. The editions of the works of this geometer are so numerous that we cannot
                    undertake to indicate all of them, and must therefore confine ourselves to the
                    principal ones. Of the complete works there are, 1. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Euclidis</hi><hi rend="italic">Opera, Groece, cum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Theonis expositione,</hi><hi rend="italic">cura</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Grĳnoei,</hi> Bale, 1530, in fol.; 2. <hi rend="italic">Euclidis</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">quoe</hi><hi rend="italic">supersunt</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >omnia, ex</hi><hi rend="italic">recensione</hi><hi rend="italic">Davidis
                        Gregorii, Groece</hi><hi rend="italic">et Latine,</hi> Oxford, 1703, in
                    fol.; 3. <hi rend="italic">Les OEuvres</hi><hi rend="italic">d Euclιde</hi><hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">on</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Grec, en Latin, et en Français, d'apres un Manuscrit très ancien, qui était
                        reste inconnu jusqu'à nos jours,</hi> par Peyrard, Paris, 1814, in 8vo. The
                    manuscript here referred to was one of several sent from Rome by Monge, and
                    supposed to date from the end of the ninth century; in it the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Data</hi> are placed immediately after the thirteenth book, and thus
                    separate from the rest of the work the fourteenth and fifteenth books, which are
                    ascribed to Hypsicles. In 1533, Her. vage published at Bale, in folio, a
                    complete edition of the <hi rend="italic">Elements,</hi> in the Greek text, with
                    the exposition of Theon, and the Commentaries of Proclus on the first book. The
                    following are the principal Latin translations: 1. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Proeclarissimum Opus</hi><hi rend="italic">Elementorum Euclidis
                        perspicacissimi</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">artem</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Gcometrioe,</hi> the first publication of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Elements</hi> by means of printing, Venice, 1482; 2. <hi
                        rend="italic">Εuelidis</hi><hi rend="italic">Elementorum libri</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">XV.</hi><hi rend="italic">una</hi><hi rend="italic">cum
                        scholiis</hi><hi rend="italic">antiquis,</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Frederico</hi><hi rend="italic">Commandino</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Urbinate</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Latinum conversi, Commentariis quibusdam illustrati,</hi> Pesaro, 1572, in
                    fol.; 3. <hi rend="italic">Euclidis Elementorum libri XV.
                        demonstrationibus</hi><hi rend="italic">αccuτα∙</hi><hi rend="italic">tisque
                        scholiis illustrati, auctore Christophoro</hi><hi rend="italic">Clαviο,</hi>
                    1574, in 8vo; 4. <hi rend="italic">Euclidis Elementorum libri XV. breviter
                        demonstrati, opera</hi><hi rend="italic">I. Harrow,</hi> London, 1678, in
                    8vo; 5. <hi rend="italic">Elementorum Euclidis libri XV.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >ad</hi><hi rend="italic">Groeci</hi><hi rend="italic">contextus fidem
                        recensiti et ad usum tyronum accommodati, edente</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Bαcrrnαηη</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> Leipsic, 1769, in 8vo; 6.
                        <hi rend="italic">Euclide Megarense</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >philοsορlιο</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">solo
                        introduttore</hi><hi rend="italic">delle</hi><hi rend="italic">scientie
                        mathematiche diligenternente reassettato</hi><hi rend="italic">per
                        Nicolo</hi><hi rend="italic">Tartaleo Brisciano.</hi> This last, however, is
                    rather a paraphrase than a translation. The following are editions which only
                    contain part of the <hi rend="italic">Elements:</hi> 1. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Analysis</hi><hi rend="italic">Geometrica</hi><hi rend="italic">sex</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">librorum Euclidis</hi><hi rend="italic">α Christiano
                        Herlino,</hi><hi rend="italic">una</hi><hi rend="italic">cum</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">commentariis et</hi><hi rend="italic">scholiis</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">perbrevibus</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >eosdem libros a</hi><hi rend="italic">Cunrado Dasypodio,</hi> 1566, in
                    fol.; 2. <hi rend="italic">Euclidis Elementorum libri</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >priores</hi><hi rend="italic">sex,</hi><hi rend="italic">item</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">undecimus</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >duodecimus,</hi> Oxford, 1747, in 8vo; 3. <hi rend="italic">Euclidis
                        Elementorum libri priores</hi><hi rend="italic">sex,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >etc.</hi><hi rend="italic">sublatis iis quibus olim hi libri a Theone
                        aliisve vitiati sunt, et quibusdam demonstrationibus restitutis</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">a Roberto</hi><hi rend="italic">Simson,</hi> Glasgow, 1756, in
                    4to; 4. <hi rend="italic">Elements de la</hi><hi rend="italic">Geometrie</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript">
                        ,</hi><hi rend="italic">Euclide,</hi><hi rend="italic">ou les six premiers
                        livres d'Euclide, avec le XI</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> e</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">et le XII</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> e</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">, traduction nouvelle par</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Frederic</hi><hi rend="italic">Castillan,</hi> Berlin, 1775, in 8vo. The
                    other works of Euclid, printed separately, are, 1. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Euclidis</hi><hi rend="italic">Data, Claudius Hardy Groece nunc</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">primum edidit, Latine vertit,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >scholiis</hi><hi rend="italic">illustravit</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">adjectus est Marini philosophi Commentarius,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Groece</hi><hi rend="italic">et Latine,</hi> Paris, 1625, in
                    4to; 2. <hi rend="italic">Euclidis Rudimenta Musices,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Groece</hi><hi rend="italic">et Latine excusa, J. Pena interprete,</hi>
                    Paris, 1557, in 4to; 3. <hi rend="italic">Euclidis Introductio
                        Harmonica,</hi><hi rend="italic">Groece etc.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Meibornius vertit ac notis explicavit</hi> in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Antiqui</hi><hi rend="italic">Musicoe</hi><hi rend="italic">Auctores,
                        VII.</hi> Amsterdam, 1652, in 4to; 4. <hi rend="italic">Optica et</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Catoptricα, Graece</hi><hi rend="italic">ei Latine
                        reddita,</hi><hi rend="italic">per Jo.</hi><hi rend="italic">Penam,</hi>
                    Paris, 1557, in 4to. For further details see Murhard, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bibliotheca</hi><hi rend="italic">Mathematico·</hi> (tom. ii. pp. 1-48),
                    and other similar works. We have not thought it necessary to notice the more
                    recent editions of the <hi rend="italic">Elements,</hi> which are in the hands
                    of every body, <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
