<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-9951-0361-09" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ERNESTI, John Augustus</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698f7b">Editing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f766849">Theologians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892p9k">Spiritism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:902451">Editing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:902462">Editions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1149517">Theologians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193749951?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">ERNESTI, <hi rend="smallcaps">John
                        Augustus</hi></label>, one of the most illustrious philologers and
                    theologians of the last century. He was or∏on the 4th August 1707, at Tennstadt,
                    of which place is father, likewise a distinguished theologian, was pastor, and
                    superintendent of the electoral dioceses of Thuringia, az, and Sangerhusen.
                    After having received his first ins ruction in the learned languages, under the
                    domestic dis-tιp me of his father, and in the gymnasium of his native , <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 0</hi> " <hi rend="superscript"> n</hi> &gt; he was sent
                    at the age of sixteen to the celebrated axon cloister school of Pforta. Here he
                    continued four J ears. At the age of twenty he entered the university of
                    Wittemberg, where he studied eloquence and ancient life rature under the
                    celebrated Berger, theology under Wernsdorf, and the Wolfian philosophy under
                    Schlosser. From Wittemberg he passed to the university of Leipsig, where he
                    applied himself to the mathematical sciences under Hausen, following the courses
                    of Boerner and Deyling on theology, and the lectures of Gottsched on German
                    eloquence. In 1730 he was made master in the faculty of philosophy. In the
                    following year he accepted the office of conrector in the T homan school of
                    Leipsig, of which J. M <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi>. Gesner was then rector;
                    and on Gesner’s vocation, as professor of eloquence, to Göttingen, he succeeded
                    him as rector. In this situation, by his erudition, diligence, and the elegance
                    of his methods, he surpassed all his contemporaries, and created an epoch in
                    Germany for the study of the ancient authors. From this office, in opposition to
                    the present custom, which precludes a translation into the universities to the
                    masters of the subordinate schools, he was, in 1742, named as extraordinary
                    professor of ancient literature in the university of Leipsig, and in 1756
                    promoted to the ordinary professorship of eloquence. In both these chairs he
                    kne¶v how to combine more intellect, philosophy, and taste, than had been done
                    by any of his predecessors. His reputation as a scholar, and his rational
                    treatment of the biblical exegesis, paved the way for his entrance into the
                    theological faculty. Through the elegance of his learning, and his manner of
                    discussion, he co-operated with Baumgarten of Halle in disengaging dogmatic
                    theology from the scholastic and mystical excrescences with which it was then
                    deformed; and thereby contributed greatly to the new revolution in theology,
                    although he himself never deyiated from the ancient system. In these deserving
                    labours, and with unbroken health, he attained an honourable old age; and died,
                    after a short illness, in his seventy-sixth year, on 11th September 1781.</p>
                <p part="N">Whether Ernesti be considered as a philologer or theologian, it is
                    perhaps as much from the impulsion which he gave to sacred and profane criticism
                    in Germany, as from the intrinsic excellence of his own works in either
                    department, that he must derive his reputation. With Gesner, he instituted a new
                    school in ancient literature; and, after Crocus, Melanchthon, and Camerarius,
                    has been perhaps the greatest reformer and promoter of classical learning in
                    Germany. With Semler he partially co-operated in the great revolution of
                    Lutheran theology; though he is guiltless of all participation in the deductions
                    which many of those who profess themselves his disciples have drawn from the
                    principles which he established.</p>
                <p part="N">An enthusiastic and enlightened study of the ancient Greek and Roman
                    authors is the well-merited boast of the present German literature. This
                    commenced, in its existing form, towards the middle of the last century. Not
                    that Germany, before that period, had neglected ancient literature, or could not
                    enumerate her proportion among the great names of classical erudition. No
                    nation, in fact, had produced so many, or more illustrious, scholars immediately
                    after the Reformation; but for a long time polite literature had become
                    deformed, if not neglected, in proportion as religious wars and polemical
                    theology had exhausted and engrossed her governments and universities. The
                    German scholars were chiefly theologians, and theologians who had studied every
                    thing in reference to their peculiar profession. Add to this, that the most
                    disgusting and inefficient methods had been introduced, whereby the spirit of
                    the instruction was at utter variance with the object of the study. Accordingly,
                    during the whole of the seventeenth and the first half of the eighteenth
                    century, Germany was far excelled by Holland in the number and excellence of her
                    nhilologers; and it was not until the appearance<pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193749964?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0709-9964-0362"/> of Gesner
                    and Ernesti, with thcĩr somewhat earlier contemporaries, Cortius, Daniel
                    Longolius, and Michael Heusinger, that she could oppose above one or two rivals
                    to the great critics of the Dutch schools. Gesner and Ernesti, however, through
                    the influence of their lectures at the greater universities of Göttingen and
                    Leipsig, through the wider extent of their labours in philology, and still more
                    through the greater excellence of their methods, are alone entitled to be held
                    the founders of the new German school of ancient literature. Both excelled their
                    philological countrymen in taste, in the elegance of their Latin style, in a
                    philosophical spirit, and in a wider acquaintance with the subsidiary branches
                    of erudition. Both made an advantageous use of their critical knowledge of the
                    languages; both looked at once to the words and to the subject of the ancient
                    writers, established and applied the rules of a legitimate interpretation, and
                    carefully analysed the meaning as well as the form of the expression. Both
                    contributed effectually to expel the old absurd and disgusting methods of
                    instruction from the schools and universities, and to introduce an improved and
                    more effectual system. To the epoch whfch they formed, many circumstances indeed
                    contributed :—their acquaintance with the Dutch criticism; the universal
                    enthusiasm of the Germans for establishing a national literature, and for
                    becoming at the same time reformers in the departments of ancient learning; and
                    withal the spirit of philosophy which at that period in Germany began more and
                    more to blend itself with every part of science and literature. It is also true
                    that their editions do not possess the complement of erudition and criticism
                    which distinguish those of many of their contemporaries; their commentaries have
                    the precision, but how inferior are they in certainty, copiousness, and depth of
                    illustration, to those of the philologers of Holland? In their editions of the
                    Latin classics, they returned back to the somewhat inconvenient method of
                    Cellarius, collecting their principal illustrations into an <hi rend="italic"
                        >Index</hi><hi rend="italic">Rerum et Verborum,</hi> as is done by Gesner in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Quintilian,</hi> and by Ernesti in his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cicero</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> not, however, that they did not possess
                    the means of illustrating their author with a rich critical and philological
                    commentary, of which the former has given ample proof in his editions of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Scriptores</hi><hi rend="italic">de Re</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Rustica,</hi> and in his <hi rend="italic">Claudian,</hi> and the latter in
                    his two most valuable labours, his <hi rend="italic">Suetonius</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Tacitus.</hi> Both, but especially Ernesti, have detected
                    grammatical niceties in the Latin tongue, which had escaped all preceding
                    critics; such, among others, are the use of the subjunctive mood after the
                    pronoun <hi rend="italic">qui,</hi> and the legitimate consecution of the
                    tenses. His canons are, however, not without exceptions. As an editor of the
                    Greek classics, Ernesti deserves hardly to be named beside his Dutch
                    contemporaries, Hemsterhuis, Valkenaer, Ruhnken, or his colleague and enemy the
                    learned and unfortunate Reiske. How insignificant are his own labours in his
                    editions of Homer and Callimachus? In regard to the higher criticism, it was not
                    even attempted by Ernesti. But to him and to Gesner the peculiar praise is owing
                    of having formed, partly by their discipline, and partly by their example,
                    philologers greater than themselves; and to them is due the honour of having so
                    strongly excited in Germany that enthusiasm for ancient learning, which has now,
                    unfortunately, no parallel, in the other countries of Europe.</p>
                <p part="N">As a theologian, Lrnesti is far less conspicuous than as a scholar, and
                    his influence not so marked either on his contemporaries or on his successors.
                    Before the middle of the eighteenth century, the Spenerian pietism had been
                    almost banished from the Lutheran theology; and the professors of that faculty
                    in the Protestant universities of Germany no longer excluded philosophy from all
                    interference in the doctrine of Christian belief. It had then been boldly
                    proclaimed and maintained with pre-eminent ability by Semler, that Luther had
                    commenced and not finished the Reformation of religion; but that this
                    Reformation must still proceed, and that religion, like other branches of
                    knowledge. must become purer and more perfect in proportion to the increase of
                    knowledge and the development of the human mind. At this date, accordingly, the
                    theologians of Germany had begun to disregard the nonconformity of their
                    doctrines with the formula of the Lutheran church; and after this period few
                    were at all apprehensive of openly controverting its tenets when at variance
                    with the results of their own speculations. From the unrestrained freedom of
                    thought in matters of religion which was now indulged, if not even encouraged,
                    by the governments in their different universities, every one was at perfect
                    liberty, without any derogation from his character as a clergyman or instnιctor,
                    to maintain and promulgate what opinions in religion he chose; and it must be
                    acknowledged that the theologians have made, and are still making, ex ery use
                    and abuse of this license, and have arrived at every conclusion that piety and
                    learning, as well as presumption, folly, and irréligion can suggest. It was at
                    the commencement of this important era that Ernesti flourished as a
                    theologian.</p>
                <p part="N">Of the three sciences subsidiary to theology, philosophy, history, and
                    grammatical exegesis, the first had been imperfectly applied, and without any
                    interesting result, by Baumgarten, a scholar of Wolf; but the second, the
                    historical interpretation, had, in the hands of Semler, been productive of
                    conclusions subversive of much that had been hitherto held orthodox and even
                    sacred. In the grammatical interpretation of the New Testament some imperfect
                    progress had been made by Bengel; but the new epoch in the biblical exegesis
                    commences with John David Michaelis for the Old, and with Ernesti for the New
                    Testament. It is, indeed, chiefly in <hi rend="italic">hermeneutic</hi> that
                    Ernesti has any claim to the character of a great theologian. But here his
                    merits arc distinguished, and, at the period when his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Institutio Interpretis</hi><hi rend="italic">N.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >T.</hi> was published, almost peculiar to himself. He applied himself to
                    the interpretation of the sacred Scriptures, after a long and familiar
                    acquaintance with the Greek and Roman writers, and when formed in his mind and
                    taste by a constant study of these patterns. His interpretation of the New
                    Testament bears the character of both these circumstances. It is not only the
                    matter, but at the same time the manner in which it is conveyed,—it is the
                    selection of subjects, with the precision, the pregnant brevity, the elegance
                    and simplicity, in which they are expressed,—that confers on this little book so
                    high and so singular a value. We find in it the principles of a general
                    interpretation, and this without the assistance of any particular philosophy,
                    not even of the Wolfian, to which Ernesti was attached; but consisting of
                    observations and rules, which, though already enunciated, and applied in the
                    criticism of the profane writers, had never rigorously been employed in the
                    biblical exegesis. He admits in the sacred writings only <hi rend="italic">one
                        acceptation,</hi> and that the <hi rend="italic">grammatical,</hi>
                    convertible into and the same with the <hi rend="italic">logical</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">historical.</hi> The Scriptures, therefore, having this in
                    common with all other writings, it follows that they can only be explained like
                    mere human compositions; that the rules of interpretation are the same in both;
                    and that only through some peculiar constitution of speech and writing could any
                    possible distinction between these subsist. He therefore justly censures the
                    opinion of those who, in the illustration θ <hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> the
                    Scriptures, refer every thing to the illumination oí the Holy Spirit ;· as well
                    as that of others who, in contempt <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> all knowledge
                    of the languages, would explain words by things, and thus introduce into the
                    holy writings their peculiar glosses and opinions. The <hi rend="italic">analogy
                        of faith,</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> as</hi><hi rend="italic
                        subscript"> t</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi> rule of
                    interpretation, he greatly limits, and teaches that it <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193749977?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0709-9977-0363"/>can never
                    alone afford the explanation of words, but only determine the choice among their
                    possible significations, <hi rend="subscript"> a</hi> ∏d must always stand in
                    need of philology as an assistant. The spirit of Ernesti’s interpretation gives
                    no countenance, however, to the results which many of his followers have deduced
                    from the grammatical and historical exegeses. Every principle of his
                    interpretation rests on the assumed inspiration of the holy books; and there is
                    not perhaps a better antidote to the poisonous tenets of many of those who
                    profess to be of his school, than the diligent study of his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Interpres,</hi> and the relative <hi rend="italic">Acroases</hi> of Morus.
                    In the higher criticism of the sacred books Ernesti did nothing. In dogmatic he
                    always expressed great contempt of strict systematic theology; and though he
                    lectured for many years on the Aphorisms of Neumann, it was rather in refutation
                    than in support of his text-book.</p>
                <p part="N">Among his works the following are the more important:</p>
                <p part="N">I. In profane literature:</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Initia</hi><hi rend="italic">Doctrines</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Solidioris,</hi> 1736, 8vo; many subsequent editions. A work
                    not only valuable by reason of the real excellence of the matter, but more
                    particularly deserving an attentive study, on account of the purity of the
                    Latin, in discussing subjects of philosophy known only to the moderns.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Initia Rhetorica,</hi> 1730.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Xenophontis</hi><hi rend="italic">Memorabilia</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Socratis,</hi><hi rend="italic">cum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >notis,</hi> 1737; often reprinted.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Ciceronis</hi><hi rend="italic">Opera cum clave,</hi>
                    1737; 2d edit. FIalae, 1757; 3d edit. ibid. 1776, 8vo, 6 vols.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Suetonius cum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Animadversionibus,</hi> 1748; 2d edit. 1775-8.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Tαeiti Opera cum</hi><hi rend="italic">notis</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">J. Lipsii, Jo. Er. Gronovii</hi><hi rend="italic">et
                        suis,</hi> 1752; 2d edit. 1772; 8vo. Another edition, with many additions
                    and improvements, has been procured by Oberlin.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Aristophanis Nubes</hi><hi rend="italic">cum
                        Scholiis</hi><hi rend="italic">Antiquis</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">proefatione,</hi> 1754, 8vo.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Corradi</hi><hi rend="italic">Quaestura cum
                        proefatione,</hi> 1754, 8vo. SeeWyt-tenbach in his <hi rend="italic">Vita
                        Ruhηlιenii.</hi><hi rend="italic">Hed&amp;rici Lexicon Groecum,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">multis Vocabulorum millibus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Αueturn,</hi> 1754-67, 8vo.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Homeri Opera Omnia, ex Recensione, et cum
                        Notis</hi><hi rend="italic">Sam. Clαrhii,</hi><hi rend="italic">accessit
                        Varietas Lectionum</hi><hi rend="italic">MS. Lips,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >et</hi><hi rend="italic">Edit. Vet.</hi><hi rend="italic">cura</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">J. A. E.</hi><hi rend="italic">qui et suas Notas
                        adspersit,</hi> 1759-64, 5 vols. 8vo.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Callimachi Hymni</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Epigrammata, cum Notis</hi><hi rend="italic">Var.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Latine</hi><hi rend="italic">vertit atque Notis adjecit.</hi>
                    Lugd. Bat. 1761, 8vo, 2 vols.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Polybius eum Notis Var.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Proefationem</hi><hi rend="italic">et Glossarium</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Pοlybiaηurn</hi><hi rend="italic">adjecit.</hi> Viennae et Lips. 1764, 3
                    vols. 8vo.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Arehaeologia</hi><hi rend="italic">Litteraria,</hi>
                    1768. A new and improved edition by Martini.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Horatius</hi><hi rend="italic">Tursellinus de</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Particulis,</hi> 1769, 8vo.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Fabricii</hi><hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Latina
                        nunc</hi><hi rend="italic">melius delecta, rectius</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >diyestα</hi><hi rend="italic">et aueta,</hi> vol. i. and ii. 1773; vol.
                    iii. 1774, 8vo, unfinished.</p>
                <p part="N">II. In sacred literature:</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Aηtimurαtorius</hi><hi rend="italic">sive Confutatio
                        Disputationis</hi><hi rend="italic">Muratori-anae de rebus Liturgicis,</hi>
                    1755—58.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Neue Theologische Bibliothek,</hi> vol. i. to x.
                    1760-69, 8vo.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Institutio Interpretis</hi><hi rend="italic">Nov.
                        Test.</hi> 1761, reprinted in the <hi rend="superscript"> 9ame</hi> year at
                    Leyden; 2d edit. 1765; 3d edit. 1775; 8vo.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Neueste Theologische Bibliothek,</hi><hi rend="italic
                        smallcaps"> no\.</hi> i. to x. 1771-75, 8vo. Besides these, he published
                    above a hundred smaller works in the form of prefaces, academical dissertations,
                    programmata, memoriae, elogia, epistles, orations, translations, &amp;c. Many of
                    these have been collected in the three 1° Jθ2 <hi rend="superscript"> v</hi> i
                        <hi rend="superscript"> n</hi> g publications:— <hi rend="italic">Opuscula
                        Oratoria,</hi> Lugd. Bat.</p>
                <p part="N">6'~; 2d edit. 1767; 8vo. <hi rend="italic">Opuscula</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Philologica ct Cri-ιcα,</hi>.Lugd. Bat. 1764; 2d edit. 1776;
                    8vo. <hi rend="italic">Opuscula</hi><hi rend="italic">The-οtοyιcα,</hi> Lips.
                    1773, 8vo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
