<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-9210-0304-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EPHESUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1076986">Prions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1131272">Stadiums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978609">Ionians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193749210?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">EPHESUS</label>, the chief city of Ionia, in Asia
                    Minor, on the south side, and near the mouth of the river Cayster (now called
                    Kutchuc Mendeι⅞, or Lesser Maeander), was 320 stadia, or forty miles, to the
                    south of Smyrna, and 540, or three days’ journey, from Sardis, the capital of
                    Lydia. It was situated at the extremity of a rich and beautiful plain, called
                    Campus Cilbianus, through which the river flowed, and which still retains its
                    former character, after centuries of Turkish oppression. Ephesus was originally
                    founded by the Leleges and Carians, who were compelled to make way for an Ionian
                    colony led by Androclus, son of Codrus. The inhabitants continued to be
                    distributed over the neighbouring district until the reign of Croesus (560 to
                    546 B. c.), when, being attacked by that prince, they are said to have dedicated
                    their city to Diana, by fastening a rope from their walls to the temple of the
                    goddess. They gradually deserted the ancient site, and approached the position
                    of the sacred temple, where they are said to have continued until the time of
                    Alexander the Great (330 <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.).</hi> Lysimachus having
                    obtained possession of the city (302 <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.),</hi> compelled
                    the inhabitants, by inundating the ancient site, to remove higher up to a spot
                    which he surrounded with walls. We find that it was delivered over to the kings
                    of Pergamus by the Romans, after the defeat of Antiochus (190 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.</hi> c.); and, amidst all the changes of government
                    which subsequently took place, Ephesus continued to increase in riches and
                    prosperity, being in the time of Strabo (24 <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.)</hi> the
                    emporium of Asia. It was considered by the Romans as the first of the three
                    chief cities of Asia, the two others being Smyrna and Pergamus; and in the later
                    divisions of the country under the Christian emperors, we are told by Hierocles
                    that it was the capital of the important provinces of Asia. Ephesus was lost to
                    the empire at an earlier period than the other parts of Western Asia. Some time
                    before the commencement of the Crusades (1096 <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.),</hi>
                    a chief of the Saracens made himself master of Ephesus; but the crusaders
                    restored it to its ancient master. In the fourteenth century it fell into the
                    hands of a prince of Caramania named Sasan; and from this time it ceased to
                    belong to the Greek empire. It still, however, continued to exist down even to
                    the time of Timur or Tamerlane (1370 <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.),</hi> who for a
                    considerable period had a camp under its walls, and who is supposed to have
                    destroyed it, as he did many other cities.</p>
                <p part="N">Ephesus was more particularly celebrated on account of the temple of
                    Diana, which, according to Pausanias, ex∙ ĩsted even before the arrival of the
                    Ionĩans. Its architect was Cbersiphron of Cnossus, in Crete, assisted by his son
                    Metagenes; and as the ground on which the temple Was erected was marshy, it is
                    said that he obtained a firm foundation by means of heaps of charcoal and wool,
                    packed closely together in sacks. It was the only temple in Asia which escaped
                    the doom pronounced against them by Xerxes on his return from Greece (480 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.</hi> c.); but it was burnt to the ground 356 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.</hi> c. by a madman named Eratostratus, who is said to
                    have taken this method of immortalizing his name. This event took place the very
                    night on which Alexander the Great was born; and the temple seems to have
                    remained in ruins till that monarch offered to restore it, on condition that he
                    should be declared the founder. This proposal, however, the Ephesians declined
                    to accept, cunningly soothing the wounded vanity of the hero by saying, “that it
                    was beneath the dignity of one god to erect a temple to another.” Having
                    collected sufficient funds amongst themselves and their neighbours, they
                    entrusted its restoration to the architect Dinocrates, who is reported to have
                    conceived the extravagant project of forming a statue of Alexander out of Mount
                    Athos. The new edifice was much larger, and constructed with more magnificence,
                    than the original temple. It was 425 feet in length and 220 in breadth, with 227
                    pillars, each 60 feet in height. It is said to have been <hi rend="italic"
                        >of</hi> the Ionic order of architecture. The interior was adorned with
                    numerous pieces of sculpture by the celebrated Praxiteles. Thraso and Scopas
                    were also e±- ployed in its decoration; and there was a picture in it by the
                    celebrated Apelles. The statue of the goddess was more particularly the object
                    of veneration, having been preserved in safety amidst all the vicissitudes to
                    which the temple and city had been exposed. It was of wood, and, according to
                    Pliny, was covered with some unctuous substance, to guard it from decay. The
                    service of the temple was performed by priests called Megabyzae, who were
                    eunuchs, and to whom were added a number of priestesses. The temple was an
                    asylum for criminals of every description. Alexander extended the privilege to a
                    stadium round the edifice; Mithridates fixed it at a bow-shot; and Antony
                    doubled the distance, so that it included part of the town. It may easily be
                    conceived that such a privilege must have been liable to great abuses; and in
                    fact it became at last so dangerous to the peace of the city, that Augustus
                    caused it to be abolished. It was seven stadia, or about an English mile, from
                    the walls of the city; but no modern traveller seems yet to have discovered its
                    remains. Pococke has indeed given a ground plan of what he considered as the
                    temple; but his description by no means agrees with w hat is related of the
                    seventh wonder of tlιe world.</p>
                <p part="N">The ruins of Ephesus are seen half a mile from the Turkish village of
                        <hi rend="italic">Aiasluk,</hi> which seems to have risen about the middle
                    of the fourteenth century. Chandler thus speaks of its present appearance:
                    “Ephesus was situated by the mountains which are the southern boundary of the
                    plain, and comprehended within its walls a portion of Mount Prion and of
                    Corissus. Mount Prion is a circular hill; Corissus a single lofty ridge,
                    extending northward from near Mount Pactyas, and approaching Prion, then making
                    an elbow, and running westerly ţ°‘ wards the sea. We entered Ephesus from <hi
                        rend="italic">Aiasluk</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">¶</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >*·</hi> Mount Prion, and the exterior lateral wall of a stadium which
                    fronted the sea, on our left hand. We measured the area, and found it 687 feet
                    long. The vestiges of the theatre alluded to in the Acts of the Apostle⅛ which
                    was very capacious, are farther on in the side <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193749223?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0709-9223-0305"/>the same
                    mountain. Going on from the theatre, you come ,to a narrow valley which divides
                    Mount Prion from Co-irissus. Within the valley you find broken columns and
                    pieces of marble, with vestiges of an odeum in the slope jf Prion. Beyond the
                    odeum the valley opens gradually into the plain of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Aiasluh.</hi> Keeping round by Prion, you meet with vestiges of buildings,
                    and come to the remains of a large edifice. This was the gymnasium. The street
                    at the entrance of the city from <hi rend="italic">Aiasluk</hi> was nearly of
                    the <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi> ength of the stadium. The opposite side was
                    composed of edifices equally ample and noble. The way was between a double
                    colonnade, as ŵe conjectured, from the many pedestals and bases of columns
                    scattered there. This street was covered by one leading from the plain to the
                    valley. It had on the left the front of the stadium, and the theatre with the
                    portico adjoining. On the right are ample substructures, with pieces of massive
                    wall. These remains reach as far as the portico, and have behind them a morass,
                    once the city port. The extent of the city towards the plain, on which side it
                    was washed by the Cayster, cannot now be ascertained; but the mountainous region
                    has preserved its boundary, the wall erected by Lysimachus, which is of
                    excellent masonry. Near the entrance of Ephesus from <hi rend="italic"
                        >Aiasluk</hi> are the vaults of several sepulchres, and others along the
                    slope of Corissus show that the Ephesians buried likewise within the city.” <hi
                        rend="italic">Travels in Asia Minor,</hi> chap. 35.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
