<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-7388-0583-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AMALEK</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 583</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1746469">Grandsons</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950737">Ham</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4g737392">Sword</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8ds25">Ham</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204236">Israel</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193037388" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AMALEK</label>, the son of Eliphaz, by Timna his concubine,
                    and the grandson of Esau. (Gen. xxxvi. 12, and 1 Chr. i. 36.) Amalek succeeded
                    Gatam in the government of Edom. He was the father of the Amalekites, a powerful
                    people who dwelt in Arabia Petraea, between the Dead Sea and the Red Sea, or
                    between Havila and Shur (1 Sam. xv. 7), sometimes in one canton and sometimes in
                    another. It does not appear that they had cities, for there is no mention of any
                    but one in the Scriptures (1 Sam. XV. 5): they lived generally in hamlets,
                    caves, or tents.</p>
                <p>The Israelites had scarcely passed the Red Sea on their way to the wilderness,
                    before the Amalekites came to attack them in the deserts of Rephidim (Exod.
                    xvii. 8, &amp;c.), and cruelly put to the sword those who were obliged either
                    through fatigue or weakness to remain behind. Moses, by divine command, directed
                    Joshua to fall upon this people,—to record in a book the act of inhumanity which
                    they had committed, in order to have it always before their eyes,—and to revenge
                    it in the most remarkable manner. Joshua therefore fell upon the Amalekites and
                    defeated them, while Moses was upon the mountain, with Aaron and Hur in company.
                    Moses, during the time of the engagement, held up his hands, to which the
                    success of the battle was owing; for as often as he let them down, Amalek
                    prevailed. But Moses’ hands being tired, Aaron and Hur supported his arms, and
                    held them extended while the battle lasted, which was from the morning till the
                    approach of night, when the Amalekites were cut in pieces. This happened in the
                    year of the world 2513, before Christ 1491.</p>
                <p>The ground of the enmity of the Amalekites against the Israelites is generally
                    supposed to have been an innate hatred, from the remembrance of Jacob’s
                    depriving their <pb break="no" facs="nls:193037401" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7401-0584"
                    />progenitor both of his birthright and blessing. Their falling upon them,
                    however, and that without any provocation, when they saw them reduced to so low
                    a condition by the fatigue of their march and an excessive drought, was an
                    inhuman action, and justly deserved the severe punishment inflicted on them by
                    Joshua. Under the Judges (v. 3), we see the Amalekites united with the
                    Midianites and Moabites in a design to oppress Israel; but Ehud delivered the
                    Israelites from Eglon, king of the Moabites (Judg. iii.), and Gideon (chap,
                    viii.) delivered them from the Midianites and Amalekites. About the year of the
                    world 2930, Saul marched against the Ama-lekites, advanced as far as their
                    capital, and put all the people of the country to the sword; but he spared the
                    best of the cattle and movables, contrary to a divine command; which act of
                    disobedience was the cause of his future misfortunes.</p>
                <p>After this war the Amalekites scarcely appear any more in history. However, about
                    the year of the world 2949, a troop of Amalekites came and pillaged Ziklag,
                    which belonged to David (1 Sam. xxx.), where he had left his two wives, Ahinoam
                    and Abigail; but he returning from an expedition which he had made in the
                    company of Achish into the valley of Jezreel, pursued them, overtook and
                    dispersed them, and recovered all the booty which they had carried off from
                    Ziklag.</p>
                <p>The Arabians maintain that Amalek was the son of Ham, and grandson of Noah; that
                    he was the father of Ad, and grandfather of Schedad. Calmet thinks that this
                    opinion is by no means to be rejected, as it is not very probable that Amalek,
                    the son of Eliphaz, and grandson of Esau, should be the father of a people so
                    powerful and numerous as the Amalekites were when the Israelites departed out of
                    Egypt. Moses, in the book of Genesis (xiv. 7), relates, that in Abraham’s time,
                    long before the birth of Amalek the son of Eliphaz, the five confederate kings
                    carried the war into Amalek’s country, about Ka-desh; and into that of the
                    Amorites, about Hazezon-tamar. The same Moses (Num. xxiv. 20) relates, that the
                    diviner Balaam, observing at a distance the land of Ama-lek, said, in his
                    prophetic style, “Amalek is the first, the head, the original of the nations;
                    but his latter end shall be, that he perish for ever.” Our commentator observes,
                    that this epithet of the first of nations cannot certainly agree with the
                    Amalekites descended from the son of Eli-phaz, because the generation then
                    living was but the third from Amalek. Besides, Moses never reproaches the
                    Ama-lekites with attacking their brethren the Israelites; an aggravating
                    circumstance which he would not have omitted had the Amalekites been descended
                    from Esau, in which case they would have been the brethren of the Israelites.
                    Lastly, we see the Amalekites almost always classed in Scripture with the
                    Canaanites and the Philistines, and lever with the Edomites; and when Saul made
                    war upon the Amalekites, and almost utterly destroyed them, we do not find that
                    the Edomites made the least attempt to assist them, or to avenge their cause
                    afterwards. Thence it is thought probable that the Amalekites who are so often
                    mentioned in Scripture were a free people descended from Canaan, and devoted to
                    the curse as well as the 3ther Amorites, and very different from the descendants
                    if Amalek, the grandson of Esau.</p>
                <p>The accounts which the Arabians give us of the Amalekites destroyed by Saul are
                    as follows: Amalek was the father of an ancient tribe in Arabia, exterminated in
                    the reign of Saul. This tribe contained only the Arabians who are called <hi
                    rend="italic">Pure,</hi> the remains whereof were mingled with the posterity of
                    Joktan and Adnan, and so became Mosarabes or Mostaarabes; that is to say,
                    Arabians blend ed with foreign nations. They further believe that Goliath, who
                    was overcome by David, was king of the Amalekites; that the giants who inhabited
                    Palestine in Joshua’s time were of the same race; and that at last part of the
                    Amalekites retired into Africa while Joshua was yet living, and settled upon the
                    coasts of Barbary, along the Mediterranean Sea. The son of Amalek was Ad, a
                    celebrated prince among the Arabians. Some make him the son of Uz, and grandson
                    of Aram the son of Shem. Be this as it may, the Mahometans say that Ad was the
                    father of an Arabian tribe called <hi rend="italic">Ädites,</hi> who were
                    exterminated, as they tell us, for not hearkening to the patriarch Eber, who
                    preached to them the unity of God. Ad had two sons, Schedad and Schedid.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
