<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-6712-0531-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALMAMON, or Mamon</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 531</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4nv99965">Amines</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bc6v">Caliphs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:844315">Caliphate</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:844318">Caliphs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807594">Amination</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807596">Amines</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193036712" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALMAMON, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Mamon</hi></label>, also
                    named <hi rend="italic">Abdallah,</hi> caliph of Bagdad, was born A. n. 785. His
                    elder brother Al Amin succeeded to the caliphate on the death of his father, and
                    Almamon at that time was governor of Chorasan. As by the will of the father it
                    was provided that his three sons should succeed to the caliphate in order,
                    Almamon ordered his elder brother to be proclaimed caliph throughout his
                    government; but his brother repaid his friendship and attachment to his interest
                    with open expressions of hatred, and unjust attempts to exclude him from the
                    destined succession. Almamon was thus forced to consult measures for his own
                    safety and promotion, by causing himself to be proclaimed caliph. After various
                    struggles, his general, Thaher, in the year 813, took possession of Bagdad,
                    pursued Al Amin to his retreat, and caused him to be assassinated, so that
                    Almamon remained without a competitor. Various rebellions disturbed the
                    tranquillity of the first years of his reign; but, by his prudent administration
                    and vigorous exertions, these were at length extinguished. Instigated by the
                    advice of his vizier, he soon after raised greater commotions, and exposed his
                    dignity to greater dangers, by countenancing the sect of Ali. He invited to
                    court Iman Rizza, gave him his daughter in marriage, and even declared him his
                    successor in the empire. He assumed the green turban, the colour of the house of
                    Ali, and obliged his courtiers and soldiers to imitate his example. Alarmed at
                    these proceedings, the orthodox Mussulmans, and the house of Abbas, excited a
                    great revolt in Bagdad, and proclaimed Ibrahim, Almamon’s uncle, caliph. A civil
                    war was just about to commence, when Fadel the vizier was assassinated, and
                    Rizza died. The people of Bagdad then deposed Ibrahim, and returned to their
                    former allegiance. Taking the advantage of Almamon’s absence, Thaher seized upon
                    the government of Chorasan, where he founded a dynasty which existed during a
                    period of sixteen years.</p>
                <p>Almamon employed the period of tranquillity that followed, in introducing
                    literature into his dominions, and in its improvement; which constitutes the
                    greatest glory of his reign. During the days of his father he discovered an
                    ardent thirst after knowledge, by forming a college in Chorasan, adorned with
                    the most eminent men of various countries; and appointed Mesue, a famous
                    Christian physician of Damascus, for their president. When his father
                    remonstrated against conferring such an honour upon a Christian, he reminded him
                    that the most learned men and the most skilful artists in his dominions were
                    Jews and Christians; and added, that he had chosen Mesue as a preceptor in
                    science and useful arts, and not as a teacher of religion. Under his auspices
                    Bagdad became the seat of literature, of private and academical instruction, and
                    the habitation of men of eminence from all quarters. Many valuable books in the
                    Greek, Persian, Chaldean, and Coptic languages, among which were the works of
                    Aristotle and Galen, were translated into the Arabic at his own expense. This
                    caliph himself deemed it an honour to set an example to others of the becoming
                    respect due to mental cultivation, by visiting the schools, and treating the
                    professors with great regard. In mathematics, astronomy, and philosophy, he made
                    a rapid and extensive progress. He was the author of astronomical tables, which,
                    on account of their accuracy, have been much admired. By these various exertions
                    the character of the Saracens was suddenly changed from a rude and ferocious to
                    a polite and civilized people, while the most powerful and extensive of the
                    European states were involved in ignorance and barbarism. Literature has
                    sustained some irreparable losses from his too great partiality to the Arabic
                    writers, which induced him to destroy the originals of the translated
                    manuscripts. He is represented by the Sonnites, or orthodox Mahometans, as
                    little better than an infidel, because of his attention to philosophy and
                    letters. His conduct, however, shows that he was not sufficiently careful to
                    preserve a philosophical mean between the different religious parties during the
                    time of his administration, as he openly manifested a predilection to the
                    doctrines of the Motazeli, who asserted the freewill of man, and denied the
                    eternity of the Koran. Some allege that, on account of the murmurs which arose
                    against him, he was induced to exhibit too great a zeal, by establishing a kind
                    of inquisition, to compel all his subjects to profess Islamism. The experiment,
                    however, soon terminated in the better and juster expedient of universal
                    toleration; and it is abundantly evident that the Christians in his dominions
                    never felt the power of his inquisition.</p>
                <p>The public transactions of his reign are in themselves important. In the year 822
                    he sent a body of his troops to the assistance of Thomas, a Greek, who made war
                    on Michael the Stammerer, the emperor of Constantinople, and besieged his
                    capital. This expedition, which on the part of the caliph seems to have been
                    founded in justice, proved unsuccessful; Thomas was taken prisoner, and suffered
                    death. In the years 829 and 830 he commenced hostilities upon the Greeks,
                    rendered himself master of many places, and carried devastation into their
                    territories. He was successful in suppressing a revolt in Egypt in the year 831.
                    In this country he was led to discover a treasure buried under two columns by
                    Merwan, the last caliph of the house of Ommijah. In repairing a decayed <hi
                    rend="italic">mihias</hi> or measuring pillar, and erecting a new one for
                    determining the gradation of the increase of the Nile, Almamon displayed his
                    love of science. In the year 833 he again visited Egypt: on his return he
                    penetrated into the territories of the Greek emperor, even into Cilicia.
                    Returning home, he encamped on the banks of a river, and, èxcited by thirst,
                    drank too freely of the water, and at the same time indulged himself
                    immoderately in eating a particular kind of dates, which brought on a complaint
                    in his stomach, and reduced him to the most imminent danger. Sensible of his
                    approaching dissolution, he sent letters into all the provinces, announcing his
                    brother Motassem his successor, and then patiently awaited the event. After a
                    tedious struggle under the pressure of his disease, and while uttering this
                    ejaculation, “0 thou who never diest, have mercy on me, a dying man !” he
                    expired at the age of 48 or 49 years. He reigned 27 years and some months, and
                    was buried at Tarsus, which some religious zealots interpreted as a mark of
                    reprobation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
