<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0702-4996-0399-06" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">ALEPPO, or Halab</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 399</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qh7s">Arminianism</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80q31">Arminians</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1141359">Syrians</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:895648">Ditches</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:937895">Gardens</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:937852">Gardening</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:937845">Gardeners</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193034996" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">ALEPPO, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Halab</hi></label>, a town of
                    Syria, the capital of a pachalic, of which the limits are not exactly defined,
                    is situated in the vast plain which extends from the Orontes to the Euphrates,
                    and which towards the south terminates in the desert. It is built on eight hills
                    or eminences, and is intersected by the Kowick, which in winter swells into a
                    large stream, overflowing its bridges, and the neighbouring gardens which cover
                    its banks. This river terminates 18 miles beyond Aleppo, in a morass which is
                    haunted by wild boars and pelicans. The city itself is above 3½ miles in
                    circumference, and is surrounded by an ancient strong stone-wall and ditch.
                    Including the suburbs, the city is about 7 or 8 miles in compass. The wall is
                    flanked by frequent towers; but the ditch is partly filled up with rubbish or
                    occupied by kitchen-gardens, and the city being commanded by the adjacent
                    heights, is entirely indefensible. The town has nine gates, all known by
                    different names. On one of the hills on which the city is built, and on its
                    north-east corner, is a castle seated on a mount. This mount is of a conic form,
                    which seems in a great measure to be raised with the earth thrown up out of a
                    deep broad ditch which surrounds it. The castle is entered from the south by a
                    bridge of seven lofty narrow arches thrown over the ditch, on which are two
                    gates fortified by turrets, and two more still higher on the hill. Aleppo is
                    esteemed the fourth city of the Ottoman empire, only exceeded by Constantinople,
                    Cairo, and Damascus. It appeared to Mr Buckingham, who visited it in 1816, to be
                    one of the best built of all the cities in the East that he had seen. In the
                    regularity of the streets, the aspect of the houses, and also in cleanliness, it
                    was decidedly superior to the generality of Turkish towns. The houses are large
                    and commodious, having terraces on their tops, on which the inhabitants sleep in
                    summer, and generally sky-lights in form of a dome to let the light into the
                    rooms, which, from their loftiness, the gilding on the window-shutters, cupboard
                    doors, &amp;c. have at first entrance a very grand and agreeable effect. They
                    are all so equal in height, that there are seldom any steps to ascend or descend
                    in going from one house to another; while several large vaulted streets increase
                    the facility of communication, by affording a passage to every part of the city
                    free from the embarrassment of the open streets. They are carefully paved, have
                    two commodious footpaths, six inches high on each side, and the middle of the
                    street is laid with brick, the small end upwards, for the convenience of the
                    horses.</p><p>The mosques in Aleppo are numerous, and seven or eight of them are considered
                    handsome, though none has more than a single minaret or steeple. They are built
                    of freestone, with a dome in the middle, which is covered with lead. The members
                    of the Greek, Arminian, Syrian, and Maronite communions have each a church; and
                    the Europeans formerly had four small convents; but in 1807 there was only one,
                    containing nine Italian monks. Before each of them is an area, with a fountain
                    in the middle, designed for ablutions before prayers; and behind some of the
                    larger there are little gardens. There are about twenty large khans or
                    caravansaries, consisting of a capacious square, on all sides of which are
                    rooms, built on the groundfloor, used occasionally for chambers, warehouses, or
                    stables. Above stairs there is a colonnade or gallery on every side, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193035009" xml:id="kp-eb0702-5009-0400"/> in
                    which are the doors of a number of small rooms, wherein the merchants, as well
                    strangers as natives, transact most of their business. Numerous coffee-houses
                    are seen in all parts, some large and handsome, with a fountain in the middle,
                    and a gallery for musicians. They are greatly frequented, and by persons of the
                    highest rank.</p><p>The bazars or market-places are long, covered, narrow streets, on each side of
                    which is a great number ∙of small shops, just sufficient to hold the tradesman
                    and his goods, the buyer being obliged to stand without. Each separate branch of
                    business has a particular bazar, which is locked up, as well as the streets, an
                    hour and a half after sunset. This city is in itself one of the most agreeable
                    in Syria, and is a trading and bustling place; and, owing to the great resort of
                    Europeans, is considered by Mr Buckingham to be more than 100 years in advance
                    of the other parts of Syria. On whatever side it is approached, its numerous
                    minarets and domes present an agreeable prospect to the eye, fatigued with the
                    continued sameness of the brown and parched plains. In the centre is an
                    artificial mountain surrounded by a dry ditch, on which is a ruinous fortress.
                    From hence we have a fine prospect of the whole city. To the north we discover
                    the snowy mountains of Bailan, and on the west those which separate the Orontes
                    from the sea, while to the south and east the eye can see as far as the
                    Euphrates. In the time of Omar this castle stopped the progress of the Arabs for
                    several months, and was at last taken by treachery; but at present it would not
                    be able to resist the feeblest assault. Its slight wall, low and without a
                    buttress, is in ruins; its little old towers are in no better condition; and it
                    has not four cannons fit for service, not excepting a culverine nine feet long,
                    taken from the Persians at the siege of Bassora. Three hundred and fifty
                    janizaries, who should form the garrison, are busy in their shops. Within the
                    walls of the castle is a well, which, by means of a subterraneous communication,
                    derives its water from a spring a league and a quarter distant. In the environs
                    of the city we find a number of large square stones, on the top of which is a
                    turban of stone, which are so many tombs. Aleppo maybe considered the emporium
                    of Armenia and Diarbekir. Four caravans annually proceed through Natolia to
                    Constantinople, and others arrive from Bagdad and Bassora with coffee from
                    Mocha, and with muslins, shawls, and other goods from India. Caravans are sent
                    also to Medina and Mecca, with which places a regular intercourse is maintained.
                    The commerce with Europe is principally carried on from Scanderoon and Latakia,
                    on the sea-coast. The chief commodities exported are, raw or spun cottons,
                    clumsy linens fabricated in the villages, silk stulfs manufactured in the city,
                    copper, <hi rend="italic">bourres</hi> (coarse cloths) like those of Rouen,
                    goats’ hair brought from Natolia, the gall-nuts of the Kourdistan, the
                    merchandise of India, and pistachio-nuts of the growth of the neighbourhood. The
                    articles supplied by Europe are cloths, Lyonese stuffs, and bonnets after the
                    fashion of Tunis from France; merceries, indigo, tea, sugar, paper, soap,
                    &amp;c.; and a great quantity of coral ornaments. The coffee of America, though
                    prohibited, is introduced, and serves to mix with that of Mocha. British,
                    French, Dutch, and Italian houses are established at Aleppo, for the purposes of
                    trade; and most of the European states have consuls resident here. Aleppo is not
                    exceeded in extent by any city in Turkey, except Constantinople and Cairo, and
                    perhaps Smyrna. It is difficult to make any estimate of its population, but it
                    is said to be increasing, and, according to the most authentic computation, does
                    not probably contain less than 250,000 inhabitants. Of these, 30,000 are
                    Christians, who enjoy the most perfect toleration, and are treated with more
                    respect than in any town of the East.</p><p>The air of Aleppo is dry and piercing, bùt at the same time salubrious for all
                    who are not troubled with asthmatic complaints. The city, however, and the
                    environs, are subject to a singular endemial disorder, which is called the
                    ringworm or pimple of Aleppo: it is in fact a pimple which is at first
                    inflammatory, and at length becomes an ulcer of the size of the nail. The usual
                    duration of this ulcer is one year: it commonly fixes on the face, and leaves a
                    scar, which disfigures almost all the inhabitants. No reason is assigned for
                    this malady; but Μ. Volney suspects it proceeds from the quality of the water,
                    as it is likewise frequent in the neighbouring villages, in some parts of
                    Diarbekir, and even in certain districts near Damascus, where the soil and the
                    water have the same appearances. But the plague is a more destructive malady, a
                    visitation of which is anticipated by the inhabitants every ten years. Its
                    ravages are most fatal, owing to the blind fatalism of the Turks, who cannot be
                    persuaded to take any precautions against the progress of this dreadful disease.
                    In the plague which immediately preceded the year 1797, about 60,000 inhabitants
                    were swept off. Of the Christian inhabitants the greater number are Greeks, next
                    to them the Armenians, then the Syrians, and lastly the Maronites; each of whom
                    has a church in the city called <hi rend="italic">Judida;</hi> in which quarter,
                    and the parts adjacent, most of them reside. The common language is the vulgar
                    Arabic, but the Turks of condition use the Turkish. Most of the Armenians can
                    speak the Armenian, some few Syrians understand Syriac, and many of the Jews
                    Hebrew; but scarcely one of the Greeks understands a word of Greek. The people
                    in general are of a middle stature, and tolerably well proportioned; but they
                    seem neither vigorous nor active. Both sexes are handsome when young; but the
                    women, as they come early to maturity, also fade very soon. The people of rank
                    here are polite and affable, making allowances for that superiority which the
                    Mahometan religion instructs its votaries to assume over all who hold a
                    different faith. All the inhabitants of both sexes smoke tobacco to great
                    excess; even the very servants have almost constantly a pipe in their mouth.
                    Coaches or carriages are not used here; therefore persons of quality ride on
                    horseback in the city, with a number of servants walking before them, according
                    to their rank. Ladies of the first distinction are even compelled to walk on
                    foot in the city, or to any place at a moderate distance: in longer journeys
                    they are carried by mules, in a kind of couch close covered up. There is a
                    number of public baths in this city, which are used by people of all ranks,
                    except those of the highest distinction, who commonly have baths and every other
                    convenience in their own houses. The bath, being the only public rendezvous of
                    the female sex, is a great scene of amusement as well as of display: the bathers
                    continue for hours conversing together, in their best apparel and most splendid
                    ornaments. The gaiety of the place is still further enlivened by refreshments
                    and music. Aleppo is of great antiquity, and is supposed to occupy the site of
                    the ancient Beraea. It was overwhelmed by the flood of Saracen invasion in 638,
                    when it was taken from the emperor Hera-clius. In 1260 it was taken possession
                    of and wasted by the Tartars, and in 1401 by Tamerlane, who defeated the
                    Syrians, when it was given up to pillage. The adjacent country is fertile, and
                    yields grain of all sorts, with which the city is plentifully supplied. All the
                    fruits of Europe, as well as those of the East, are cultivated in gardens. The
                    pistachio-nut is regularly cultivated. Aleppo is 70 miles east of Scanderoon, on
                    the sea-coast, and 234 north-east of Damascus. Long. 37. 4. E. Lat. 36.12.
                    N.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Aleppo,</hi><hi rend="italic">The PachaJ,ic
                    of,</hi> one of the five governments<pb break="no" facs="nls:193035022" xml:id="kp-eb0702-5022-0401"/> into which
                    Syria is divided. It comprehends the country extending from the Euphrates to the
                    Mediterranean, between two lines, one drawn from Scanderoon to Beer, along the
                    mountains; the other from Beles to the sea, by Mara and the bridge of Shoger.
                    This space principally consists of two plains, that of Antioch to the west, and
                    that of Aleppo to the east: the north and the seacoast are occupied by
                    considerably high mountains, known to the ancients by the names of Amanus and of
                    Rhosus. In general, the soil of this government is fat and loamy. The lofty and
                    vigorous plants which shoot up everywhere after the winter rains, prove its
                    fertility, but its actual fruitfulness is but little. The greater part of the
                    lands lies waste; scarcely can we trace any marks of cultivation in the environs
                    of the towns and villages. Its principal produce consists in wheat, barley, and
                    cotton, which are found especially in the flat country. In the mountains they
                    rather choose to cultivate the vine, mulberry, olive, and fig trees. The sides
                    of the hills towards the sea-coast are appropriated to tobacco, and the
                    territory of Aleppo to pistachios. The pasturage is not to be reckoned, because
                    that is abandoned to the wandering hordes of the Turcomans and Curds. The
                    condition of the people depends entirely on the character of the pacha, who,
                    when he is a tyrant, oppresses and plunders them without any restraint. From the
                    mild administration of some of the late pachas, the people appear to be
                    prosperous and happy. Mr Buckingham mentions, that the pacha who ruled in Aleppo
                    at the time he visited this city acknowledged the influence of public opinion,
                    and generally consulted the happiness of his subjects in the measures which he
                    pursued.</p></div></body></text></TEI>