<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7609-0600-04" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">AMBROSE</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 600</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1163799">Valentinians</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:814376">Arianism</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:828176">Basilicas</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term><term n="13" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198492">Faith</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v36q">Arianism</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45s7h">Basilicas</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term><term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f8z">Faith</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193037609" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">AMBROSE</label>, of Alexandria, lived in the beginning of the
                    third century, and was the intimate friend of Origen. Jerome and Eusebius differ
                    in the account they give of this man. The one denominates him a Marcionite, the
                    other a Valentinian; but they both agree that he was converted to the orthodox
                    faith by the preaching of Origen. As is generally the case with new proselytes,
                    he became very zealous, and was appointed deacon either at Alexandria, or at
                    Caesarea, where Protectetus was presbyter. Origen dedicated many of his works,
                    and among others his book on martyrdom, to Ambrose, at whose desire and expense
                    they were published. Origen and Ambrose were alike indefatigable in their
                    application to study, and lived on terms of the most intimate friendship. Origen
                    being poor, Ambrose assisted him, by providing notaries and amanuenses to copy
                    his works. In that period of society, when the increase of copies was a work of
                    immense labour and great expense, these were not only instances of private
                    friendship, but of public utility. Ambrose is thus justly entitled to rank among
                    the patrons of learning. He has been blamed by some for having made no provision
                    at his death for the poor infirm Origen. His friends plead in defence of his
                    conduct, that Origen chose to live poor, and daily dependent on a divine
                    Providence. According to some historians, Ambrose died a martyr, along with his
                    friend Protectetus, in the persecution under Maximin, about the year 236; but
                    the dedication of Origen’s eight books against Celsus proves, that though he
                    died before Origen, yet he lived to the year 250, or near that period. Origen
                    speaks of him as a man of sincere piety, and much devoted to the study of the
                    sacred Scriptures.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ambrose,</hi><hi rend="italic">Saint,</hi> Bishop of Milan,
                    was one of the most eminent fathers of the church in the fourth century. He was
                    a citizen of Rome, and born in France; according to some historians, in the year
                    334, but, according to others, in 340. The birth of Ambrose is said to have been
                    attended with a remarkable presage of his future eloquence, by a swarm of bees
                    settling upon his mouth as he lay in his cradle. At the period of his birth his
                    father was pretorian prefect of Gallia Narbonensis; but upon his death, the
                    widow repaired to Rome with her family. Ambrose received a religious education,
                    and was reared in habits of virtuous conduct by his mother, an accomplished
                    woman, and eminent for her piety. The names of his instructors in the rudiments
                    of Greek and Roman literature have not been transmitted to posterity; but in
                    these branches he made early proficiency; and, having directed his attention to
                    the law, he employed his eloquence with such reputation in the pretorian court
                    of Anicius Probus, that he was soon deemed worthy of a place in the council.
                    After he had continued in this station for some time, Probus appointed him
                    consular of Liguria and Emilia, comprehending the territories of Milan, Liguria,
                    Turin, Genoa, and Bologna. Milan was chosen for the place of his residence; and,
                    by the prudent and gentle use of his power, he conducted the affairs of the
                    province with general approbation and growing popularity.</p><p>In the year 374 Auxentius, the bishop of that city, died, and his death gave
                    sudden change to the fortune and literary pursuits of Ambrose. At that period
                    the tide of religious contention ran high between the Catholics and the Arians,
                    and there ensued a violent contest concerning the choice of a new bishop. When
                    the people were assembled in the church to elect, Ambrose, in the character of
                    governor of the place, presented himself to the assembly, and in a grave,
                    eloquent, and pathetic address, admonished the multitude to lay aside their
                    contentions, and, in the spirit of religious meekness, to proceed to the
                    important work of choosing a bishop. It is reported, that when Ambrose had
                    finished his address, a child cried out, “Ambrose is bishop.” The agitated
                    multitude suddenly caught the superstitious flame, and regarding this as a
                    miraculous intimation, they unanimously elected Ambrose bishop of Milan. Some
                    suppose that this was entirely a device of Ambrose or his friends, and others
                    ascribe it to mere accident. Ambrose strongly affected reluctance, and even
                    pretended to fly from the city in order to avoid the intended honour. It is,
                    however, unfortunate for the artifice of the governor, that the place of his
                    concealment was soon discovered, when the emperor’s confirmation of his election
                    was made known to him. Finding it inconvenient any longer to resist the public
                    choice, he exchanged the ensigns of civil for those of ecclesiastical dignity;
                    and, after being baptized, he was ordained bishop of Milan, about the end of the
                    year 374. But whatever may be the sentiments of mankind concerning the singular
                    conduct of Ambrose in accepting an office for which he was certainly unqualified
                    in respect of previous studies, habits, and employments, yet it must be
                    admitted, that he immediately betook himself to the necessary studies, and
                    acquitted himself in his new elevation with ability, boldness, and integrity.
                    Having appropriated his money to the poor, settled his lands upon the church,
                    with the exception of making his sister tenant during life, and having committed
                    the care of his family to his brother, he entered upon a regular course of
                    theological study, under the care of Simplician, a presbyter of Rome, and
                    devoted himself to the labours of the church.</p><p>Compelled by the irruption of the Goths and the northern barbarians, who rushed
                    down upon the Roman empire, spreading terror and desolation all around, Ambrose,
                    along with several others, fled to Illyricum; but his exile was of short
                    duration, for the northern invaders having been quickly defeated by the forces
                    of the emperor, and driven back with considerable loss into their dominions, he
                    and his companions returned to their respective habitations.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193037622" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7622-0601"/><p>After his return to the ecclesiastic station, his eloquence and abilities found
                    ample scope in the dispute between the Arians and Catholics. About this era the
                    doctrine of Arius concerning the person of Christ had been extensively received,
                    and had many powerful defenders both among the clergy and the common people.
                    Ambrose espoused the cause of the Catholics: Gratian, the son of the elder
                    Valentinian, marshalled on the same side; but the younger Valentinian, who was
                    now become his colleague in the empire, adopted the opinions of the Arians; and
                    all the arguments and eloquence of Ambrose were insufficient to reclaim the
                    young prince to the orthodox faith. Theodosius, the emperor of the East, also
                    professed the orthodox faith; yet there were numerous adherents to Arius
                    scattered throughout his dominions. In this distracted state of religious
                    opinion, two leaders of the Arians, Palladius and Secundianus, confident of
                    numbers, prevailed upon Gratian to call a general council from all parts of that
                    empire. This request appeared so equitable that he complied without hesitation;
                    but Ambrose, aware of the consequence, had the eloquence to persuade the emperor
                    that a general council was improper, and that the matter could be determined by
                    a council of the western bishops. The result was, that a synod, composed of 32
                    bishops, was held at Aquileia in the year 381. Ambrose was elected president;
                    and Palladius being called upon to defend his opinions, declined, insisting that
                    the meeting was a partial one, and that the whole bishops of the empire not
                    being present, the sense of the Christian church concerning the question in
                    dispute could not be obtained. Ambrose mentioned several precedents in favour of
                    the authority of the court; and added, that the oriental bishops, being
                    acquainted with the place and nature of the meeting, might have been present, if
                    they had deemed the matter in discussion worthy of their attention; therefore
                    the court, although Palladius persisted in his refusal to plead his cause, put
                    the vote, and he, along with his associate Secundianus, was ejected from the
                    episcopal office. If Ambrose displayed great ardour in opposing the errors of
                    Arius, he was equally zealous in combating the heathen superstitions. Upon the
                    accession of Valentinian II., many of the senators who remained attached to the
                    pagan idolatry made a vigorous effort to restore the worship of the heathen
                    deities. Symmachus, a very opulent man and a great orator, who was at that time
                    prefect of the city, was intrusted with the management of the pagan cause, and
                    drew up a petition, praying that the altar of Victory might be restored to its
                    ancient station in the hall of the senate, and for the proper support of seven
                    vestal virgins, and the regular observance of the other pagan ceremonies. Great
                    eloquence and peculiar insinuation characterized the petition. He argued that
                    this form of religion had long been profitable to the Roman state, reminded the
                    emperor how much Rome had been indebted to Victory, and that it had been the
                    uniform custom of the senators to swear fidelity to the government upon that
                    altar. He likewise produced many facts to prove the advantages derived to the
                    state from its ancient religious institutions, and insinuated that it was one
                    divinity that all men worshipped under different forms, so that ancient practice
                    should not be rashly laid aside. He even proceeded so far as to state the
                    injustice of increasing the public revenue by robbing the church, and attributed
                    the late famine which had overtaken the empire to the neglect of the ancient
                    worship.</p><p>To this petition Ambrose replied in a letter to Valentinian, arguing that the
                    devoted worshippers of idols had often been forsaken by their deities; that the
                    native valour of the Roman soldiers had gained their victories, and not the
                    pretended influence of pagan priests; that these idolatrous worshippers
                    requested for themselves what they refused to Christians; that voluntary was
                    more honourable than constrained virginity; that as the Christian ministers
                    declined receiving temporal emoluments, they should also be denied to pagan
                    priests; that it was absurd to suppose that God would inflict a famine upon the
                    empire for neglecting to support a religious system contrary to his revealed
                    will in the Scriptures; that the whole process of nature encouraged innovations,
                    and that all nations had permitted these, even in religion; that heathen
                    sacrifices were exceedingly offensive to Christians; and that every Christian
                    prince should suppress these pagan ceremonies.</p><p>In the epistles of Symmachus and of Ambrose both the petition and the reply are
                    preserved, in which sophistry, superstition, sound sense, and solid argument,
                    are strangely blended. It is scarcely necessary to add, that the petition was
                    unsuccessful.</p><p>The increasing strength of the Arians proved too formidable for the zealous
                    Ambrose. The young emperor and Justina, along with a considerable number of
                    clergy and laity professing the Arian faith, requested from the bishop the use
                    of two churches, one in the city, the other in the suburbs of Milan. The prelate
                    believing the bishops to be the guardians both of the temporal and spiritual
                    interests of the church, and that the religious edifices were the unquestionable
                    property of the church, positively refused to deliver up the temples of the Lord
                    into the impious hands of the heretics. Filled with indignation, Justina
                    resolved to employ the imperial authority of her son in procuring by force what
                    she could not procure by persuasion. Ambrose was required to answer for his
                    conduct before the council. He went, attended by a numerous crowd of people,
                    whose impetuous zeal so overawed the ministers of Valentinian, that he was
                    permitted to retire without making the surrender of the churches. The day
                    following, when he was performing divine service in the Basilica, the prefect of
                    the city came to persuade him to give up at least the Portian church in the
                    suburbs. Still continuing obstinate, the court proceeded to violent measures:
                    the officers of the household were commanded to prepare the Basilica and the
                    Portian churches to celebrate divine service upon the arrival of the emperor and
                    his mother at the ensuing festival of Easter. The order respecting one of them
                    was carried into effect; but the court, perceiving the growing strength of the
                    prelate’s interest, deemed it prudent to use more lenient measures. But all
                    measures proved in vain; the bishop boldly replied, “If you demand my person, I
                    am ready to submit: carry me to prison or to death, I will not resist; but I
                    will never betray the church of Christ. I will not call upon the people to
                    succour me; I will die at the foot of the altar, rather than desert it. The
                    tumult of the people I will not encourage; but God alone can appease.” This
                    strong declaration was followed by a torrent of eloquence from the pulpit,
                    pursuing his scheme with the most violent zeal. But the court remained
                    unconvinced, and another attempt being made, under a strong guard of ferocious
                    Goths, to seize the church of Basilica, when they were about to enter, Ambrose
                    thundered the sentence of excommunication against them, and so overawed them
                    that they retired, and he and his friends remained in possession of the
                    churches. About this time, also, an Arian bishop challenged Ambrose to a dispute
                    before the emperor; but he declined, saying that matters of faith should be
                    determined by a council of bishops.</p><p>Many circumstances in the history of Ambrose are strongly characteristic of the
                    general spirit of the times. The chief causes of his victory over his opponents
                    were, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193037635" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7635-0602"/>his great popularity, and the superstitious
                    reverence paid to the episcopal character at that period of society. But it must
                    also be admitted, that he used several indirect means to obtain and support his
                    popular authority. Many indigent persons were supported by his liberal bounty;
                    in his explanations of Scripture he made constant and severe allusions to
                    existing and public characters; the alternate mode of singing had no small
                    effect upon the minds of the vulgar. At a time when the influence of Ambrose
                    required vigorous support, he fortunately was admonished in a dream to search
                    for the remains of Gervasius and Protasius, two martyrs who quietly reposed
                    under the pavement of the church. The skeletons were found entire, stained with
                    the blood, and the head of one of them separated from the body. The vulgar
                    crowded in thousands to behold these venerable relics. According to report, a
                    blind man was restored to sight, several demons were expelled, and sick persons
                    healed, by touching these bones. Ambrose exulted in these miracles, and appealed
                    to them in his eloquent sermons; while the court derided and called in question
                    their existence. The bishop continued firm in his opinions, the people believed,
                    and the existence of the miracles was established. And it is a very singular
                    fact that these and many other miracles obtained current credit among the
                    Christian historians of the second, third, and fourth centuries. Dr Cave, in
                    speaking of them, says, “I make no doubt but God suffered them to be wrought, at
                    this time, on purpose to confront the Arian impieties.”</p><p>Although the court were displeased with the religious principles and conduct of
                    Ambrose, yet they respected his great political talents; and when necessity
                    required, they solicited his aid, which he generously granted. When Maxentius
                    usurped the supreme power in Gaul, and was meditating a descent upon Italy,
                    Valentinian sent Ambrose to him, who prevailed upon him to desist from the
                    undertaking. On a second attempt of the same kind Ambrose was employed; and
                    although he was unsuccessful, yet, if his advice had been followed upon his
                    return, the schemes of the usurper would have proved abortive; but, indifferent
                    to his counsels, the enemy was permitted to enter Italy, and Milan was taken.
                    Justina and her son fled; but Ambrose remained in his station, and proved
                    beneficial to many of the sufferers, by causing the plate of the church to be
                    melted for their relief. Theodosius, the emperor of the East, espoused the cause
                    of Justina, and by force of arms regained the kingdom.</p><p>In the year 390 a tumult happened at Thessalonica, in which Botheric, one of the
                    imperial officers, was slain. At this Theodosius was so enraged, that he issued
                    a royal mandate for the promiscuous massacre of the inhabitants of that place;
                    and about seven thousand persons were assassinated, without distinction or
                    mercy. The courageous Ambrose, informed of this deed, wrote to the emperor a
                    severe reproof, and an earnest admonition, charging him not to approach the holy
                    communion with his hands stained with innocent blood. When the emperor was about
                    to enter the church of Milan to attend upon the service, the bishop met him, and
                    with a stern countenance prohibited him from approaching the temple of God. The
                    emperor reminded him that David had been guilty of murder and of adultery. The
                    bishop replied, “You have imitated David in his guilt; go and imitate him in his
                    repentance.” The prince obeyed the priest, and, by a course of penitential
                    sorrow, during the space of eight months, he laboured to regain the favour of
                    the church. After the termination of this period he was absolved, but at the
                    same time was made to sign an edict, that an interval of thirty days should
                    intervene before the sentence of death or confiscation should be put in
                    execution. When the mind reflects upon the pernicious effects of sudden and
                    violent passion, this measure was certainly fraught with policy and humanity. If
                    the reader laments the weakness which subjected the conscience to the clerical
                    power, he must be gratified that so moderate a use was made of that
                    authority.</p><p>The undaunted courage of Ambrose received another severe trial in the year 393,
                    after the assassination of Valentinian, and the base Eugenio had usurped the
                    empire of the West. Rather than join the standard of the usurper, he fled from
                    Milan; but after the army of Theodosius was victorious, he generously
                    supplicated the emperor for the pardon of those who had supported the cause of
                    Eugenio. Theodosius, soon after he had acquired the uncontrolled possession of
                    the Roman empire, died at Milan. The bishop did not long survive the emperor,
                    but died in the year 397. In his last illness he preserved perfect composure of
                    mind, informing his friends that he had endeavoured so to conduct himself that
                    he might neither be ashamed to live nor to die.</p><p>On many accounts the character of the bishop of Milan stands high among the
                    fathers of the ancient church. With unvarying steadiness he delivered his
                    religious sentiments on all occasions; with unwearied assiduity he discharged
                    the duties of his office; with unabated zeal and boldness he defended the
                    orthodox cause, in opposition to the Arians; with a liberal hand he fed the
                    numerous poor who flocked to his dwelling; with uncommon generosity he
                    manifested kindness to his adversaries; and with Christian affection he sought
                    the happiness of all men. His general habits were amiable and virtuous, and his
                    powers of mind were uncommonly vigorous and persevering. Ambition and bigotry
                    were the chief blemishes in his character.</p><p>The writings of Ambrose are voluminous, although little more than adulterated
                    editions of Origen and other Greek fathers. The great design of his writings was
                    to defend and propagate the Catholic faith. In some of these he recommends
                    perpetual celibacy as the perfection of Christian virtue. Modern judgment and
                    taste may perhaps induce some to esteem the writings of Ambrose absurd, trivial,
                    and even ludicrous; but there is a smartness and vigour in his style, and there
                    are excellent sentiments interspersed, which render the writings of the bishop
                    of Milan worthy of a perusal. With his usual severity and acrimony, Gibbon too
                    severely censures this prelate. “Ambrose,” says he, “could act better than he
                    could write; his compositions are destitute of taste or genius, without the
                    spirit of Tertullian, the copious elegance of Lactantius, the lively wit of
                    Jerome, or the grave energy of Augustin.” The most accurate and complete edition
                    of his works is that published by the Benedictines, printed at Paris in 1682, in
                    two volumes folio.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ambrose,</hi><hi rend="italic">Saint,</hi> an island in the
                    South Pacific Ocean, on the coast of Chili, four or five leagues due west from
                    St Felix Island. At first view it appears like two small islands; but, after a
                    nearer approach, they are found to be joined by a reef. It lies in long. 80. 55.
                    W. and lat. 26. 13. S. from Greenwich. There is a large rock four miles to the
                    northward of the island, called from its appearance <hi rend="italic">Sail-rock.</hi> Captain Roberts, who was here in 1792, found St Felix Island
                    inaccessible. On St Ambrose Island his crew in seven weeks killed 13,000 seals,
                    and cured the skins, which were of the best quality. The island has little else
                    to recommend it. Fish and crawfish aboun . The best season for sealing is from
                    the first of April to the first of August. _ . .</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ambrose,</hi><hi rend="italic">Isaac,</hi> an eminent
                    Presbyterian minister, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193037648" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7648-0603"/>was educated at Brazen-nose College, Oxford, where
                    he took the degree of bachelor of arts, and became minister of Preston, and
                    afterwards of Garstang in Lancashire, whence he was ejected for nonconformity in
                    1662. It was usual for him to retire every year for a month into a little hut in
                    a wood, where he shunned all society, and devoted himself to religious
                    contemplation. Dr Calamy observes, that he had a very strong presentiment of the
                    approach of death, and took a formal leave of his friends at their houses a
                    little before his departure; and on the last night-of his life he sent his
                    discourse concerning <hi rend="italic">angels</hi> to the press. The next day he
                    shut himself up in his parlour, where, to the great surprise and regret of all
                    who saw him, he was found just expiring. He died in 1663-4, in the 72d year of
                    his age. He wrote several other books, as the <hi rend="italic">Prima,</hi><hi rend="italic">Media,</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Ultima,</hi> or the First, Middle, and Last Things; War with Devils; Looking
                    unto Jesus, &amp;c.</p></div></body></text></TEI>