<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-6621-0524-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALLESTRY, Richard</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 524</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:878299">Cope</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193036621" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALLESTRY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard</hi></label>, D. D.
                    was born at Upping-ton in Shropshire in 1619, and educated in the grammar school
                    of Coventry, and afterwards at Christ Church in Oxford. His natural talents,
                    which were uncommonly vigorous, he carefully improved by an unwearied
                    application to study. Accordingly, his promotion was rapid. First he obtained
                    the degree of bachelor of arts; next he was chosen moderator in philosophy; then
                    made a canon of Christ Church, created doctor of divinity, appointed chaplain in
                    ordinary to the king, and afterwards regius professor of divinity.</p>
                <p>But in the early part of life his studies were interrupted, and he was called to
                    military service by hostile occurrences of the times. In the year 1641 he and
                    many other students of Oxford entered the royal service, and gave eminent proofs
                    of their courage and loyal attachment. A short interval of hostilities permitted
                    them to return to their literary pursuits; but a republican party soon after
                    disturbed their repose, and entering Oxford, attempted to plunder the colleges.
                    Having entered the treasury, and finding nothing but fourpence and a halter,
                    they hastened to the deanery, and seizing many valuable articles, they locked
                    them in an apartment, intending next day to carry them along with them. During
                    the night, however, Allestry having a key to that apartment, found means to
                    remove the whole of the articles. Informed that he was the cause of their
                    disappointment, they seized him; and had they not been unexpectedly called off
                    by an order of the earl of Essex, they would have severely wreaked their
                    indignation upon him. In October following he again took up arms, was present at
                    the battle of Keinton-field, and on his way to Oxford to prepare for the
                    reception of the king he was taken prisoner, but soon afterwards released by the
                    king’s forces.</p>
                <p>A violent disease which then prevailed in the garrison of Oxford brought Allestry
                    to the brink of the grave; but recovering, he again joined a regiment of
                    volunteers, chiefly consisting of Oxford students. Here he served as a common
                    soldier, and was often seen with the musket in one hand and the book in the
                    other. When the republican party prevailed, he returned at the termination of
                    the war to his favourite studies, but still continued true to that side of
                    politics which he had adopted. This conduct occasioned his expulsion from the
                    college; but he was provided with a comfortable retreat in the families of the
                    honourable Franċis Newport and Sir Anthony Cope.</p>
                <p>Such was the confidence reposed in him, that when the friends of Charles II. wθre
                    secretly preparing the way for his restoration, they intrusted him with personal
                    messages to the king. In returning from one of these interviews he was seized at
                    Dover, and upon examination committed a prisoner to Lambeth-house. The earl of
                    Shaftesbury obtained his release in a few weeks. Returning to visit his friends,
                    and among others the learned Dr Hammond, he met his corpse at the gate of his
                    house, carrying to the grave. This deeply affected his mind, and added much to
                    his present distresses. The doctor left him his valuable library, assigning as a
                    reason that “he well knew that his books in his hands would be useful weapons
                    for the defence of that cause he had so vigorously supported.” This valuable
                    library, along with his own, Allestry bequeathed at his death to the
                    university.</p>
                <p>During his life he erected at his own private expense the west side of the
                    outward court of Eton College, the grammar school in Christ Church College, and
                    settled several liberal pensions upon individual persons and families. His
                    original biographer gives him the following character. “Memory, fancy, judgment,
                    elocution, great modesty, and no less assurance, a comprehension of things, and
                    a fluency of words; an aptness for the pleasant, and sufficiency for the rugged
                    parts of knowledge; a courage to encounter and an industry to master all things,
                    make up the character of his happy genius. There was not in the world a man of
                    clearer honesty and courage; no temptation could bribe him to do a base thing,
                    or terror affright him from the doing a good one. This made his friendship as
                    lasting and inviolable as his life, without the mean considerations of profit,
                    or sly reserves of craft; without the pageantry of ceremonious address, the cold
                    civility of some, and the servile falseness and obsequious flattery of others.”
                    He left a volume of sermons, printed at Oxford in 1684, from the perusal of
                    which posterity may judge of his literary abilities. Although his lectures gave
                    universal satisfaction, yet he prohibited their publication.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Allestry,</hi><hi rend="italic">Jacob,</hi> an English poet
                    of the last century. He was the son of James Allestry, a bookseller of London,
                    who was ruined by the great fire in 1666. Jacob was educated at Westminster
                    School, entered at Christ Church, Oxford, in the act-term 1671, at the age of
                    18,, and was elected student in 1672. He took the degree of arts; was music
                    reader in 1679, and terrae-filius in 1681; both which offices he executed with
                    great applause, being esteemed a good philologist and poet. He had a chief hand
                    in the verses and pastorals spoken at the theatre at Oxford, 21st May 1681, by
                    Mr William Saville, second son of the marquis of Halifax, and George
                    Cholmondeley, second son of Robert Viscount Kells (both of Christ Church),
                    before James duke of York, his duchess, and the lady Anne; which verses and
                    pastorals were afterwards printed in the <hi rend="italic">Examen Poeticum.</hi>
                    He died on the 15th October 1686, and was buried in St Thomas’s churchyard.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
