<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7440-0587-08" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">AMAZONS</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 587</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="21" ref="fasttopic:806706">Amazons</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1109953">Scythians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:819237">Assyrians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term><term n="20" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term><term n="14" ref="fasttopic:1739388">Womanism</term><term n="14" ref="fasttopic:1895887">Womanizers</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1095872">Rest</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205534">Libya</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="21" ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c55w">Amazons</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vd72">Scythians</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16p3t">Albanians</term><term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x62g">Rest</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kk48">Arm</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9789n">Girls</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193037440" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">AMAZONS</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Antiquity,</hi> a
                    nation of female warriors, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193037453" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7453-0588"/>who founded an empire in Asia Minor, upon the
                    river Thermodoon, along the coasts of the Black Sea. They are said to have
                    formed a state, out of which men were excluded, their commerce with that sex
                    being confined to strangers. They killed all their male children, and cut off
                    the right breasts of their females, to make them more fit for the combat. From
                    the last circumstance they are supposed to derive their name, viz. from the
                    privative α, and μαζο;, <hi rend="italic">mamma,</hi> breast. But Bryant, in his
                    <hi rend="italic">Analysis of Ancient Mythology,</hi> vol. iii. p. 463, rejects
                    this account as fabulous; and observes that they were in general Cuthite
                    colonies from Egypt and Syria, who formed settlements in different countries,
                    and that they derived their name from <hi rend="italic">zon,</hi> the sun, which
                    was the national object of worship.</p><p>The Amazons are mentioned by the most ancient of the Greek writers. In the third
                    book of the Iliad, Homer represents Priam speaking of himself as having been
                    present, in the earlier part of his life, in a battle with the Amazons; and some
                    of them afterwards came to the assistance of that prince during the siege of
                    Troy.</p><p>The Amazons are particularly mentioned by Herodotus. That historian informs us
                    that the Grecians fought a battle with them on the river Thermodoon, and
                    defeated them. After this victory the Grecians carried off in three ships all
                    the Amazons they had taken prisoners. But while they were out at sea, the
                    Amazons conspired against the men, and killed them all. Having, however, no
                    knowledge of navigation, nor any skill in the use of the rudder, sails, or oars,
                    they were driven by wind and tide till they arrived at the precipices of the
                    lake Maeotis, in the territories of the Scythians. Here the Amazons went ashore,
                    and marching into the country, seized and mounted the first horses they met
                    with, and began to plunder the inhabitants. The Scythians at first conceived
                    them to be men; but after having several skirmishes with them, and taking some
                    prisoners, they discovered them to be women. They were then unwilling to carry
                    on hostilities against them; and by degrees a number of the young Scythians
                    formed connections with them, and were desirous that these gentle dames should
                    live with them as wives, and be incorporated with the rest of the Scythians. The
                    Amazons agreed to continue their connection with their Scythian husbands, but
                    refused to associate with the rest of the inhabitants of the country, and
                    especially with the women. They afterwards prevailed upon their husbands to
                    retire to Sarmatia, where they settled. “Hence,” says Herodotus, “the wives of
                    the Sarmatians still continue their ancient way of living. They hunt on
                    horseback in the company of their husbands, and sometimes alone. They march with
                    their armies, and wear the same dress as the men. The Sarmatians use the
                    Scythian language, but corrupted from the beginning, because the Amazons never
                    learned to speak correctly. Their marriages are attended with this circumstance:
                    no virgin is permitted to marry till she has killed an enemy in the field; so
                    that some always grow old before they can qualify themselves as the law
                    requires.”</p><p>Diodorus Siculus says, “There was formerly a nation who dwelt near the river
                    Thermodoon, which was subjected to the government of women, and in which the
                    women, like men, managed all the military affairs. Among these female warriors,
                    it was said, was one who excelled the rest in strength and valour. She assembled
                    together an army of women, whom she trained up in military discipline, and
                    subdued some of the neighbouring nations. Afterwards, having by her valour
                    increased her fame, she led her army against the rest; and being successful, she
                    was so puffed up, that she styled herself the daughter of Mars, and ordered the
                    men to spin wool, and do the work of the women within doors. She also made laws,
                    by which the women were enjoined to go to the wars, and the men to be kept at
                    home in a servile state, and employed in the meanest offices. They also
                    debilitated the arms and thighs of those male children who were born of them
                    that they might be rendered unfit for war. They seared the right breasts of
                    their girls, that they might be no interruption to them in fighting: whence they
                    derived the name of Amazons. Their queen, having become extremely eminent for
                    skill and knowledge in military affairs at length built a large city at the
                    mouth of the river Thermodoon, and adorned it with a magnificent palace. In her
                    enterprises she adhered strictly to military discipline and good order; and she
                    added to her empire all the adjoining nations, even to the river Tanais. Having
                    performed these exploits, she at last ended her days like a hero, falling in a
                    battle, in which she had fought courageously. She was succeeded in the kingdom
                    by her daughter, who imitated the valour of her mother, and in some exploits
                    excelled her. She caused the girls from their very infancy to be exercised in
                    hunting, and to be daily trained up in military exercises. She instituted solemn
                    festivals and sacrifices to Mars and Diana, which were named Tauropoli. She
                    afterwards carried her arms beyond the river Tanais, and subdued all the people
                    of those regions, even unto Thrace. Returning then with a great quantity of
                    spoils into her own kingdom, she caused magnificent temples to be erected to the
                    deities before mentioned; and she gained the love of her subjects by her mild
                    and gentle government. She afterwards undertook an expedition against those who
                    were on the other side of the river, and subjected to her dominion a great part
                    of Asia, extending her arms as far as Syria.”</p><p>Diodorus also mentions another race of Amazons who dwelt in Africa, and whom he
                    speaks of as being of greater antiquity than those who lived near the river
                    Thermodoon. “In the western parts of Libya,” says he, “upon the borders of those
                    tracts that are habitable, there was anciently a nation under the government of
                    women, and whose manners and mode of living were altogether different from ours.
                    It was the custom of those women to manage all military affairs; and for a
                    certain time, during which they preserved their virginity, they went out as
                    soldiers into the field. After some years employed in this manner, when the time
                    appointed for this purpose was expired, they associated themselves with men, in
                    order to obtain children. But the magistracy, and all public offices, they kept
                    entirely in their own hands. The men, as the women are with us, were employed in
                    household affairs, submitting themselves wholly to the authority of their wives.
                    They were not permitted to take any part in military affairs, or to have any
                    command, or any public authority, which might have any tendency to encourage
                    them to cast off the yoke of their wives. As soon as any child was born, it was
                    delivered to the father, to be fed with milk, or such other food as was suitable
                    to its age. If females were born, they seared their breasts, that they might not
                    be burdensome to them when they grew up; for they considered them as great
                    obstacles in fighting.</p><p>Justin represents the Amazonian republic as having taken its rise in Scythia. The
                    Scythians had a great part of Asia under their dominion upwards of 400 years,
                    till they were conquered by Ninus, the founder of the Assyrian empire. After his
                    death, which happened about 1150 years before the Christian era, and that of
                    Semiramis an their son Ninyas, Ilinus and Scolopites, princes of the royal blood
                    of Scythia, were driven from their country by other princes, who like them
                    aspired to the crown. They <pb break="no" facs="nls:193037466" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7466-0589"/> departed with their wives, children, and friends;
                    and being followed by a great number of young people of both sexes, they passed
                    into Asiatic Sarmatia, beyond Mount Caucasus, where they formed an
                    establishment, supplying themselves with the riches they wanted, by making
                    incursions into the countries bordering on the Euxine Sea. The people of those
                    countries, exasperated by the incursions of their new neighbours, having united,
                    surprised and massacred the men.</p><p>The women then resolving to revenge their death, and at the same time to provide
                    for their own security, resolved to form a new kind of government, to choose a
                    queen, enact laws, and maintain themselves, without men, even against the men
                    themselves. This design was not so very surprising as at first sight appears:
                    for most of the girls among the Scythians had been inured to the same exercises
                    as the boys; to draw the bow, to throw the javelin, to manage other arms; to
                    riding, hunting, and even the painful labours that seem reserved for men; and
                    many of them among the Sarmatians accompanied the men in war. No sooner had they
                    formed their resolution, than they prepared to execute it, and exercised
                    themselves in all military operations. They soon secured the peaceable
                    possession of the country; and, not content with showing their neighbours that
                    all their efforts to drive them thence or subdue them were ineffectual, they
                    made war upon them, and extended their own frontiers. They had hitherto made use
                    of the instructions and assistance ĵf a few men that remained in the country;
                    but finding it length that they could stand their ground and aggrandize
                    themselves without them, they killed all those whom flight or chance had saved
                    from the fury of the Sarmatians, and for ever renounced marriage, which they now
                    considered as an insupportable slavery. But as they could inly secure the
                    duration of their new kingdom by propagation, they made a law to go every year
                    to the frontiers, ;o invite the men to come to them; to deliver themselves up to
                    their embraces, without choice on their part, or the east attachment; and to
                    leave them as soon as they were pregnant. Those whom age rendered fit for
                    propagation, and who were willing to serve the state by breeding girls, did not
                    all go at the same time in search of men: for in order to obtain a right to
                    promote the multiplication of he species, they must first have contributed to
                    its destruction; nor was any one thought worthy of giving birth to children till
                    she had killed three men.</p><p>If from this commerce they brought forth girls, they educated them; but with
                    respect to the boys, if we may believe Justin, they strangled them at the moment
                    of their birth. According to Diodorus Siculus, they twisted their legs and arms,
                    so as to render them unfit for military exercises; but Quintus Curtius,
                    Philostratus, and Jornandes say that the less savage sent them to their fathers.
                    It is probable, that at first, when their fury against the men was carried to
                    the greatest height, they filled the boys; that when this fury abated, and most
                    of he mothers were filled with horror at depriving the little features of the
                    lives they had just received from them, they fulfilled the first duties of a
                    mother; but, to prevent heir causing a revolution in the state, maimed them in
                    such a manner as to render them incapable of war, and employed them in the mean
                    offices which these warlike women thought beneath them: in short, that when
                    their conquests had confirmed their power, their ferocity subsiding, they
                    entered into political engagements with their neighbours; and the number of the
                    males they had preserved becoming burdensome, they, at the desire of those who
                    rendered them pregnant, sent them the boys, and continued still to keep the
                    girls.</p><p>As soon as the age of the girls permitted, they took , away the right breast,
                    that they might draw the bow with greater force. The common opinion is, that
                    they burnt that breast, by applying to it, at eight years of age, a hot i brazen
                    instrument, which insensibly dried up the fibres and glands: some think that
                    they did not make use of i so much ceremony, but that when the part was formed
                    they got rid of it by amputation: some again, with much greater probability,
                    assert that they employed no violent measures, but, by a continual compression
                    of that part from infancy, prevented its growth, at least so far as to hinder
                    its ever being incommodious in war.</p><p>Plutarch, treating of the Amazons in his life of Theseus, considers the accounts
                    which had been preserved concerning them as partly fabulous and partly true. He
                    gives some account of a battle which had been fought between the Athenians and
                    the Amazons at Athens; and he relates some particulars of this battle which had
                    been recorded by an ancient writer named Clidemus. He says that “the left wing
                    of the Amazons moved towards the place which is yet called Amazonium, and the
                    right to a place called Pnyx, near Chrysa; upon which the Athenians, issuing
                    from behind the temple of the Muses, fell upon them; and that this is true, the
                    graves of those who were slain, to be seen in the streets that lead to the gate
                    Piraica, by the temple of the hero Chalcodon, are a sufficient proof. And here
                    it was that the Athenians were routed, and shamefully turned their backs to
                    women, as far as to the temple of the Furies. But fresh supplies coming in from
                    Palladium, Ardettus, and Lyceum, charged their right wing, and beat them back
                    into their very tents; in which action a great number of the Amazons were
                    slain.” In another place he says, “It appears that the passage of the Amazons
                    through Thessaly was not without opposition; for there are yet to be seen many
                    of their sepulchres near Scotussaea and Cynoscephalae.” And in his life of
                    Pompey, speaking of the Amazons, Plutarch says, “They inhabit those parts of
                    Mount Caucasus that look towards the Hyrcanian Sea, not bordering upon the
                    Albanians, for Gelae and Leges lie between; and with these people do they
                    yearly, for two months only, accompany and cohabit, bed and board, near the
                    river Thermodon. After that they retire to their own habitations, and live alone
                    all the rest of the year.”</p><p>Quintus Curtius says, “The nation of the Amazons is situated upon the borders of
                    Hyrcania, inhabiting the plains of Themiscyra, near the river Thermodon. Their
                    queen was named Thalestris, and she had under her subjection all the country
                    that lies between Mount Caucasus and the river Phasis. This queen came out of
                    her dominions in consequence of an ardent desire she had conceived to see
                    Alexander; and being advanced near the place where he was, she previously sent
                    messengers <hi rend="italic">to</hi> acquaint him that the queen was come to
                    have the satisfaction of seeing and conversing with him. Having obtained
                    permission to visit him, she advanced with 300 of her Amazons, leaving the rest
                    of her troops behind. As soon as she came within sight of the king, she leaped
                    from her horse, holding two javelins in her right hand. The apparel of the
                    Amazons does not cover all the body, for their left side is naked down to the
                    stomach; nor do the skirts of their garments, which they tie up in a knot, reach
                    below their knees. They preserve their left breast entire, that they may be able
                    to suckle their female offspring; and they cut off and sear their right, that
                    they may draw their bows and cast their darts with the greater ease. Thalestris
                    looked at the king with an undaunted countenance, and narrowly examined his
                    person, which did not, according to her ideas, come up to the fame of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193037479" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7479-0590"/> his
                    great exploits; for the barbarians have a great veneration for a majestic
                    person, esteeming those only to be capable of performing great actions on whom
                    nature has conferred a dignified appearance. The king having asked her whether
                    she had any thing to desire of him, she replied, without scruple or hesitation,
                    that she was come with a view to have children by him, she being worthy to bring
                    him heirs to his dominions. Their offspring, if of the female sex, she would
                    retain herself; and if of the male sex, it should be delivered to Alexander. He
                    then asked her, whether she would accompany him in his wars. But this she
                    declined, alleging that she had left nobody to take care of her kingdom. She
                    continued to solicit Alexander that he would not send her back without
                    conforming to her wishes; but it was not till after a delay of 13 days that he
                    complied. She then returned to her own kingdom.”</p><p>Justin also repeatedly mentions this visit of Thalestris to Alexander; and in one
                    place he says that she made a march of 25 days in order to obtain this meeting
                    with him. The interview is likewise mentioned by Diodorus Siculus.</p><p>The Amazons are represented as being armed with bows and arrows, with javelins,
                    and also with an axe of a particular construction, which was denominated the axe
                    of the Amazons. According to the elder Pliny, this axe was invented by
                    Penthesilea, one of their queens. On many ancient medals are representations of
                    the Amazons armed with these axes. They are also said to have had bucklers in
                    the shape of a half-moon.</p><p>That at any period there should have been women who, without the assistance of
                    men, built cities and governed them, raised armies and commanded them,
                    administered public affairs, and extended their dominion by arms, is undoubtedly
                    so contrary to all that we have seen and known of human affairs, as to appear in
                    a very great degree incredible; but that women may have existed sufficiently
                    robust, and sufficiently courageous, to have engaged in warlike enterprises, and
                    even to have been successful in them, is certainly not impossible, however
                    contrary to the usual course of things. That much of what is said of the Amazons
                    is fabulous, there can be no reasonable doubt; but it does not therefore follow
                    that the whole is without foundation. The ancient medals and monuments on which
                    they are represented arc very numerous, as are also the testimonies of ancient
                    writers. It seems not rational to suppose that all this originated in fiction,
                    though it be much blended with it.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Amazonian</hi><hi rend="italic">Habit,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Antiquity,</hi> denotes a dress formed in imitation of the
                    Amazons. Marcia, the famous concubine of the emperor Commodus, had the
                    appellation of <hi rend="italic">Amazonian,</hi> because she charmed him most in
                    a habit of this kind. Hence also that prince himself engaged in combat in the
                    amphitheatre in an Amazonian habit; and of all titles the <hi rend="italic">Amazonius</hi> was one of those in which he most delighted. In honour either of
                    the gallant or his mistress, the month of December was also denominated <hi rend="italic">Amazonius.</hi> Some also apply <hi rend="italic">Amazonian</hi>
                    habit to the hunting-dress worn by many ladies among us.</p></div></body></text></TEI>