<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-4853-0388-12" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALCORAN, or Al-koran</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 388</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="25" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44t5k">Koran</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4mp4vm9b">Alcoran</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193034853" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALCORAN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Al-koran</hi></label>, the
                    scripture or bible of the Mahometans. The word is compounded of the Arabic
                    particle <hi rend="italic">al,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">coran</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">koran,</hi> derived from the verb <hi rend="italic">cαταα</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">karaa,</hi> to read. It therefore properly signifies <hi
                    rend="italic">the reading,</hi> or rather <hi rend="italic">that which ought to
                    be read.</hi> By this name the Mahometans denote not only the entire book or
                    volume of the Koran, but also any particular chapter or section of it; just as
                    the Jews call either the whole Scripture, or any part of it, by the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">Karah</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Mikra,</hi> words of the same
                    origin and import.</p>
                <p>Besides this peculiar name, the Koran is also honoured with several appellations
                    common to other books of Scripture: as <hi rend="italic">al Farkan,</hi> from
                    the verb <hi rend="italic">foraka,</hi> to divide or distinguish; not, as the
                    Mahometan doctors say, because those books are divided into chapters or
                    sections, or distinguish between good and evil, but in the same notion that the
                    Jews use the word <hi rend="italic">Per eh</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Pirka,</hi>
                    from the same root, to denote a section or portion of Scripture. It is also
                    called <hi rend="italic">al Moshaf,</hi> the volume, and <hi rend="italic">al
                    Kitah,</hi> the book, by way of eminence, which answers to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Biblia</hi> of the Greeks; and <hi rend="italic">al Dhikr,</hi> the admonition,
                    which name is also given to the Pentateuch and Gospel.</p>
                <p>The Koran is divided into 114 larger portions of very unequal length, which we
                    call <hi rend="italic">chapters,</hi> but the Arabians <hi rend="italic"
                    >sou∙ar,</hi> in the singular <hi rend="italic">sura,</hi> a word rarely used on
                    any other occasion, and properly signifying a row, order, or a regular series;
                    as a course of bricks in a building, or a rank of soldiers in an army; and is
                    the same in use and import with the Sura or Tora of the Jews, who also call the
                    fifty-three sections of the Pentateuch <hi rend="italic">Sedarim,</hi> a word of
                    the same signification.</p>
                <p>These chapters are not distinguished in the manuscript copies by their numerical
                    order, but by particular titles, which are taken sometimes from a particular
                    matter treated of, or person mentioned therein; but usually from the first word
                    of note, exactly in the same manner as the Jews have named their <hi
                    rend="italic">Sedarim;</hi> though the word from which <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193034866" xml:id="kp-eb0702-4866-0389"/>some chapters are denominated
                    be very far distant, towards the middle, or perhaps the end of the chapter;
                    which seems ridiculous. But the occasion of this appears to have been, that the
                    verse or passage wherein such word occurs was, in point of time, revealed and
                    committed to writing before the other verses of the same chapter which precede
                    it in order; and the title being given to the chapter before it was completed,
                    or the passages reduced to their present order, the verse from whence such title
                    was taken did not always happen to begin the chapter. Some chapters have two or
                    more titles, occasioned by the difference of the copies.</p>
                <p>Some of the chapters having been revealed at Mecca, and others at Medina, the
                    noting of this difference makes a part of the title: but the reader will observe
                    that several of the chapters are said to have been revealed partly at Mecca and
                    partly at Medina; and as to others, it is yet a dispute among the commentators
                    to which of the two places they belong.</p>
                <p>Every chapter is subdivided into smaller portions, of very unequal length also,
                    which we customarily call <hi rend="italic">verses;</hi> but the Arabic word is
                    <hi rend="italic">ay at,</hi> the same with the Hebrew ûto/Ä, and signifies <hi
                    rend="italic">signs</hi> or <hi rend="italic">wonders</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >:</hi> such as are the secrets of God, his attributes, works, judgments, and
                    ordinances, delivered in those verses; many of which have their particular
                    titles also, imposed in the same manner as those of the chapters.</p>
                <p>Besides these unequal divisions of chapter and verse, the Mahometans have also
                    divided their Koran into sixteen equal portions, which they call <hi
                    rend="italic">Ahzab,</hi> in the singular <hi rend="italic">liizb,</hi> each
                    divided into four equal parts; which is also an imitation of the Jews, who have
                    an ancient division of their Mishna into sixty portions called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Massictoth.</hi> But the Koran is more usually divided into thirty sections
                    only, named <hi rend="italic">Ajza,</hi> from the singular <hi rend="italic"
                    >Joz,</hi> each of twice the length of the former, and in like manner subdivided
                    into four parts. These divisions are for the use of the readers of the Koran in
                    the royal temples, or in the adjoining chapels, where the emperors and great men
                    are interred. There are thirty of these readers belonging to every chapel, and
                    each reads his section every day; so that the whole Koran is read over once a
                    day.</p>
                <p>Next after the title, at the head of every chapter, except only the ninth, is
                    prefixed the following solemn form, by die Mahometans called the <hi
                    rend="italic">Bismallah,</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">In the name of the most
                    merciful God</hi>; which form they constantly place at the beginning of all
                    their books and writings in general, as a peculiar mark or distinguishing
                    characteristic of their religion, it being counted a sort of impiety to omit it.
                    The Jews, for the same purpose, make use of the form, <hi rend="italic">In the
                    name of the</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Lord,</hi> or, <hi rend="italic">In
                    the name of the great</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> God;</hi> and the eastern
                    Christians that of <hi rend="italic">In the name of the Father, and of the Son,
                    and of the Holy Ghost.</hi> But Mahomet probably took this form, as he did many
                    other things, from the Persian Magi, who used to begin their books in these
                    words, <hi rend="italic">Benam Yezdan bakskaishgher dadar;</hi> that is, <hi
                    rend="italic">In the name of the most merciful just</hi><hi rend="italic
                    smallcaps"> God.</hi></p>
                <p>There are twenty-nine chapters of the Koran which have this peculiarity, that
                    they begin with certain letters of the alphabet, some with a single one, others
                    with more. These letters the Mahometans believe to be the peculiar marks of the
                    Koran, and to conceal several profound mysteries, the certain understanding of
                    which, the most intelligent con fess, has not been communicated to any mortal,
                    their prophet only excepted. Notwithstanding which, some will take the liberty
                    of guessing at their meaning by that species of Cabala called by the Jews <hi
                    rend="italic">Notarikon,</hi> and suppose the letters to stand for as many
                    words, expressing the names and attributes of God, his works, ordinances, and
                    decrees; and therefore these mysterious letters, as well as the verses
                    themselves, seem in the Koran to be called <hi rend="italic">signs.</hi> Others
                    explain the intent of these letters from their nature or organ, or else from
                    their value in numbers, according to another species of the Jewish Cabala,
                    called <hi rend="italic">Gematria</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the uncertainty
                    of which conjectures sufficiently appears from their disagreement. Thus, for
                    example, five chapters, one of which is the second, begin with these letters,
                    A.L. Μ. which some imagine to stand for <hi rend="italic">Allah latiff
                    magid,</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> God</hi><hi rend="italic">is gracious
                    and to be glorified;</hi> or, <hi rend="italic">Ana li minni,</hi> i. e. <hi
                    rend="italic">to me and from me,</hi> viz. belongs all perfection, and proceeds
                    all good; or else for <hi rend="italic">Ana Allah</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >alam,</hi><hi rend="italic">I am the most wise</hi><hi rend="italic
                    smallcaps"> God,</hi> taking the first letter to mark the beginning of the first
                    word, the second the middle of the second word, and the third the last of the
                    third word; or for <hi rend="italic">Allah, Gabriel, Mohammed,</hi> the author,
                    revealer, and preacher of the Koran. Others say, that as the letter A belongs to
                    the lower part of the throat, the first of the organs of speech; L to the
                    palate, the middle organ; and Μ to the lips, which are the last organ; so these
                    letters signify that God is the beginning, middle, and end, or ought to be
                    praised in the beginning, middle, and end, of all our words and actions: or, as
                    the total value of those three letters, in numbers, is seventy-one, they
                    signify, that, in the space of so many years, the religion preached in the Koran
                    should be fully established. The conjecture of a learned Christian is at least
                    as certain as any of the former, who supposes those letters were set there by
                    the amanuensis, for <hi rend="italic">Amar li Mohamed,</hi> i. e. <hi
                    rend="italic">at the command of Mohammed,</hi> as the five letters prefixed to
                    the nineteenth chapter seem to be there written by a Jewish scribe, for <hi
                    rend="italic">Coh yaas, Thus he commanded.</hi></p>
                <p>The Koran is universally allowed to be written with the utmost elegance and
                    purity of language, in the dialect of the tribe of Koreish, the most noble and
                    polite of all the Arabians, but with some mixture, though very rarely, of other
                    dialects. It is confessedly the standard of the Arabic tongue, and, as the more
                    orthodox believe and are taught by the book itself, inimitable by any human pen
                    (though some sectaries have been of another opinion), and therefore insisted on
                    as a permanent miracle, greater than that of raising the dead, and alone
                    sufficient to convince the world of its divine original.</p>
                <p>And to this miracle did Mahomet himself chiefly appeal for the confirmation of
                    his mission, publicly challenging the most eloquent men in Arabia, which was at
                    that time stocked with thousands whose sole study and ambition it was to excel
                    in elegance of style and composition, to produce even a single chapter that
                    might be compared with it.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="superscript"/> As the composition and arrangement of words,
                    however, admit, of infinite varieties, it can never be absolutely said that any
                    one is the best possible. In fact, Hainzah Benahmed wrote a book against the
                    Alcoran with at least equal elegance; and Moselema another, which even surpassed
                    it, and occasioned a defection of a great part of the Mussulmans. (Journ. de
                    Scaν. tom. xiii. n. 280. (Euv. de Sçav. Nov. 1708, p. 404.)</p></note></p>
                <p>To the pomp and harmony of expression some ascribe all the force and effect of
                    the Alcoran, which they consider as a sort of music, equally fitted with other
                    species of that art to ravish and amaze. In this Mahomet succeeded so well, and
                    so strangely captivated the minds of his audience, that several of his opponents
                    thought it the effect of witchcraft and enchantment, as he himself complains.
                    Others have attributed the effect of the Alcoran to the frequent mention of
                    rewards and punishments,—heaven <pb break="no" facs="nls:193034879"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0702-4879-0390"/>and hell occurring almost in every page. Some
                    suppose that the sensual pleasures of paradise, so frequently set before the
                    imaginations of the readers of the Alcoran, were what chiefly bewitched them;
                    though, with regard to these, there is a great dispute whether they are to be
                    understood literally or spiritually. Several have even allegorized the whole
                    book.</p>
                <p>The general design of the Koran was to unite the professors of the three
                    different religions then followed in the populous country of Arabia (who for the
                    most part lived promiscuously, and wandered without guides, the far greater
                    number being idolaters, and the rest Jews and Christians mostly of erroneous and
                    heterodox belief) in the knowledge and worship of one God, under the sanction of
                    certain laws, and the outward signs of ceremonies partly of ancient and partly
                    of novel institution, enforced by the consideration of rewards and punishments
                    both temporal and eternal, and to bring them all to the obedience of Mahomet, as
                    the prophet and ambassador of God, who, after the repeated admonitions,
                    promises, and threats of former ages, was at last to establish and propagate
                    God’s religion on earth, and to be acknowledged chief pontiff in spiritual
                    matters, as well as supreme prince in temporal.</p>
                <p>The great doctrine, then, of the Koran is the unity of God, to restore which
                    point, Mahomet pretended, was the chief end of his mission; it being laid down
                    by him as a fundamental truth, that there never was, nor ever can be, more than
                    one true orthodox religion. For, though the particular laws or ceremonies are
                    only temporary, and subject to alteration, according to the divine directions,
                    yet the substance of it being eternal truth, is not liable to change, but
                    continues immutably the same. And he taught, that whenever this religion became
                    neglected, or corrupted in essentials, God had the goodness to re-inform and
                    re-admonish mankind thereof, by several prophets, of whom Moses and Jesus were
                    the most distinguished, till the appearance of Mahomet, who is their seal, and
                    no other to be expected after him. The more effectually to engage people to
                    hearken to him, great part of the Koran is employed in relating examples of
                    dreadful punishments formerly inflicted by God on those who rejected and abused
                    his messengers; several of which stories, or some circumstances of them, are
                    taken from the Old and New Testaments, but many more from the apocryphal books
                    and traditions of the Jews and Christians of those ages, set up in the Koran as
                    truths in opposition to the Scriptures, which the Jews and Christians are
                    charged with having altered; and indeed few or none of the relations or
                    circumstances in the Koran were invented by Mahomet, as is generally supposed,
                    it being easy to trace the greater part of them much higher, as the rest might
                    be, were more of those books extant, and were it worth while to make the
                    inquiry.</p>
                <p>The rest of the Alcoran is taken up in prescribing necessary laws and directions,
                    frequent admonitions to moral and divine virtues, the worship and reverence of
                    the Supreme Being, and resignation to his will. One of their most learned
                    commentators distinguishes the contents of the Alcoran into <hi rend="italic"
                    >allegorical</hi> and <hi rend="italic">literal</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi>
                    under the former are comprehended all the obscure, parabolical, and enigmatical
                    passages, with such as are repealed or abrogated; under the latter, such as are
                    clear and in full force.</p>
                <p>The most excellent moral in the whole Alcoran, interpreters say, is that in the
                    chapter <hi rend="italic">Al Alraf,</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> nvl.</hi>
                    “Show mercy, do good to all, and dispute not with the ignorant or, as Mr Sale
                    renders it, “Use indulgence, command that which is just, and withdraw far from
                    the ignorant.” Maliomet, according to the authors of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Keschaf,</hi> having begged of the angel Gabriel a more ample explication of
                    this passage, received it in the following terms: “Seck him who turns thee out,
                    give to him who takes from thee, pardon him who injures thee; for God will have
                    you plant in your souls the roots of his chief perfections.” It is easy to see
                    that this commentary is copied from the gospel. In reality, the necessity of
                    forgiving enemies, though frequently inculcated in the Alcoran, is of a later
                    date among the Mahometans than among the Christians; among those latter, than
                    among the heathens; and to be traced originally among the Jews. (See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Exodus</hi> xxiii. 4, 5.) But it matters not so much who had it
                    first, as who observes it best. The caliph Hassan, son of Hali, being at table,
                    a slave unfortunately let fall a dish of meat reeking hot, which scalded him
                    severely. The slave fell on his knees, rehearsing these words of the Alcoran,
                    “Paradise is for those who restrain their anger.” “I am not angry with thee,”
                    answered the caliph. “And for those who forgive offences against them,”
                    continues the slave. “I forgive thee thine,” replies the caliph. “But, above
                    all, for those who return good for evil,” adds the slave. “I set thee at
                    liberty, rejoined the caliph; and I give thee ten dinars.”</p>
                <p>There are also a great number of occasional passages in the Alcoran, relating
                    only to particu!ar emergencies. For, in the piecemeal method of receiving his
                    revelation, Mahomet had this advantage, that whenever he happened to be
                    perplexed and gravelled with any thing, he had a certain resource in some new
                    morsel of revelation. It wasanad-mirable contrivance of his to bring down the
                    whole Alcoran at once only to the lowest heaven, not to earth; since, had the
                    whole been published at once, innumerable objections would have been made, which
                    it would have been impossible for him to solve; but as he received it by
                    parcels, as God saw fit they should be published for the conversion and
                    instruction of the people⅛ he had a sure way to answer all emergencies, and to
                    extricate himself with honour from any difficulty which might occur.</p>
                <p>It is the general and orthodox belief among the Mahometans that the Koran is of
                    divine original; nay, that it is eternal and uncreated, remaining, as some
                    express it, in the very essence of God; that the first transcript has been from
                    everlasting by God’s throne, written on a table of vast bigness, called the <hi
                    rend="italic">preserved table,</hi> in which are also recorded the divine
                    decrees past and future; that a copy from this table, in one volume on paper,
                    was by the ministry of the angel Gabriel sent down to the lowest heaven, in the
                    month of Ramadan, on the night of <hi rend="italic">power·,</hi> from whence
                    Gabriel revealed it to Mahomet by parcels, some at Mecca, and some at Medina, at
                    different times, during the space of 23 years, as the exigency of affairs
                    required; giving him, however, the consolation to show him the whole (which they
                    tell us was bound in silk, and adorned with gold and precious stones of
                    paradise) once a year; but in the last year of his life he had the favour to see
                    it twice. They say, that few chapters were delivered entire, the greater part
                    being revealed piecemeal, and written down from time to time by the prophet’s
                    amanuensis in such a part of such and such a chapter till they were completed,
                    according to the directions of the angel. The first parcel that was revealed is
                    generally agreed to have been the first five verses of the 46th chapter.</p>
                <p>After the new-revealed passages had been from the prophet’s mouth taken down in
                    writing by his scribe, they were published to his followers, several of whom
                    took copies for their private use, but the far greater number got them by heart.
                    The originals, when returned, were put promiscuously into a chest, observing no
                    order of time; for which reason it is uncertain when many passages were
                    revealed.</p>
                <p>When Mahomet died, he left his revelations in the <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193034892" xml:id="kp-eb0702-4892-0391"/>same disorder, and not
                    digested into the method, such as it is, in which we now find them. This was the
                    work of his successor Abu Becr, who, considering that a great number of passages
                    were committed to the memory of Mahomet’s followers, many of whom were slain in
                    their wars, ordered the whole to be collected, not only from the palm-leaves and
                    skins on which they had been written, and which were kept between two boards or
                    covers, but also from the mouths of such as had gotten them by heart. And this
                    transcript, when completed, he committed to the custody of Hassa, the daughter
                    of Omar, one of the prophet’s widows.</p>
                <p>From this relation it is generally imagined that Abu Becr was really the compiler
                    of the Koran, though, for aught that appears to the contrary, Mahomet left the
                    chapters complete as we now have them, excepting such passages as his successor
                    might add or correct from those who had gotten them by heart; what Abu Beer did
                    else being perhaps no more than to range the chapters in their present order,
                    which he seems to have done without any regard to time, having generally placed
                    the longest first.</p>
                <p>However, in the 30th year of the Hegira, Othman being then caliph, and observing
                    the great disagreement in the copies of the Koran in the several provinces of
                    the empire,—∙ those of Irak, for example, following the reading of Abu Musa al
                    Ashari, and the Syrians that of Macdad Ebn Aswad,—he, by the advice of the <hi
                    rend="italic">companions,</hi> ordered a great number of copies to be
                    transcribed from that of Abu Becr, in Hassa’s care, under the inspection of Zeid
                    Ebn Thabet, Abdallah Ebn Zobair, Said Ebn al As, and Abd’al-rahman Ebn al Hareth
                    the Makhzumite; whom he directed, that wherever they disagreed about any word,
                    they should write it in the dialect of the Koreish, in which it was at first
                    delivered. These copies, when made, were dispersed in the several provinces of
                    the empire, and the old ones burnt and suppressed. Though many things in Hassa’s
                    copy were corrected by the above-mentioned revisers, yet some few various
                    readings still occur.</p>
                <p>“The most prominent feature of the Koran, that point of excellence in which the
                    partiality of its admirers has ever delighted to view it, is the sublime notion
                    it generally impresses of the nature and attributes of God. If its author had
                    really derived these just conceptions from the inspiration of that Being whom
                    they attempt to describe, they would not have been surrounded, as they now are
                    on every side, with error and absurdity. But it might easily be proved, that
                    whatever it justly defines of the Divine attributes, was borrowed from our Holy
                    Scripture; which even from its first promulgation, but especially from the
                    completion of the New Testament, has extended the views and enlightened the
                    understandings of mankind; and thus furnished them with arms, which have too
                    often, though ineffectually, been turned against itself by its ungenerous
                    enemies.</p>
                <p>“In this instance particularly, the copy is far below the great original, both in
                    the propriety of its images and the force of its descriptions. Our Holy
                    Scriptures are the only compositions that can enable the dim sight of mortality
                    to penetrate into the invisible world, and to behold a glimpse of the Divine
                    perfections. Accordingly, when they would represent to us the happiness of
                    heaven, they describe it, not by any thing minute and particular, but by
                    something general and great,—something that, without descending to any
                    determinate object, may at once by its beauty and immensity excite our wishes
                    and elevate our affections. Though in the prophetical and evangelical writings
                    the joys that shall attend us in a future state are often mentioned with ardent
                    admiration, they are expressed rather by allusion than similitude, rather by
                    indefinite and figurative terms than by any thing fixed and determinate. ‘ Eye
                    hath not seen, nor ear heard, neither have entered into the heart of man, the
                    things which God hath prepared for them that love him.’ (1 <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cor.</hi> ii. 9.) What a reverence and astonishment does this passage excite in
                    every hearer of taste and piety! What energy, and at the same time what
                    simplicity, in the expression! How sublime, and at the same time how obscure, is
                    the imagery!</p>
                <p>“Different was the conduct of Mahomet in his descriptions of heaven and of
                    paradise. Unassisted by the necessary influence of virtuous intentions and
                    divine inspiration, he was neither desirous, nor indeed able, to exalt the minds
                    of men to sublime conceptions or to rational expectations. By attempting to
                    explain what is inconceivable, to describe what is ineffable, and to materialize
                    what in itself is spiritual, he absurdly and impiously aimed to sensualize the
                    purity of the Divine essence. Thus he fabricated a system of incoherence, a
                    religion of depravity, totally repugnant indeed to the nature of that Being who,
                    as he pretended, was its object; but therefore more likely to accord with the
                    appetites and conceptions of a corrupt and sensual age.</p>
                <p>“That we may not appear to exalt our Scriptures thus far above the Koran by an
                    unreasonable preference, we shall produce a part of the second chapter of the
                    latter, which is deservedly admired by the Mahometans, who wear it engraved on
                    their ornaments, and recite it in their prayers. ‘ God! there is no God but he;
                    the living, the self-subsisting: neither slumber nor sleep seizcth on him: to
                    him belongeth whatsoever is in heaven and on earth. Who is he that can intercede
                    with him but through his good pleasure? He knoweth that which is past, and that
                    which is to come. His throne is extended over heaven and earth, and the
                    preservation of both is to him no burden. He is the high, the mighty.’” (<hi
                    rend="italic">Sales Kor.</hi> ii. p. 30.4to edit.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Alcoran</hi> is also figuratively applied to certain other
                    books full of impieties and impostures. In this sense we meet with the Alcoran
                    of the Cordeliers, which has made a great noise; wherein St Francis is
                    extravagantly magnified, and put on a level with Jesus Christ. The Alcoran of
                    the Cordeliers is properly an extract of a very scarce book, entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">The Conformity of the Life of the seraphiΛ father St Francis with
                    the Life of Christ,</hi> published in 1510, 4to; since at Bologna in folio.
                    Erasmus Albertus, being by the elector of Brandenburg appointed to visit a
                    monastery of Franciscans, found this book; and being struck with the extreme
                    folly and absurdity of it, collected a number of curiosities out of it, and
                    published them under the title of the <hi rend="italic">Alcoran</hi> of the
                    Franciscans, with a preface by Martin Luther.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
