<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-1967-0166-12" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ADULTERY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 166</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1739388">Womanism</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1895887">Womanizers</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:964412">Husbands</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:882984">Crime</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:887617">Danes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193031967" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ADULTERY</label>, an unlawful commerce between one married
                    person and another, or between a married and unmarried person.</p>
                <p>Punishments have been annexed to adultery in most ages and nations, though of
                    different degrees of severity. In many it has been capital; in others venial,
                    and attended only with slight pecuniary mulcts. Some of the penalties are
                    serious, and even cruel; others of a jocose and humorous kind. Even contrary
                    things have been enacted as punishments for adultery. By some laws the criminals
                    are forbidden marrying together in case they become single; by others they are
                    forbidden to marry any besides each other: by some they are incapacitated from
                    ever committing the like crime again; by others they are glutted with it till it
                    becomes nauseous.</p>
                <p>Among the rich Greeks, adulterers were allowed to redeem themselves by a
                    pecuniary fine: the woman’s father, in such cases, returned the dower he had
                    received from her husband, which some think was refunded by the adulterer.
                    Another punishment among those people was putting out the eyes of
                    adulterers.</p>
                <p>The Athenians had an extraordinary way of punishing adulterers, called <hi
                    rend="italic">ατrοζα(ρανιδuισις και &lt;καζpτι</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">μος,</hi> practised at least on the poorer sort who were not able
                    to pay the fines. This was an awkward sort of empalement, performed by thrusting
                    one of the largest radishes up the anus of the adulterer, or, in defect thereof,
                    a fish with a large head, called <hi rend="italic">mugil,</hi> mullet. Alcaeus
                    is said to have died, in this way, though it is doubted whether the punishment
                    was reputed mortal. Juvenal and Catullus speak of this custom as received also
                    among the Romans, though not authorized by an express law, as it was among the
                    Greeks.</p>
                <p>There are various conjectures concerning the ancient punishment of adultery among
                    the Romans. Some will have it to have been made capital by a law of Romulus, and
                    again by the twelve tables; others, that it was first made capital by Augustus;
                    and others, not before the emperor Constantine. The truth is, the punishment in
                    the early days was very various, much being left to the discretion of the
                    husband and parents of the adulterous wife, who exercised it differently, rather
                    with the silence and countenance of the magistrate than by any formal authority
                    from him. Thus, we are told the wife’s father was allowed to kill both parties,
                    when caught in the fact, provided he did it immediately, killed both together,
                    and as it were with one blow. The same power ordinarily was not indulged the
                    husband, except the crime were committed with some mean or infamous person;
                    though, in other cases, if his rage carried him to put them to death, he was not
                    punished as a murderer. On many occasions, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193031980"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0702-1980-0167"/>however, revenge was not carried so far; but
                    mutilating, castrating, cutting off the ears, noses, &amp;c. served the turn.
                    The punishment allotted by the <hi rend="italic">lex Julia</hi> was not, as many
                    have imagined, death, but rather banishment or deportation, being interdicted
                    fire and water; though Octavius appears in several instances to have gone beyond
                    his own law, and to have put adulterers to death. Under Macrinus, many were
                    burnt at a stake. Constantine first by law made the crime capital. Under
                    Constantius and Constans, adulterers were burnt, or sewed in sacks and thrown
                    into the sea. Under Leo and Marcian, the penalty was abated to perpetual
                    banishment, or cutting off the nose. Under Justinian, a further mitigation was
                    granted, at least in favour of the wife, who was only to be scourged, lose her
                    dower, and be shut up in a monastery. After two years, the husband was at
                    liberty to take her back again; if he refused, she was shaven, and made a nun
                    for life; but it still remained death in the husband. The reason alleged for
                    this difference is, that the woman is the weaker vessel. Matthaeus declaims
                    against the empress Theodora, who is supposed to have been the cause of this
                    law, as well as of others procured in favour of that sex from the emperor.</p>
                <p>Under Theodosius, women convicted of this crime were punished after a very
                    singular manner, viz. by a public constupration; being locked up in a narrow
                    cell, and forced to admit to their embraces all the men that would offer
                    themselves. To this end the gallants were to dress themselves on purpose, having
                    several little bells fastened to their clothes, the tinkling of which gave
                    notice to those without of every motion. This custom was abolished by the same
                    prince.</p>
                <p>By the Jewish law, adultery was punished with death in both parties, where they
                    were both married, or only the woman. The Jews had a particular trial or ordeal
                    for a woman suspected of the crime, by making her drink the bitter waters of
                    jealousy; which, if she were guilty, made her swell.</p>
                <p>Amongst the Mingrelians, according to Chardin, adultery is punished with the
                    forfeiture of a hog, which is usually eaten in good friendship between the
                    gallant, the adulteress, and the cuckold. In some parts, of the Indies, it is
                    said any man’s wife is permitted to prostitute herself to him who will give an
                    elephant for the use of her; and it is reputed no small glory to her to have
                    been rated so high. Adultery is said to be so frequent in Ceylon, that there is
                    not a woman who does not practise it, notwithstanding its being punishable with
                    death. Among the Japanese, and divers other nations, adultery is only penal in
                    the woman. In the Marian islands, the woman is not punishable for adultery; but
                    if the man go astray he pays severely; the wife and her relations waste his
                    lands, turn him out of hi∙s house, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>In Spain they punished adultery in men by cutting off the instrument of the
                    crime. In Poland, before Christianity was established, they punished adultery
                    and fornication in a particular manner: the criminal they carried to die
                    market-place, and there fastened him by the offending part with a nail, laying a
                    razor within his reach, and leaving him under a necessity either of doing
                    justice upon himself, or of perishing in that condition.</p>
                <p>In England adultery by the ancient laws was severely punished. King Edmund the
                    Saxon ordered it to be punished in the same manner as homicide; and Canute the
                    Dane ordered that a man who committed adultery should be banished, and that the
                    woman should have her nose and ears cut off. In the time of Henry I. it was
                    punished with the loss of eyes and genitals.</p>
                <p>In Britain adultery is now reckoned a spiritual offence, that is, cognizable by
                    the spiritual courts, where it is punished by fine and penance. The common law
                    takes no further notice of it than to allow the party aggrieved an action and
                    damages. This practice is often censured by foreigners, as making too light of a
                    crime, the bad consequences of which, public as well as private, are so great.
                    It has been answered, that perhaps this penalty, by civil action, joined with
                    the ignominy attached to it, is more calculated to prevent the frequency of the
                    offence, which ought to be the end of all laws, than a severer punishment.</p>
                <p>Adultery is, both in England and Scotland, a ground of divorce; but in the former
                    a <hi rend="italic">complete</hi> divorce can only be obtained through an act of
                    parliament, whereas in the latter a complete divorce may be effected by the
                    sentence of the consistorial or commissary court. The adulterous parties are by
                    the law of Scotland prohibited from intermarrying with each other. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Divorce.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Adultery</hi> is used in
                    Scripture for idolatry, or departing from the true God to the worship of a false
                    one.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Adultery</hi> is used by ecclesiastical writers for a
                    person’s invading or intruding into a bishopric during the former bishop’s life.
                    The reason of the appellation is, that a bishop is supposed to contract a kind
                    of spiritual marriage with his church. The translation of a bishop from one see
                    to another was also reputed a species of adultery, on the supposition of its
                    being a kind of second marriage, which in those days was esteemed a degree of
                    adultery. This conclusion was founded on the text of St Paul, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Let a bishop be the husband of one wife</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> by a
                    forced construction of church for wife, and of bishop for husband.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Adultery</hi> is used by ancient naturalists for the act of
                    ingrafting one plant upon another; in which sense Pliny speaks of the adulteries
                    of trees, <hi rend="italic">arborum adulteria,</hi> which he represents as
                    contrary to nature, and a piece of luxury or needless refinement.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
