<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7310-0577-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">ALVA de Tormes</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 577</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1137041">Success</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1156290">Trials</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193037310" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">ALVA <hi rend="smallcaps">de Tormes</hi></label>, a
                    considerable town in Spain, in the kingdom of Leon, and territory of Salamanca,
                    with a very handsome castle. It is seated on the north bank of the river Tormes.
                    Long. 6. 1. W. Lat. 4L 0. N.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Alva,</hi><hi rend="italic">Ferdinand Alvarez of Toledo,
                    Duhe of,</hi> was born in 1508, and descended from one of the most illustrious
                    families in Spain. His grandfather, Frederick de Toledo, was his preceptor in
                    the military and political arts; and he displayed his valour at the battle of
                    Pavia and at the siege of Tunis. The ambitious Charles V. selected Alva as a
                    proper instrument for conducting his military enterprises. In 1538 he made him
                    his general; and, after several operations, in which he displayed both valour
                    and military skill, in 1542 he successfully defended Perpignan against the
                    dauphin of France.</p><p>In 1546 Alva was made general in chief of the army which marched against the
                    German Protestants, who were marshalled under the banners of the elector of
                    Saxony. Francis, the king of France, died at Rambouillet, and by his death a
                    considerable change was made in the state of Europe. Charles therefore instantly
                    began his march from Egra on the borders of Bohemia, and entering the southern
                    frontier of Saxony, attacked Altorf upon the Elster. Incessantly pushing
                    forward^ he arrived on the evening of the 23d of April on the banks of the Elbe,
                    opposite to Muhlberg. The river at that place was three hundred paces in breadth
                    and about four feet in depth, its current rapid, and the bank possessed by the
                    Saxons was higher than that which he occupied. In opposition to the opinion of
                    the duke of Alva and his other officers, Charles, with undaunted courage, though
                    with inexpressible difficulty, led his army through the river and engaged the
                    Saxons. The elector displayed great personal courage and military knowledge; but
                    having received a wound in the face, he at last surrendered himself prisoner.
                    The emperor proceeded towards Wittenberg, whither the remains of the Saxon army
                    had fled, carrying along with him the captive prince, as a spectacle of
                    consternation and amazement to his own subjects. But when he approached the
                    town, he found it defended by the vigorous efforts of the elector’s wife, along
                    with the inhabitants. He summoned Sibylla once and a second time to open the
                    gates, informing her, that if she persisted in her obstinacy, the elector should
                    answer for it with his head. Accordingly he brought his prisoner to an immediate
                    trial. The proceedings against him were as irregular as the stratagem was
                    barbarous. Instead of consulting the states of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193037323" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7323-0578"/>the empire, or
                    remitting the cause to any court, which, according to the German constitution,
                    might have legally taken cognizance of the elector’s crime, he subjected the
                    greatest prince in the empire to the jurisdiction of a court-martial. The
                    emperor selected the unrelenting duke of Alva as a proper instrument to carry
                    into effect any measure of violence and oppression, and therefore made him
                    president of that court, composed of Spanish and Italian officers. Moved more by
                    the entreaties of his wife than by a sense of his own danger, the elector, in
                    order to save his life, submitted to all the rigorous and unjust measures that
                    were proposed; but when it was added, that he should also renounce the
                    Protestant faith and become a Roman Catholic, he refused to act in opposition to
                    his conscience, and bravely fell a sacrifice to the cause of truth.</p><p>In 1552 Alva was intrusted with the command of the army intended to invade
                    France, and was constrained by the opinion and authority of the emperor to lay
                    siege to Mentz, in opposition to his own military knowledge; but notwithstanding
                    all his valour and abilities, the duke of Guise successfully defended the place.
                    In consequence of the success of the French arms in Piedmont, he was made
                    commander in chief of all the emperor’s forces in Italy, and at the same time
                    invested with unlimited power. Success did not, however, attend his first
                    attempts, and after several unfortunate attacks he was obliged to retire into
                    winter quarters. The next year he was sent into the pope’s territories; and, had
                    he not been restrained by his master, he would have taken possession of all his
                    fortified places, and deterred Henry from entering into any new connection with
                    him, and have thereby prevented the renewal of the war. Philip was strongly
                    disposed to peace, but Alva was inclined to severe measures: he, however,
                    yielded to the instructions of his master, until being deluded, and sometimes
                    haughtily answered, he at length sent Pino de Loffredo with a letter to the
                    college of cardinals, and another to Paul, in which, after enumerating the
                    various injuries which his master had received, and renewing his former offers
                    of peace and friendship, he concluded with protesting that, if his offers were
                    again rejected, the pope should be chargeable with all the calamities that might
                    follow. The pope threw Loffredo into prison; and, had not the college of
                    cardinals interposed, he would even have put him to death; and on account of
                    Philip’s failing to pay tribute for Naples, he deprived him of the sovereignty
                    of that kingdom. This violent conduct of Paul gave great offence throughout all
                    Europe, and greatly lessened his influence in Italy; but Philip, though a young,
                    ambitious, and powerful monarch, and of a temper impatient of injuries and
                    affronts, moved with a religious veneration, discovered an amazing reluctance to
                    proceed to extremities. After much time spent in negotiation, Philip was at last
                    forced to give orders for Alva to take the field. He cheerfully obeyed, and
                    began his march in the beginning of September 1556, with a well-disciplined
                    army; and after reducing several towns in the Campagna di Roma, he pursued his
                    conquests to the very gates of Rome. The circumstances, however, in which Alva
                    found his army, induced him to make a truce of forty days, and after several
                    negotiations he yielded to peace. One of its terms was, that the duke of Alva
                    should in person ask forgiveness of the haughty pontiff whom he had conquered.
                    Proud as the duke was by nature, and accustomed to treat with persons of the
                    highest dignity, yet such was the superstitious veneration then entertained for
                    the papal character, that he confessed his voice failed him at the interview,
                    and his presence of mind forsook him. Not long after this he was sent at the
                    head of a splendid embassy to Paris, to espouse, in the name of his master,
                    Elizabeth, daughter of Henry, kin∏∙ of France. ^ <hi rend="superscript"> ,
                    c</hi></p><p>Philip II., his new master, being strongly devoted to the Roman see, and
                    determined, by the most unrelenting severity and unbounded cruelty, to reclaim
                    rebels to his government and dissenters from his faith, pitched upon Alva as the
                    fittest person to carry this system into practice. With this design, therefore,
                    he was sent into the Low Countries in 1567. Having received his orders, armed
                    with such power as left only the shadow of authority to the natural governor,
                    and provided with 10,000 veterans, he marched towards that devoted country. When
                    he arrived, he soon showed how much he merited the confidence which his master
                    reposed in him, and instantly erected a bloody tribunal to try all persons who
                    had been engaged in the late commotions which the civil and the religious
                    tyranny of Philip had excited. He imprisoned the counts Egmont and Horn, the two
                    popular leaders of the Protestants, and soon brought them to an unjust trial,
                    and condemned them to death. In a little time he totally annihilated every
                    privilege of the people, and, with uncontrolled fury and cruelty, put multitudes
                    of them to death. Beholding herself deprived of all authority, and her subjects
                    devoted to destruction, the duchess of Parma resigned her office, disdaining to
                    hold the nominal, while the actual reins of power were in the hands of Alva.
                    This event increased the general tide of wretchedness, and every place was
                    filled with scenes of horror and dismay. Unable for the present to administer
                    the least aid, the prince of Orange saved his life by flight. This noble prince
                    suddenly collecting an army in Germany, returned to the relief of his
                    countrymen; and at the same time Prince Lewis, his brother, marched with an army
                    into Friesland. Although success at first attended Lewis, yet the activity and
                    experience of Alva prevailed, and he was totally defeated. The prince of Orange
                    proved a more formidable foe; and it required the united talents of Alva and his
                    son Frederick of Toledo to prevent the prince from making a descent upon the
                    Netherlands. But notwithstanding all the address and military skill of the
                    prince of Orange, the descent was prevented; and Alva had the glory of baffling
                    that great leader, and of compelling him, after great loss of men, to disband
                    the remainder of his army. Alva could now indulge his cruelty unrestrained. The
                    executioner was instantly employed in removing all those friends of freedom whom
                    the sword had spared. In most of the considerable towns Alva built citadels. In
                    the city of Antwerp he erected a statue of himself, which was a monument no less
                    of his vanity than of his tyranny: he was figured trampling on the necks of two
                    smaller statues, representing the two estates of the Low Countries. By his
                    unusual and arbitrary demand of new supplies from the states, he greatly
                    aggravated this haughty insult. The exiles from the Low Countries, roused to
                    action by his oppression, fitted out a kind of piratical fleet, and, after
                    strengthening themselves by successful depredations, ventured upon the bold
                    exploit of seizing the town of Bricl. Thus Alva, by his cruelty, became the
                    unwitting instrument of the future independence of the seven Dutch provinces.
                    The fleet of the exiles having met the Spanish fleet, totally defeated it, and
                    reduced North Holland and Mons. Many cities hastened to throw off the yoke:
                    while the states-general assembling at Dordrecht, openly declared against Alva’s
                    government, and marshalled under the banners of the prince of Orange. This
                    situation of affairs convinced Alva of the instability of a government upheld by
                    terror and oppression; he therefore began, when too late, to employ more lenient
                    measures. His preparations to oppose the gathering<pb break="no" facs="nls:193037336" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7336-0579"/> storm were
                    concerted with his usual vigour, and the succeeded in recovering Mons, Mechlin,
                    and Zutphen, under the conduct of his son Frederick, where his soldiers more
                    than retaliated upon the prince of Orange. With the exception of Zealand and
                    Holland, he regained all the provinces; and at last his son stormed Waerden,
                    and, massacring its inhabitants with the most savage cruelty, proceeded to
                    invest the city of Haerlem. Fully convinced of the miseries that awaited their
                    surrender, this city stood an obstinate siege; and nothing less than the
                    inflexible and persevering spirit of Alva could have overcome difficulties
                    almost insurmountable. Despairing of success, Frederick was at one time disposed
                    to raise the siege, but the stern reproaches of his father urged him on; and at
                    length the inhabitants, overcome with fatigue, surrendered. The victorious
                    Frederick gaíve tolerable conditions to the town; but his inhuman father
                    arriving on the third day after the surrender, sacrificed to his vengeance many
                    who had been flattered with a promise of mercy. Their next attack was upon
                    Alemaar; but the spirit of desperate resistance was raised to such 'a height in
                    the breasts of the Hollanders, that the Spanish veterans were repulsed with
                    great loss, and Frederick constrained reluctantly to retire. Alva now resolved
                    to try his fortune by sea, and with great labour and expense fitted out a
                    powerful fleet, with which he proceeded to attack the Zealanders, but was
                    entirely defeated, and the commander taken prisoner. About the same period the
                    prince of Orange proceeded to attack the town of Gertruydenberg. Alva’s feeble
                    state of health and continued disasters induced him to solicit his recall from
                    the government of the Low Countries; a measure which, in all probability, was
                    not displeasing to Philip, who was now resolved to make trial of a milder
                    administration. In December 1573 that devoted country was relieved from the
                    presence and oppressions of the duke of Alva, who, returning home, accompanied
                    by his son, made the inglorious boast that during the course of six years,
                    besides the multitudes destroyed in battle and massacred after victory, he had
                    consigned 18,000 persons to the executioner.</p><p>Returning from this scene of oppression and blood, he was treated for some time
                    with great distinction by his master. Justice, however, soon overtook the crimes
                    of Alva; for his son, having debauched one of the king’s attendants, under
                    promise of marriage, was committed to prison; and being aided in his escape by
                    his father, and married by him to a cousin of his own, Alva was banished from
                    court, and confined in the castle of Uzeda. In this disgraceful situation he
                    remained two years, when the success of Don Antonio, in assuming the crown of
                    Portugal, determined Philip to turn his eyes towards a person in whose fidelity
                    and abilities he could on this occasion most confide. A secretary was instantly
                    dispatched to Alva, to ascertain whether his health was sufficiently vigorous to
                    enable him to undertake the command of an army. The aged chief returned an
                    answer full of loyal zeal, and was immediately appointed to the supreme command
                    in Portugal. It is a singular fact, however, that the enlargement and elevation
                    of Alva were not followed by forgiveness. It is a characteristic mark of the
                    unrelenting temper of Philip, and, at the same time, a noble testimony to the
                    honour and loyalty of Alva, that although placed in this important trust, he did
                    not procure his pardon. In 1581 Alva entered Portugal, defeated Antonio, drove
                    him from the kingdom, and soon reduced the whole under the subjection of Philip.
                    Entering Lisbon, he seized an immense treasure, and suffered his soldiers, with
                    their accustomed violence and rapacity, to sack the suburbs and vicinity. It is
                    reported, that Alva being requested to give an account of the money expended on
                    that occasion, sternly replied, “If the king asks me for an account, I will make
                    him a statement of kingdoms preserved or conquered, of signal victories, of
                    successful sieges, and of sixty years’ service.” Philip deemed it proper to make
                    no further inquiries. Alva, however, did not enjoy the honours and rewards of
                    his last expedition, for he died in 1582, at the age of 75.</p></div></body></text></TEI>