<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0702-1681-0144-11" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">ADDISON, Lancelot</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 144</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:939255">Gays</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61b6d">Drummers</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205592">Morocco</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193031681" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">ADDISON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Lancelot</hi></label>, son of
                    Lancelot Addison, a clergyman, was born in the parish of Crosby-Ravensworth, in
                    Westmoreland, in the year 1632. He was educated at Queen’s College, Oxford, and
                    at the restoration of King Charles II. accepted of the chaplainship of the
                    garrison of Dunkirk; but that fortress being delivered up to the French in 1662,
                    he returned to England, and was soon after made chaplain to the garrison of
                    Tangier, where he continued seven years, and was greatly esteemed. In 1670 he
                    returned to England, and was made chaplain in ordinary to the king; but his
                    chaplainship of Tangier being taken from him on account of his absence, he found
                    himself straitened in his circumstances, when he seasonably obtained the rectory
                    of Milston in Wiltshire, worth about L.120 per annum.. He afterwards became a
                    prebendary of Sarum, took his degree of doctor of divinity at Oxford, and in
                    1683 was made dean of Lichfield, and the next year archdeacon of Coventry. His
                    life was exemplary, his conversation pleasing and greatly instructive, and his
                    behaviour as a gentleman, a clergyman, and a neighbour, did honour to the place
                    of his residence. He wrote, 1. A Short Narrative of the Revolutions of the
                    Kingdoms of Fez and Morocco; 2. The present State of the Jews; 3. A Discourse on
                    Catechising; 4. A Modest Plea for the Clergy; 5. An Introduction to the
                    Sacrament; 6. The first State of Mahometism; and several other pieces. This
                    worthy divine died on the 20th of April 1703, and left three sons; Joseph, the
                    subject of the next article; Gulston, who died while governor of Fort St George;
                    Lancelot, master of arts, and fellow of Magdalen College in Oxford; and one
                    daughter, first married to</p><p>Dr Sarte, prebendary of Westminster, and afterwards to Daniel Combes, Esq. '</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Addison,</hi><hi rend="italic">Joseph,</hi> the son of the
                    preceding Dean Addison, was born at Milston, near Ambresbury, in Wiltshire, on
                    the 11th of May 1672; and not being thought likely to live, was baptized the
                    same day. He received the first rudiments of his education at the place of his
                    nativity under the reverend Mr Naish, but was soon removed to Salisbury under
                    the care of Mr Taylor, and from thence to the Charter-house, where his
                    acquaintance with Sir Richard Steele commenced. About the age of 15, he was
                    entered at Queen’s College, Oxford, where he applied very closely to the study
                    of classical learning, in which he made a surprising proficiency.</p><p>In the year 1687, Dr Lancaster, dean of Magdalen College, having by chance seen a
                    Latin poem of Mr Addison’s, was so pleased with it, that he immediately got him
                    elected into that house, where he took his degrees of bachelor and master of
                    arts. His Latin pieces, in the course of a few years, were exceedingly admired
                    in both universities; nor were they less esteemed abroad, particularly by the
                    celebrated Boileau, who is reported to have said, that he would not have written
                    against Perrault had he before seen such excellent pieces by a modern hand. He
                    published nothing in English before the 22d year of his age, when there appeared
                    a short copy of verses written by him, and addressed to Mr Dryden, which
                    procured him great reputation from the best judges. This was soon followed by a
                    translation of the fourth Géorgie of Virgil (omitting the story of Aristaeus),
                    much commended by Mr Dryden. He wrote also the Essay on the Georgies prefixed to
                    Mr Dryden’s translation. There are several other pieces written by him about
                    this time; amongst the rest, one dated the 3d of April 1694, addressed to H. S.
                    that is, Dr Sacheverel, who became afterwards so famous, and with whom Mr
                    Addison lived once in the greatest friendship; but their intimacy was some time
                    after broken off, by their disagreement in political principles. In the year
                    1695 he wrote a poem to King William on one of his campaigns, addressed to Sir
                    John Somers, lord-keeper of the great seal. This gentleman received it with
                    great pleasure, took the author into the number of his friends, and bestowed on
                    him many marks of his favour.</p><p>Mr Addison had been closely pressed while at the university to enter into holy
                    orders, and had once resolved upon it; but his great modesty, his natural
                    diffidence, and an uncommonly delicate sense of the importance of the sacred
                    function, made him afterwards alter his resolution; and having expressed an
                    inclination to travel, he was encouraged thereto by his patron above mentioned,
                    who by his interest procured him from the crown a pension of L.300 per annum to
                    support him in his travels. He accordingly made a tour to Italy in the year
                    1699; and in 1701 he wrote a poetical epistle from Italy to the earl of Halifax,
                    which has been much esteemed both abroad and at home. It was translated into
                    Italian verse by the abbot Antonio Maria Salvini, Greek professor at Florence.
                    In the year 1705 he published an account of his travels, dedicated to Lord
                    Somers; which, though at first but indifferently received, yet in a little time
                    met with its deserved applause.</p><p>In the year 1702 he was about to return to England, when he received advice of
                    his being appointed to attend Prince Eugene, who then commanded for the emperor
                    in Italy; but the death of King William happening soon after, put an end to this
                    affair, as well as his pension; and he remained for a considerable time
                    unemployed. But an unexpected incident at once raised him, and gave him an <pb break="no" facs="nls:193031694" xml:id="kp-eb0702-1694-0145"/>
                    opportunity of exerting his fine talents to advantage; for, in the year 1704,
                    the lord treasurer Godolphin happened to complain to Lord Halifax that the duke
                    of Marlborough’s victory at Blenheim had not been celebrated in verse in the
                    manner it deserved; and intimated, that he would take it kindly if his lordship,
                    who was the known patron of the poets, would name a gentleman capable of doing
                    justice to so elevated a subject. Lord Halifax replied, somewhat hastily, that
                    he did know such a person, but would not mention him; adding, that long had he
                    seen with indignation men of no merit maintained in luxury at the public
                    expense, whilst those of real worth and modesty were suffered to languish in
                    obscurity. The treasurer answered very coolly, that he was sorry there should be
                    occasion for such an observation, but that he would do his endeavour to wipe off
                    such reproaches for the future; and he engaged his honour, that whoever might be
                    named by his lordship as a person capable of celebrating this victory, should
                    meet with a suitable recompense. Lord Halifax thereupon named Mr Addison;
                    insisting, however, that the treasurer himself should send to him; which he
                    promised. Accordingly he prevailed on Mr Boyle (afterwards Lord Carlton), then
                    chancellor of the exchequer, to make the proposal to Mr Addison; which he did in
                    so polite a manner, that our author readily undertook the task. The lord
                    treasurer had a sight of the piece when it was carried no further than the
                    celebrated simile of the angel, and was so pleased with it, that he immediately
                    appointed Mr Addison a commissioner of appeals, vacant by the promotion of Mr
                    Locke, chosen one of the lords commissioners for trade« The Campaign is
                    addressed to the duke of Marlborough: it gives a short view of the military
                    transactions in 1704, and contains a noble description of the two great actions
                    at Schellemberg and Blenheim. In 1705 he attended Lord Halifax to Hanover, and
                    the ensuing year was appointed under secretary to Sir Charles Hedges, secretary
                    of state, in which office he acquitted himself so well that the earl of
                    Sunderland, who succeeded Sir Charles in December, continued Mr Addison in his
                    employment.</p><p>A taste for operas beginning at this time to prevail in England, and many persons
                    having solicited Mr Addison to write one, he complied with their request, and
                    composed his <hi rend="italic">Rosamond.</hi> This, however, whether from the
                    defect of the music, or from the prejudices in favour of the Italian taste, did
                    not succeed upon the stage; but the poetry of it has been, and always will be,
                    justly admired. About this time Sir Richard Steele composed his comedy of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Tender Husband,</hi> to which Mr Addison wrote a prologue. Sir
                    Richard surprised him with a dedication of this play, and acquainted the public
                    that he was indebted to him for some of the most excellent strokes in the
                    performance. The marquis of Wharton, being appointed lord lieutenant of Ireland
                    in 1709, took Mr Àddison with him as his secretary. Her Majesty also made him
                    keeper of the records of Ireland, and as a further mark of her favour,
                    considerably augmented the salary annexed to that place. Whilst he was in this
                    kingdom, the <hi rend="italic">Tatler</hi> was first published; and he
                    discovered his friend Sir Richard Steele to be the author, by an observation on
                    Virgil, which he had communicated to him. He afterwards assisted considerably in
                    carrying on this paper, which the author acknowledges. The <hi rend="italic">Tatler</hi> being laid down, the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> was set on
                    foot, and Mr Addison furnished great part of the most admired papers. The <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> made its first appearance in March 1711, and was
                    brought to a conclusion in September 1712.</p><p>His celebrated <hi rend="italic">Cato</hi> appeared in 1713. He formed the design
                    of a tragedy upon this subject when he was very young, and wrote it when on his
                    travels: he retouched it in England, without any intention of bringing it on the
                    stage; but his friends being persuaded it would serve the cause of liberty, he
                    was prevailed on by their solicitations, and it was accordingly exhibited in the
                    theatre, with a prologue by Mr Pope, and an epilogue by Dr Garth. It was
                    received with the most uncommon applause, having run 35 nights without
                    interruption. The Whigs applauded every line in which liberty was mentioned, as
                    a satire on the Tories; and the Tories echoed every clap, to show that the
                    satire was unfelt. When it was printed, notice was given that the queen would be
                    pleased if it was dedicated to her; “but as he had designed that compliment
                    elsewhere, he found himself obliged,” says Tickell, “by his duty on the one
                    hand, and his honour on the other, to send it into the world without any
                    dedication.” It was no less esteemed abroad, having been translated into French,
                    Italian, and German; and it was acted at Leghorn and several other places with
                    vast applause. The Jesuits of St Omer made a Latin version of it, and the
                    students acted it with great magnificence.</p><p>About this time another paper called the <hi rend="italic">Guardian</hi> was
                    published by Steele, to which Addison was a principal contributor. It was a
                    continuation of the <hi rend="italic">Spectator,</hi> and was distinguished by
                    the same elegance and the same variety; but, in consequence of Steele’s
                    propensity to politics, was abruptly discontinued in order to write the <hi rend="italic">Englishman.</hi></p><p>The papers of Addison are marked in the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> by one
                    of the letters in the name of <hi rend="italic">Clio,</hi> and in the Guardian
                    by a <hi rend="italic">Hand.</hi> Many of these papers were written with powers
                    truly comic, with nice discrimination of characters, and accurate observation of
                    natural or accidental deviations from propriety; but it was not supposed that he
                    had tried a comedy for the stage, till Steele, after his death, declared him the
                    author of the <hi rend="italic">Drummer.</hi> This, however, he did not know to
                    be true by any cogent testimony; for when Addison put the play into ,his hands,
                    he only told him it was the work of a gentleman in the company: when it was
                    received, as is confessed, with cold disapprobation, he was probably less
                    willing to claim it. Tickell omitted it in his collection; but the testimony of
                    Steele, and the total silence of any other claimant, has determined the public
                    to assign it to Addison, and it is now printed with his other poetry. Steele
                    carried the <hi rend="italic">Drummer</hi> to the playhouse, and afterwards to
                    the press, and sold the copy for 50 guineas. To Steele’s opinion may be added
                    the proof supplied by the play itself, of which the characters are such as
                    Addison would have delineated, and the tendency such as Addison would have
                    promoted.</p><p>It is said that Mr Addison intended to compose an English dictionary, upon the
                    plan of the Italian <hi rend="italic">Della Crusea</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    but that upon the death of the queen, being appointed secretary to the lords
                    justices, he had not leisure to carry on such a work. When the earl of
                    Sunderland was appointed lord-lieutenant of Ireland, Mr Addison was again made
                    secretary for the affairs of that kingdom; and upon the earl’s being removed
                    from the lieutenancy, he was chosen one of the lords of trade.</p><p>Not long afterwards an attempt was made to revive the <hi rend="italic">Spectator,</hi> at a time indeed by no means favourable to literature, when the
                    accession of a new family to the throne filled the nation with anxiety, discord,
                    and confusion; and either the turbulence of the times or the satiety of the
                    readers put a stop to the publication, after an experiment of 80 numbers, which
                    were afterwards collected into an eighth volume, perhaps more valuable than any
                    of those that went before it: Addison produced more, than a fourth part.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193031707" xml:id="kp-eb0702-1707-0146"/><p>In 1715 he began the <hi rend="italic">Freeholder,</hi> a political paper, which
                    was much admired, and proved of great use at that juncture. He published also,
                    about this time, verses to Sir Godfrey Kneller upon the king’s picture, and some
                    to the princess of Wales with the tragedy of Cato.</p><p>Before the arrival of King George he was made secretary to the regency, and was
                    required by his office to send notice to Hanover that the queen was dead, and
                    that the throne was vacant. To do this would not have been difficult to any man
                    but Addison, who was so overwhelmed with the greatness of the event, and so
                    distracted by choice of expression, that the lords, who could not wait for the
                    niceties of criticism, called Mr Southwell, a clerk in the house, and ordered
                    him to dispatch the message. Southwell readily told what was necessary, in the
                    common style of business, and valued himself upon having done what was too hard
                    for Addison.</p><p>In 1716 he married the countess dowager of Warwick, whom he had solicited by a
                    very long and anxious courtship. He is said to have first known her by becoming
                    tutor to her son. The marriage, if uncontradicted report can be credited, made
                    no addition to his happiness. The year after, 1717, he rose to his highest
                    elevation, being made secretary of state; but is represented as having proved
                    unequal to the duties of his place. In the House of Commons he could not speak,
                    and therefore was useless to the defence of the government. In the office he
                    could not issue an order without losing time in quest of fine expressions. At
                    last, finding by experience his own inability for public business, he was forced
                    to solicit his dismission, with a pension of L.1500 a year. Such was the account
                    of those who were inclined to detract from his abilities; but by others his
                    relinquishment was attributed to declining health, and the necessity of recess
                    and quiet.</p><p>In his retirement he applied himself to a religious work,<note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Evidences of the Christian
                    Religion.</hi></p></note> which he had begun long before; part of which, scarce
                    finished, has been printed in his works. He intended also to give an English
                    paraphrase of some of David’s psalms; but his ailments increased, and cut short
                    his designs. He had for some time been oppressed by an asthmatic disorder, which
                    was now aggravated by a dropsy, and he prepared to die conformably to his
                    precepts and professions. He sent, as Pope relates, a message by the earl of
                    Warwick to Mr Gay, desiring to see him. Gay, who had not visited him for some
                    time before, obeyed the summons, and was received with great kindness. The
                    purpose for which the interview had been solicited was then discovered: Addison
                    told him that he had injured him, but that if he recovered he would recompense
                    him. What the injury was he did. not explain, nor did Gay ever know; but
                    supposed that some preferment designed for him had by Addison’s intervention
                    been withheld. Another death-bed interview, of a more solemn nature, is
                    recorded. Lord Warwick was a young man of very irregular life, and perhaps of
                    loose opinions: Addison, for whom he did not want respect, had very diligently
                    endeavoured to reclaim him; but his arguments and expostulations had no effect.
                    One experiment, however, remained to be tried. When he found his life near its
                    end, he directed the young lord to be called; and when he desired, with great
                    tenderness, to hear his last injunctions, told him, “I have sent for you that
                    you may see how a Christian can die.” What effect this awful scene had on the
                    earl’s behaviour is not known: he died himself in a short time. Having given
                    directions to Mr Tickell for the publication of his works, and dedicated them on
                    his death-bed to his friend Mr Craggs, he died June 17. 1719, at Holland-house,
                    leaving only one child, a daughter, by his marriage.</p><p>Addison’s course of life before his marriage has been detailed by Pope. His chief
                    companions were Steele, Bugdell, Philips, Carey, Davenant, and Colonel Brett.
                    With one or other of these he always breakfasted. He studied all morning; then
                    dined at a tavern, and went afterwards to Button's. From the coffee-house he
                    went to the tavern, where he often sat late and drank too much wine.</p><p>Dr Johnson justly observes, that Addison “not only made the proper use of wit
                    himself, but taught it to others; and from his time it has been generally
                    subservient to the cause of reason and of truth. He has dissipated the prejudice
                    that had long connected gaiety with vice, and easiness of manners with laxity of
                    principles. He has restored virtue to its dignity, and taught innocence not to
                    be ashamed. This is an elevation of literary character, <hi rend="italic">above
                    all Greek, above all Fomajι fame.</hi> No greater felicity can genius attain,
                    than that of having purified intellectual pleasure, separated mirth from
                    indecency, and wit from licentiousness; of having taught a succession of writers
                    to bring elegance and gaiety to the aid of goodness; and, to use expressions yet
                    more awful, of having <hi rend="italic">turned many to righteousness."</hi><hi rend="italic">—“</hi> As a describer of life and manners,” says the same author,
                    “he must be allowed to stand perhaps the first of the first rank. His humour,
                    which, as Steele observes, is peculiar to himself, is so happily diffused as to
                    give the grace of novelty to domestic scenes and daily occurrences. He never <hi rend="italic">outsteps the modesty of nature,</hi> nor raises merriment or
                    wonder by the violation of truth. His figures neither divert by distortion nor
                    amaze by aggravation. He copies life with so much fidelity, that he can hardly
                    be said to invent; yet his exhibitions have an air so much original, that it is
                    difficult to suppose them not merely the product of imagination. As a teacher of
                    wisdom he may be confidently followed. His religion has nothing in it
                    enthusiastic or superstitious; he appears neither weakly credulous nor wantonly
                    sceptical; his morality is neither dangerously lax nor impracticably rigid. All
                    the enchantment of fancy and all the cogency of argument are employed to
                    recommend to the reader his real interest, the care of pleasing the Author of
                    his being. Truth is shown sometimes as the phantom of a vision, sometimes
                    appears half-veiled in an allegory; sometimes attracts regard in the robes of
                    fancy, and sometimes steps forth in the confidence of reason. She wears a
                    thousand dresses, and in all is pleasing.</p><p>“His prose is the model of the middle style; on grave subjects not formal, on
                    light occasions not grovelling; pure without scrupulosity, and exact without
                    apparent elaboration; always equable, and always easy, without glowing words or
                    pointed sentences. Whoever wishes to attain an English style, familiar but not
                    coarse, and elegant but not ostentatious, must give his days and nights to the
                    volumes of Addison.” (Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Lives of the Poets.)</hi></p><p>Dr Johnson has related the following anecdote, which every admirer of Addison,
                    every man of feeling, must be reluctant to believe, “Steele,” says the doctor,
                    “whose imprudence of generosity or vanity of profusion kept him always incurably
                    necessitous, upon some pressing exigence, in an evil hour, borrowed a hundred
                    pounds of his friend, probably without much purpose of repayment; but Addison,
                    who seems to have had other notions of a hundred pounds, grew impatient of
                    delay, and reclaimed his loan by an execution. Steele felt, with great
                    sensibility, the obduracy of his creditor; but with emotions of sorrow rather
                    than of anger.” It is much to be wished, says Dr Kippis, that Dr Johnson had
                    produced his authority<pb break="no" facs="nls:193031720" xml:id="kp-eb0702-1720-0147"/> for this narration. It is very possible that it
                    may be only a story the doctor had somewhere heard in conversation, and which is
                    entirely groundless; “and this I am the rather inclined to believe, as I have
                    been assured, by one of the most respectable characters in the kingdom, that the
                    fact hath no foundation in truth.” Mr Potter, in a late publication, hath
                    informed us, that he is told by the best authority that the story is an absolute
                    falsehood.</p><p>Mr Tyers, in <hi rend="italic">A Historical Essay on Mr Addison,</hi> printed,
                    but not published, has mentioned some facts concerning him, with which we were
                    not before acquainted. These are, that he was laid out for dead as soon as he
                    was born; that when he addressed his verses on the English poets to Henry
                    Sacheverel, he courted that gentleman’s sister; that whenever Jacob Tonson came
                    to him for the Spectator, Bayle’s French Historical and Critical Dictionary lay
                    always open before him; that upon his return to England, after his travels, he
                    discharged some old debts he had contracted at Oxford, with the generosity of
                    good interest; that he was put into plentiful circumstances by the death of a
                    brother in the East Indies; that, having received encouragement from a married
                    lady, of whom he had been formerly enamoured, he had the integrity to resist the
                    temptation; that he refused a gratification of a three hundred pounds bank-note,
                    and afterwards of a diamond-ring of the same value, from a Major Dunbar, whom he
                    had endeavoured to serve in Ireland by his interest with Lord Sunderland; and
                    that his daughter by Lady Warwick died unmarried, residing at Bilton near Rugby,
                    and possessing an income of more than twelve hundred a year.</p><p>The following letter, which probably relates to the case of Major Dunbar,
                    reflects great honour on Mr Addison’s integrity. <hi rend="italic">“</hi><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 26. 1715. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir,</hi> —I find there
                    is a very strong opposition formed against you; but I shall wait on my
                    lord-lieutenant this morning, and lay your case before him as advantageously as
                    I can, if he is not engaged in other company. I am afraid what you say of his
                    grace does not portend you any good. And now, Sir, believe me, when I assure you
                    I never did, nor ever will, on any pretence whatsoever, take more than the
                    stated and customary fees of my office. I might keep the contrary practice
                    concealed from the world, were I capable of it, but I could not from myself; and
                    I hope I shall always fear the reproaches of my own heart more than those of all
                    mankind. In the mean time, if I can serve a gentleman of merit, and such a
                    character as you bear in the world, the satisfaction I meet with on such an
                    occasion is always a sufficient, and the only reward to, Sir, your most obedient
                    humble servant, J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Addison.”</hi></p><p>The anecdote which follows was told by the late Dr Birch. Addison and Mr Temple
                    Stanyan were very intimate. In the familiar conversations which passed between
                    them, they were accustomed freely to dispute each other’s opinions. Upon some
                    occasion Mr Addison lent Stanyan five hundred pounds. After this Mr Stanyan
                    behaved with a timid reserve, deference, and respect; not conversing with the
                    same freedom as formerly, or canvassing his friend’s sentiments. This gave great
                    uneasiness to Mr Addison. One day they happened to fall upon a subject, on which
                    Mr Stanyan had always been used strenuously to oppose his opinion. But even upon
                    this occasion he gave way to what his friend advanced, without interposing his
                    own view of the matter. This hurt Mr Addison so much, that he said to Mr
                    Stanyan, “Either contradict me, or pay me the money.”</p><p>In TickelΓs edition of Mr Addison’s works, published in 4 vols. 4to, there are
                    several pieces hitherto unmentioned, viz. The Dissertation on Medals; The
                    Present State of the War, and the Necessity of an Augmentation considered; The
                    late Trial and Conviction of Count Tariff; The Whig Examiner. Five of these
                    papers were attributed to Mr Addison, and they are the severest pieces he ever
                    wrote. He is said also to have been the author of a performance entitled <hi rend="italic">Dissertatio</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">insignioribus Romanorum Poetis,</hi> and of a Discourse on Ancient and Modern
                    Learning.</p></div></body></text></TEI>