<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-2942-0241-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AGATE, or Achat</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 241</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1165047">Veins</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:864856">Clouds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:836543">Boots</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qz22h3h">Veins</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gg1n">Clouds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r47q">Cuttings</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193032942" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AGATE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Achat</hi></label> (among the
                    Greeks and Latins Aχαrjjς and <hi rend="italic">Achates,</hi> from a river in
                    Sicily, on the banks of which it was first found), a very extensive genus of the
                    semipellucid gems.</p>
                <p>These stones are variegated with veins and clouds, but have no zones like those
                    of the onyx. They are composed of crystal debased by a large quantity of earth,
                    and neither formed by repeated incrustations round a central nucleus, nor made
                    up of plates laid evenly on one another, but are merely the effect of one simple
                    concretion, and variegated only by the disposition given by the fluid they were
                    formed in to their differently coloured veins or matters.</p>
                <p>Agates are arranged according to the different colours of their ground. Of those
                    with a <hi rend="italic">white</hi> ground there are three species. 1. The <hi
                    rend="italic">dendrachtes, mocoa stone,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">arborescent
                    agate.</hi> This seems to be the same with what some authors call the achates
                    with rosemary in the middle, and others achates with little branches of black
                    leaves. 2. The <hi rend="italic">dull milhy-loohing agate.</hi> This, though
                    greatly inferior to the former, is yet a very beautiful stone. It is common on
                    the shores of rivers in the East Indies, and also in Germany and some other
                    parts of Europe. Our lapidaries cut it into counters for card-playing, and other
                    toys of small value. 3. The <hi rend="italic">lead-coloured agate,</hi> called
                    the <hi rend="italic">phassachates</hi> by the ancients.</p>
                <p>Of the agates with a <hi rend="italic">reddish</hi> ground there are four
                    species. 1. An impure one of a flesh-coloured white, which is but of little
                    beauty in comparison with other agates. The admixture of flesh colour is but
                    very slight; and it is often found without any clouds, veins, or other
                    variegations; but sometimes it is prettily veined or variegated with spots of
                    irregular figures, having fimbriated edges. It is found in Germany, Italy, and
                    some other parts of Europe, and is wrought into toys of small value, and often
                    into the German gunflints. It has been sometimes found with evident specimens of
                    the perfect mosses bedded deep in it. 2. That of a pure blood colour, called <hi
                    rend="italic">hoemachates, or</hi> the <hi rend="italic">bloody agate,</hi> by
                    the ancients. 3. The clouded and spotted agate, of a pale flesh colour, called
                    by the ancients the <hi rend="italic">carnelian achates</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">sardachates.</hi> 4. The red-lead coloured one, variegated with
                    yellow, called the <hi rend="italic">coral agate,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >coralla achates,</hi> by the ancients.</p>
                <p>Of the agates with a <hi rend="italic">yellowish</hi> ground there are only two
                    known species; the one of the colour of yellow wax, called <hi rend="italic"
                    >cerachates</hi> by the ancients; the other a very elegant stone, of a yellow
                    ground, variegated with white, black, and green, called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >leonina,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">leonteseres,</hi> by the ancients.</p>
                <p>Lastly, Of the agates with a <hi rend="italic">greenish</hi> ground, there is
                    only one known species, called by the ancients <hi rend="italic"
                    >jaspachates.</hi></p>
                <p>Of all these species there are a great many varieties, some of them having upon
                    them natural representations of men and different kinds of animals, &amp;c.
                    Those representations are not confined to the agates whose ground is of any
                    particular colour, but are occasionally found on all the different species.
                    Velschius had in his custody a flesh-coloured agate, on one side of which
                    appeared a half-moon in great perfection, represented by a milky semicircle; on
                    the other side, the phases of <hi rend="italic">vesper,</hi> or the evening
                    star; whence he denominated it an <hi rend="italic">aphrodisian agate.</hi> An
                    agate is mentioned by Kircher,<note anchored="true" place="margin"
                    type="authorial"><p>Ephem. German. dec. i∙ an. 1. obs. 151.</p></note> on which
                    was the representation of a heroine armed; and one in the church of St Mark in
                    Venice has the representation of a king’s head adorned with a diadem. On
                    another, in the museum of the prince of Gonzaga, was represented the body of a
                    man with all his clothes, in a running posture. A still more curious one is
                    mentioned by De Boot,<note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>De
                    Gem. 1. ü. c. 95.</p></note> wherein appears a circle struck in brown, as
                    exactly as if done with a pair of compasses, and in the middle of the circle the
                    exact figure of a bishop with a mitre on: but inverting the stone a little,
                    another figure appears; and if it is turned yet farther, two others appear, the
                    one of a man, and the other of a woman. But the most celebrated agate of this
                    kind was that of Pyrrhus, wherein were represented the nine Muses, with their
                    proper attributes, and Apollo in the middle playing on the harp.<note
                    anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Pliny. 1. xxxvii∙ c.
                    3.</p></note> We have also seen accounts of an oriental agate, of such size as
                    to be fashioned into a cup, whose diameter is an ell abating two inches. In the
                    cavity is found delineated in black specks, <hi rend="smallcaps">b.
                    xristor.</hi> s. <hi rend="smallcaps">xxx.</hi> Other agates have also been
                    found, representing the numbers 4191, 191; whence they were called <hi
                    rend="italic">arithmetical</hi> agates, as those representing men or women have
                    obtained the name of <hi rend="italic">anthropomorphous.</hi></p>
                <p>Agates may be stained artificially with solution of silver in spirit of nitre,
                    and afterwards exposing the part to the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193032955"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0702-2955-0242"/>sun; and though these artificial colours disappear
                    on laying the stone for a night in aquafortis, yet a knowledge of the
                    practicability of thus staining agates must render these curious figures above
                    mentioned strongly suspected of being the work, not of nature, but of art. Some
                    account for these phenomena from natural causes. Thus Kircher, who had seen a
                    stone of this kind in which were depicted the four letters usually inscribed on
                    crucifixes, I. N. R. I. apprehends that some real crucifix had been buried
                    underground, among stones and other rubbish, where the inscription happening to
                    be parted from the cross, and to be received among a soft mould or clay
                    susceptible of the impression of the letters, came afterwards to be petrified.
                    In the same manner he supposes the agate of Pyrrhus to have been formed. Others
                    resolve much of the wonder into fancy.</p>
                <p>The agate is used for making cups, rings, seals, handles for knives and forks,
                    hilts for swords and hangers, beads to pray with, smelling-boxes, patch-boxes,
                    &amp;c. being cut or sawed with no great difficulty.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Agate,</hi> among <hi rend="italic">Antiquaries,</hi>
                    denotes a stone of this kind engraven by art. In this sense, agates make a
                    species of antique gems, in the workmanship whereof we find eminent proofs of
                    the great skill and dexterity of the sculptors. Several agates of exquisite
                    beauty are preserved in the cabinets of the curious; but the facts or histories
                    represented on these antique agates, however well executed, are now become so
                    obscure, and their explications so difficult, that several diverting mistakes
                    and disputes have arisen among those who undertook to give their true
                    meaning.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Agate</hi> is also the name of an instrument used by
                    gold-wire drawers; so called from the agate in the middle of it, which forms its
                    principal part.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
