<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0702-2994-0245-05" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">AGINCOURT</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 245</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93d6n">Bar</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fb1j">Archers</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4h12v74r">Arrows</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sx6497c">Wings</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kk48">Arm</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:813040">Archers</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1176014">Wings</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193032994" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">AGINCOURT</label>, a village of the French Netherlands,
                    situated in N. lat. 50. 35. E. long. 2. 10. famous on account of the victory
                    obtained by Henry V. of England over the French.</p><p>On the morning of Friday the memorable 25th of October, A. D. 1415, the day of
                    Crispin and Crispianus, the English and French armies were ranged in order of
                    battle, each in three lines, with bodies of cavalry on each wing. The constable
                    D’Albert, who commanded the French army, fell into the snare that was laid for
                    him, by drawing up his army in the narrow plain between the two woods. This
                    deprived him, in a great measure, of the advantage he should have derived from
                    the prodigious superiority of his numbers; obliged him to make his lines
                    unnecessarily deep, about 30 men in file; to crowd his troops, particularly his
                    cavalry, so close together, that they could hardly move or use their arms; and,
                    in a word, was the chief cause of all the disasters that followed. The French,
                    it is said, had a considerable number of cannon of different sizes in the field;
                    but we do not hear that they did any execution, probably for want of room. The
                    first line of the French army, which consisted of 8000 men-at-arms on foot,
                    mixed with 4000 archers, with 500 men-at-arms mounted on each wing, was
                    commanded by the constable D’Albert, the dukes of Orleans and Bourbon, and many
                    other nobles; the dukes of Alençon, Brabant, and Bar, &amp;c. conducted the
                    second line; and the earls of Marie, Damartine, Fauconberg, &amp;c. were at the
                    head of the third line. The king of England employed various arts to supply his
                    defect of numbers. He placed 200 of his best archers in ambush, in a low meadow,
                    on the flank of the first line of the French. His own first line consisted
                    wholly of archers, four in file; each of whom, besides his bow and arrows, had a
                    battle-axe, a sword, and a stake pointed with iron at both ends, which he fixed
                    before him in the ground, the point inclining outwards, to protect him - from
                    cavalry. This was a new invention, and had a happy effect. That he might not be
                    encumbered, he dismissed all his prisoners on their word of honour to surrender
                    themselves at Calais if he obtained the victory, and lodged all his baggage in
                    the village of Agincourt, in his rear, under a slender guard. The command of the
                    first line was, at his earnest request, committed to Edward duke of York,
                    assisted by the lords Beaumont, Willoughby, and Fanhope; the second was
                    conducted by the king, with his youngest brother Humphrey duke of Gloucester,
                    the earls of Oxford, Marshal, and Suffolk; and the third was led by the duke of
                    Exeter, the king’s uncle. The lines being formed, the king, in shining armour,
                    with a crown of gold adorned with precious stones on his helmet, mounted on a
                    fine white horse, rode along them, and addressed each corps with a cheerful
                    countenance and animating speeches. To inflame their resentment against their
                    enemies, he told them that the French hail determined to cut off three fingers
                    of the right hand of every prisoner; and to rouse their love of honour, he
                    declared, that every soldier in that army who behaved well should from
                    henceforth be deemed a gentleman, and entitled to bear coat armour.</p><p>When the two armies were drawn up in this manner, they stood a considerable time
                    gazing at one another in solemn silence. But the king, dreading that the French
                    would discover the danger of their situation, and decline a battle, commanded
                    the charge to be sounded, about ten o’clock in the forenoon. At that instant the
                    first line of the English kneeled down and kissed the ground; and then starting
                    up, discharged a flight of arrows, which did great execution among the crowded
                    ranks of the French. Immediately after, upon a signal being given, the archers
                    in ambush arose, and discharged their arrows on the flank of the French line,
                    and threw it into some disorder. The battle now became general, and raged with
                    uncommon fury. The English archers, having expended all their arrows, threw away
                    their bows, and rushing forward, made dreadful havock with their swords and
                    battle-axes. The first line of the enemy was by these means defeated, its
                    leaders being either killed or taken prisoners. The second line, commanded by
                    the duke D’Alençon (who had made a vow either to kill or take the king of
                    England, or to perish in the attempt), now advanced to the charge, and was
                    encountered by the second line of the English, conducted by the king. This
                    conflict was more close and furious than the former. The duke of Gloucester,
                    wounded and unhorsed, was protected by his royal brother till he was carried off
                    the field. The duke D’Alençon forced his way to the king, and assaulted him with
                    great fury; but that prince brought him to the ground, where he was instantly
                    dispatched. Discouraged by this disaster, the second line made no more
                    resistance, and the third fled without striking a blow; yielding a complete and
                    glorious victory to the English, after a violent struggle of three hours’
                    duration.</p></div></body></text></TEI>