<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-6582-0521-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALLEGRI, Antonio</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 521</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1010895">Martinis</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1037627">Night</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193036582" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALLEGRI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Antonio</hi></label>, called
                    <hi rend="italic">Corregio,</hi> from the place of his birth, an eminent
                    historical painter, was born in the year 1494. Being descended of poor parents,
                    and educated in an obscure village, he enjoyed none of those advantages which
                    contributed to form the other great painters of that illustrious age. He saw
                    none of the statues of ancient Greece or Rome, nor any of the works of the
                    established schools of Rome and Venice. But Nature was his guide; and Corregio
                    was one of her favourite pupils. To express the facility with which he painted,
                    he used to say that he always had his thoughts ready at the end of his
                    pencil.</p>
                <p>The agreeable smile, and the profusion of graces, which he gave to his madonas,
                    saints, and children, have been taxed with being sometimes unnatural; but still
                    they are amiable and seducing. An easy and flowing pencil, a union and harmony
                    of colours, and a perfect intelligence of light and shade, give an astonishing
                    relief to all his pictures, and have been the admiration both of his
                    contemporaries and his successors. Annibal Caracci, who flourished 50 years
                    after him, studied and adopted his manner in preference to that of any other
                    master. In a letter to his cousin Louis, he expressed with great warmth the
                    impression which was made on him by the first sight of Corregio’s paintings:
                    “Every thing which I see here,” says he, “astonishes me; particularly the
                    colouring and the beauty of the children. They live, they breathe, they smile
                    with so much grace and so much reality, that it is impossible to refrain from
                    smiling and partaking of their enjoyment. My heart is ready to break with grief
                    when I think on the unhappy fate of poor Corregio—that so wonderful a man (if he
                    ought not rather to be called an angeD should finish his days so miserably, in a
                    country where his talents were never known !”.</p>
                <p>From want of curiosity or of resolution, or from want of patronage, Corregio
                    never visited Rome, but remained his whole life at Parma, where the art of
                    painting was little esteemed, and of consequence poorly rewarded. This
                    occurrence of unfavourable circumstances occasioned at last his premature death
                    at the age of 40. He was employed to paint the cupola of the cathedral at Parma,
                    the subject of which is the Assumption of the Virgin; and having executed it in
                    a manner that has long been the admiration of every person of good taste, for
                    the grandeur of design, and especially for the boldness of the fore-shortenings
                    (an art which he first and at once brought to the utmost perfection), he went to
                    receive his payment. The canons of the church, either through ignorance or
                    baseness, found fault with his work; and although the price originally agreed
                    upon had been very moderate, they alleged that it was far above the merit of the
                    artist, and forced him to accept of the paltry sum of 200 livres; which, to add
                    to the indignity, they paid him in copper money. To carry home this unworthy
                    load to his indigent wife and children, poor Corregio had to travel six or eight
                    miles from Parma. 1he weight of his burden, the heat of the weather, and chagrin
                    at this villanous treatment, immediately threw him into a pleurisy, which in
                    three days put an end to his life and his misfortunes.</p>
                <p>For the preservation of this magnificent work the world is indebted to Titian. As
                    he passed through Parma, in the suite of Charles V., he ran instantly to see the
                    <hi rend="italic">chef</hi><hi rend="italic">d’oeuvre</hi> of Corregio. While he
                    was attentively viewing it, one of the principal canons of the church told him
                    that such a grotesque performance did not merit his notice, and that they
                    intended soon to have the whole defaced. “Have a care of what you do,” replied
                    the other; “if I were not Titian, I should certainly wish to be Corregio.”</p>
                <p>Corregio’s exclamation upon viewing a picture by Raphael is well known. Having
                    long been accustomed to hear the most unbounded applause bestowed on the works
                    of that divine painter, he by degrees became less desirous than afraid of seeing
                    any of them. One, however, he at last had occasion to see. He examined it
                    attentively for some minutes in profound silence; and then with an air of
                    satisfaction exclaimed, <hi rend="italic">I am still a painter.</hi> Julio
                    Romano, on seeing some of Corregio’s pictures at Parma, declared they were
                    superior to any thing in painting he had yet beheld. One of these, no doubt, was
                    the famous Virgin and Child, with Mary Magdalen and St Jerome; but whether our
                    readers are to depend upon his opinion, or upon that of Lady Millar, who in her
                    <hi rend="italic">Letters from Italy</hi> gives a very unfavourable account of
                    it, we shall not presume to determine. This lady, however, speaks in a very
                    different style of the no less famous <hi rend="italic">Notte</hi> or Night of
                    Corregio, of which she saw only a copy in the duke’s palace at Modena, the
                    original having been sold for a great sum of money to the king of Poland. “It
                    surprises me very much,” she says, “to see how different the characters are in
                    this picture from that which I already have described to you. The subject is a
                    Nativity; and the extraordinary beauty of this picture proceeds from the <hi
                    rend="italic">clair</hi><hi rend="italic">obscure.</hi> There are two different
                    lights introduced, by means of which the personages are visible; namely, the
                    light proceeding from the body of the child, and the moonlight. These two are
                    preserved distinct, and produce a most wonderful effect. The child’s body is so
                    luminous, that the superficies is nearly transparent, and the rays of light
                    emitted by it are verified in the effect they produce upon the surrounding
                    objects. They are not rays distinct and separate, like those round the face of a
                    sun that indicates an insurance office; nor linear, like those proceeding from
                    the man in the almanack; but of dazzling brightness; by their light you see
                    clearly the face, neck, and hands, of the virgin (the rest of the person being
                    in strong shadow), the faces of the <hi rend="italic">pastori</hi> who crowd
                    round the child, and particularly one woman, who holds her hand before her face,
                    lest her eyes should be so dazzled as to prevent her from beholding the infant.
                    This is a beautiful natural action, and is most ingeniously introduced. The
                    straw on which the child is laid appears gilt, from the light of his body
                    shining on it. The moon lights up the back ground of the picture, which
                    represents a landscape. Every object is distinct, as in a bright moonlight
                    night; and there cannot be two lights in nature more different than those which
                    appear in the same picture. The virgin and the child are of the most perfect
                    beauty. There is a great variety of character in the different .persons present,
                    yet that uniformity common to all herdsmen and peasants. In short, this copy is
                    so admirable, that I was quite sorry to be obliged to lose sight of it so soon;
                    but I never shall forget it. The duke of Modena, for whom Corregio did the
                    original picture, gave him only 600 livres of France for it,—a great sum in
                    those days; but at present what ought it to cost ?” This great painter’s death
                    happened in 1534.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193036595" xml:id="kp-eb0702-6595-0522"/>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Allegri,</hi><hi rend="italic">Gregorio,</hi> an
                    ecclesiastic by profession, and a celebrated composer of music of the
                    seventeenth century, ,was a native of Rome. He was the disciple of Nanini, the
                    intimate friend and contemporary of Palestrina. His abilities as a singer were
                    not remarkable, but he was deemed an excellent master of harmony; and so much
                    respected by all the musical professors of his time, that the pope, in the year
                    1629, appointed him to be one of the singers of his chapel. To his uncommon
                    merit as a composer of church music he united an excellent moral character,
                    exhibiting in his actions the devotion and benevolence of his heart. The poor
                    crowded daily to his door, whom he relieved to the utmost of his ability; and
                    not content with these beneficent actions, he daily visited the prisons of Rome,
                    in order to relieve the most deserving and afflicted objects which were immured
                    in these dreary mansions. With such divine simplicity and purity of harmony did
                    he compose many parts of the church service, that his loss was severely felt and
                    sincerely lamented by the whole college of singers in the papal service. He died
                    on the 18th February 1650, and was interred in the Chiesa Nuova, in ā vault
                    destined for the reception of deceased singers in the pope’s chapel, before the
                    chapel of S. Filippo Neri, near the altar of annunciation.</p>
                <p>Among his other musical works preserved in the pontifical chapel, is the
                    celebrated <hi rend="italic">Miserere,</hi> which, for 170 years, has been
                    annually performed at that chapel on Wednesday and Good Friday, in Passion week,
                    by the choral band, and the best singers in Italy. It is, however, generally
                    believed that it owes its reputation more to the manner in which it is
                    performed, than to the composition itself. The beauty and effect of the music is
                    not discernible upon paper, but the singers have, by tradition, certain customs,
                    expressions, and graces of convention, which produce wonderful effects. Some of
                    the effects produced may be justly attributed to the time, the place, and the
                    solemnity of the ceremonials observed during the performance. “The pope and
                    conclave are all prostrated on the ground, the candles of the chapel and the
                    torches of the balustrade are extinguished one by one, and the last verse of
                    this psalm is terminated by two choirs; the <hi rend="italic">maestro di</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">cappella</hi> beating time slower and slower, and the singers
                    diminishing or rather extinguishing the harmony by little and little, to a
                    perfect point.” Padre Martini says, that there was never more than three copies
                    made by authority, “one of which was for the emperor Leopold, one for the late
                    king of Portugal, and the other for himself; but a very complete one was
                    presented by the pope himself to King George III. as an inestimable curiosity.”
                    <hi rend="italic">{Gen. Biog.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
