<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7232-0571-07" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">ALUM</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 571</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:806253">Alum</term><term n="36" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term><term n="31" ref="fasttopic:1073274">Potash</term><term n="30" ref="fasttopic:1120349">Slate</term><term n="25" ref="fasttopic:979089">Iron</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bk43">Levant</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45x25p07">Winter</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term><term n="36" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term><term n="31" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f47d">Potash</term><term n="30" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m776">Slate</term><term n="25" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term><term n="23" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s24m">Acids</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term><term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193037232" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">ALUM</label>, a compound salt employed by dyers and other
                    artists in their different processes. It is soluble in water, has an astringent,
                    acid, and sweetish taste; reddens vegetable blues, and crystallizes in regular
                    octahedrons. When heated, it liquefies; and if the heat be continued, the water
                    of crystallization is driven off, the salt frothes and swells, and at last a
                    white matter remains, known by the name of <hi rend="italic">burnt
                    alum.</hi></p><p>Its constituents are sulphuric acid, alumina, an alkali, and water. The alkali
                    may be either <hi rend="italic">potash, soda,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ammonia.</hi> Hence there are three distinct species of alum, depending upon
                    the nature of the alkali which each contains. <hi rend="italic">Potash alum</hi>
                    (in which the alkali is potash) is the common alum of this country. In France
                    both potash and ammoniacal alum are manufactured; while soda alum is met with
                    native in different states, and probably in considerable quantity, in South
                    America; for it is curious that, on that continent, soda almost uniformly
                    replaces potash. Instead of nitrate of potash, which occurs in the old
                    continent, there are great depositos of nitrate of soda in South America. It is
                    likely that albite will be found replacing felspar in the granite of South
                    America.</p><p>The progress made by chemists in the discovery of the constitution of alum was
                    very slow. The species first investigated was potash alum. That it contained
                    sulphuric ≡cid as a constituent, was known even to the alchemists. Pott and
                    Margraaf demonstrated that alumina was another constituent. Mr Pott, in his <hi rend="italic">Lithogeognosia,</hi> showed that the earth of alum, or the
                    precipitate obtained when an alkali is poured into a solution of alum, is quite
                    different from lime and chalk, with which it had been confounded by Stahl.
                    Margraaf went much farther. He not only showed that alumina is one of the
                    constituents of <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi>.⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> n,</hi>
                    but that this earth possesses peculiar properties, is different from every other
                    substance, and is one of the ingredients in common clay. <hi rend="italic">(Experiences</hi><hi rend="italic">faites sur</hi><hi rend="italic">la
                    Terre</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">lAlwι.∙</hi>
                    Margraaf s <hi rend="italic">Opusc.</hi> ii. 111.) Margraaf showed likewise, by
                    many experiments, that crystals of alum cannot be obtained by dissolving alumina
                    in sulphuric acid, and evaporating the solutions. The crystals formed are always
                    soft, and quite different in their appearance from alum crystals. But when a
                    solution of potash or ammonia is dropt into this liquid, it immediately deposits
                    perfect crystals of alum. <hi rend="italic">(Sur la Régénération</hi><hi rend="italic">de l’Alun</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Margraafs <hi rend="italic">Opusc.</hi> ii. 86.) He mentions likewise, that manufacturers of
                    alum in general were unable to procure the salt without a similar addition, and
                    that at first it had been customary to add a quantity of putrid urine, and that
                    afterwards a solution of carbonate of potash was substituted in its place. But
                    subsequent chemists do not seem to have paid much attention to these important
                    observations of Margřaaf: they still continued, without any rigid examination,
                    to consider alum as a sulphate of alumina.</p><p>Bergman indeed had observed, that the addition of potash or ammonia made the alum
                    crystallize, but that the same effect was not produced by the addition of soda
                    or of lime. <hi rend="italic">(De</hi><hi rend="italic">Confectione
                    Aluminis</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi> Bergman’s <hi rend="italic">Opusc.</hi>
                    i. 225.) He had observed likewise, that sulphate of potash is frequently found
                    in alum. He decomposed the solution of alum by means of ammonia, evaporated the
                    filtered liquid to dryness, and exposed the residue to a red heat. A quantity of
                    sulphate of potash often remained behind in the crucible. <hi rend="italic">(Ibid.</hi> p. 326.) From these facts he drew the conclusion that sulphate of
                    potash readily combines with sulphate of alumina. Yet it is obvious, from the
                    whole of his dissertation, that he had no conception that alum is a double salt.
                    He ascribed the difficulty of crystallization to the excess of sulphuric acid
                    present He thought that the only use of the potash was to saturate this excess;
                    and advises manufacturers to substitute clay instead of potash, as a method
                    which would not only saturate the excess of acid, but increase the quantity of
                    alum. This very bad advice was not, we presume, followed by any alum-makers. If
                    they had tried it, they would soon have been convinced of its injurious
                    consequences. Instead of alum, they would have obtained an insoluble, tasteless
                    powder, well known by the name of <hi rend="italic">alum saturated with its
                    earth.</hi></p><p>After Klaproth had discovered the existence of potash as an ingredient in <hi rend="italic">leucite</hi> and <hi rend="italic">lepidolite,</hi> it occurred to
                    Vauquelin, that it was probably an ingredient likewise in many other minerals.
                    He recollected that alum crystals often make their appearance during the
                    analysis of stony bodies; and, considering that alum cannot be obtained in
                    crystals without the addition of potash, he began to suspect that this alkali
                    constituted an essential ingredient in the salt. A set of experiments,
                    undertaken on purpose to elucidate this important point, soon satisfied him that
                    his conjecture was well founded. Accordingly, in the year 1797 he published a
                    dissertation, demonstrating that alum is a double salt, composed of sulphuric
                    acid, alumina, and potash. <hi rend="italic">(Annales</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Chimie,</hi> xxii. 258.) Soon after, Chaptai published the analysis of four
                    different kinds of alum, namely, Roman alum, Levant alum, British alum, and alum
                    manufactured by himself. This analysis led to the same result as that of
                    Vauquelin. <hi rend="italic">(Ann. de Chim.</hi> xxii. 280.)</p><p>Since that time alŋm has been admitted by chemists to be a triple salt; tt∏α
                    various analyses of it have been made to determine its constituents. Vauquelin
                    <hi rend="italic">(Ann. de Chim.</hi> 1. 167), Thenard and Roard <hi rend="italic">(ibid.</hi> tom. lix. 72), Curaudau <hi rend="italic">(Journal de
                    Physique,</hi> lxvii. 1), and Berzelius <hi rend="italic">(Ann. de Chim.</hi>
                    lxxxii. 258), successively published the results of their experiments. These
                    analyses gradually led to an accurate knowledge of the composition of this <pb break="no" facs="nls:193037245" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7245-0572"/>
                    salt. The atomic weights of the constituents of alum are as follows :—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Sulphurie acid</p><p>Alumina</p><p>Potash..</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>5</p><p>2∙25</p><p>6</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Soda</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>4</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Ammonia</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>2∙125</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Water</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙125</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Potash alum is a compound of</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>4 atoms sulphurie acid .</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.... - 20</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1 atom potash</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.... - 6</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>3 atoms alumina</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.... - 6∙75</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>25 atoms water</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.... - 28∙125</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Hence the integrant particle of it weighs
                            60∙875</p></cell></row></table><p>Every atom of the sulphuric acid is combined with an atom of base; so that potash
                    alum is a compound of sulphate of potash and sulphate of alumina, in the
                    proportion of one atom of the former salt to three atoms of the latter. We may
                    therefore state the constituents of potash alum as follows :—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>3 atoms sulphate of alumina...</p><p>1 atom sulphate of
                            potash</p><p>25 atoms water</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>. = 21∙75</p><p>.. - 11</p><p>.. - 28∙125</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>60∙875</p></cell></row></table><p>Soda alum differs from potash alum in containing sulphate of soda instead of
                    sulphate of potash. Its constituents are as follows :—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>3 atoms sulphate of alumina·...</p><p>1 atom sulphate of
                            soda</p><p>25 atoms water</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.. - 21∙75</p><p>.. - 9</p><p>.. - 28∙125</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>58∙875</p></cell></row></table><p>The weight of an integrant particle of this alum is only 58∙875; because the alum
                    of soda weighs only 4, while that of potash is 6.</p><p>The constituents of ammoniacal alum are as follows :—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>3 atoms sulphate of alumina...</p><p>1 atom sulphate of
                            ammonia..</p><p>25 atoms water</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.. - 21∙75 .. = 7∙125</p><p>.. - 28∙125</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>57</p></cell></row></table><p>The weight of the integrant particle is only 57, because ammonia has an atomic
                    weight of only 2 ’ 125.</p><p>One of the most remarkable differences between these three species of alum is the
                    śolubility of each in water. At the temperature of 60°, 100 parts of water
                    dissolve 9∙37 parts of ammoniacal alum,</p><p>14∙79 parts of potash alum,</p><p>327∙6 parts of soda alum.</p><p>This great solubility of soda alum renders the manufacture of it very difficult
                    It does not easily cryallize; indeed, when the weather is hot, cryals of it can
                    hardly be obtained. This great solubility, together with the inferior weight of
                    its integrant particle, would render it more convenient and more economical for
                    dyers and calico printers, provided it could be furnished at the same rate with
                    common alum. But the greater difficulty attending the making of it would
                    probably prevent it from being saleable at a price sufficiently low to make it
                    available as a mordant.</p><p>Soda alum was first mentioned by Mr Winter in 1810, in his account of the Whitby
                    alum processes (Nicholson’s <hi rend="italic">Jour.</hi> XXV. p. 254, 255); but
                    before that time it had been made by Charles Macintosh, Esq. of Crossbasket Mr
                    William Wilson, at Hurlet, .near Glasgow, afterwards made it in considerable
                    quantities. Specimens of it have been still more recently sent by Dr Gillies
                    from the neighbourhood of Mendoza, in South America, where it occurs native in
                    considerable quantity.</p><p>These three different species of alum differ also somewhat from each other in
                    their specific gravities, which are as follows :—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Ammoniacal alum</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙56 Sp. Gr.</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Potash alum</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙75</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Soda alum</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1∙88<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                            soda alum whose specific gravity is here given was the native, from the
                            province of St Juan, on the north of Mendoza. B contains less water, and
                            therefore is probably heavier than common soda
                            alum.</p></note></p></cell></row></table><p>The word <hi rend="italic">alumen,</hi> which we translate <hi rend="italic">alum,</hi> occurs in Pliny’s <hi rend="italic">Natural History.</hi> In the
                    15th chapter of his 35th book, he gives us a detailed description of it By
                    comparing this with the account of <hi rend="italic">crmrr∣ζia</hi> given by
                    Dioscorides in the 123d chapter of his 5th book, it becomes quite obvious that
                    he alludes to the same substance. Hence it follows, that <hi rend="italic">ΰτυντηοια</hi> is the Greek name for <hi rend="italic">alumen.</hi> Pliny
                    informs us that alumen was found naturally in the earth. He calls it <hi rend="italic">salsugo</hi><hi rend="italic">terrae.</hi> Different substances,
                    he informs us, were distinguished by the name of alumen; but they were all
                    characterized by a certain degree of astringency, and were all employed in
                    dyeing and in medicine. The light-coloured alumen was useful in brilliant dyes,
                    the dark-coloured only in dyeing black or very dark colours. One species of
                    alumen was a liquid, which was apt∙to be adulterated; but, when pure, it had the
                    property of striking a black with the juice of the pomegranate. This property
                    seems to characterize a solution of sulphate of iron in water. It is quite
                    obvious that a solution of our alum would possess no such property. Pliny says
                    that there is another kind of alum which the Greeks call <hi rend="italic">schistos.</hi> It forms in white threads upon the surface of certain stones.
                    From the name <hi rend="italic">schistos,</hi> and the mode of formation, there
                    can be little doubt that this species was the salt which forms spontaneously on
                    certain slaty minerals, as alum slate and bituminous shale, and which consists
                    chiefly of sulphate of iron and sulphate of alumina. Possibly in certain places
                    the sulphate of iron may have been nearly wanting, and then the salt would be
                    white, and would answer, as Pliny says it did, for dyeing bright colours.
                    Several other speeies of alumen are described by Pliny, but we are unable to
                    make out towhat minerals he alludes.</p><p>The alumen of the ancients, then, was not the same with the alum of the moderns.
                    It was most commonly a sulphate of iron, sometimes probably a sulphate of
                    alumina, and usually a mixture of the two. But the ancients were unacquainted
                    with our alum. They were acquainted with sulphate of iron in a crystallized
                    state, and distinguished it by the names of <hi rend="italic">misy, sory,
                    chalcanthum. (JPliny,</hi> xxxiv. 12.) As alum and green vitriol were applied to
                    a variety of purposes in common, and as both are distinguished by a sweetish and
                    astringent taste, writers, even after the discovery of alum, do not seem to have
                    discriminated the two salts accurately from each other. In the writings, of the
                    alchemists we find the words <hi rend="italic">misy, sory, chalcanthum,</hi>
                    applied to alum as well as to sulphate of iron; and the name <hi rend="italic">atramentum sutorium,</hi> which ought to belong, one should suppose,
                    exclusively to green vitriol, applied indifferently to both.</p><p>When our alum was discovered is entirely unknown. Beckman devoted a good deal of
                    time to trace the history of this salt, and published a curious dissertation on
                    the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193037258" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7258-0573"/>subject; but his attempts to trace its origin were
                    unsuccessful. The manufacture of it was discovered in the East, but at what time
                    or place is totally unknown. It would appear that, about four or five hundred
                    years ago, there was a manufactory of it at Edessa in Syria, at that time called
                    Rocca; hence, it is supposed, the origin of the term <hi rend="italic">Roch</hi><hi rend="italic">alum,</hi> commonly employed in Europe: though there are
                    others who pretend that the term originated at Civita Vecchia, where alum is
                    made from a yellow mineral in the state of a hard rock.</p><p>Different alum works existed in the neighbourhood of Constantinople. About the
                    time of the fall of the Grecian empire, the art of making alum was transported
                    into Italy, at that period the richest and most manufacturing country in Europe.
                    Bartholomew Pernix, a Genoese merchant, discovered alum ore in the island of
                    Ischia, about the year 1459. Nearly at the same time John di Castro, who was
                    well acquainted with the alum works in the neighbourhood of Constantinople,
                    suspected that a mineral fit for yielding alum existed at Tolfa, because it was
                    covered with the same trees that grew on the alum mineral near Constantinople.
                    His conjecture was verified by trials, and the celebrated manufactory at Tolfa
                    established. Another was begun in the neighbourhood of Genoa; and the
                    manufacture flourished in different parts of Italy. To this country it was
                    confined for the greater part of a century. Various manufactories of it were
                    established in Germany by the year 1544. In the time of Agricoa there was a
                    manufactory of it at Commotau, in Bohemia. About the same time an alum work was
                    established at Alemaron, near Carthagena, in Spain.</p><p>England possessed no alum works till the reign of Charles I. Thomas Chaloner,
                    Esq. son of Dr Chaloner, who had been tutor to Charles, while hunting on a
                    common in Yorkshire took notice of the soil and herbage, and tasted the water.
                    He found them similar to what he had seen in Germany, where alum works were
                    established. In consequence of this, he got a patent from Charles for an alum
                    work. This manufactory was worth two thousand a year, or perhaps more. But some
                    of the courtiers thinking this too much for him, prevailed with the king,
                    notwithstanding the patent, to grant a moiety of it to another person. This was
                    the reason why Mr Cha-loner was such a partisan of the parliament, and such an
                    enemy of the king, that, at the end of the civil war, he was one of those who
                    sat in judgment upon his majesty and condemned him.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Letters written by Eminent
                    Persons in the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries,</hi> &amp;c.; <hi rend="italic">and Lives of Eminent Men,</hi> by John Aubrey, Esq. vol. ii∙ p.
                    281. Lond. 1813.</p></note> Since that time various alum works have been
                    established in different parts of England and Wales; but no one at present
                    exists in Britain except the Whitby works, originally established by Mr
                    Chaloner, and two works at Hurlet and Campsie, both in the neighbourhood of
                    Glasgow.</p><p>Several alum works likewise exist in Sweden, particularly in West Gothland. There
                    is one, for example, at Haensaeter, near the borders of the Wene Lake, on the
                    west side of the mountain called Kinnekulle. But, for a description of the
                    Swedish works, we refer to Bergman’s <hi rend="italic">Opuscula,</hi> vol. i. p.
                    284, or the English translation, vol. i. p. 342. We do not know if any alum
                    works exist in Poland or Russia; but as the greater part of these extensive
                    countries consists of alluvial soil to a great depth, it is probable that little
                    alum ore will be found in them.</p><p>Various minerals are employed in the manufacture of alum, but by far the most
                    important of them are the following three; <hi rend="italic">alum-stone,
                    alum-slate, bituminous shale.</hi></p><p>Alum-stone was first observed at Tolfa, in the neighbourhood of Rome; afterwards
                    in Hungary; and Cordier has shown that it is very common in volcanic rocks, but
                    that it never occurs anywhere else. <hi rend="italic">{Annales</hi><hi rend="italic">des Mines,</hi> tom. iv. p. 205, and tom. v. p. 303.)</p><p>The colour is white, greyish-white, or sometimes yellowish-white; most commonly
                    amorphous; but it occurs also crystallized in rhomboids approaching to cubes,
                    the angles being about 89° and 91°. In some crystals the apex of the rhomboid is
                    replaced by a tangent plane. The size of these crystals varies from 0∙03937 to
                    041811 of an inch in length.</p><p>The specific gravity is 2*7517; but the amorphous specimens, owing probably to
                    cavities, are rather lighter. Haüy states the specific gravity to be 2*587;
                    harder than calcareous, but softer than fluor, spar; fracture foliated in a
                    direction perpendicular to the axis of the rhomboid; in all other directions the
                    fracture is conchoidal; fragments irregular, with blunt edges; easily
                    pulverized; feels harsh, and does not stain; decrepitates before the blowpipe;
                    gives out sulphureous acid when heated on platinum-foil; and tastes of alum when
                    applied to the tongue. In a strong heat it loses its acid, and becomes
                    tasteless.</p><p>The constituents of the pure crystals, according to the analysis of Cordier,
                    are—-</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Sulphuric acid</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>35∙495</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Alumina</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>39∙654</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Potash</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>10∙02l</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Water and loss</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>14∙830</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>100.</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>This approaches very nearly to</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>3 atoms trisulphate<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"/> By <hi rend="italic">trisulphate of alumina</hi> is meant a compound of <hi rend="italic">three</hi> atoms of alumina and <hi rend="italic">one</hi> atom of
                            sulphuric acid. <hi rend="italic">Ter sulphate</hi> indicates <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> compound of three atoms of sulphuric acid and
                            one atom of base.</p></note> of alumina.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.. = 35∙25</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1 atom sulphate of potash</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>. - 11</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>7 atoms water</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>,. - 7∙875</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>54425</p></cell></row></table><p>We see from this constitution that alum-stone contains in itself all the
                    ingredients of alum. The absence of iron accounts for the superior purity for
                    which Roman alum was so long celebrated.</p><p>In the alum manufactory at Campsie, near Glasgow, the alum is made from a shale
                    taken out of the old abandoned coal-pits in the neighbourhood. At first this
                    shale furnished alum by simple lixiviation with water. This process having been
                    continued for a number of years, a great quantity of washed shale gradually
                    accumulated in the neighbourhood of the works. This shale, when burnt, was found
                    to yield a new crop of alum. Now, in this burnt shale thin bands of a
                    greyish-white matter occasionally make their appearance, intermixed with
                    portions having a yellow colour, and which are unequally distributed. The
                    fracture is earthy; the matter is opaque, friable, and has an astringent, acid,
                    and sweetish taste. The specific gravity is 1 ’ 887L</p><p>It occurred to the writer of this article, that this substance bore a
                    considerable analogy to <hi rend="italic">alum-stone.</hi> This induced him to
                    subject it to chemical examination.</p><p>When digested in water it dissolves, with the exception of a white powder,
                    amounting to 15*31 per cent, which is a subsulphate of alumina.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193037271" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7271-0574"/><p>When heated it melts sotnewhat like alum, and gives out ' pure water. WheiĻ
                    heated to redness it swells out like alum, and finally leaves a yellowish-white,
                    porous, tasteless matter, nearly similar to what would be left by alum treated
                    in the same manner, making allowance for the difference of colour.</p><p>The constituents were found to be—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>1. Insoluble portion, amounting to 15∙31 per
                            cent</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Alumina .</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.... 5∙11</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Sulphuric acid</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>....10∙20</p><p>15*31</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>2. Soluble portion, amounting to 84∙69</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>per cent.</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Sulphuric acid</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>...30*225</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Alumina .....∙∙.∙...... ∙∙</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>....5∙372</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Peroxide of iron</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>,....8∙530</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Potash</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>....1472</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Water.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>...36-295</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Loss, chiefly water</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>3∙096</p><p>84∙690</p></cell></row></table><p>These constituents are equivalent to</p><p>24 atoms sulphate of alumina,</p><p>9 atoms bipersulphate of iron,</p><p>1 atom bisulphate of potash; and each of these atoms is combined with about 5
                    atoms of water.</p><p>From this analysis we see that the substance which appears after burning the
                    Campsie shale is not the same with <hi rend="italic">alum-stone;</hi> but it
                    constitutes an excellent article for the manufacture of alum, being highly
                    productive; and is consequently much valued by the manufacturers.</p><p>Alum-slate is a much more abundant mineral thqn alum-stone. It is said to
                    alternate with primitive clayslate. It occurs abundantly along with
                    transition-slate; and there can be little doubt that it occurs likewise in the
                    floetz formations. In West Gothland in Sweden, it constitutes a part of
                    different hills, as Kinnekulle, Hunne-berg, and Halleberg; in all of which it
                    appears to alternate with floetz trap rocks. It occurs likewise abundantly at
                    Whitby, in Yorkshire. We have never ourselves been upon the spot ;· but, from
                    the general structure of Yorkshire and the neighbouring counties, indeed of the
                    whole east coast of England, there can be very little doubt that, in this
                    position, it is also a floetz rock.</p><p>Alum-slate, as the name implies, is a slaty rock, though sometimes it occurs in
                    balls. The colour is bluish-black, with a strong shade of grey; fracture
                    straight slaty; fragments tabular; its internal lustre is glimmering; it retains
                    its colour in the streak, but acquires more lustre; soft; not particularly
                    brittle; when exposed to the air it effloresces, and acquires an aluminous
                    taste.</p><p>This mineral has never been accurately analyzed; but there can be no doubt , that
                    it contains silica, alumina, iron, sulphur, charcoal, and often likewise potash.
                    Probably this was the mineral upon which the <hi rend="italic">alumen
                    scissile</hi> of the ancients was found.</p><p>Bituminous shale, the <hi rend="italic">Brandschiefer</hi> of the Germans, is a
                    slaty mineral, which almost constantly accompanies beds of coal, and accordingly
                    is very common in Great Britain. Its colour is brownish-black; its fracture is
                    thin slaty; fragments tabular; internal lustre glimmering, but the colour is not
                    altered; very soft; rather sectile; feels rather greasy; easily frangible. When
                    heated it burns with a pale flame and sulphureous odour, and becomes white. It
                    has never been accurately analyzed; but it is probably nothing more than
                    slate-clay, which occurs so abundantly in the independent coal formation '
                    impregnated with the matter of coal. Its other principal constituents must be
                    silica, alumina, and iron pyrites.</p><p>Slate-clay itself, at least not sufficiently impregnated with coaly matter to
                    deserve the name of bituminous shale, is frequently employed in the making of
                    alum. This is the case in the neighbourhood of Glasgow.</p><p>. Several native varieties of sulphate of alumina and soda alum occur in South
                    America, some of the most remarkable of which it may be proper to specify.</p><p>1. Sulphate .of alumina from Rio Saldana. It is said to occur in nests in the
                    transition-slate of the Andes. The colour is white, here and there tinged
                    yellow, obviously from external impurities. It occurs in fine crystalline
                    needles; lustre silky; taste that of alum, but stronger; specific gravity
                    1.6606; soft; before the blowpipe behaves like alum. The writer of this article
                    subjected it to a chemical analysis, and found its constituents as follows
                    :—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Water</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.46∙375</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Alumina</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.14∙645</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Peroxide of iron</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>...0∙500</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Soda</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>...2∙262</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Sulphuric acid</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.35∙872</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Mechanical impurity, consisting of</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>ferruginous silica</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>...0400</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>99∙754</p></cell></row></table><p>This is equivalent to</p><p>1 atom sulphate of alumina,</p><p>6 atoms water, ∙τ⅞θ atom sulphate of soda, ∙ <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> θ atom persulphate of iron.</p><p>So that if the sulphate of soda and persulphate of iron be only accidental
                    ingredients, the mineral is a compound of</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1 atom sulphate of alumina</p><p>6 atoms water .</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>- 7∙25 - 6∙75</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>14</p></cell></row></table><p>2. Polcura, or alum-earth, found near the summit of a lofty ridge near El Paso de
                    las Damas, in the Chilian Andes, and used as a mordant by the inhabitants in
                    dyeing red. This mineral was brought over to Great Britain by Dr Gillies, who
                    was kind enough to favour the writer of this article with a specimen. It occurs
                    in hard masses, partly earthy, partly fibrous. The fibres have a silky lustre.
                    The colour is white, and the taste that of alum.</p><p>When digested in water, a portion was dissolved, and a portion remained in the
                    form of a white insipid earth. The quantity of insoluble matter differed very
                    much in different parts of the specimen. The least was 8∙62, and the greatest
                    34∙65 per cent. This insoluble matter contained a little sulphur; for, when
                    heated, it emitted a blue flame with the smell of sulphureous acid. The rest of
                    it was a mixture of alumina and silica, tinged yellow by peroxide of iron. The
                    portion dissolved in water, being subjected to analysis, was found to consist
                    of</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1 atom disulphate<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>By <hi rend="italic">disulphate of alumina</hi> is
                            meant a compound of <hi rend="italic">one</hi> atom of sulphuric acid
                            and <hi rend="italic">two</hi> atoms of alumina.</p></note><hi rend="superscript"> l</hi> of alumina....</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>... - 9∙5</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1 atom sulphate of soda</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>... - 9</p><p>18∙5</p></cell></row></table><p>3. Soda-alum. It occurs native in the province of St .Tuan, situated to the north
                    of Mendoza, on the east side of the Chilian Andes, at about lat. 30° S. The alum
                    is white, and composed of fibres adhering longitudinally.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193037284" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7284-0575"/><p>and having a certain breadth, but very thin. It bears some resemblance to fibrous
                    gypsum, but is harder, not being scratched by the nail, though the knife
                    scratches it with great ease. It is sectile. The outer fibres are white and only
                    slightly translucent, as if they had lost a portion of their water; but the
                    internal fibres are transparent, and have a silky aspect.</p><p>It tastes precisely like alum, and is very soluble, water at the temperature of
                    62° dissolving 3∙773 parts of it, and boiling water dissolving any quantity
                    whatever. When exposed to heat, it behaves very nearly as common alum.</p><p>Its constituents were found to be—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Sulphuric acid</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>20-000</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Alumina</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>6∙360</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Soda</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>4∙000</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Silica</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙012</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Lime</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙136</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Protoxide of iron</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙423</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Peroxide of iron</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>0∙110</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Water .</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>22∙209</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>53∙250</p></cell></row></table><p>It will be observed that the sulphuric acid constitutes just four atoms, the soda
                    one atom, and the alumina just 0∙29 less than three atoms. But the quantity of
                    lime and oxides of iron present is exactly equivalent to 0*29 atom of alumina.
                    Hence these substances appear to have displaced a small∙quantity of alumina in
                    the salt. The water amounts to very nearly twenty atoms. It is obvious from all
                    this, that the true constitution of the salt is—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>3 atoms sulphate of alumina</p><p>1 atom sulphate of soda</p><p>20
                            atoms water</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>,. = 21∙75 .. - 9∙00 . - 22∙50</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>53∙25</p></cell></row></table><p>It contains five atoms less water than soda-alum artificially crystallized.</p><p>4. There is a mineral called <hi rend="italic">aluminite,</hi> which was observed
                    in the environs of Halle many years ago, and which was afterwards detected by Mr
                    Webster in the chalk rocks of Ncwhaven in Sussex, which, if it were sufficiently
                    abundant, would constitute an excellent material for the manufacture of
                    alum.</p><p>Its colour is snow-white. It occurs in reniform pieces of greater or smaller
                    size; fracture fine earthy; dull; streak glistening; opaque; adheres feebly to
                    the tongue; soils very slightly; very soft; feels fine, but meagre; specific
                    gravity 1∙7054. Its constituents, as determined by three several analyses of
                    Stromeycr, are—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1 atom sulphuric acid</p><p>3 atoms alumina</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>- 5 - 6∙75</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>9 atoms water</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>— 10-125</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>21∙875</p></cell></row></table><p>It is therefore a hydrous trisulphate of alumina.</p><p>Four different processes are employed in the manufacture of alum, according to
                    the nature of the mineral from which the alum is to be extracted.</p><p>The process employed at Tolfa is the simplest of all. If the Tolfa stone be kept
                    constantly moistened with water for about two months, it falls to powder of
                    itself, and yields alum by lixiviation. But this is not the process employed by
                    the manufacturers. The alum-stone is broken into small pieces, and piled on the
                    top of a perforated dome, in which a wood fire is kindled. The smoke and flame
                    of the wood penetrate through the pieces of alum-stone, and a sulphureous odour
                    is disengaged, owing to the decomposition of a portion of the sulphuric acid in
                    the stone. This roasting is twice performed; the pieces of ore which, the first
                    time, were at the edge of the dome, being the second time put in the middle. The
                    process of roasting this stone requires considerable attention. If the heat be
                    too great, the quality of yielding alum is destroyed: if the heat be too small,
                    the stone does not readily fall to powder. There can be little doubt that the
                    unroasted stone would yield more alum than the roasted; but probably the
                    additional labour requisite in the latter case would more than swallow up the
                    increase of product.</p><p>The roasted stone, which has now acquired a reddish colour, is placed in rows
                    between trenches filled with water. This liquid is so frequently sprinkled on
                    it, that the stone is always moist. In two or three days it falls to powder,
                    like slacked quicklime; but the daily watering is continued for a month. The
                    success of this part of the operation is said to depend very much on the
                    weather. When the weather is rainy, the alum is all washed out, and little or
                    nothing left for the manufacturer to extract. In such cases, it is obvious that
                    the alum-stone should be protected from the rain by a shed.</p><p>When the stone has by this process been reduced to a sufficiently fine powder, it
                    is thrown into a leaden boiler filled two thirds with water. During the boiling,
                    the powder is frequently stirred up, and the water that evaporates is replaced.
                    When the boiling has been continued for a sufficient time, the fire is
                    withdrawn, and time allowed for the earthy matter to subside to the bottom. A
                    cock is then opened, which allows the clear liquor to flow out into deep wooden
                    square vessels, so made that they can be easily taken to pieces. Here the alum
                    gradually crystallizes, and attaches itself to the sides and bottom of the
                    vessel. The mother liquid is now drawn off into shallower wooden troughs, where
                    more alum crystals are deposited. The liquid has now a red colour, and is muddy;
                    and the last alum crystals are mixed with this red matter. They are washed clean
                    in the mother liquor, which is finally pumped into a trough, and used in
                    subsequent processes.</p><p>The alum obtained at Tolfa is known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Roman
                    alum,</hi> and is in very high estimation. It is always mixed with a little
                    reddish powdery matter, which is easily separated from it. What this red matter
                    is, has not been ascertained; but it is not peroxide of iron. To the eye it has
                    very much the appearance of a vegetable matter. We have some notion that it is
                    added artificially by the sellers of Roman alum. Probably Roman alum at first
                    had a red tinge, in consequence of the red matter in the mother liquor remaining
                    partially attached to it. The goodness of the alum may have given the purchasers
                    a partiality to the red colour, and induced the sellers to add a red powder
                    artificially. We have never had an opportunity ourselves of examining this
                    matter, but have been informed by those who have, that it contains no iron.</p><p>It is not improbable that this process would be improved by grinding the Tolfa
                    stone to a fine powder in a mill, without any previous roasting, and then
                    keeping the powder moistened with water for a considerable time. It the residual
                    earth, after the alum is extracted, be boiled with sulphuric acid, the liquid
                    yields alum crystals by evaporation. This is a demonstration that neither the
                    alumina nor the potash is exhausted, and that the sulphuric acid driven off by
                    the roasting is so much alum lost to the manufacturer. Indeed the quantity of
                    sulphuric acid in the alum-stone is not sufficient to occupy the whole of the
                    potash in the formation of alum. It would be necessary to add about one tenth of
                    the weight of the alum-stone of sulphuric acid, if it were wanted to employ the
                    whole potash present in the stone. The consequence of this addition, supposing
                    no loss, would be an additional quantity<pb break="no" facs="nls:193037297" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7297-0576"/> of alum,
                    amounting to rather more than one fifth of the weight of the alum-stone
                    employed.</p><p>Alum-slate, being very different in its composition, requires a different
                    treatment to fit it for yielding alum. If the alum-slate contain a notable
                    quantity of lime or magnesia, it does not answer the purposes of the
                    manufacturer so well. ' Indeed the proportion of lime present may be conceived
                    to be such that no alum whatever would be obtained. As alum-slate has never been
                    subjected to accurate analysis, we do not know in what proportion these two
                    earths exist in it, or whether they may not, in many cases, be absent
                    altogether. The essential ingredients in alum-slate, for the alum-makers, are
                    alumina and iron pyrites.</p><p>The first process is to roast the ore. In Sweden, where the fuel is wood, and
                    consequently expensive, it is customary to use the alum-slate itself as fuel for
                    roasting the ore. For this purpose a small layer of brushwood is covered with
                    pieces of alum-slate, and set on fire; and, as the combustion proceeds, new
                    layers of alum-slate are added. It is usual to place alternate layers of roasted
                    and unroasted alum-slate. The combustion continues for a month or six weeks. At
                    Whitby, coal is employed for roasting the alum-slate. Indeed the alum-slate of
                    Whitby is lighter coloured than that of Sweden, and probably would not burn of
                    itself. So great is the quantity of combustible matter in the Swedish
                    alum-slate, that it is employed as fuel for burning limestone. Great quantities
                    of limestone are burnt in this manner at Hunneberg, near the south side of the
                    lake Wener. The roasted ore has usually a brown colour. When it is red, the
                    quantity of alum which it yields is considerably diminished.</p><p>By this roasting the pyrites is decomposed. The sulphur is converted into
                    sulphuric acid, while the iron is oxidized. In what manner this change is
                    produced it is not easy to say. Indeed it does not seem certain that pyrites is
                    a constant ingredient in alum-slate. We have never been able to detect any, by
                    the eye, in any specimens of Whitby alum-slate which we have examined. At
                    Haensaeter, in Sweden, no sulphate of iron crystallizes when the liquid is
                    evaporated; yet, if pyrites had been present, it is difficult to see any reason
                    that should prevent this salt from being formed. Hence it is probable, that in
                    alum-slate the sulphur is sometimes at least combined with other substances than
                    iron. It must always be in a state of combination; for, if it were in a loose
                    state, it would be driven off by the roasting. This point deserves to be
                    elucidated by analyzing different varieties of alum-slate.</p><p>The roasted ore has an astringent taste, owing to the sulphate of iron and
                    sulphate of alumina which it contains. The next process is to lixiviate it with
                    water, in order to dissolve these salts. For this purpose it is put into
                    reservoirs made of wood or masonry, with a stopcock at the bottom to draw off
                    the water. The usual method is to keep the water for twelve hours in contact
                    with ore that has been twice lixiviated; then to draw it off, and allow it to
                    remain for an equal period on ore that has been once lixiviated. Lastly, it is
                    run upon fresh ore, and allowed to remain on it for twelve hours longer. If the
                    specific gravity of the liquid thus treated be 1∙25 at the temperature of 55°,
                    it may be considered as saturated with sulphate of alumina and sulphate of iron.
                    But we presume that this specific gravity is not often obtained.</p><p>The liquid, thus impregnated with salt, is now boiled down in leaden vessels to
                    the proper consistency for crystallization. In Sweden, the fuel employed for
                    this purpose is alum-slate. By this means a double effect is produced; the
                    liquid is evaporated, and the alum-slate is roasted. During the boiling,
                    abundance of oxide of' iron falls mixed with selenite, if lime be one of the
                    constituents of the alum-slate. When the liquid is sufficiently concentrated, it
                    is let into a square reservoir, in order to crystallize. Great quantities of
                    sulphate of iron crystals are usually deposited in this vessel. These are
                    collected by drawing the liquid off into another reservoir. When all the
                    sulphate of iron that can be obtained has been separated, a quantity of sulphate
                    of potash, muriate of potash, or putrid urine, is mixed with the liquid. The
                    sulphate of potash is procured from the sulphuric acidmakers, and the muriate of
                    potash from the soap-makers. By this addition, alum is formed in the liquid, and
                    it gradually deposits itself in crystals on the sides of the vessel. These
                    crystals are collected, and dissolvedin the smallest quantity of boiling water
                    that will take them up. This solution is poured into large wooden casks. In a
                    fortnight or three weeks the alum crystallizes, and covers the side’s and bottom
                    of the cask. The hoops are now taken off, and the staves of the cask removed. A
                    mass of alum crystals, having the shape of the cask, remains. This mass is
                    pierced, the mother liquor allowed to run out, and preserved for a subsequent
                    process. The alum, being now broken in pieces, is fit for sale.</p><p>The manufacture of alum from bituminous shale and slate-clay bears a considerable
                    resemblance to the manufacture from alum-slate, but differs in several
                    particulars. There are two works of this kind in the neighbourhood of Glasgow,
                    managed with great skill, and excellent in every respect. We shall give a sketch
                    of the processes followed in these works. The bituminous shale and slate-clay
                    employed are obtained from old coal-pits, which are very extensive in the
                    neighbourhood of Glasgow. The air in these coal-pits is moist, and its average
                    temperature about 62°. The shale, having been exposed for many years, has
                    gradually opened in the direction of its slaty fracture, so as to resemble in
                    some respects a half-shut fan; and all the chinks in it are filled with a saline
                    efflorescence in threads. This salt is white, with a shade of green; has a
                    sweetish astringent taste; and consists of a mixture of sulphate of iron and
                    sulphate of alumina. In order to obtain these salts in a state of solution,’
                    nothing more is requisite than to lixiviate this shale with water. The
                    lixiviated ore being left exposed to the weather, forms more salt, which is
                    gradually washed out of it by the rain-water, and this water is collected and
                    preserved for use.</p><p>The next step in the process is to boil down the liquid to a sufficient state of
                    concentration. At Campsie, all these boilers are composed of stone, and the heat
                    is applied to the surface. This is a great saving, as leaden vessels are not
                    only much more expensive, but require more frequent renewal. When the liquid is
                    raised to a sufficiently high temperature in the stone reservoir, pounded
                    sulphate of potash, or muriate of potash, as they can be procured, is mixed with
                    it; and there is an agitator in the vessel, by which it is continually stirred
                    about. This addition converts the sulphate of alumina into alum. The liquid is
                    now let into another trough, and allowed to remain till it crystallizes. In this
                    liquid there are two salts contained in solution, viz. sulphate of iron and
                    alum; and it is an object of great consequence to separate them completely from
                    each other. The principal secret consists in drawing off the mother liquor at
                    the proper time; for the alum is much less soluble in water than the sulphate of
                    iron, and therefore crystallizes first. The first crystals of alum formed are
                    very impure. They have a yellow colour, and seem to be partly impregnated with
                    <pb break="no" facs="nls:193037310" xml:id="kp-eb0702-7310-0577"/>
                    sulphate of iron. They are dissolved in hot water, and the solution poured into
                    troughs, and allowed to crystallize a second time. These second crystals, though
                    much purer, are not quite free from sulphate of iron; but the separation is
                    accomplished by washing them repeatedly with cold water; for sulphate of iron is
                    much more soluble in that liquid than alum. These second crystals are now
                    dissolved in as small a quantity of hot water as possible, and the concentrated
                    liquid poured while hot into large casks, the surface of which is covered with
                    two cross beams. As the liquor cools, a vast number of alum crystals form on the
                    sides and surface. The casks are allowed to remain till the liquid within is
                    supposed to be nearly of the temperature of the atmosphere. This, in winter,
                    requires eleven days; in summer, fourteen or more. We have seen the liquid in a
                    cask that had stood eleven days in summer, still more than blood-hot. The hoops
                    are then removed, precisely as in the manufacture of alum from alum-slate.</p><p>There always remains in the boilers a yellowish substance, consisting chiefly of
                    peroxide of iron. This is exposed to a strong heat in a reverberatory furnace,
                    and it becomes red. In this state it is washed, and yields more alum. The red
                    residue is ground to a fine powder, and dried. It then answers all the purposes
                    of Venetian red as a pigment. By altering the temperature to which this matter
                    is exposed, a yellow ochre is obtained instead of a red.</p><p>In France, where alum-ores are by no means abundant, alum is manufactured from
                    clay. This method of making the salt was first put in practice by Chaptal, when
                    professor of chemistry at Montpellier. His methods have been since gradually
                    improved, and brought to a state of considerable perfection. The first process
                    tried was this: the clay was reduced to a fine powder in a mill, and then mixed
                    with sulphuric acid. After remaining some days, it was exposed for twenty-four
                    hours to a temperature of about 130°. It was then lixiviated, and the liquid
                    mixed with urine or potash. This method being found inconvenient, was abandoned
                    for the following: the clay being well ground, was mixed with half its weight of
                    the saline residue from a mixture of sulphur and nitre. This residue is little
                    else than sulphate of potash. The mixture was formed into balls about five
                    inches in diameter, which were calcined in a potter’s furnace. They were then
                    placed on the floor of a chamber in which sulphuric acid was made. The acid
                    vapour caused them to swell, and to open on all sides. In about a month they
                    were sufficiently penetrated with the acid. They were then exposed to the air,
                    under shades, that the saturation might become more complete. Finally, they were
                    lixiviated, and the liquid being evaporated, yielded pure alum.</p><p>This process has been considerably improved by Berard, the present proprietor of
                    the Montpellier alum work. Instead of exposing the calcined balls to the fumes
                    of sulphuric acid, he sprinkles them with a quantity of sulphuric acid of the
                    specific gravity 1∙367, equal to the weight of the clay employed: but it is
                    obvious that the proportion must vary with the nature of the clay. The solution
                    takes place with the greatest facility, and crystals of alum are obtained by
                    evaporating the liquid.</p><p>Another process was put in practice by Chaptal, in the neighbourhood of Paris,
                    and is still followed, or was at least followed some years ago, by Μ. Bouvier. A
                    mixture is made of 100 parts of clay, 50 parts of nitre, and 50 parts of
                    sulphuric acid of the specific gravity 1∙367; and this mixture is put into a
                    retort, and distilled. Aquafortis comes over, and the residue in the retort
                    being lixiviated with water, yields abundance of excellent alum.</p><p>We may mention another process described by Caraudau, and certainly practicable,
                    and even easy, though we do not believe that it would be attended with profit?
                    He forms 100 parts of clay into a paste with water, holding 5 parts of common
                    salt in solution. This paste is formed into cakes, and calcined in a
                    reverberatory furnace. The calcined mass is reduced to powder, and well mixed
                    with the fourth part of its weight of concentrated sulphuric acid. When the
                    muriatic acid vapours are dissipated, as much water is added as there had been
                    employed of acid, and the mass is carefully kneaded. A strong heat is produced;
                    the composition swells; more water is added; and at last a solution of potash,
                    in which the alkali amounts to one fourth of the acid employed. The liquor is
                    now drawn off, and, on cooling, it yields a copious deposite of alum crystals.
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(l.)</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>