<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0702-8623-0678-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">ANABAPTISTS</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 678</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35664">Baptism</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dp5n">Communion</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rj14">Anabaptists</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:827229">Baptism</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:987598">Kindness</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:827285">Baptists</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:808176">Anabaptists</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:896825">Donatists</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193038623" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">ANABAPTISTS</label>, a name which has been indiscriminately
                    applied to Christians of very different principles and practices, though many of
                    them object to the denomination, and hold nothing in common besides the opinion,
                    that baptism ought always to be performed by immersion, and not administered
                    before the age of discretion.</p><p>The word Anabaptist is compounded of <hi rend="italic">ανα, new,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">βaπ</hi><hi rend="italic">τιστ</hi><hi rend="italic">ης, a
                    baptist;</hi> and in this sense the Nova-tians, the Cataphrygians, and the
                    Donatists, may be considered as a kind of Anabaptists in the earlier ages,
                    though not then denoted by this name; for they contended that those Christians
                    of the Catholic church who joined themselves to their respective parties should
                    be rebaptized. But we must not class under the same denomination those bishops
                    of Asia and Africa who, in the third century, maintained that baptism
                    administered by those whom they called heretics was not valid, and therefore
                    that such of them as returned into their churches ought to be rebaptized. Nor do
                    the English and Dutch Baptists consider the denomination as at all applicable to
                    their sect, by whom the baptism appointed by Christ is held to be “nothing short
                    of <hi rend="italic">immersion upon a personal profession of faith;”</hi> of
                    which profession infants being incapable, and sprinkling being no adequate
                    symbol of the thing included, the baptizing of proselytes to their communion,
                    who in their infancy had undergone the ceremony of sprinkling, cannot, it is
                    urged, be interpreted a repetition of the baptismal ordinance.</p><p>Anabaptists, in a strict and proper sense, appear to be those who not only
                    rebaptize, when they arrive at an adult age, persons that were baptized in their
                    infancy, but also, as often as any person comes from one of their sects to
                    another, or as often as any one is excluded from their communion and again
                    received into the bosom of the church, they baptize him. And such were many of
                    the German Baptists. But the single opinion common to all the sects to which the
                    name of <hi rend="italic">Anabaptists</hi> has been indiscriminately applied, is
                    that of the invalidity of <hi rend="italic">infant baptism,</hi> in whatever way
                    administered; and hence the general denomination of <hi rend="italic">Antipcedobaptists,</hi> which included Anabaptists, Baptists, Mennonites,
                    Waterlandians, &amp;c., as distinguished by their respective peculiarities;
                    though <hi rend="italic">Anabaptists</hi> seems to have been adopted by most
                    writers as the general term.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193038636" xml:id="kp-eb0702-8636-0679"/><p>To the above peculiar notion concerning the baptismal sacrament, the Anabaptists
                    added principles of a different nature, depending upon certain ideas which they
                    entertained concerning a perfect church establishment, pure in its members, and
                    free from the institutions of human policy·</p><p>The Anabaptists appear to have made little noise, or to have been little noticed,
                    before the time of the reformation in Germany. The most prudent and rational
                    part of them considered it possible, by human wisdom, industry, and vigilance,
                    to purify the church from the contagion of the wicked, provided the manners and
                    spirit of the primitive Christians could but recover their lost dignity and
                    lustre; and seeing the attempts of Luther, seconded by several persons of
                    eminent piety, prove so successful, they hoped that the happy period was arrived
                    in which the restoration of the church to purity was to be accomplished, under
                    the divine protection, by the labours and counsels of pious and eminent men.
                    Others, far from being satisfied with the plan of reformation proposed by
                    Luther, looked upon it as much beneath the sublimity of their views, and
                    consequently undertook a more perfect reformation, or, to express more properly
                    their visionary enterprise, they proposed to found a new church, entirely
                    spiritual, and truly divine.</p><p>This sect was soon joined by great numbers, and (as usually happens in sudden
                    revolutions of this nature) by many persons whose characters and capacities were
                    very different, though their views seemed to turn upon the same object. Their
                    progress was rapid; for, in a very short space of time, their discourses,
                    visions, and predictions, excited commotions in a great part of Europe, and drew
                    into their communion a prodigious multitude, whose ignorance rendered them easy
                    victims to the illusions of enthusiasm. The most pernicious faction of all those
                    which composed this motley multitude, was that which pretended that the founders
                    of the new and <hi rend="italic">perfect church</hi> already mentioned were
                    under the direction of a divine impulse, and were armed against all opposition
                    by the power of working miracles. It was this faction that, in the year 1521,
                    began their fanatical work, under the guidance of Munzer, Stubner, Storck,
                    &amp;c.</p><p>These persons were disciples of Luther; but well knowing that their opinions were
                    such as would receive no sanction from him, they availed themselves of his
                    absence to disseminate them in Wittenburg, and had the address to overreach the
                    piety of Melanchthon. Their principal purpose was to gain over the populace, and
                    to form a considerable party. To effect this, says Bayle, they were industrious
                    and active, each in his own way. Storck, wanting knowledge, boasted of
                    inspiration; and Stubner, who had both genius and erudition, laboured at
                    commodious explications of Scripture. Not content with discrediting the court of
                    Rome, and decrying the authority of consistories, they taught, that among
                    Christians, who had the precepts of the gospel to direct, and the Spirit of God
                    to guide them, the office of magistracy was not only unnecessary, but an
                    unlawful encroachment on their spiritual liberty; that the distinctions
                    occasioned by birth, or rank, or wealth, being contrary to the spirit of the
                    gospel, which considers all men as equal, should be entirely abolished; that all
                    Christians, throwing their possessions into one common stock, should live
                    together in that state of equality which becomes members of the same family;
                    that as neither the laws of nature nor the precepts of the New Testament had
                    placed any restraint upon men with regard to the number of wives which they
                    might marry, they should use that liberty which God himself had granted to the,
                    patriarchs.</p><p>They employed at first the various arts of persuasion in order to propagate their
                    doctrine. They preached, exhorted, admonished, and reasoned, in a manner that
                    seemed proper to impress· the multitude; and related a great number of visions
                    and revelations with which they pretended to have been favoured from above. But
                    when they saw that these methods of making proselytes were not attended with
                    such rapid success as they fondly expected, and that the ministry of Luther and
                    other eminent reformers was detrimental to their cause, they then had recourse
                    to more expeditious measures, and madly attempted to propagate their fanatical
                    doctrine by force of arms. Munzer and his associates, in the year 1525&gt; put
                    themselves at the head of a numerous army, composed for the most part of the
                    peasants of Suabia, Thuringia, Franconia, and Saxony; and declared war against
                    all laws,, government, and magistrates of every kind, under the chimerical
                    pretext that Christ was now to take the reins of civil and ecclesiastical
                    government into his own hands, and to rule alone over the nations. But this
                    seditious crowd was routed and dispersed without much difficulty by the elector
                    of Saxony and other princes; and Munzer, their ringleader, ignominiously put to
                    death, and his factious counsellors scattered abroad in different places.</p><p>Many of his followers, however, survived and propagated their opinions through
                    Germany, Switzerland, and Holland. In the year 1533 a party of them settled at
                    Munster under the direction of two Anabaptist prophets, John Matthias, a baker
                    of Haerlem, and John Bockholdt, a journeyman tailor of Leyden. Having made
                    themselves masters of the city, they deposed the magistrates, confiscated the
                    estates of such as had escaped, and deposited the wealth they amassed together
                    in a public treasury for common use. They made preparations of every kind for
                    the defence of the city; and sent out emissaries to the Anabaptists in the Low
                    Countries, inviting them to assemble at Munster, which was now dignified with
                    the name of Mount Sion, that from hence they might be deputed to reduce all the
                    nations of the earth under their dominion. Matthias, who was the first in
                    command, was soon cut off, in an act of frenzy, by the bishop of Munster’s,
                    army, and was succeeded by Bocklioldt, who was proclaimed, by a special
                    designation of Heaven, as he pretended, king of Sion, and invested with
                    legislative powers like those of Moses. The extravagancies of Bocklioldt were
                    too numerous to be recited: it will be sufficient to add, that the city of
                    Munster was taken after a long siege and an obstinate resistance; and Bockholdt,
                    the mock monarch,, was punished with a most painful and ignominious death.</p><p>It must, however, be acknowledged, that the true rise, of the numerous
                    insurrections of this period ought not to be attributed to religious opinions.
                    The first insurgents groaned under the most grievous oppressions—they took up
                    arms principally in defence of their civil liberties; and of the commotions that
                    took place, the Anabaptist leaders above mentioned seem rather to have availed
                    themselves,, than to have been the prime movers. That a great part of the main
                    body, indeed, consisted of Anabaptists, seems· indisputable; and whatever
                    fanaticism existed among them would naturally be called forth or inflamed by
                    particular situations or circumstances, and run riot in its wildest; shapes. At
                    the same time it appears from history, that a. great part also consisted of
                    Roman Catholics, and a still greater of persons who had scarcely any religious
                    principles at all. Indeed, when we read of the vast numbers that were concerned
                    in those insurrections, of whom it is≈ reported that 100,000 fell by the sword,
                    it appears reasonable to conclude that a great majority of them were not
                    Anabaptists.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193038649" xml:id="kp-eb0702-8649-0680"/><p>Before concluding this article, it must be remarked, that the Baptists or
                    Mennonites in England and Holland are to be considered in a very different light
                    from the enthusiasts we have been describing; and it appears equally uncandid
                    and invidious to trace up their distinguishing tenet, as some of their
                    adversaries have done, to those obnoxious characters, and there to stop, in
                    order as it were to associate with it the ideas of turbulence and fanaticism,
                    with which it certainly has no natural connection. Their coincidence with some
                    of those oppressed and infatuated people in denying baptism to infants, is
                    acknowledged by the Baptists; but they disavow the practice which the
                    appellation of <hi rend="italic">Anabaptists</hi> implies, and their doctrines
                    seem referable to a more ancient and respectable origin. They appear supported
                    by history in considering themselves as the descendants of the Waldenses, who
                    were so grievously oppressed and persecuted by the despotic heads of the Roman
                    hierarchy; and they profess an equal aversion to all principles of rebellion on
                    the one hand, and to all suggestions of fanaticism on the other.</p></div></body></text></TEI>