<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-6556-0519-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALLEGIANCE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 519</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="20" ref="fasttopic:1042646">Oaths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:899352">Dues</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1079619">Protectionism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198492">Faith</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1026097">Moralities</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1026093">Morale</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="20" ref="lcsh1910:b4f47h15q">Oaths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4f766g40">Sovereigns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f8z">Faith</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20m3b">Moralities</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40k55d">Morals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193036556" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALLEGIANCE</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> is the
                    tie, or <hi rend="italic">ligamen,</hi> which binds the subject to the king, in
                    return for that protection which the king affords the subject. The thing itself,
                    or substantial part of it, is founded in reason and the nature of government:
                    the name and the form are derived to us from our Gothic ancestors. Under the
                    feudal system, every owner of lands held them in subjection to some superior or
                    lord, from whom or from whose ancestors the tenant or vassal had received them;
                    and there was a mutual trust or confidence subsisting between the lord and
                    vassal, that the lord should protect the vassal in the enjoyment of the
                    territory he had granted him; and, on the other hand, that the vassal should be
                    faithful to the lord, and defend him against all his enemies. This obligation on
                    the part of the vassal was called his <hi rend="italic">fidelitas</hi> or
                    fealty: and an oath of fealty was required by the feudal law to be taken by all
                    tenants to their landlord, which is couched in almost the same terms as our
                    ancient oath of allegiance; except that in the usual oath of fealty there was
                    frequently a saving or exception of the faith due to a superior lord by name,
                    under whom the landlord himself was perhaps only a tenant or vassal. But when
                    the acknowledgement was made to the absolute superior himself, who was vassal to
                    no man, it was no longer called the oath of fealty, but the oath of allegiance;
                    and therein the tenant swore to bear faith to his sovereign lord, in opposition
                    to all men, without any saving or exception. Land held by this exalted species
                    of fealty was called <hi rend="italic">feudurn legium,</hi> a liege fee; the
                    vassals, <hi rend="italic">homines legii,</hi> or liege men; and the <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193036569" xml:id="kp-eb0702-6569-0520"/> sovereign, their
                    <hi rend="italic">dominus</hi><hi rend="italic">legius,</hi> or liege lord. And
                    when sovereign princes did homage to each other for lands held under their
                    respective sovereignties, a distinction was always made between <hi
                    rend="italic">simple</hi> homage, which was only an acknowledgement of tenure,
                    and <hi rend="italic">liege</hi> homage, which included the fealty before
                    mentioned, and the services consequent upon it. In Britain, it becoming a
                    settled principle of tenure that all lands in the kingdom are holden of the king
                    as their sovereign and lord paramount, no oath but that of fealty could ever be
                    taken to inferior lords; and the oath of allegiance was necessarily confined to
                    the person of the king alone. By an easy analogy, the term of <hi rend="italic"
                    >allegiance</hi> was soon brought to signify all other engagements which are due
                    from subjects to their prince, as well as those duties which were simply and
                    merely territorial. And the oath of allegiance, as administered in England for
                    upwards of 600 years, contained a promise “ to be true and faithful to the king
                    and his heirs, and truth and faith to bear of life and limb and terrene honour,
                    and not to know or hear of any ill or damage intended him, without defending him
                    therefrom.” But, at the Revolution, the terms of this oath being thought perhaps
                    to savour too much of the notion of non-resistance, the present form was
                    introduced by the convention parliament; which is more general and indeterminate
                    than the former, the subject only promising “that he will be faithful and bear
                    <hi rend="italic">true</hi> allegiance to the king,” without mentioning “his
                    heirs,” or specifying in the least wherein that allegiance consists. The oath of
                    supremacy is principally calculated as a renunciation of the pope’s pretended
                    authority; and the oath of abjuration, introduced in the reign of King William,
                    very amply supplies the loose and general texture of the oath of allegiance; it
                    recognising the right of his majesty, derived under the act of settlement
                    engaging to support him to the utmost of the juror’s power, promising to
                    disclose all traitorous conspiracies against him, and expressly renouncing any
                    claim on the descendants of the late Pretender, in as clear and explicit terms
                    as the English language can furnish. This oath must be taken by all persons in
                    any office, trust, or employment, and may be tendered by two justices of the
                    peace to any person whom they shall suspect of disaffection; and the oath of
                    allegiance may be tendered to all persons above the age of twelve years, whether
                    natives, denizens, or aliens.</p>
                <p>But, besides these express engagements, the law also holds that there is an <hi
                    rend="italic">implied, original,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">virtual</hi>
                    allegiance, owing from every subject to his sovereign, antecedently to any
                    express promise, and although the subject never swore any faith or allegiance in
                    form. Thus, Sir Edward Coke very justly observes that “all subjects are equally
                    bounden to their allegiance as if they had taken the oath, because it is written
                    by the finger of the law in their hearts, and the taking of the corporal oath is
                    but an outward declaration of the same.”</p>
                <p>Allegiance, both express and implied, is, however, distinguished by the law into
                    two sorts or species, the one <hi rend="italic">natural,</hi> the other <hi
                    rend="italic">local;</hi> the former being also perpetual, the latter
                    temporary.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Natural</hi> allegiance is such as is due from all men born
                    within the king s dominions immediately upon their birth; for immediately upon
                    their birth they are under the king’s protection, at a time, too, when (during
                    their infancy) they arc incapable of protecting themselves. Natural allegiance
                    is, therefore, a debt of gratitude, which cannot be forfeited, cancelled, or
                    altered, by any change of time, place, or circumstance, nor by any thing but the
                    united concurrence of the legislature. A Briton who removes <hi rend="italic"
                    >to</hi> France or to China, owes the same allegiance to the king of Britain
                    there as at home, and 20 years hence as well as now; for it is a principle of
                    universal law, that the natural-born subject of one prince cannot by any act of
                    his own, no, not by swearing allegiance to another, put off or discharge his
                    natural allegiance to the former; for this natural allegiance was intrinsic and
                    primitive, and antecedent to the other, and cannot be divested without the
                    concurrent act of that prince to whom it was first due.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Local</hi> allegiance is such as is due from an alien, or
                    stranger born, for so long å time as he continues within the king’s dominion and
                    protection; and.it ceases the instant such stranger transfers himself from this
                    kingdom to another. Natural allegiance is, therefore, <hi rend="italic"
                    >perpetual,</hi> and local <hi rend="italic">temporary</hi> only; and that for
                    this reason, evidently founded upon the nature of government, that allegiance is
                    a debt due from the subject, upon an implied contract with the prince; that so
                    long as the one affords protection, so long the other will demean himself
                    faithfully.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">oath</hi> of allegiance, or rather the <hi rend="italic"
                    >allegiance</hi> itself, is held to be applicable, not only to the political
                    capacity of the king, or regal office, but to his natural person and blood
                    royal. And, for the misapplication of their allegiance, viz. to the regal
                    capacity or crown, exclusive of the person of the king, were the Spencers
                    banished in the reign of Edward II. And hence arose that principle of personal
                    attachment and affectionate loyalty which induced our forefathers (and, if
                    occasion required, would doubtless induce their sons) to hazard all that was
                    dear to them, life, fortune, and family, in defence and support of their liege
                    lord and sovereign.</p>
                <p>It is to be observed, however, in explanation of this allegiance, that it does
                    not preclude resistance to the king, when his misconduct or weakness is such as
                    to make resistance beneficial to the community. It seems fairly presumable, that
                    the convention parliament, which introduced the oath of allegiance in its
                    present form, did not intend to exclude all resistance; since the very authority
                    by which the members sat together was itself the effect of a successful
                    opposition to an acknowledged sovereign.</p>
                <p>Again, the allegiance above described can only be understood to signify obedience
                    to lawful commands. If, therefore, the king should issue a proclamation, levying
                    money or imposing any service or restraint upon the subject beyond what the law
                    authorized, there would exist no sort of obligation to obey such a proclamation
                    in consequence of having taken the oath of allegiance.</p>
                <p>Neither can allegiance be supposed to extend to the king after he is actually and
                    absolutely deposed, driven into exile, or otherwise rendered incapable, of
                    exercising the regal office. The promise of allegiance implies, that the person
                    to whom the promise is made continues king; that is, continues to exercise the
                    power and afford the protection which belong to the office of king; for it is
                    the possession of these which makes such a particular person the object of the
                    oath. See Blackstone’s <hi rend="italic">Commentaries,^</hi> Paley’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Moral and Political Philosophy.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
