<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-5243-0418-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALFRED, or Aelfred</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 418</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="19" ref="fasttopic:887617">Danes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1116439">Ships</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193035243" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALFRED, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Aelfred</hi></label>, the
                    Great, king of England, was the fifth and youngest son of Aethelwolf, king of
                    the West Saxons, and was born at Wantage, in Berkshire, in 849. He distinguished
                    himself, during the reign of his brother Ethelred, in several engagements
                    against the Danes, and upon his death succeeded to the crown, in the year 871,
                    and the 22d of his age. At his ascending the throne he found himself involved in
                    a dangerous war with the Danes, and placed in such circumstances of distress as
                    called for the greatest valour, resolution, and all the other virtues with which
                    he was adorned. The Danes had already penetrated into the heart of his kingdom;
                    and before he had been a month upon the throne, he was obliged to take the field
                    against those formidable enemies. After many battles gained on both sides, he
                    was at length reduced to the greatest distress, and was entirely abandoned by
                    his subjects. In this situation Alfred, conceiving himself no longer a king,
                    laid aside all marks of royalty, and took shelter in the house of one who kept
                    his cattle. He retired afterwards to the isle of Aethelingey, in Somersetshire,
                    where he built a fort for the security of himself, his family, and the few
                    faithful servants who repaired thither to him. When he had been about a year in
                    this retreat, having been informed that some of his subjects had routed a great
                    army of the Danes, killed their chief, and taken their magical standard,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“This,” says Sir John
                    Spelman, “was a banner, with the image of a raven magically wrought by the three
                    sisters of Hi∏guar and Hubba, on purpose for their expedition, in revenge of
                    their father Lodebroch’s murder; made, they say, almost in an instant, being by
                    them at once begun and finished in a noontide, and believed by the Danes to have
                    carried great fatality with it, for which it was highly esteemed by them. It is
                    pretended, that being carried in a battle, towards good success it would always
                    seem to clap its wings, and make as if it would fly; but towards the approach of
                    mishap, it would hang down and not move.” <hi rend="italic">{LΛfe of
                    Alfred,</hi> p∙ 61∙)</p></note> he issued his letters, giving notice where he
                    was, and inviting his nobility to come and consult with him. Before they came to
                    a final determination, Alfred, putting on the habit of a harper, went into the
                    enemy’s camp, where, without suspicion, he was everywhere admitted, and had the
                    honour to play before their princes. Having thereby acquired an exact knowledge
                    of their situation, he returned in great secrecy to his nobility, whom he
                    ordered to their respective homes, there to draw together each man as great a
                    force as he could; and upon a day appointed there was to be a general rendezvous
                    at the great wood called <hi rend="italic">Selwood,</hi> in Wiltshire. This
                    affair was transacted so secretly and expeditiously, that, in a little time, the
                    king, at the head of an army, approached the Danes, before they had the least
                    intelligence of his design. Alfred, taking advantage of the surprise and terror
                    they were in, fell upon them, and totally defeated them at Aethendune, now
                    Eddington. Those who escaped fled to a neighbouring castle, where they were soon
                    besieged, and obliged to surrender at discretion. Alfred granted them better
                    terms than they could expect. He agreed to give up the whole kingdom of the East
                    Angles to such as would embrace the Christian religion, on condition that they
                    would oblige the rest of their countrymen to quit the island, and, as much as
                    was in their power, prevent the landing of any more foreigners. For the
                    performance thereof he took hostages; and when in pursuance of the treaty,
                    Guthrum the Danish captain came, with thirty of his chief officers, to be
                    baptized, Alfred answered for him at the font, and gave him the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">Aethelstane</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and certain laws were
                    drawn up betwixt the king and Guthrum for the regulation and government of the
                    Danes settled in England. In 884 a fresh number of Danes landed in Kent and laid
                    siege to Rochester· but the king coming to the relief of that city, they were
                    obliged to abandon their design. Alfred had now great success, which was chiefly
                    owing to his fleet, an advantage of his own creating. Having secured the
                    sea-coasts, he fortified the rest of the kingdom with castles and walled towns;
                    and he besieged and recovered from the Danes the city of London, which he
                    resolved to repair, and to keep as a frontier.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The Danes had possessed themselves of London
                    in the time of his father, and had held it till now as a convenient place for
                    them to land at, and fortify themselves in; neither was it taken from them but
                    by a close siege. However, when it came into the kings hands, it was in a
                    miserable condition, scarcely habitable, and all its fortifications ruined. The
                    king, moved by the importance of the place, and the desire of strengthening his
                    frontier against the Danes, restored it to its ancient splendour. And observing,
                    that through the confusion of the times, many, both Saxons and Danes, lived in a
                    loose, disorderly manner, without owning any government, he offered them now a
                    comfortable establishment, if they would submit and become his subjects. This
                    proposition was better received than he expected; for multitudes, growing weary
                    of a vagabond kind of life, joyfully accepted such an offer. (CΛzw. <hi
                    rend="italic">Sax.</hi> p. 88.)</p></note></p>
                <p>After some years’ respite, Alfred was again called into the field; for a body of
                    Danes, being worsted in the west of France, came with a fleet of 250 sail on the
                    coast of Kent, and having landed, fixed themselves at Appletree. Shortly after,
                    another fleet of eighty vessels coming up the Thames, the men landed, and built
                    a fort at Middleton. Before Alfred marched against the enemy, he obliged the
                    Danes settled in Northumberland and Essex to give him hostages for their good
                    behaviour. He then moved towards the invaders, and pitched his camp between
                    their armies, to prevent their junction. A great body, however, moved off to
                    Essex, and, crossing the river, came to Farnham in Surrey, where they were
                    defeated by the king’s forces. Meanwhile the Danes settled in Northumberland, in
                    breach of treaty, and notwithstanding the hostages given, equipped two fleets,
                    and, after plundering the northern and southern coasts, sailed to Exeter and
                    besieged it. The king, as soon as he received intelligence, marched against
                    them; but before he reached Exeter they had got possession of it. He kept them,
                    however, blocked up on all sides, and reduced them at last to such extremities,
                    that they were obliged to eat their horses, and were even ready to devour each
                    ether. Being at length rendered desperate, they made a general sally on the
                    besiegers; but were defeated, though with great loss on the king’s side. The
                    remainder of this body of Danes fled into Essex, to the fort they had built
                    there, and to their ships. Before Alfred had time to recruit himself, another
                    Danish leader, whose name was Laf, came with a great army out of Northumberland,
                    and destroyed all before him, marching on to the city of Werheal in the west,
                    which is supposed to be Chester, where they remained the rest of that year. The
                    year following they invaded North Wales; and after having plundered and
                    destroyed every thing, they divided, one body returning to Northumberland,
                    another into the territories of the East Angles, from whence they proceeded to
                    Essex, and took possession of a small island called <hi rend="italic"
                    >AIeresig.</hi> Here they did not <pb break="no" facs="nls:193035256"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0702-5256-0419"/>long remain; for having separated, some sailed up
                    the 'river Thames, and others up the Lea road, where, drawing up their ships,
                    they built a fort not far from London, which proved a great check upon the
                    citizens, who went in a body and attacked it, but were repulsed with great loss.
                    At harvest-time the king himself was obliged to encamp with a body of troops in
                    the neighbourhood of the city, in order to cover the reapers from the excursions
                    of the Danes. As he was one day riding by the side of the river Lea, after some
                    observations he began to think that the Danish ships might be laid quite dry:
                    this he attempted, and having succeeded, the Danes were forced to desert their
                    fort and ships, and march away to the banks of the Severn where they built a
                    fort, and wintered at a place called <hi rend="italic">Quatbrig.</hi><note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The king’s contrivance is
                    thought to have produced the meadow between Hertford and Bow; for at Hertford
                    was the Danish tort, and from thence they made frequent excursions on the
                    inhabitants of London. Authors are not agreed as to the method the mg pursued in
                    laying dry the Danish ships. Dugdale supposes that he did it by straightening
                    the channels; but Henry of Huntingdon alleges that he cut several canals, which
                    exhausted its water.</p></note> Such of the Danish ships as could be got off,
                    the Londoners carried into their own road; the rest they burned and
                    destroyed.</p>
                <p>Alfred enjoyed a profound peace during the last three years of his reign, which
                    he chiefly employed in establishing and regulating his government, for the
                    security of himself and his successors, as well as the ease and benefit of his
                    subjects in general. After a troublesome reign of 28 years, he died on the 28th
                    of October <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d.</hi> 900, and was buried at Winchester, in
                    Hyde-abbey, under a monument of porphyry.</p>
                <p>All our historians agree in distinguishing him as one of the most valiant,
                    wisest, and best of kings that ever reigned in England; and it is also generally
                    allowed, that he not only digested several particular laws still in being, but
                    that he laid the first foundation of our present happy constitution. There is
                    great reason to believe that we are indebted to this prince for trials by
                    juries; and the Doomsday Book, which is preserved in the Exchequer, is thought
                    to be no more than another edition of Alfred’s book of Winchester, which
                    contained a survey of the kingdom. It is said also that he was the first who
                    divided the kingdom into shires. What is ascribed to him is not a bare division
                    of the country, but the settling of a new form of judicature; for after having
                    divided his dominions into shires, he subdivided each shire into three parts,
                    called <hi rend="italic">trytldngs.</hi> There are some remains of this ancient
                    division in the ridings of Yorkshire, the laths of Kent, and the three parts of
                    Lincolnshire. <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> Each trything was divided into
                    hundreds or wapentakes; and these again into tythings or dwellings of ten
                    householders. Each of these householders stood engaged to the king, as a pledge
                    for the good behaviour of his family, and all the ten were mutually pledges for
                    each other; so that if any one of the tythings was suspected of an offence, if
                    the head-boroughs or chiefs of the tythings would not be security for him, he
                    was imprisoned; and, if he made his escape, the tything and hundred were fined
                    to the king. Each shire was under the government of an earl, under whom was the
                    reive, his deputy, since, from his office, called shire-reive, or sheriff. And
                    so effectual were these regulations, That it is said he caused bracelets of gold
                    to be hung up in the highways, as a challenge to robbers; and they remained
                    untouched.</p>
                <p>In private life Alfred was the most amiable man in his dominions; of so equal a
                    temper, that he never suffered either sadness or unbecoming gaiety to enter his
                    mind; but appeared always of a calm yet cheerful disposition, íamiliar to his
                    friends, just even to his enemies, kind and tender to all. He was a remarkable
                    economist of his time; and Asserius has given us an account of the method he
                    took for dividing and keeping an account of it. He caused six wax-candles to be
                    made, each of 12 inches long, and of as many ounces weight; on the candles the
                    inches were regularly marked, and having found that one of them burned just four
                    hours, he committed them to the care of the keepers of his chapel, who from time
                    to time gave him notice how the hours went. But as in windy weather the candles
                    were wasted by the impression of the air on the flame, to remedy this
                    inconvenience he invented lanthorns, there being then no glass in his
                    dominions.</p>
                <p>This prince, we are told, was 12 years of age before a master could be procured
                    in the western kingdom to teach him the alphabet; such was the state of learning
                    when Alfred began to reign. He had felt the misery of ignorance, and determined
                    even to rival his contemporary Charlemagne in the encouragement of literature.
                    He is supposed to have appointed persons to read lectures at Oxford, and is
                    thence considered as the founder of that university. By other proper
                    establishments, and by a general encouragement to men of abilities, he did every
                    thing in his power to diffuse knowledge throughout his dominions. Nor was this
                    end promoted more by his countenance and encouragement than by his own example
                    and his writings; for notwithstanding the lateness of his initiation, he had
                    acquired extraordinary erudition; and, had he not been illustrious as a king, he
                    would have been famous as an author. His works are, 1. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Breviarium</hi><hi rend="italic">quoddam</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >collectum</hi><hi rend="italic">ex</hi><hi rend="italic">Legibus
                    Trojanorum,</hi> &amp;c. lib. i.; a Breviary collected out of the Laws of the
                    Trojans, Greeks, Britons, Saxons, and Danes, in one book. Leland saw this book
                    in the Saxon tongue, at Christ-Church, in Hampshire. 2. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Visi-Saxonum Leges,</hi> lib. i.; the Laws of the West Saxons, in one book.
                    Pitts tells us that it is in Bennet-College library, at Cambridge. 3. <hi
                    rend="italic">Instituta</hi><hi rend="italic">quaedam,</hi> lib. i.; certain
                    Institutes, in one book. This is mentioned by Pitts, and seems to be the second
                    capitulation with Guthrum. 4. <hi rend="italic">Contra Judices</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Iniquos,</hi> lib. i.; an invective against Unjust Judges, in one
                    book. 5. <hi rend="italic">Acta</hi><hi rend="italic">Magistratuum suorum,</hi>
                    lib. i.; Acts of his Magistrates, in one book. This is supposed to be the Book
                    of Judgments mentioned by Horne, and was in all probability a kind of Reports
                    intended for the use of succeeding ages. 6. <hi rend="italic">Regum
                    Fortunae</hi><hi rend="italic">varice,</hi> lib. i.; the various Fortunes of
                    Kings, in one book. 7. <hi rend="italic">Dicta Sapientum,</hi> lib. i.; the
                    Sayings of Wise Men, in one book. 8. <hi rend="italic">Parabolae</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Sales,</hi> lib. i.; Parables and
                    pleasant Sayings, in one book. 9. <hi rend="italic">Collectiones
                    Chronicoum,</hi> Collection of Chronicles. 10. <hi rend="italic">Epistolae ad
                    Wulfsigium</hi><hi rend="italic">Episcopum,</hi> lib. i.; Epistles to Bishop
                    Wulfsig, in one book. 11. <hi rend="italic">Manuale Meditationum,</hi> a Manual
                    of Meditations.—Besides those original works, he translated many authors from
                    the Latin, &amp;c. into the Saxon language, viz. 1. Bede’s History of England.
                    2. Paulinus Orosinus’s History of the Pagans. .3. St Gregory’s Pastoral, &amp;c.
                    The first of these, with his prefaces to the others, together with his laws,
                    were printed at Cambridge, 1644. His laws are likewise inserted in Spelman’s
                    Councils. 4. <hi rend="italic">Boethius dc Consolationci</hi> lib. v.;
                    Boethius’s Consolations of Philosophy, in five books. Dr Plot tells us King
                    Alfred translated it at Woodstock, as he found in a MS. in the Cotton Library.
                    5. <hi rend="italic">Aesopi Fa-· bulae,</hi> Aesop’s Fables; which he is said to
                    have translated from the Greek both into Latin and Saxon. 6. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Psalterium Davidicum,</hi> lib. i·; David’s Psalter, in one book.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193035269" xml:id="kp-eb0702-5269-0420"/>
                <p>This was the last work the king attempted, death surprising him before he had
                    finished it. It was, however, completed by another hand, and published at London
                    in 1640, in quarto, by Sir John Spelman. Several others are mentioned by
                    Malmsbury, and the old history of Ely asserts that he translated the Old and New
                    Testaments.</p>
                <p>The life of this great king was written by Asserius Me-nevensis, and published by
                    Archbishop Parker, in the old Saxon character, at the end of his edition of
                    Hessing-ham’s history, printed in 1674, folio.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
