<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-6686-0529-14" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALMAGRO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 529</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h12vc6h">Incas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx4522p">Peruvian</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058953">Peruvians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1939019">Chili</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198642">Conquest</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205585">Panama</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193036686" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALMAGRO</label>, a fortress of Spain, the capital of one of
                    the districts of La Mancha. It was built by the archbishop Roderic of Toledo,
                    who finished it in 1214, and put a considerable garrison into it to restrain the
                    incursions of the Moors. This was hardly done when the fortress was besieged by
                    an army of 5000 horse and foot, under the command of a Moorish officer of great
                    reputation; but the prelate, its founder, took care to supply those within with
                    such plenty of necessaries, that at length the enemy found themselves obliged to
                    raise the siege and retire with great loss.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Almagro,</hi><hi rend="italic">Diego de,</hi> a Spanish
                    commander, was of such obscure birth and mean parentage, that he derived his
                    name from the village where he was born in ¼63. Deprived of the means of early
                    instruction, he could neither read nor write; but nevertheless, in consequence
                    of his improvements in the military art, he formed an association with Francisco
                    Pizarro and Hernando de Luque, for the purpose of discoveries and conquest upon
                    the Peruvian coast. The governor of Panama having sanctioned their enterprise,
                    they devoted their united exertions to that undertaking. Pizarro directed the
                    conquest, and Almaġro was appointed to conduct the supplies of provisions and
                    reinforcements. In the first two unsuccessful attempts, he performed this office
                    with persevering fidelity and uncommon activity. His perseverance was followed
                    with complete success; for they at last discovered the coast of Peru, and landed
                    at Ťumbez, situated about three degrees south of the line, and distinguished by
                    its temple, and a palace of the incas or sovereigns. Pizzaro was sent over to
                    Spain to solicit further powers, after the three adventurers had previously
                    adjusted their future preferments, and agreed that Pizarro should be governor,
                    Almagro lieutenant-governor, and Luque bishop. In this negotiation Pizarro
                    obtained the clerical dignity for Luque; but, chiefly concerned about his own
                    interest, he neglected the preferment of Almagro. On his return, Almagro was so
                    enraged, that he refused to act with such a perfidious companion, and resolved
                    to form a new association. Pizarro for the present artfully endeavoured to avert
                    the indignation of Almagro, and gradually soothed the rage and disappointment of
                    the soldier. The union was renewed upon the former terms; and it was solemnly
                    stipulated that a common expense and a common advantage should take place.</p>
                <p>In February 1531, leaving Almagro at Panama to supply provisions and
                    reinforcements, Pizarro set sail for. Peru. He attacked a principal settlement
                    of the natives in the province of Coaque, obtained immense spoil, and made such
                    ample remittances to Almagro as enabled him to complete his reinforcement; and
                    in the close of the year 1532 Almagro arrived at St Michael with a body of <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193036699" xml:id="kp-eb0702-6699-0530"/> men nearly double
                    the number of those whom Pizarro had along with him. The Spaniards about this
                    time took captive the unfortunate Inca Atahualpa; and after they had received an
                    immense sum for his ransom, they barbarously put him to death. Ferdinand Pizarro
                    sailed for Spain with the news of their success, and with remittances to a great
                    amount; and consequently Almagro gained that elevated station he had so long and
                    so eagerly desired. But no sooner did he receive the intelligence of his
                    promotion by the royal grant, than he attempted to seize Cuzco, the imperial
                    residence of the incas, under pretence that it lay within his destined
                    territory. This produced a new quarrel; but peace was restored upon condition
                    that Almagro should attempt the conquest of Chili, and, if he did not find in
                    that province an establishment adequate to his merit, that Pizarro should yield
                    up to him a part of Peru.</p>
                <p>In 1535 he accordingly set out at the head of 570 Europeans, and in crossing the
                    mountains he suffered great hardships and losses by mistaking the route; but at
                    length he descended into the plains of that devoted region. Here he met with a
                    more vigorous resistance from the natives than the Spaniards had ever
                    experienced in other countries. He had, however, made some progress, when he was
                    recalled to Peru by the news of the natives having risen in great numbers, and
                    attacked Lima and Cuzco. He pursued a new route, and marching through the sandy
                    plains on the coast, he suffered by heat and drought calamities not inferior to
                    those which he had endured from cold and famine on the summits of the Andes.
                    Arriving at a favourable moment, he resolved to hold the place both against the
                    Indians and his Spanish rivals. He attacked the Peruvian army with great vigour,
                    and making a great slaughter, he proceeded to the gates of Cuzco without any
                    further interruption. The open, affable, and generous temper of Almagro gained
                    over to his side many of the adherents of the Pizarros, who were disgusted with
                    their harsh and oppressive conduct. With the aid of these he advanced towards
                    the city by night, surprised the sentinels, and surrounded the house where the
                    two brothers Ferdinand and Gonzalo Pizarro resided, who were compelled, after an
                    obstinate defence, to surrender at discretion. A form of government was settled
                    in the name of Almagro, and his jurisdiction over Cuzco was universally
                    acknowledged. This was the origin of a civil war, the beginning of which was
                    very advantageous to Almagro, who by skilful manoeuvres entirely routed a body
                    of Spanish troops advancing to the relief of Cuzco, and made Alvarado, their
                    commander, prisoner. But instead of improving these advantages, he unwisely
                    marched back to Cuzco, and there awaited the arrival of Pizarro, who, convinced
                    of his own feeble resources, proposed an accommodation, and with his usual art
                    protracted the negotiation until he found himself in a condition to meet his
                    antagonist in the field of battle. Meanwhile Alvarado and one of the Pizarros,
                    by bribing their keepers, found means to escape, and persuaded 60 of the men who
                    guarded them to attend them in their flight; and the governor released the
                    other. When Pizarro thought himself sufficiently prepared to settle the dominion
                    of Peru, he marched with an army of 500 men to Cuzco. Almagro, previously to
                    this, worn out with age and infirmity, resigned the command to Orgognez. A
                    fierce and bloody battle ensued, in which Almagro’s army was defeated, and the
                    commander wounded. About 140 soldiers fell in the field, and Orgognez, along
                    with several officers of distinction, was massacred in cold blood. During that
                    fatal day, Almagro, placed in a litter, which was stationed on an eminence,
                    beheld from thence the total discomfiture of his troops, and felt all the
                    indignation of a soldier who had seldom expe rienced defeat. He was taken
                    prisoner, remained several months in confinement, and was afterwards tried and
                    condemned to death. In the view of an ignominious death, the courage of the
                    veteran forsook him, and he unsuccessfully supplicated for life in a manner
                    unworthy of his former character. All the arguments he could employ were
                    ineffectual. The Pizarros remained unmoved by all his entreaties. As soon,
                    however, as Almagro saw that his fate was inevitable, he resumed his courage,
                    and exhibited all his usual dignity and fortitude. In the year 1538, and in the
                    75th year of his age, he was strangled in prison, and afterwards beheaded. He
                    left one son by an Indian woman of Panama; and, in consequence of a power which
                    the emperor had granted him, he declared his son his successor in the
                    government, although he was then a prisoner in Lima.</p>
                <p>With the qualities of intrepid valour, indefatigable activity, and insurmountable
                    constancy, he blended the more amiable dispositions of frankness, generosity,
                    and candour. These qualities rendered him beloved by his followers, and his
                    misfortunes excited their sympathy and pity; so that his death was universally
                    regretted, and particularly by the poor Indians, who deemed him their guardian
                    and protector against the cruel and unfeeling Pizarro. Upon the whole review of
                    his character, it appears just to conclude, that he was, although of inferior
                    abilities, a more amiable man than his rival.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Almagro,</hi> the Younger, by his courage, generosity, and
                    other accomplishments, was placed at the head of the party after the death of
                    his father. The father, conscious of his own inferiority from the total want of
                    education, used every possible means to improve the mind and embellish the
                    manners of his son; so that he soon acquired those accomplishments which
                    rendered him respected by illiterate adventurers, who cheerfully ranged round
                    his standard, and by his dexterity and skill sought deliverance from the
                    oppressions of Pizarro. Juan de Herrada, an officer of great abilities,
                    continued still to direct his councils, and to regulate his enterprises; and,
                    while Pizarro confided in his own security, a conspiracy wa&lt;s formed against
                    him, which terminated in his death. The assassins, exulting in their success,
                    and waving their bloody swords, hastened to the street, proclaimed the death of
                    the tyrant, and compelled the magistrates and principal citizens of Lima to
                    acknowledge Almagro as lawful successor of his father. But his reign was of
                    short duration; for, in 1541, Vaca de Castro, arriving at Quito, produced the
                    royal commission, appointing him governor of Peru, together with all the
                    privileges and authority of Pizarro. The talents and influence of the new
                    governor soon overpowered the interest of Almagro, who, perceiving the rapid
                    decline of his influence, hastened with his troops to Cuzco, where his opponents
                    had erected the royal standard under the command of Pedro Alvarcz Holguin.
                    Herrada, the guide of his counsels, died during his march; and from that time
                    his measures were conspicuous for their violence, concerted with little
                    ingenuity, and executed with little address. At length, on September 16, 1542,
                    the forces of Almagro and Vaca de Castro met, and victory long remained
                    doubtful, till at last it declared for the new governor. Almagro conducted the
                    military operations of that fatal day with a gallant spirit, worthy of a better
                    cause, and deserving of a better fate; and his followers displayed uncommon
                    valour. In proportion to the number of combatants the carnage was very great. Of
                    Ið'ļ men, 500 fell in the field, and many more were wounded. Almagro escaped,
                    but being betrayed by some of ms own officers, he was publicly beheaded at
                    Cuzco, and in him the name and spirit of the party of Almagro became
                    extinct.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193036712" xml:id="kp-eb0702-6712-0531"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
