<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-6491-0514-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALI</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 514</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44t5k">Koran</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v698j66">Prophets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bc6v">Caliphs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1079211">Prophets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:844315">Caliphate</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:844318">Caliphs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1024194">Moas</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193036491" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALI</label>, the son of Abu Taleb, is one of the most
                    celebrated characters in Mahometan history. He was cousin to Mahomet, and at the
                    age of fourteen engaged with youthful ardour in his cause. When Mahomet first
                    revealed his prophetic character to his friends, and inquired who among them
                    would undertake to be his companion Ali exclaimed, “O prophet, I will be thy
                    attendant; the man who dares to rise against thee I will break his legs, pluck
                    out his eyes, dash out his teeth, and even rip up his belly.” Mahomet accepted
                    his services, and honoured him with the titles of brother, vicegerent, and Aaron
                    to a new Moses. He was remarkable both for eloquence and valour; and the latter
                    obtained him the surname of “<hi rend="italic">the Lion of God, always
                    victorious."</hi> He succeeded to the chief dignity of the renowned house of
                    Hashem, and was also hereditary guardian of the temple and city of Mecca.
                    Mahomet gave him his daughter Fatimah in marriage, and the grandfather lived to
                    embrace the children of his daughter. These advantages induced Ali to cast a
                    wistful eye towards the regal succession; however, Abubeker, Omar, and Othman,
                    reigned before him. But after the death of the latter, he was saluted caliph by
                    the chiefs of the tribes and companions of the prophet, when he was repairing to
                    the mosque of Medina at the hour of prayer, A. n. 655, hcgira 35.</p>
                <p>Ayesha, the widow of the prophet, strenuously opposed his succession; and under
                    her influence two powerful chiefs soon raised the standard of rebellion. Ali
                    greatly increased his difficulties by the imprudent removal of all the governors
                    of provinces from their stations. Telha and Zobcir, two chiefs of great
                    influence, collected a numerous army, and induced Ayesha to attend them to the
                    field of battle; but Ali gained a complete victory, and took Ayesha prisoner.
                    Telha fell in the field, and Zobeir was assassinated after surrendering upon
                    promise of quarter. This dastardly action was severely reprehended by Ali. He
                    likewise kindly treated the captive widow, and sent her back to the tomb of the
                    prophet.</p>
                <p>Ali next attacked Moawiyah, who had been proclaimed caliph, and strongly
                    supported by a powerful and numerous party. When the two armies approached each
                    other, Ali proposed to decide the matter by single combat; but to this his
                    opponent would not agree. Several skirmishes were fought with considerable loss
                    on both sides; but at length a pious fraud produced a division of sentiment in
                    the army of Ali. They fixed to the points of lances a number of copies of the
                    Koran, carried them before the troops, and exclaimed, “This is the book which
                    forbids Mussulmans to shed each other’s blood, and ought therefore to decide our
                    disputes.” Ali was constrained to yield, and umpires were mutually chosen; on
                    the side of Ali, Abu Moussa; Amru, the conqueror of Egypt, on the part of
                    Moawiyah. The day of final decision arrived. Abu Moussa ascended the pulpit, and
                    cried, “As I draw this ring from my finger, so I depose both Ali and Moa-wiyah
                    from the caliphate.” When Amru ascended, he cried, “As I put on this ring, so I
                    invest Moawiyah with the caliphate, and also depose Ali.” He also added, that
                    Othman, the former caliph, had declared Moawiyah both his successor and avenger.
                    Thus began that memorable contest among the Mahometans, which was long agitated
                    with considerable violence by both parties.</p>
                <p>Ali was highly enraged at this injustice; but, constrained for the present to
                    yield, he retired to Kufa. A sect of enthusiasts, called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kharejites,</hi> revolted against Ah; but he quickly reduced them to
                    subjection, and again obtained possession of Arabia. But Syria, Persia, and
                    Egypt fell to the share of his rival.</p>
                <p>An unexpected event terminated the existing disputes. Three Kharejites one day
                    conversing together concerning the blood which had been shed, and the impending
                    calamities, resolved to assassinate Ali, Moawiyah, and Amru, the three authors
                    of the present disasters. They provided themselves with poisoned swords, and
                    hastened <pb break="no" facs="nls:193036504" xml:id="kp-eb0702-6504-0515"/>to
                    accomplish their purpose. Moawiyah was wounded, 'but the wound did not prove
                    fatal. A friend of Amru fell in his stead. Ali was fatally wounded at the door
                    of the mosque; and, in the 63d year of his age, he expired on the fifth day
                    after his wound, A. <hi rend="smallcaps">d.</hi> 660, hegira 40.</p>
                <p>Ali had eight wives besides Fatimah, and left a numerous family, who were very
                    remarkable for their valour. He also rose to high eminence for learning and
                    wisdom; and of his works there are still extant a hundred maxims, a collection
                    of verses, and a prophecy of all the great events which are to happen to the end
                    of time.</p>
                <p>The Mussulmans term Ali <hi rend="italic">the heir of Mahomet, and the accepted
                    of God</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and his particular followers have possessed
                    various states in Africa and Asia, and the Persian part of the Usbec Tartars;
                    and some sovereigns of India are at present of the sect of Ali. A monument is
                    raised upon his tomb near Kufa, which the kings of Persia have successively
                    decorated and religiously revered. Near the ruins of Kufa, a city named Meshed
                    Ali has been built to his memory. Some of his deluded followers imagine that he
                    is still alive, and that he will revisit the earth and fill the same with
                    justice. A green turban still continues to distinguish the descendants of
                    Ali.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Alī</hi><hi rend="italic">Bey,</hi> an eastern adventurer,
                    is said to have been a native of Mount Caucasus, and about the age of twelve or
                    fourteen he was sold for a slave in Cairo. The two Jews who became his masters
                    presented him to Ibrahim, then one of the most respectable men in the kingdom.
                    In the family of this powerful man he received the rudiments of literature, and
                    was also instructed in the military art. Both in letters and military skill he
                    made rapid improvement. He gradually gained the affection of his patron to such
                    a degree, that he gave him his freedom, permitted him to marry, promoted him to
                    die rank of governor of a district, and afterwards by election he was raised to
                    the elevated station of one of the governors of provinces. Deprived of his
                    protector by death, and engaging in the dangerous intrigues that pave the way to
                    power in that unstable government, he procured his own banishment to Upper
                    Egypt. Here he spent two years in maturing his schemes for future greatness; and
                    in 1766, returning to Cairo, he either slew or expelled the beys, and seized the
                    reins of government.</p>
                <p>Emboldened by success, he rescued himself from the power of the Porte, coined
                    money in his own name, and assumed the rank of sultan of Egypt. Occupied in more
                    important concerns, the Porte made no vigorous opposition to his measures, and
                    Ali Bey seized this favourable opportunity to recover a part of the Said, or
                    Upper Egypt, which had been taken away by an Arab sheik. Next lie sent out a
                    fleet from Suez, which seizing upon Djedda, entered the port of Mecca; while a
                    body of cavalry, commanded by Mohammed Bey, his favourite, took and plundered
                    Mecca itself. A young Venetian merchant laid before him a plan of reviving the
                    ancient trade to the East Indies through the Mediterranean and Red Sea. Having
                    formed an alliance in 1770 with one Sheik Daher, a rebel against the Porte in
                    Syria, he aimed at the conquest of all Syria and Palestine. He first endeavoured
                    to secure Gaza; then his army, forming a junction with that of Daher at a place
                    called Acre, advanced to Damascus. On the 6th of June 1771 a battle was fought
                    at this place with the Turkish pachas, and Mohammed and Daher, the commanders of
                    Ali Bey, touted them with great slaughter. They instantly took possession of
                    Damascus, and the castle itself had also capitulated, when all on a sudden
                    Mohammed hastened back to Egypt with all his Mamelukes. Some ascribe this
                    strange conduct to an impression made upon Mohammed by the Turkish agents, and
                    others to a report of the death of Ali Bey.</p>
                <p>Although unsuccessful, Ali Bey never lost sight of his favourite object; and
                    Mohammed, losing his confidence, was forced to save his life by exile. Mohammed,
                    however, quickly returned with an army, and drove Ali Bey from Cairo. In this
                    unfortunate state of affairs Ali Bey fled to Daher, and, combining their forces,
                    they attacked the Turkish commander at Sidon, and came off victorious, although
                    the Turkish army was three times their number. After a siege of eight months,
                    they next took the town of Jaffa. Deceived by letters from Cairo, which were
                    only intended to ensnare him, and stimulated with recent victories, he returned
                    to Cairo. Entering the deserts which divide Gaza from Egypt, he was furiously
                    attacked by a thousand chosen Mamelukes led on by Murad Bey, who was enamoured
                    with the beauty of All’s wife, and had obtained the promise of her, provided
                    that he could take Ali Bey captive. Murad wounded and made Ali Bey prisoner, and
                    carried him up to Mohammed, who received him with affected respect; but in three
                    days, either in consequence of poison or the effects of his wounds, Ali breathed
                    his last.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
