<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-4826-0736-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FOOTE, Samuel (7th edition, volume 9, page 736)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353970">Performances</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1057829">Performance</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1165037">Veils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1144120">Tea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:820963">Auctions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:820954">Auctioneers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891974">Devil</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4251ft9s">Tea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45717n86">Auctions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fk98">Devil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41g0hw2j">Capuchins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42z12r4v">Tailoring</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193754826?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FOOTE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Samuel</hi></label>, was bom at
                    Truro, in Cornwall, and descended from an ancient and respectable family. His
                    father was member of parliament for Tiverton in Devonshire, and enjoyed the post
                    of commissioner of the prize office; his mother was heiress of the Dinely and
                    Goodere families. Foote was educated at Worcester College, Oxford, which owed
                    its foundation to Sir Thomas Cookes Windford. On leaving the university he
                    commenced student of law in the Temple; but as the dryness of this study did not
                    suit the liveliness of his genius, lie soon relinquished it. He then married a
                    young lady of a good family and some fortune; but their tempers not agreeing,
                    harmony did not long subsist between them. He now launched into all the
                    fashionable follies of the age, gambling not excepted, and in a few years
                    squandered away his whole fortune. His necessities led him to the stage, and he
                    made his first appearance in the character of Othello. He next perform ed
                    Fondlewife with much greater applause; and this, indeed, was ever afterwards one
                    of his capital parts. He likewise attempted Lord Foppington, but afterwards gave
                    it up as unsuitable to his talents. In 1747 he opened the little theatre in the
                    Haymarket, taking upon himself the double character of author and performer; and
                    he appeared in a dramatic piece of his own composition, called the <hi
                    rend="italic">Diversions of the Morning.</hi> The piece consisted of nothing
                    more than the exhibition of several characters well known in real life, whose
                    style and manner of conversation and expression the author had very happily hit
                    off in the diction of his drama, and still more happily represented on the
                    stage, by an exact and indeed amazing imitation, not only of the manner and tone
                    of voice, but even of the very persons of those whom he intended to take off.
                    This performance at first met with some opposition from the civil magistrates of
                    Westminster, under the sanction of the act of parliament for limiting the number
                    of playhouses, as well as from the jealousy of one of the managers of Drury Lane
                    theatre. But the author being patronized by many of the principal nobility, and
                    other persons σf distinction, this opposition was overruled; and having altered
                    the title of his performance, Mr Foote proceeded, without further molestation,
                    to give <hi rend="italic">Tea</hi><hi rend="italic">in a Morning</hi> to his
                    friends, and represented it through a run of forty mornings to crowded and
                    splendid audiences. In the ensuing season he produced another piece of the same
                    kind, which he called <hi rend="italic">An Auction of Pictures.</hi> Into this
                    performance he introduced several new and popular characters; particularly Sir
                    Thomas de Veil, then the acting justice of peace for Westminster, Mr Cock the
                    celebrated auctioneer, and the equally famous Orator Henley. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Auction</hi> had also a very great run. His <hi rend="italic"
                    >Knights,</hi> which was the production of the ensuing season, exhibited
                    somewhat more of dramatic regularity. But still, although his plot and
                    characters seemed less immediately personal, it was apparent that in the
                    performance he kept some real persons strongly in his eye; and the town took it
                    upon themselves to fix these where the resemblances appeared most striking. Thus
                    Mr Foote continued from time to time to select, for the entertainment of the
                    town, such public characters as seemed most likely to engage their attention.
                    But his dramatic pieces, exclusively of the interlude called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Piety in Pattens,</hi> are only to be ranked among the <hi rend="italic"
                    >petites</hi><hi rend="italic">pieces</hi> of the theatre. In the execution they
                    are somewhat loose, negligent, and unfinished; the plots are often irregular,
                    and the catastrophes frequently inconclusive; but, with all these deficiencies,
                    they contain more strength of character, more strokes of keen satire, and more
                    touches of temporary hmnour, than are to be found in the writings of any other
                    modern dramatist. Even the language spoken by his characters, incorrect as <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193754839?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0709-4839-0737"/> it
                    may sometimes seem, will on a closer examination be found altogether dramatical:
                    abounding with those natural minutiae of expression which frequently form the
                    very basis of character, and which render it the truest mirror of the
                    conversation of the times to which it applies.</p>
                <p>In the year 1766, being on a party of pleasure with the Duke of York, Lord
                    Mexborough, and Sir Francis Délavai, Mr Foote had the misfortune to break his
                    leg by a fall from his horse, in consequence of which he was compelled to
                    undergo an amputation. This accident so sensibly affected the duke, that he made
                    a point of obtaining for Mr Foote a patent for life, by which he was allowed to
                    perform, at the little theatre in the Haymarket, from the 15th of May to the
                    15th of September every year.</p>
                <p>Mr Foote, finding his health declining, entered into an agreement with Mr Colman,
                    for his patent of the theatre, according to which he was to receive from Mr
                    Colman L.1600 per annum, besides a stipulated sum whenever he chose to perform.
                    Mr Foote made his appearance two or three times in some of the most admired
                    characters; but being suddenly affected with a paralytic stroke one night whilst
                    upon the stage, he was compelled to retire. He was advised to bathe; and
                    accordingly retired to Brighton, where he apparently recovered his former health
                    and spirits, and continued what is called the cock of the company who resorted
                    to that agreeable place of amusement. A few weeks before his death he returned
                    to London; but, by the advice of his physicians, set out with an intention to
                    spend the winter at Paris and in the south of France. He had got no farther than
                    Dover, when he was suddenly attacked by another stroke of the palsy, which in a
                    few hours terminated his existence. He died on the 21st of October 1777, in the
                    fifty-sixth year of his age, and was privately interred in the cloisters of
                    Westminster Abbey. Foote’s published dramas, twenty in number, were written in
                    the following order: 1. Taste, a comedy, in 1752; 2. The Englishman in Paris,
                    1753; 3. The Knights, 1754; 4. The Englishman returned from Paris, 1756; 5. The
                    Author, 1757; 6. The Minor, 1760; 7. The Lyar, 1761; 8. The Orators, 1762; 9.
                    The Mayor of Garrat, 1763; 10. The Patron, 1764; 11. The Commissary; 12. Prelude
                    on opening the Theatre, 1767; 13. The Devil upon Two Sticks, 1768; 14. The Lame
                    Lover, 1770; 15. The Maid of Bath, 1771; 16. The Nabob, 1772; 17. The Bankrupt,
                    1772; 18. The Cozeners, 1774; 19. A Trip to Calais, 1776; 20. The Capuchin,
                    altered from the former, but prohibited. <hi rend="italic">Piety in
                    Pattens,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Diversions of a Morning,</hi> altered
                    from <hi rend="italic">Taste,</hi> were never published. The anonymous mock
                    tragedy entitled <hi rend="italic">The Tailors</hi> is usually printed with
                    Foote’s works, being generally thought to be his composition. Foote borrowed
                    liberally from Molière and others; but what he took without ceremony he
                    generally contrived to make his own by a certain originality in the manner of
                    employing it; and his own humour was so peculiar and effective, that no player
                    has since been equally successful in the parts which he himself performed.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
