<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0081-0072-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FÉNELON, François de</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 72</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:981348">Jansenists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v131">Pastors</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bv7p">Jansenists</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4610vs0f">Archbishops</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n81/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FÉNELON, <hi rend="smallcaps">François de</hi></label><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Salignac</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">de Lamothe</hi> (1651-1715),
                    archbishop of Cambray, and one of the most celebrated names in the intellectual
                    and ecclesiastical history of France in the 17th century, was born at the
                    Chateau de Fénelon in Périgord, August 6, 1651. The family of Salignac or
                    Salagnac, to which he belonged, had been ennobled from the middle of the 15 th
                    century, and produced already many distinguished names. The father of the future
                    archbishop was Count Pons de Salignac, of whose second marriage, contracted in
                    mature years, François was the only child. From his birth he was of a delicate
                    and sensitive temperament; and, greatly beloved by his old father, he was
                    educated at home till he was twelve years of age. He received, according to one
                    of his biographers, “a simple Christian education devoid of anything
                    remarkable.” But he must have been lucky in his tutor or of rare aptitude for
                    learning, for he seems then to have laid the foundation of his admirable
                    scholarship and love of letters. After a short time at the college of Cahors, he
                    went to Paris to complete his studies under the Jesuits at the Collége du
                    Plessis. There his great gifts soon drew to him distinction, and, like his rival
                    Bossuet, he ventured to preach to an admiring audience at the age of fifteen.
                    His father seems to have died before this time, and his uncle, the Marquis de
                    Fénelon, who had assumed the care of his education, withdrew his charge from
                    what might have proved injurious seductions, and placed him in the seminary of
                    St Sulpice under the saintly Trouson. His uncle was himself a remarkable man.
                    Distinguished as a soldier and a statesman, he became no less distinguished for
                    his piety and moral heroism. In conjunction with Μ. Olier, the founder of St
                    Sulpice, he inaugurated and became the first president of an association for the
                    suppression of duelling. The association was composed only of men whose valour
                    was unimpeachable, and whose oath binding them to refuse any challenge or take
                    part in any duel could not therefore be mistaken. The Marquis de Fénelon and his
                    daughter, who became Madame de Montmorenci Laval, wife of the Marquis de
                    Montmorenci Laval, both exercised a decisive and happy influence over the young
                    Fénelon. Many of his early letters are addressed to his cousin, whom he looked
                    upon as a sister—the only one he had ever known. But the head of St Sulpice, Μ.
                    Trouson, shared with these relatives the task of his higher education, and no
                    one, both now and afterwards, enjoyed so much of his confidence. “Great as is my
                    freedom and openheartedness with you,” the young student writes to his uncle
                    after being placed at the seminary, “I must confess without any fear of making
                    you jealous that I am still more unreserved with M. Trouson; if you could hear
                    our conversation and the ease with which I lay bare my heart to him, and with
                    which he teaches me to know God, yoιi would not know your pupil, and you would
                    see that God has very marvellously helped on the work which you began.”</p>
                <p>Fénelon’s first aspirations were towards a missionary life. The congregation at
                    St Sulpice had established a missionary society at Canada which many of its
                    pupils had joined, and he wished to follow their steps; and when this project
                    failed he still more earnestly desired to undertake a mission to Greece. In one
                    of his letters, dated October 9, 1675, he draws a glowing sketch of his desire
                    to visit “the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n82/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0082-0073"/> glorious scenes,” redolent of the spirit of
                    antiquity, which he had so often pictured in imagination, and “to seek out the
                    Areopagus whence St Paul proclaimed the unknown God to heathen sages.” But his
                    delicate health, and the dissuasion of another uncle, the bishop of Sarlat,
                    interfered with his missionary longings. He was induced to remain at home and
                    accept the office of superior of the community of Nouvelles Catholiques, a
                    community founded for the protection and instruction of women converted from
                    Protestantism. He spent ten years (1675-85) of quiet and successful labour in
                    connexion with this institution, became intimately associated with a select
                    circle, at the head of which was the Due de Beauvilliers, began his career as an
                    author, and otherwise laid the foundation of his remarkable influence. It was at
                    the request of the Duchesse de Beauvilliers that he is said to have written his
                    first work, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">V Education</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Filles,</hi> which long maintained its reputation among the
                    higher families of France, and may still be consulted with advantage. It
                    contains many admirable precepts. To this same period belong a <hi rend="italic"
                    >Refutation of</hi><hi rend="italic">Malebranche'</hi><hi rend="italic">s
                    Treatise of Nature and-Grace,</hi> in which he was assisted with marginal notes
                    by Bossuet, and a treatise on the <hi rend="italic">Ministry of Pastors,</hi> in
                    which he set forth the blessing of a divine order appointed in uninterrupted
                    succession from the apostles to guard men from error, seeing that all experience
                    proves how unable ordinary men are “to decide for themselves as to the details
                    of dogmas.” This treatise had a polemical aim against the Protestants, but was
                    at the same time written with great moderation and fairness.</p>
                <p>In 1685 Louis XIV. carried out his infamous policy of expelling the Protestants
                    from France by the revocation of the edict of Nantes. Great disturbance arose in
                    consequence in the districts of Poitou and Saintonge. It was necessary, by firm
                    yet gentle mean3, to do something to allay the violent irritation which had been
                    caused. On the recommendation of Bossuet, Fénelon was chosen as the head of a
                    mission for this purpose. He made two conditions, —that all troops should be
                    withdrawn from the provinces, and that he should be allowed to choose his fellow
                    workers. The result was that his mission was attended with considerable success,
                    although he himself complains more than a year afterwards, “Our converts get on
                    very slowly;—it is no easy matter to change the opinions of a whole people.” On
                    his return to Paris he had several interviews with the king to report the result
                    of his labours, and afterwards resumed in comparative privacy his old duties
                    among the Nouvelles Catholiques. M. de Harlay, the well-known brilliant but
                    profligate archbishop of Paris, who had first advanced him to this position,
                    withdrew his favour from him when he saw he could make no use of him. “It seems,
                    M. l’Abbé, that you wish to be forgotten, and you shall be,” was his bitter
                    speech on one occasion; and he so far succeeded as to prevent Fénelon’s
                    appointment to the see of Poitiers which had been contemplated by the king.</p>
                <p>Suddenly he was called to the responsible position of preceptor of the dauphin’s
                    son, the young duke of Burgundy. This was the work especially of his friend the
                    Due de Beauvilliers, who in 1689 was appointed governor of the royal grandson.
                    But other friends warmly rejoiced in Fénelon’s advancement, and amongst these
                    Bossuet wrote to Madame de Montmorenci Laval congratulating her. “We shall not
                    lose the Abbé Fénelon,” he says; “you will be able to enjoy him, and, provincial
                    as I am, I shall escape from time to time to embrace him.” It is interesting to
                    notice this renewed trace of hearty friendship between these two illustrious
                    men, considering the unhappy relations which afterwards arose between them.</p>
                <p>No man probably was ever better fitted than Fénelon for the difficult position
                    which he now assumed, and to which he mainly devoted himself during the next six
                    years (1689- 95). He was a. born teacher in the highest sense,—gifted with the
                    most charming qualities of patience, sweetness of temper, tact, and address, yet
                    inflexible in principle, and severe and unbending in his methods of training. He
                    had the manners of a <hi rend="italic">grand seigneur,</hi> with all the
                    intellectual refinements of an accomplished churchman. Saint Simon in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> (t. xxii. p. 135) has left a portrait of him about
                    this time which has been often quoted, and from which we extract only a few
                    sentences. “He was a tall thin man, well made, pale, with a large nose, eyes
                    whence fire and talent streamed like a torrent, and a physiognomy the like of
                    which I have never seen in any other man, and which once seen one could never
                    forget. It combined everything, and the greatest contradictions produced no want
                    of harmony. It united seriousness and gaiety, gravity and courtesy—the
                    prevailing characteristic, as in everything about him, being refinement,
                    intellect, gracefulness, modesty, and above all <hi rend="italic">noblesse.</hi>
                    It was difficult to take one’s eyes off him. All his portraits are speaking, and
                    yet none of them have caught the exquisite harmony which struck one in the
                    original, or the exceeding delicacy of every feature. His manner altogether
                    corresponded to his appearance; his perfect ease was infectious to others, and
                    his conversation was stamped with the grace and good taste which are only
                    acquired by habitual intercourse with the best society and the great world.” He
                    had need of all his brilliant and solid qualities in the task which he had
                    undertaken. The young duke of Burgundy, as the same writer remarks, “was born
                    with a <hi rend="italic">naturel</hi> which made one tremble. He was so
                    passionate that he would break the clocks which summoned him to some unwelcome
                    duty, and fly into the wildest rage with the rain which hindered some pleasure.”
                    He was withal warm-hearted and clever,—in fact, “dangerously quick in
                    penetrating both things and people.” Fénelon had full scope for the exercise of
                    his marvellous educational art, and the result was a success far beyond what is
                    usual in such cases. - The impetuous but affectionate and bright child grew
                    under his charge into an earnest, well-disciplined, and promising, if somewhat
                    over-scrupulous and timid youth, whose life if spared might have brought
                    blessing to France. Fénelon carefully planned all the details of his education,
                    and has embodied in his well-known <hi rend="italic">Telemaque</hi> and other
                    writings the principles on which he based it. It was his aim to train the young
                    prince not merely in habits of self-control, to direct his scholarly
                    acquirements and religious convictions, but, moreover, to awaken in him true and
                    large political instincts fitted to qualify him for his high position. Fénelon
                    himself, while an aristocrat both by birth and feeling, and strongly favourable
                    to the maintenance of these class distinctions which were especially marked in
                    France in the 17th century, was at the same time essentially liberal in his
                    recognition of the radical equality of all men, and the moral regards which
                    should regulate the relation of classes to one another. His ideal was that of a
                    limited monarchy, surrounded by national institutions, each having its due place
                    and function in the body politic, and representing in due degree public opinion.
                    A written constitution, one sovereign law for all, universal education provided
                    by the state, the reciprocal independence of the temporal and spiritual powers,
                    detestation of war, free industry in agriculture and trade, a people growing in
                    intelligence and self-dependence round the throne and under the guidance of the
                    church,—such were the broad principles which he sought to instil into his pupil,
                    and so to make him,' in his own language, “a philosophic king,” “a new Saint
                    Louis.” The task was a noble one, and it was pursued with all the fascination,
                    patience, and quiet earnestness which distinguished him.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n83/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0083-0074"/>
                <p>But a train of circumstances was preparing, destined to impair and finally to
                    overthrow his influence at court, and to banish him from all intercourse with
                    his royal pupil. We can only very briefly indicate the causes which led to this
                    result. A system of religious mysticism known as Quietism had been set afloat
                    towards the end of the 17th century by a Spanish priest of the name of Molinos.
                    The system was espoused in France amongst others especially by Madame Guyon, a
                    remarkable woman devoted to the cause of religion, but of an erratic and
                    restless temperament. Her writings on the subject attracted wide attention, and
                    speedily called forth ecclesiastical condemnation. The archbishop of Paris took
                    up a position of violent hostility towards her; the severe and methodical
                    character of the king was greatly offended by her excesses; and Bossuet was by
                    and by drawn into the circle of her vehement opponents. Strangely it was by
                    Fénelon’s advice that the subject was first brought under Bossuet’s notice.
                    Attracted by Madame Guyon’s genuine enthusiasm, and no doubt finding something
                    in her view of disinterested mysticism which appealed to his own religious
                    temperament, he recommended her to place her writings in the hands of the bishop
                    of Meaux, and to abide by his decision. Many conferences were held on the
                    subject, in which Fénelon at first took no part, and during the progress of
                    which he held friendly communication with his old friend, and in fact supplied
                    Bossuet, who professed his ignorance of the mystical writers, with extracts from
                    the fathers and others bearing on the controversy. Therelation of the two
                    friendscontinued apparently cordial; the atmosphere of the court had not yet
                    changed towards him, for it was at this very time, in the beginning of 1695,
                    that the king nominated Fénelon for the archbishopric of Cambray; but gradually
                    out of this miserable business there sprung up a host of embittered feelings.
                    After his appointment as archbishop, Fénelon had joined in the conferences at
                    Issy which finally condemned Madame Guyon’s doctrines. He scrupled, however, to
                    subscribe her condemnation; he scrupled also to express approval of a
                    publication of Bossuet attacking these doctrines; and in vindication of his own
                    position and principles he published his <hi rend="italic">Maximes</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Saints sur la vie</hi><hi rend="italic">intérieure.</hi> The
                    result was to kindle into greater fury the storm of controversy, to provoke the
                    jealous and violent animosity of Bossuet, and to fan the suspicions with which
                    the king had always more or less regarded him into such a vehement outbreak as
                    to lead to his permanent banishment from court, and his condemnation at Rome
                    (1699). He submitted himself to the pontifical decision. But this did not save
                    him either from the continued anger of Bossuet or from the displeasure of the
                    monarch, which w ere further excited by the publication, through the treachery
                    of a secretary, of his <hi rend="italic">Télémaque,</hi> under the allegorical
                    disguise of which Louis and his courtiers recognized a satire against the
                    absolutist principles of the French Government.</p>
                <p>Fénelon himself disclaimed any such intention. “He had,” he said, “introduced all
                    the virtues necessary for a good government, and the faults to which sovereign
                    power is liable, but none were drawn with the slightest approach to any
                    personality or portraiture. The more the book is examined, the more it will be
                    seen that it only expressed principles fully, without attempting to draw any
                    finished character. My only object was to amuse the duke of Burgundy with a tale
                    of adventure, and to instruct him at the same time, without ever thinking of
                    giving the work to the public” <hi rend="italic">(fforresp.,</hi> t. iii. p.
                    247).</p>
                <p>The remainder of Fénelon’s life was spent in his diocese in ceaseless works of
                    Christian piety and charity. Cambray abounded in Protestants and Jansenists,
                    whom he greatly won by his toleration and evangelical simplicity. It was,
                    moreover, a great thoroughfare for the armies of the time, to the necessities of
                    which, and especially of the sick and wounded, he personally ministered. His own
                    palace was sometimes crowded with invalided officers, who remained his guests
                    for months. He became in consequence endeared to the army and the people.
                    Mingling familiarly with the poorest peasants under his spiritual charge,
                    dispensing with liberality, yet without ostentation, the duties of Christian
                    hospitality, carrying on an extensive correspondence with the clergy and some of
                    his old friends at court, he became more honoured in his retirement even than he
                    had been in Paris. “In everything,” says Saint Simon, “he was a true bishop, in
                    everything a <hi rend="italic">grand seigneur,</hi> in everything, too, the
                    author of <hi rend="italic">Tel'emaquef</hi> A curious picture is preserved of
                    these later years of Fénelon by a Scotchman of the name of Andrew Ramsay, who
                    had wandered over Holland and Germany in search of something more satisfying
                    than the sectarianism of his native country, or the deism which seemed to him
                    for a time the only alternative. Won by the spiritual beauty of Fénelon’s
                    character, and the elevation of his teaching, he embraced the Catholic faith,
                    spent much of his time at Cambray, and wrote the first life ever published of
                    his teacher and friend. The last years of the good archbishop’s life were
                    saddened by the loss of most of his friends. “Our best friends,” he said, on
                    hearing of the death of the Due de Beauvilliers in</p>
                <p>1714, “are the source of our greatest sorrow and bitterness.” And again he wrote
                    to a remaining friend, “I only live in friendship now, and friendship will be
                    the cause of my death.” He died on the 17th January</p>
                <p>1715.</p>
                <p>Fénelon is chiefly remembered for the beauty of his character, his tender and
                    mystic devotion, and the charm of his style as a writer. He is not great as a
                    thinker, nor can the substance of his writings be said to have a permanent
                    value. But there is the same subtle delicacy, sensibility, and tenderness and
                    purity of expression in his style as in his character. An exquisite highly-toned
                    and noble genius pervade the one and the other. As a man he is one of the
                    greatest figures in a great time. As a writer he has been placed in prose on the
                    same level with Racine in poetry. In both there is the same full harmony and
                    clearness, the same combination of natural grace with perfect art.</p>
                <p>In addition to the works of Fénelon already noticed, the following deserve to be
                    mentioned -The <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi><hi rend="italic">des Morts,
                    composés</hi><hi rend="italic">pour Γ</hi><hi rend="italic">Éducation
                    d’un</hi><hi rend="italic">Prince,</hi> 1712; <hi rend="italic">Dialogues sur
                    V</hi><hi rend="italic">Éloquence,</hi> &amp;c., 1718; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lettres</hi><hi rend="italic">sur divers sujets concernant</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">la religion</hi><hi rend="italic">et la métaphysique,</hi> 1718;
                    <hi rend="italic">Traité d VExistence de Dieu,</hi> &amp;c., 1713. There are
                    many collected editions of his works. That of Leclerc (Paris, 1827-1830), 38
                    small vols., is the latest. An excellent life of Fénelon has recently appeared
                    in English (1877) by the same author as the <hi rend="italic">Life of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Bossuet</hi> mentioned under that article. (J. T.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
