<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0519-0488-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FOURCROY, Antoine François, Comte de (9th edition,
                    volume 9, page 488)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136041">Students</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817519">Artisans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19s90">Students</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w950p9z">Chemists</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n519/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FOURCROY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Antoine François, Comte
                            de</hi></label> (1755- 1809), a celebrated chemist, son of an apothecary
                    in the household of the duke of Orleans, was born at Paris, June 15, 1755. Some
                    of his ancestors had been distinguished at the bar, but the branch of the family
                    to which he belonged had become greatly reduced in circumstances. At the age of
                    fourteen Fourcroy left the college at Harcourt, where he had profited but little
                    by the instruction of a harsh teacher. Deterred by the ill-success of a friend
                    from going upon the stage, he for two years maintained himself as a copyist and
                    writing-master; he then, in consequence of unjust treatment there received, left
                    the office of his employer. At this juncture, Vicq d’Azyr, who having boarded at
                    his home had become acquainted with the young man’s talents, encouraged him to
                    enter upon a medical career. ,We accordingly now behold Fourcroy a poor and
                    hard-working student of medicine, his lodging a garret, in the middle only of
                    which was it possible to stand upright, and his near neighbour a water-carrier,
                    to whose family of twelve he acted as physician, receiving for his services a
                    good supply of water. To support himself he gave lessons to other students, and
                    made translations for a bookseller, who, 30 years later, when Fourcroy had
                    become director-general of public instruction, conscientiously offered to make
                    up for the meagreness of his former remuneration. In 1777, under the auspices of
                    the Société Royale de Médecine, appeared Fourcroy’s first publication, <hi
                        rend="italic">Essai sur</hi><hi rend="italic">les Maladies des
                        Artisans,</hi> the translation of a Latin work by Ramazzini, with notes and
                    additions. At length Fourcroy, who was recognized as the most successful alumnus
                    of the Parisian medical school, became an applicant for a gratuitous degree and
                    licence, provision for the granting of which to the best deserving poor student
                    had been made by the bequest of a Dr Diest. It so happened that the faculty of
                    physic at Paris entertained feelings of the most jealous enmity against the
                    newly-founded Société Royale de Médecine, of which Vicq d’Azyr was perpetual
                    secretary, and to humiliate him, and in him the whole society, it rejected his
                    protégé Fourcroy.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n520/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0520-0489"/>
                <p>Upon this the society itself subscribed the fees requisite for a diploma (£250),
                    which was obtained by Fourcroy in 1780; but as the degree of “docteur regent”
                    was unanimously refused, it was impossible for him to procure any professorship
                    under the faculty. However, in 1784 his reputation as a chemist gained for him,
                    although Berthollet was his fellow candidate, the lectureship of chemistry at
                    the college of the Jardin du Roi, which had become vacant by the death of
                    Macquer, one of the last of the phlogistic school. This post he continued to
                    hold for the next 25 years; and so great were the crowds which his eloquence
                    attracted that it was twice necessary to enlarge his lecture-theatre. Fourcroy
                    was one of the first converts to the theories of Lavoisier, which he designated
                    “La Chimie Française,” a name which, as Thomson remarks <hi rend="italic"
                        >(History of Chemistry,</hi> ii. ρ. 130), “certainly contributed more than
                    anything else to give the new notions currency, at least in France.” Together
                    with Berthollet, Fourcroy was associated with Lavoisier and Guyton de Morveau in
                    1786 and 1787 in the preparation of a work entitled <hi rend="italic">Methode de
                        Nomenclature</hi><hi rend="italic">Chimique,</hi> published in the latter
                    year. In 1785 a memoir on the tendons, subsequently completed in six parts,
                    gained for him admission into the French Academy of Sciences. He became in 1792
                    one of the deputies of the National Convention, and in 1793 a member of the
                    Assembly, and soon proved himself one of the most active of the committee for
                    the public instruction. To him was due the enlargement of the Jardin des
                    Plantes, and the formation of a commission for the preservation of works of art.
                    He further was the means of releasing from imprisonment Desault, surgeon of the
                    Hôtel-Dieu, and of preventing the execution of Darcet, though, unfortunately for
                    science, he found no opportunity of rescuing Lavoisier. On the 9th of Thermidor
                    he was appointed a member of the committee for the public safety, and in this
                    capacity he instituted three schools of medicine, assisted in the organization
                    of the École Polytechnique (at that time the École des Travaux Publiques), and
                    was concerned also in the establishment of the École Normale, the Institut, and
                    the Musée d’Histoire Naturelle. After the revolution of the 9th November 1799 he
                    was made a councillor of state; and, being appointed director-general of
                    instruction, he in the course of 5 years superintended the formation of 12
                    schools of law, over 30 lyceums, afterwards called royal colleges, and 300
                    elementary schools. His incessant labours at length told on his health, and he
                    suffered greatly from palpitation of the heart. On the 16th December 1809, the
                    very day on which by letters patent he had been created a count of the French
                    empire, with a yearly pension of 20,000 francs, he was signing some despatches
                    when he suddenly exclaimed “Je suis mort,” and with those words expired.</p>
                <p>Among the separate publications of Fourcroy are <hi rend="italic">Leçons
                        élémentaires</hi><hi rend="italic">d'Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >naturelle, et de Chimie,</hi><hi rend="italic">2</hi> vols. 8vo, 1782,
                    enlarged, after several editions, to 10 vols. 8vo, with the title <hi
                        rend="italic">Système</hi><hi rend="italic">des</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Connaissances chimiques,</hi> 6 vols. 4to, 1801-2; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mémoires et Observations de Chimie,</hi> 8vo, 1784; <hi rend="italic">L'Art
                        de connaître et Remployer les Médicamens dans les Maladies,</hi> 2 vols.
                    8vo, 1785; <hi rend="italic">Essai sur le Phlogistique et les Acides,</hi> 8vo,
                    1788, from the English of Kirwan, with notes by De Morveau and De Fourcroy; <hi
                        rend="italic">Philosophie Chimique, ou Vérités fondamentales de la Chimie
                        moderne,</hi> 8vo, 1795, perhaps his best work, of which several editions
                    and translations appeared; <hi rend="italic">Notice</hi><hi rend="italic">sur
                        la</hi><hi rend="italic">Vie</hi><hi rend="italic">et les Travaux</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de Lavoisier,</hi> 8vo, 1796; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Tableaux</hi><hi rend="italic">synoptiques de Chimie,</hi> 4to, 1800; <hi
                        rend="italic">Discours sur l'instruction publique,</hi> 8vo, 1802. He was
                    the author of more than 160 papers on chemical subjects, contributed to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> of the Academy and the Institute, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Annales de Chimie,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Annales</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Musée d Histoire
                        Naturelle,</hi> and was editor of <hi rend="italic">Le Médecin Éclairé.</hi>
                    The more important of his later researches were published jointly in his own
                    name and that of Vanquelin, whom he befriended, and was the means of first
                    bringing into notice.</p>
                <p>See Palissot de Beauvois, <hi rend="italic">Éloge Historique,</hi> 1810; G.
                    Cuvier, “Éloge His-todque," <hi rend="italic">Mém. de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >ΓInst.,</hi> 1810. pp. xcvi.-cxxviii., and <hi rend="italic">Ann.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Mus.</hi><hi rend="italic">Hist. Nat.,</hi> xvii. 1811, pp.
                    99-132; Thomson, <hi rend="italic">Anna's,</hi> i., 1818</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
