<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0041-0032-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FAREL, Guillaume</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 32</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x59s">Calvinism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p527">Basel</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:844591">Calvinism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1149517">Theologians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1156290">Trials</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1025507">Monks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n41/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FAREL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Guillaume</hi></label>
                    (1489-1565), a celebrated French Reformer, was born near Gap in Dauphiny in
                    1489. He was of noble descent, and it was the wish of his parents that he should
                    adopt the military profession, but the pursuit of knowledge proved so attractive
                    to him that he characteristically determined to have his own way, and succeeded
                    in obtaining permission to enter the university of Paris. Here he became the
                    intimate friend of Jacobus Faber (Stapulensis), from whom in all probability he
                    imbibed his first doubts regarding many of the usages and customs of the Roman
                    Catholic Church. Through the introduction of Faber he was appointed professor to
                    the college of Cardinal Lemoine, but not long afterwards, on the invitation of
                    Bishop Briçonnet, he went to Meaux to assist Faber and others in preaching the
                    doctrine of the Reformation. He was, however, compelled to leave France by the
                    outbreak of the persecution of 1523, and went to Basel, where, in 1524, he
                    defended the Reformation doctrines in a public disputation with great ability,
                    but with such acrimonious keenness that Erasmus sided with the opponents of the
                    Reformation in requiring his expulsion from the city. From Basel he went to
                    Strasburg, and thence, on the invitation of the duke of Würtemberg, to
                    Montbéliard, where he preached for a time with great success; but since, as
                    usual, he forgot to temper his zeal with discretion, he was compelled to leave
                    the town in the spring of 1525. He shortly afterwards began his Reformation
                    crusade at Aigle in Switzerland, and notwithstanding the strenuous opposition of
                    the monks, he, in 1528, obtained permission from the authorities to preach in
                    any place within the canton of Bern. He also extended his itineracies to the
                    cantons of Neufchâtel and Vaud, and although often seriously maltreated by the
                    mobs whom he provoked by his violent invectives, continued his crusade in these
                    districts with unabated zeal till 1531, when increasing manifestations of
                    hostility rendered it imperative that he should seek another sphere for his
                    labours. In that year, accordingly, he paid a short visit to the Waldenses,
                    after which he went to Geneva, where he began to hold meetings of the Reformers
                    in his private house. On this account he was summoned to appear before the
                    bishop’s vicar, and after being frequently insulted and threatened, during the
                    progress of his trial, by the monks and canons, who drowned his defence by their
                    clamour, he was rudely and violently pushed out of the court, and was commanded
                    to leave the town within three hours. Escaping with great difficulty from the
                    fury of his opponents, he went by sea to Orbe. In 1533, however, he returned to
                    Geneva under the protection of the Government of Bern, and so successful were
                    his sermons and his public disputations that in August 1535 the town renounced
                    the authority of the pope, and the simple worship of the Reformation was
                    instituted in the churches. About this time Calvin visited Geneva, and
                    Farel—whose superabounding zeal seems to have exercised a kind of spell over the
                    calmer spirit of the great theologian-—prevailed on him to give up all thoughts
                    of a life of quiet study, and to devote himself to the cause of the Reformation
                    in Geneva. Leaving Geneva to the care of Calvin, Farel returned to his work of
                    itinerant preaching, chiefly in Neufchâtel, where, although the violent
                    hostility of the priests and women showed no signs of diminution, he attracted
                    large audiences, and gained a considerable number of adherents. At intervals he
                    visited Geneva, over whose ecclesiastical affairs he seems to have exercised a
                    kind of supervision; but the strictness of his doctrines and discipline
                    gradually provoked the opposition of many of the inhabitants, and in 1538 he and
                    Calvin were banished from the town. Farel went to Strasburg, and afterwards, in
                    1542, to Metz, where he laboured with his usual energy and want of discretion,
                    and with the usual mingled results. In 1541 Calvin was permitted to return to
                    Geneva, and although Farel visited the town only at long intervals, he seems to
                    have been consulted by Calvin in all important matters. When the trial of
                    Servetus was in progress Farel was earnestly entreated by Calvin to be present
                    before the case was finally decided, but he did not arrive until after the
                    sentence of condemnation had been passed. He, however, accompanied the unhappy
                    man to the place of execution, and continued until the last moment his
                    exhortations to him to renounce his errors. About 1558 Farel married a young
                    girl, and the marriage was the occasion of a quarrel between him and Calvin.
                    Farel continued his labours with unabated zeal and vigour till 1565. In that
                    year he visited Metz, where he had an enthusiastic reception, and preached with
                    all his old fire and eloquence; but after returning to the house where he was
                    residing, he was overpowered by exhaustion, from which he never rallied, dying
                    on the 13th September. Farel wrote a considerable number of works, but as these
                    were all thrown off in haste, and merely for a temporary purpose, it is scarcely
                    fair to make them the criterion by which to estimate his powers as a thinker or
                    theologian. His nature was, however, rather practical than meditative, the most
                    remarkable features of his character being his dauntlessness and his untiring
                    energy and zeal, in which respects he is perhaps to be ranked second to none of
                    the Reformers with the exception of Luther, if he is to be considered second
                    even to him. He possessed all but the greatest qualities of an orator, a
                    sonorous and tuneful voice, appropriate gesture, fluency of language, and
                    passionate earnestness. But although seldom failing to awaken the attention and
                    interest of his large audiences, he often, by imprudent torrents of denunciation
                    aroused against his doctrines unnecessary opposition; and it would be difficult
                    to determine whether, on the whole, the cause of the Reformation gained or lost
                    by his advocacy. A monument to Farel was unveiled at Neufchâtel on the 4th of
                    May 1876.</p>
                <p>SeeAncillon, <hi rend="italic">Vie de Guillauιne Farel, Amsteτ. ^1B91;</hi>
                    Kirchhof er, <hi rend="italic">Das Leben Wilhelm Farel's,</hi> 2 vols., Zurich,
                    1831-33; Schmidt, <hi rend="italic">Études</hi><hi rend="italic">sur Farel,</hi>
                    Stras. 1834; and Schmidt, <hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Farel and Peter</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Viret,</hi> Elberfeld, 1860.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
