<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0733-0698-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FRANCISCANS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 698</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:875210">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1041386">Nuns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:935118">Friars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:996188">Lent</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:797427">Advent</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:877187">Convents</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1119758">Sisters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v395">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pn9b">Advent</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4154ds5t">Friars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41g0hw2j">Capuchins</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kq6z">Nuns</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4057cr7r">Convents</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0mz4b">Conventions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n733/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FRANCISCANS</label>. The Franciscan orders include the three
                    orders of the Minorites, and all the less important associations who trace their
                    rule to Francis of Assisi. The three orders of the Minorites, or Franciscans
                    proper, include (1) the Minorite friars, properly so-called, under a succession
                    of generals of the whole order from the foundation; (2) the order of the Poor
                    Ladies or Poor Clares—the Franciscan nuns; (3) the order of Penitent Men and
                    Women, which includes (a) all those who dwell in Franciscan cloisters and keep
                    the third rule, (δ) those who live in cloisters of their own, keeping the third
                    rule, and (c) the Tertiaries properly so-called. All these three orders of
                    Friars, Nuns, and Tertiaries are more or less under the jurisdiction of the
                    general-minister of the Franciscan order.</p>
                <p>I. The Minorite friars, or the first order, are divided into two “families,”
                    Cismontana, or convents in Italy, Germany, Hungary, Poland, Syria, and
                    Palestine, and Ultramontana, or convents in France, Spain, the Low Countries,
                    Saxony, the Islands of the Mediterranean, Africa, Asia, and the Indies—the one
                    ruled directly by the minister-general, and the other by a commissary-general.
                    Each family is divided into provinces ruled over by a provincial. The Cismontane
                    has sixty-six provinces, and the Ultramontane has eighty-one. A province is the
                    union of a certain number of convents under a chief directly responsible to the
                    minister-general. Besides provinces the order originally contained <hi
                    rend="italic">vicarates</hi> and <hi rend="italic">custodia.</hi> The vicarates
                    were a number of convents united together, but too few to be counted a province.
                    The custodia were at first subdivisions of provinces, but since Leo X. the
                    custodia are like the old vicarates, and are governed by a vicar or custos
                    directly responsible to the minister-general. The convents of the order <hi
                    rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">partibus infidelium</hi> are governed by
                    prefects. The minister-general is chosen in full chapter for a term of six
                    years, and if he dies or removes to a higher office during his term, the
                    “discreet perpetual fathers” choose a deputy for the remainder of the term. The
                    minister-general is chosen from the two families alternately, and the chapter at
                    the same time elects a commissary-general for the other family.</p>
                <p>The rule originally prescribed by St Francis was very strict, and, rigidly
                    enforced, would have made all the members of the order pious beggars. This was
                    the founder’s idea, but when the order became popular it was found that few of
                    its members could act up to its requirements; and even in the life-time of the
                    founder attempts were made to relax them. The relaxations sanctioned by the
                    decrees of popes and by general usage were repeatedly fought against by small
                    but zealous minorities, and these struggles gave rise to various divisions in
                    the order. Since the time of Leo X. and his union bull these divisions have been
                    reduced to three,—the Observants, the Conventuals, and the Capuchins,—all of
                    whom belong to the first order of the Franciscans; and they are the survivals of
                    a much more numerous division. The Observants are supposed to keep the rule of
                    Francis with some strictness, and they take the first rank among the
                    Franciscans; their minister-general has pre-eminence. The Conventuals follow the
                    rule of Francis with certain relaxations permitted by successive popes. Their
                    general has to be confirmed by the great ministergeneral, but otherwise they are
                    independent. Since 1528 the Capuchins have had an independent general under the
                    minister-general.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">The Observants.—</hi> The relaxation of the rule of Francis
                    and attempts at reformation to the original simplicity and strictness date from
                    the time of Elias, successor as ministergeneral to Francis himself. Some of
                    these reforms were unsuccessful, and only resulted in small schisms condemned by
                    the general and by the pope; others were successful, and resulted in the
                    formation of separate congregations more or less independent, until they were
                    all abolished or rather brought together under one rule by Leo X. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Ccesarins</hi> were the followers of Caesarinus of Spires, who
                    revolted against the relaxations and innovations of Elias. After varying
                    fortunes the reformers were punished as rebels. They gradually returned to the
                    ranks of the order, and ceased to exist separately in 1256. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Celestines</hi> were the followers of Peter of Macerata, who
                    called himself Liberatus, and Peter of Fossombrone, called Angelus, from his
                    frequent fellowship with angels. They taught and professed a life of the
                    strictest poverty and solitude, and were permitted to live separately from the
                    rest of the order by Pope Celestine V. in 1294. The permission was recalled by
                    later popes, and after many struggles the Celestine hermits were reckoned
                    schismatics and heretics (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Celestines).</hi> From them
                    came the Fratricelli (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Fratricelli).</hi> The <hi
                    rend="italic">Congrégation</hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Narbonne,</hi> the Spirituales, were mainly followers of Peter John de Oliva.
                    They <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n734/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0734-0699"/> were really a branch of the Celestines settled at
                    Narbonne; but their special grievances were that their laxer brethren did not
                    wear the clothes prescribed by Francis,— their robes were too long and too rich,
                    and their hoods too large,—and that they accepted presents of wine and corn
                    during the vintage and harvest. After some struggles they forced on a
                    controversy in 1282, and were finally condemned by John XXII. at Vienna in 1312.
                    They refused to submit, and were pronounced schismatic in 1318. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Clarenins</hi> were a revival, in 1302, of the Celestine hermits
                    under Angelus of Cordova. They fought for recognition and existence down to
                    1581. The <hi rend="italic">Congregation of Philip of Majorca</hi> arose in
                    1308. They were refused recognition, but struggled on only to disappear among
                    the fanatical schismatics of the period. The reform of John of Vallées and
                    Gentilis of Spoleto was occasioned by a further relaxation of the rule in 1336,
                    sanctioned by Pope Benedict XII. Their fight for existence lasted almost forty
                    years.</p>
                <p>These six attempts to return to the original rule of St Francis, and to follow in
                    the letter and spirit his principles of a religious life, were all unsuccessful.
                    The historians of the order ascribe the failures to the rashness of the
                    reformers or their followers, but the real cause was the utter incompatibility
                    of the rule of Francis with social life in any form. Any thorough-going return
                    to the primitive rule was impossible, but many partial reforms were attempted.
                    The aim of each reformer was to reconstruct the society, or at least to found a
                    small society, which would be so independent of the rules and officials of the
                    Franciscan order as to be free from interference with their endeavours to obey
                    the rule of Francis in their own way. Some of these reforms achieved a very
                    considerable degree of independence, and lasted for a long time. They were all,
                    nominally at least, brought under the common government of the order by the
                    famous union bull of Pope Leo X. Of these reforms the most important are the
                    following :—</p>
                <p>The Soccolantes (named from wearing a wooden sandal), were founded by Paul of
                    Foligny in 1368, noted from his fourteenth year for his enthusiastic piety. This
                    is the most important, because it started with the principles of the earlier
                    unsuccessful reforms, and succeeded because it professed unconditional
                    submission to the pope. Paul and his companions showed all the idiosyncracies of
                    Francis their cells were full of frogs, and their beds of serpents; they
                    rejoiced in ill health, and nausea at the sight of food was esteemed a sign of
                    the complete mortification of the body. They obtained permission, and retained
                    it against many attempts at deprivation, to live in independence of the ordinary
                    officials of the order. Their reform became successful and spread, and when Leo
                    X. issued his bull of union they were sufficiently numerous to impose their name
                    <hi rend="italic">(Observantes)</hi> on one of the great divisions of the
                    reorganized order. At the first they held disputations with the Fratricelli and
                    Beghards regarding the principles of Francis, for these heretics witlι great
                    justice declared that they were more true to the Christian ideal of Francis than
                    the professed followers of the saint. The only argument the Observants could
                    adduce against their opponents was that Francis had made unconditional
                    submission to the pope part of his ideal.</p>
                <p>The congregation of Villacrezes was founded by Peter of Villacrezes, in the
                    convent of Our Lady of Salceda in Castile, about 1390. His principles were very
                    like those of Paul of Foligny, but were even more strictly enforced. The
                    brethren were obliged to wear the scantiest and coarsest raiment, and to content
                    themselves with the barest necessaries of life. The independence of the
                    congregation was finally secured at the council of Constance. <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Cf.</hi> Mendoza, <hi rend="italic">Hist. del Monte Celia de nuestra Señora de
                    la Salcedal)</hi></p>
                <p>The Congregation of Collette, from the nun Collette, is noticed below.</p>
                <p>The Congregation founded by Amadeus of Assisi obtained independence in 1469 and
                    1471; it was never very strong, laboured under suspicion of heresy, refused to
                    submit to the bull of Leo X., and was finally suppressed by Pius V.</p>
                <p>The Congregation of Philip Berbegal took its rise from attempts of Martin V. to
                    reform the order in 1430. Nominally suppressed in 1433, it reappeared under
                    another name (the Neutrals), obtained recognition, but was finally suppressed in
                    1463.</p>
                <p>The Caperolani, or followers of Peter Caperole, were for a short time
                    independent, and then were reunited with the Observants. Two famous preachers,
                    Anthony of Castel St Jean and Matthew of Tivoli, held out and gathered around
                    them a new congregation, which for long refused to submit itself to the
                    order.</p>
                <p>More important, however, than any of these reforms, save the first, were the
                    series of national reformatory movements within the order, which produced in
                    Spain the Bare-footed Friars under the leadership of John of Guadaloupe, in
                    Italy the Riformati led by Stephen Molina, and in France the Récollets. These
                    congregations arose to emlκ&gt;dy the reforms suggested by John of Puebla, and
                    survived Leo’s bull of union. Lapse of time brought relaxations, and these led
                    again to a reaction which produced the reform of Peter of Alcantara, who named
                    his fellows The Brethren of the Strictest Observance. Peter obtained a species
                    of independence for his convents. They were under the rule of the general of the
                    order, but not of the provincials. From this congregation arose a further reform
                    under John of Paschase and Jerome of Lanza, which, after some years of
                    independent life, reunited with the congregation of Peter of Alcantara.</p>
                <p>Most of these reforms were brought together by the bull of Leo X., and are merged
                    under the general name of Observants.</p>
                <p>2. The <hi rend="italic">Conventuals</hi> included, at the time of Leo X., all
                    the Franciscans who kept the rule in a relaxed form, and had not been influenced
                    by the various attempts at reformation. They claimed to be <hi rend="italic"
                    >the</hi> Franciscan order, and in fact at the time were so. Now they are only
                    one of the great divisions of the order. An attempt was made after the council
                    of Trent to reform the Conventuals, and a congregation of Reformed Conventuals
                    was founded, but it did not exist very long.</p>
                <p>3. The <hi rend="italic">Capuchins</hi> exist as an independent congregation, and
                    do not take rank with the Observants and Conventuals. They owe their origin to
                    Matthew of Bassi, a Franciscan of the family of Observance, who had
                    conscientious scruples about the shape of his hood or capuce. It was revealed to
                    him in visions that St Francis had worn a long pointed hood, and he began to
                    wear one of the revealed pattern. Others began to copy it. They were persecuted
                    by their fellows, strove for freedom, and at length got it. In 1536 Paul III.
                    formally recognized them under the title of Capuchins of the order of the
                    Minorites, but ordained that their vicar-general or chief was to be confirmed by
                    the general of the Conventuals, and that they were to march under the cross of
                    the Conventual Minorites in religious processions. In 1619 Paul V. removed these
                    restrictions. They now have their own cross and choose their own chief quite
                    independently, and he is called general, not vicargeneral. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Capuchins.</hi></p>
                <p>II. The Franciscan nuns owed their origin to Clara, a noble maiden of Assisi.
                    Born in 1193, she left her home iu 1212, fled to the Portiuncula to Francis, and
                    refused to return. The same year she gathered a company of ladies, including her
                    three younger sisters, and founded the order of Franciscan nuns. The order
                    spread rapidly through Italy, France, Spain, Germany, and Bohemia. In 1220
                    Cardinal Ilugolin gave them a rule of life taken from the rule for the strictest
                    sect of the Benedictine nuns, with some special observances. Four years later
                    Francis gave them a •written rule, which was approved of by Gregory IX. and by
                    Innocent IV.</p>
                <p>The rule of Hugolin compelled the nuns among other things to fast every day, to
                    abstain at all seasons on Wednesdays and Fridays from wine and soup, and to
                    content themselves on those days with some fruits or raw herbs, to fast also on
                    bread and water thrice a week during Lent and twice during Advent. They were
                    also to keep perpetual silence, to be broken only by the permission of the
                    superior. They were to wear two tunics, a mantle and scapulary, besides a hair
                    shirt. The rule of Francis was not so strict; he did not oblige them to fast on
                    bread and water during certain seasons, and there were other relaxations. These
                    two rules gave rise to disputes and divisions, and Pope Urban IV. gave the
                    sisters a third rule which was less strict than either. The result was that
                    several convents adhered to the first and strictest rule; that of the reform <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n735/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0735-0700"/> of Collette, a French sister, adhered to the
                    second rule, that of Francis; while the large proportion of the nuns followed
                    the new rule of Urban.</p>
                <p>The Capuchin movement within the Franciscan order also affected the Minorite
                    nuns, and the Capuchin nuns soon became a large and prosperous community. The
                    only other important reform was that set in motion by Peter of Alcantara. The
                    sisters who followed him are called the Poor Clares of the Strictest Observance.
                    They take the vow of perpetual silence.</p>
                <p>ÎII. The Tertiaries consist of lay brethren and sisters in the Franciscan
                    monasteries, confraternities who keep the third rule of St Francis, and men and
                    women living in society who have taken the third rule. The Tertiaries of the
                    begging monks have become so famous that many are disposed to trace their origin
                    to Francis and Dominic, but the class of penitents existed in connexion with
                    other and older orders. The third rule was intended to suit the requirements of
                    all those who wished to live a higher religious life, and who could not from
                    their circumstances embrace the monastic life. It is said that the origin of the
                    Franciscan Tertiaries dates from Francis preaching at Canari, a small town near
                    Assisi, where the whole population wished <hi rend="italic">en</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">masse</hi> to enter the Franciscan order and desert their life and
                    duties in society. Francis refused to permit this, but to assist them framed a
                    third rule to serve as a religious guide. Its provisions resemble the rules
                    commonly found in pious books with which the present ritualistic movement has
                    made us familiar, and the associations of Tertiaries may be compared with the
                    guilds now found in connexion with many High Church congregations. These
                    Tertiaries believed that they were imitating not Christ but his early disciples;
                    they had to spend some time in novitiate, and then vowed obedience to the third
                    rule, which enjoined that they were to wear poor clothing of an unobtrusive
                    colour, without worldly ornament of any kind. It forbade them to bear arms save
                    for the defence of the church or their country. It prohibited attendance at
                    fêtes, balls, dancing parties, and the theatre. It forbade meat on Monday,
                    Wednesday, Friday, and Saturday. It enjoined fasting at Lent and Advent, and at
                    other times only two meals a-day. The hours of devotion and the devotional
                    exercises were prescribed. Tertiaries were bound to attend mass and preaching at
                    least once a month, to go to confession and holy communion at least thrice a
                    year, and to attend the funerals of their fellows. This third order was very
                    successful, but it is worth noticing that the common people, after the first
                    burst of enthusiasm, seemed unable to distinguish the Tertiaries from the
                    Fratricelli and Beghards, who professed a somewhat similar mode of life, and had
                    been condemned by various popes.</p>
                <p>At some period of their existence, when it is difficult to say, many of the
                    Tertiaries began to practise the monastic life, and to take the vow of chastity
                    in addition to the third rule. Convents of the third rule were in existence in
                    the 15th century, and in 1433 brethren living under this rule were permitted to
                    choose a general. The earlier bulls permitting such confraternities were at
                    first generally addressed to penitents living in particular countries, and the
                    divisions of the brethren take generally a local name. There were, for example,
                    the religious penitents of the third order of St Francis of the regular
                    observance in Italy, in Sicily, Dalmatia, and Istria, and in the Low Countries;
                    these three were united in the congregation of Lombardy. There were besides the
                    congregations of Germany, Spain, Portugal, and France. Congregations were also
                    formed to observe the rule with complete and literal strictness. The Tertiaries
                    included women as well as men, and these also began to take a special vow of
                    chastity and live in cloisters. O∏e branch of these includes the lay sisters in
                    the ordinary convents of the Poor Clares, who devote themselves to menial work.
                    Their foundress was Elizabeth of Hungary. Another branch was founded by Angeline
                    of Corbaro, and has convents of its own. There are also the Grey Sisters, the
                    Recollectines, and several other congregations, who live in cloisters under
                    regular government, but practise the third and not the second rule. From the
                    beginning of the move-/ ment the Tertiaries were charged to take special care of
                    the poor, the sick, and the aged; and several confraternities, both of men and
                    of women, have been formed, who live under the third rule, and devote themselves
                    to hospital work.</p>
                <p>Besides these three orders of Friars, Nuns, and Tertiaries, the Franciscans may
                    also be said to include one or two orders of minor importance which trace their
                    origin to Francis,—such, for example, as the Chevaliers of the Order of the
                    Immaculate Conception of the Blessed Virgin, and the Archiconfraternity of the
                    Stigmata of St Francis, but they are of minor importance.</p>
                <p>The Franciscan soon became one of the most important of the mediaeval monastic
                    orders. It had a peculiar character, and attracted minds of the sympathetic
                    mystical cast. This led to its curious connexion with many of the mediaeval
                    heretical sects. The Franciscan theology was also peculiar. It had the same
                    Pelagian characteristics that distinguish the modern Jesuit theology, which has
                    done little more than develop the Franciscan ideas on the immaculate conception,
                    the doctrines of freedom and grace, &amp;c. During the Middle Ages the
                    Franciscans, however, furnished many strong opponents to the papal theology and
                    ecclesiastical claims. The order has produced a long array of distinguished
                    theologians and churchmen,—Bonaventura, Alexander of Hales, John Duns Scotus,
                    and William of Occam were all Franciscans. Wadding, the great historian of the
                    Franciscans, has filled a folio volume with names of distinguished members of
                    the order.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—</hi> Wadding, <hi rend="italic">Annales
                    Minorum,</hi> 22 vols, fol., and Brother Anthony’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Supplement</hi>; Tossinian, <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Scraphica;</hi> Dominic de Gubernatis, <hi rend="italic">Orbis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Seraphicus</hi>; Helyot, <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des</hi><hi rend="italic">Ordres Monastiques,</hi> vol. vii.;
                    Marianus, <hi rend="italic">Chronic. Obscrv.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Strictior,</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Reform.</hi>;
                    Boverius, <hi rend="italic">Annal. Fr. F.</hi><hi rend="italic">Min.
                    Capucinorum</hi>; Brewer’s <hi rend="italic">Monumenta</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Franciscana</hi>; Hase, <hi rend="italic">Franz v. Assisi,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ein Heiligenbild,</hi> 1864; Mrs Oliphant’s <hi rend="italic">Life
                    of Francis of Assisi</hi>; Maclear’s <hi rend="italic">History of Christian
                    Missions in the Middle Ages</hi> (where the mission work of St Francis has been
                    well described, chap. 16); Mrs Jameson’s <hi rend="italic">Legends of the
                    Monastic Orders as represented in the Fine Arts;</hi> Milman’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Latin Christianity,</hi> bk. ix. chap. 9. (T. Μ. L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
