<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0049-0040-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FARQUHAR, George</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 40</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nz3s">Hunting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2td33">Goldsmithing</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47659k3h">Goldsmiths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cc21">Coaches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fb1j">Archers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:964162">Hunting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:944605">Goldsmiths</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:963738">Humorists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n49/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FARQUHAR, <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi></label>
                    (1678-1707), a dramatist of the last century, the successor in comedy of
                    Wycherley and Congreve, was the son of a clergyman, and was born in Londonderry,
                    Ireland, in the year 1678. In his sixteenth year he was sent to Trinity College,
                    Dublin, under the patronage of the bishop of Dromore. He was entered as a sizar
                    or servitor, a class of poor scholars, who were compelled to wear a peculiar
                    dress and perform menial offices. These are no longer exacted from their
                    successors, but Goldsmi th, sixty years after the date of Farquhar’s admission,
                    had to submit to the humiliations incident to the position of a sizer—to sweep
                    part of the college courts, to carry up the fellows’ dinner to table, and to
                    wait in the hall till the fellows had dined. It certainly implied a
                    contradiction, as Goldsmith observed, for men to be “at once learning the
                    liberal arts, and at the same time treated as slaves,” and neither in the case
                    of Farquhar nor of Goldsmith was the system attended with favourable results.
                    The former soon broke away from his studies, and appeared as an actor on the
                    Dublin stage. He had the advantage of a good person, though with a weak voice,
                    but was timid and sensitive, and an accident which happened to him when he had
                    only been about a twelvemonth on the boards made him resolve to quit the
                    profession. When performing the part of Guyomar in Dryden’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Indian Emperor</hi> he had omitted to exchange his sword for a foil, and in a
                    fencing scene wounded a brother performer so severely that his life was
                    despaired of. The sufferer recovered, but Farquhar would never again return to
                    the stage. The earl of Orrery gave him a lieutenancy in his regiment then in
                    Ireland, and as a soldier Farquhar is said to have given proofs of his courage
                    and conduct, though none are recorded. We have two letters written by him in
                    Holland in 1700, but in these he says nothing of military service. While yet a
                    minor he appeared as a dramatist. His comedy of <hi rend="italic">Love and a
                    Bottle</hi> was performed at Drury Lane in 1698, and its success far exceeded
                    his expectations. His next comedy, <hi rend="italic">The Constant Couple</hi>
                    (1700), was still more favourably received. Wilks, a popular comedian and a
                    special friend of Farquhar’s (they had been associates in Dublin), by his
                    performance of the part of Sir Harry Wildair contributed very much to the
                    success of the play. “He <hi rend="italic">made</hi> the part,” says Farquhar.
                    In the following year the dramatist brought out a sequel to it, entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Sir Harry Wildair.</hi> Wilks’s acting was again attractive, but
                    like all continuations (that of Don Quixote excepted) the second part was much
                    inferior to the first. Leigh Hunt has stated that Mrs Oldfield, like Wilks,
                    performed to admiration in this piece, but Mrs Oldfield was not the original
                    heroine (Lady Lurewell). The part was acted by Mrs Verbruggen. Mrs Oldfield
                    performed in the two last and best of Farquhar’s seven comedies, and is said to
                    have taken to the stage by his advice. She was the theatrical idol—the Mrs
                    Jordan—of her day. Her exquisite acting and lady-like carriage were the delight
                    of her contemporaries, and her beauty, her vanity, and her generosity found
                    innumerable eulogists—</p>
                <p>“Engaging Oldfield, who, with grace and ease, Could join the arts to ruin and to
                    please.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Pope— <hi
                    rend="italic">Sober Advice from Horace.</hi> It was to this fascinating actress
                    that the satirist alluded as the lady who detested being buried in woollen, and
                    said to her attendant—</p><p>“One would not sure be frightful when one’s
                    dead—</p><p>And—Betty—give this cheek a little red."</p><p>She was only
                    forty-seven when she died, leaving all the court and half the town in
                    tears.</p></note></p>
                <p>In 1702 Farquhar published a trifling volume of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Miscellanies—</hi> poems, letters, and a discourse on comedy. The poems are
                    below mediocrity, and the letters are written in that overstrained style of
                    gallantry and smartness which was then fashionable and considered witty. In one
                    letter he gives a lady a picture of himself “drawn from the life.” His mind, he
                    says, was generally dressed, like his person, in black; he was taken for an
                    easy-natured man by his own sex, and an ill-natured clown by the ladies;
                    strangers had a worse opinion of him than he deserved, but this was recompensed
                    by the opinion of his acquaintance, which was above his desert. Self-portraiture
                    is seldom faithful, but we may conclude from Farquhar’s outline, that the young
                    dramatist was somewdiat grave and reserved, and wanted address for general
                    society. He was liveliest with the pen in his hand. The discourse on comedy is
                    more worthy of the author than his poems or letters. In it he defends the
                    English disregard of the dramatic unities. “The rules of English comedy,” he
                    says, “don’t lie in the compass of Aristotle or his followers, but in the pit,
                    box, and galleries.” In 1703 Farquhar had another comedy on the stage— <hi
                    rend="italic">The Inconstant, or the way to win him—</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
                    >hint</hi> of which he says, he took from Fletcher’s <hi rend="italic">Wild
                    Goose Chase,</hi> but was charged with spoiling the original. The poetry of
                    Fletcher certainly evaporates when its scenes are transmuted into the prose
                    dialogue of Farquhar.</p>
                <p>About this time the dramatist was betrayed into what was perhaps the greatest
                    blunder of his life. A lady conceived a violent passion for him, and, though
                    penniless like himself, contrived to circulate a report that she was possessed
                    of a large fortune. Farquhar snapped at the gilded bait. He married the lady,
                    and found too late that he had been deceived. It is related, however, that he
                    had the magnanimity to pardon a deception which must <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n50/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0050-0041"/> have appeared a compliment to his genius, and in
                    truth there was something to forgive on his own part for having been so readily
                    entrapped contrary to all the rules of love and the drama. Increased exertion,
                    however, was necessary, and in 1704 he produced <hi rend="italic">The Stage
                    Coach,</hi> a piece adapted from the French by Farquhar in conjunction with
                    Anthony Motteux, a clever, reckless playwright and essayist, and remarkable as
                    having, though a Frenchman, given the world the best English translation of Don
                    Quixote. Three more comedies proceeded from Farquhar before his career was sadly
                    closed at the age of thirty. <hi rend="italic">The Twin Rivals</hi> was brought
                    out in 1705, <hi rend="italic">The Recruiting Officer</hi> in 1706, and <hi
                    rend="italic">The Beaux Stratagem</hi> in 1707. The last two are vastly superior
                    to Farquhar’s other plays, and are the works by which he is now remembered. To
                    relieve the poor dramatist from his difficulties, increased by his ill-starred
                    marriage, the duke of Ormond is said to have advised him to sell his commission
                    in the army and pay his debts, his grace promising at the same time to give him
                    a captaincy in his own regiment. Farquhar sold his commission, but the duke
                    either forgot or was unable to fulfil his promise. Farquhar’s earliest
                    biographer ascribes the unfortunate counsel to a “certain great courtier,” who
                    made solemn assurance which he forgot to keep. <hi rend="italic">The Beaux
                    Stratagem</hi> was written in six weeks, while death was impending over its
                    author. Before he had finished the second act he knew that he was stricken with
                    a mortal illness, but it was necessary to persevere and to be “consumedly
                    lively” to the end. He had received in advance £30 for the copyright from Lintot
                    the bookseller. The play was brought on the stage March 8, and Farquhar lived to
                    have his third night, and an extra benefit on the 29th of April, on which day he
                    is said to have died. He left his two children to the care of his friend
                    Wilks:—“Dear Bob, I have nothing to leave thee to perpetuate my memory but two
                    helpless girls. Look upon them sometimes and think of him that was to the last
                    moment of his life thine, <hi rend="smallcaps">George Farquhar.”</hi> Wilks
                    obtained a benefit at the theatre for the dramatist’s widow, and the daughters
                    had a pension of £30 a year, which one of them was in receipt of so late as
                    1761. The plots of Farquhar’s comedies are skilfully conducted and evolved; his
                    situations are well chosen (in these his friend Wilks’s advice would be useful),
                    and his dialogues are full of life and spirit. To the polished wit and
                    brilliancy of Congreve he has no pretension. His scenes are light and sketchy,
                    and his characters altogether on a lower level than Congreve’s, but they were
                    quite equal to them in stage effect. Sergeant Kite, Scrub, Archer, and Boniface
                    are distinct original characters which long charmed on the stage, while the
                    incidents with which they are mixed up—the unexpected encounters, adventures,
                    artifices, and disguises— are irresistibly comic and attractive in
                    representation. Pope considered Farquhar a mere farce writer, while Goldsmith
                    (who evidently adopted him as a model) preferred him to Congreve. On the stage,
                    with good actors, he might be so preferred, but never in the library. He had the
                    advantage of being less designedly and elaborately licentious than Congreve.
                    Love intrigues then formed the chief business of the comic drama; and in the
                    management of them the homely domestic virtues that form the happiness and
                    cement of society were disregarded or made the subject of ridicule. It is true
                    that the world of comedy was, as argued by Charles Lamb, an artificial world,
                    never perhaps regarded as real or as supplying patterns of morals or manners,
                    but the effect of such representations was to lower and corrupt the national
                    taste, while the fact that no pursuit was then so profitable to an author as
                    writing for the stage was also injurious to our imaginative literature. On this
                    moral view of the question, the reasoning of Macaulay and the eloquent
                    objurgation of Thackeray are un answerable.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See Macaulay’s essay on the Comic Dramatists of the
                    Reformation, and Thackeray’s <hi rend="italic">English Humorists.</hi> In 1840
                    Leigh Hunt published biographical and critical notices of Wycherley, Congreve,
                    Vanbrugh, and Farquhar, prefixed to an edition of their dramatic works—a
                    valuable addition to our dramatic literature.</p></note> The artificial comedy,
                    or comedy of manners, as seen in the beginning of the last century, is now
                    “quite extinct on our stage,” as Leigh Hunt has observed; but Hunt is surely in
                    error in dating the decline of English comedy from the time of Farquhar. To say
                    nothing of Goldsmith’s two plays, Sheridan’s <hi rend="italic">Rivals</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">School for Scandal</hi> show no declension in brilliancy of
                    dialogue, wit, or vivacity, aud some of the plays of Cumberland and the Colmans
                    evince high dramatic talent. <hi rend="smallcaps">(r. ca.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
