<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0723-0688-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FRANCIA, José Gaspar Rodriguez (9th edition, volume 9,
                    page 688)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205550">Paraguay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1052895">Paraguayans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n723/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FRANCIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">José Gaspar
                        Rodriguez</hi></label>, commonly called Dr Francia, dictator of Paraguay,
                    one of the most remarkable men connected with the history of South America. The
                    date of his birth is not definitely ascertained, but probably falls about 1757.
                    According to one account, he was of French descent; but the truth seems to be
                    that his father, Garcia Rodriguez França, was a native of S. Paulo in Brazil,
                    and came to Paraguay to take charge of a plantation of black tobacco for the
                    Government. He studied theology at the college of Cordova de Tucuman, and is
                    said to have been for some time a professor in that faculty; but he afterwards
                    turned his attention to the Jaw, and practised in Asuncion. Having attained a
                    high reputation at once for ability and integrity, he was naturally selected for
                    various important offices, and exercised great personal influence. The
                    Robertsons, whose accounts have done so much to blacken his memory, relate how,
                    when he was requested by one of his friends to undertake an unjust cause in his
                    behalf, he not only refused, but went and offered his services to the man who
                    was likely to be wronged, and by his boldness and energy secured his case. On
                    the declaration of Paraguayan independence in 1811, he was appointed secretary
                    to the national junta, and exercised an influence on affairs greatly out of
                    proportion to his nominal position. When the congress or junta of 1813 changed
                    the constitution and established a duumvirate, Dr Francia and the Gaucho general
                    Fulgencio were elected to the office. A story is told in connexion with their
                    installation, which recalls the self-coronation of William I. of England and
                    Napoleon the great. In theatrical imitation of Roman custom, two curule chairs
                    had been placed in the assembly, one of them bearing the name of Caesar and the
                    other that of Pompey. Francia seated himself in the Caesar chair, and left his
                    colleague to play the part of Pompey as best he might. In 1814 he secured his
                    own election as dictator for three years, and at the end of that period he
                    obtained the dictatorship for life. He was no mere nominal sovereign; but for
                    the next twenty-five years he might have boasted, with even more truth than
                    Louis XIV., “L’état e’est moi.” In the accounts which have been published of his
                    administration we find a strange mixture of capacity and caprice, of far-sighted
                    wisdom and reckless infatuation, strenuous endeavours after a high ideal and
                    flagrant violations of the simplest principles of justice. He put a stop to the
                    foreign commerce of the country, but carefully fostered its internal industries;
                    was disposed to be hospitable to strangers from other lands, and kept them
                    prisoners for years; lived a life of republican simplicity, and punished with
                    Dionysian severity the slightest want of respect. As time went on he appears to
                    have grown more arbitrary and despotic, more determined to maintain his mastery
                    over the <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n724/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0724-0689"/> country, and more apprehensive lest he should
                    lose it. And yet at the time of his death it is said that he was generally
                    regretted, and his bitterest opponents cannot deny that if he did much evil he
                    also did much good. Deeply imbued with the principles of the French Revolution,
                    he was a stern antagonist of the church. He abolished the Inquisition,
                    suppressed the college of theology, did away with the tithes, and inflicted
                    endless indignities on the priests. “What are they good for!” was his saying;
                    “they make us believe more in the devil than in God.” He discouraged marriage
                    both by precept and example, and left behind him several illegitimate children.
                    For the extravagances of his later years the plea of insanity has been put
                    forward; and it was evident that his worst characteristics were at their worst
                    when the east wind blew. The circumstances of his death were in strange keeping
                    with his life. He was about to sabre his doctor when he was seized with a fit,
                    and he expired the same day, September 20, 1840. He was buried in the cathedral
                    of Asuncion, but the spot is no longer known, and a story is told by Mr
                    Mansfield and by Lieutenant-Colonel Thomson, to the effect that his body was dug
                    up by some private enemies and flung into the river. On the other hand, it is
                    well known that the greatest respect was shown to his memory by those who
                    succeeded him in the government of Paraguay. Unfortunately for the history of
                    his administration, Francia kept no records; and he caused all his orders to be
                    returned to him with the word “executed” on the margin, and then to be
                    destroyed.</p>
                <p>The first and fullest account of Dr Francia was given to the world by two Swiss
                    surgeons, Rengger and Longchamps', whom lie had detained from 1819 to 1825— <hi
                        rend="italic">Essai historique sur la révolution de Paraguay et la
                        gouvernement dictatorial du docteur Francia,</hi> Paris, 1827. Their work
                    was almost immediately translated into English under the title of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Reign of Doctor Joseph</hi><hi rend="italic">G.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">R.</hi><hi rend="italic">De Francia</hi><hi rend="italic">in
                        Paraguay,</hi> 1827. About eleven years after there appeared at London <hi
                        rend="italic">Letters on Paraguay,</hi> by J. P. and W. P. Robertson, two
                    young Scotchmen whose hopes of commercial success hail been rudely destroyed by
                    the dictator’s interference. The account which they gave of his character and
                    government was naturally of the most unfavourable description, and they
                    rehearsed and emphasized their accusations in <hi rend="italic">Francia's Reign
                        of Terror,</hi> 1839, and <hi rend="italic">Letters on South America,</hi> 3
                    vols., 1843. From the very pages of his detractors Thomas Carlyle succeeded in
                    extracting materials for a brilliant defence of the dictator “as aman or
                    sovereign of iron energy and industry, of great and severe labour.” It appeared
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Quarterly Review</hi> for 1843, and is
                    reprinted in vol. iv. of the author’s <hi rend="italic">Critical and
                        Miscellaneous Essays.</hi> Comparatively little new light has since been
                    thrown on the subject Captain Richard F. Burton gives a graphic sketch of
                    Francia’s life and a favourable notice of his character in his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Letters from the Battlefields of Paraguay,</hi> 1870, while C. A. Washburn
                    takes up a hostile position in his <hi rend="italic">History of Paraguay,</hi>
                    1871.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
