<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0062-0053-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FAURIEL, Charles Claude</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 53</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:881894">Cousins</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n62/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FAURIEL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Claude</hi></label>
                    (1772-1844), a distinguished French historian, philologist, and critic, was born
                    at St Etienne, 21st October 1772. His parents belonged to the artisau class, but
                    their circumstances were such as to enable them to afford him a good education
                    at Tournon and Lyons. Though from his earliest years preferring a life of study
                    and retirement, Fauriel could not at first altogether escape the claims of the
                    restless times in which he lived, and in 1793 he became sub-lieutenant in the
                    fourth battalion of light infantry then in garrison at Perpignan. He would
                    appear to have resigned this appointment within a year, but it is certain in any
                    case that he was for some time secretary to General Dugommier, and that he also
                    served under Latour d’Auvergne. In 1794, however, he had returned to St Etienne,
                    where, but only for a short period, he filled a municipal office; and from 1795
                    to 1799 he devoted himself to strenuous study, more especially of the literature
                    and history, both ancient and modern, of Greece and Italy. Having paid a visit
                    to Paris in 1799, he was introduced to Fouche, minister of police, who
                    immediately conceived for him a strong liking, and induced him to become his
                    private secretary. The duties of this office Fauriel discharged both to the
                    satisfaction of Fouchd and with such courtesy and kindness as to secure many
                    lasting friendships; but he must have found it scarcely congenial; and as he
                    continued to unite with the labour it entailed upon him the same continuous
                    application to study as formerly, he found it necessary in 1801 to recruit his
                    health by foreign travel. In resigning his office in the following year, he was
                    therefore actuated doubtless as much by these considerations as by the
                    ostensible excuse that he had scruples in serving longer under Napoleon, when
                    the latter, in violation of strict republican principles, became consul for
                    life.</p>
                <p>Some articles which Fauriel in 1800 published in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Decade</hi> on a work of Madame de Stael were the means of ripening his slight
                    acquaintance with that distinguished authoress into intimate friendship—a
                    friendship which in its intellectual relations had considerable influence on her
                    future career. Through her he was shortly afterwards introduced into the
                    literary society of Auteuil. Neither in the literary history of his time nor in
                    that particular circle can Fauriel be called the most prominent figure, but his
                    position would not have been so unique in relation to either had it been more
                    obtrusive. By nature strongly sympathetic, gifted also with a finely balanced
                    judgment which was informed and cultivated to a high degree of perfection by an
                    almost unexampled erudition, and so intensely interested in all that related to
                    literature and history as to be almost forgetful of self and devoid of the love
                    of fame, he soon became the confidant and almost the literary mentor of the most
                    distinguished of his contemporaries, whom he benefited, not only by his
                    contagious enthusiasm and suggestive criticism, but by placing at their disposal
                    the results of his own laborious researches. Those who enjoyed his closest
                    intimacy were the physiologist Cabanis and the Italian poet Manzoni, and perhaps
                    after these, the historians Guizot and Thierry, the latter of whom in his
                    preface to his <hi rend="italic">Etudes historiques</hi> speaks of him as the
                    friend and sure and faithful counsellor, whose judgment was his rule in doubt,
                    and whose sympathy with his labours his greatest incentive to progress. During
                    his connexion with Auteuil the attention of Fauriel was naturally turned to
                    philosophy, and from the letter which Cabanis addressed to him on final causes
                    it would appear that he must be named the precursor of that school of philosophy
                    in France which recognizes Cousin as its head—that he was the first to direct
                    attention to the importance of studying philosophy in its historical relations,
                    and to advocate what is known as eclecticism. His great merit indeed is in
                    emphasizing the necessity of studying, not only the philosophy, but the general
                    literature and civilization of modern times in their primitive sources; although
                    it must be admitted that his preference for early and uncultured forme of
                    literature has in it something of exaggeration. For some years he was engaged on
                    a history of Stoicism, but perhaps more on account of his attention having been
                    accidentally directed to the subject by others than from any special interest in
                    philosophy, and at any rate the work was never completed, all the papers
                    connected with it having accidentally perished in 1814. He also occupied himself
                    at the same time with the study of Arabic, Sanskrit, and the old French
                    dialects, but all with a special reference to his historical researches. The
                    chief task he had set before <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n63/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0063-0054"/> him was an inquiry into the origin of modern
                    civilization, the wide range of his preliminary studies being accounted for by
                    the fact that they were of the nature of soundings taken with a view to discover
                    with some approximation to certainty where the treasure he was in search of was
                    concealed; and it was because he became convinced that the object of his quest
                    was to be found in southern Gaul that his studies gradually came to have a
                    bearing more or less direct on the elucidation of the early history of that
                    country. His opinions on subjects which had an incidental relation to his chief
                    purpose were occasionally contributed to periodicals; and as a kind of interlude
                    to his severer studies he published in 1810 a translation of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Parthenais</hi><hi rend="italic">oder</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >die</hi><hi rend="italic">Alpenreise</hi> of the Danish poet Baggesen, with a
                    preface on the various kinds.of poetry; in 1823 translations of two tragedies of
                    his friend Manzoni, with a preface <hi rend="italic">Sur la</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">théorie</hi><hi rend="italic">de l</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic"
                    >art</hi><hi rend="italic">dramatique</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and in 1824
                    his translation of the popular songs of modern Greece, with a <hi rend="italic"
                    >Discours préliminaire</hi> on popular poetry, in which he claims for that
                    species of literature a preference in some respects over the most cultivated and
                    artistic productions on account of its freshness and its intimate connexion with
                    nature and reality, and also as the best key to the comprehension of a nation’s
                    history inasmuch as it is the spontaneous expression and outflow of its peculiar
                    genius and of its deepest experiences.</p>
                <p>After the revolution of 1830 the Government was persuaded by his friends to
                    establish expressly for Fauriel a chair of foreign literature. In 1836 he was
                    elected a member of the Academy of Inscriptions and Belles Lettres, and in the
                    same year he published in four volumes <hi rend="italic">L’Histoire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de la Gaule méridionale</hi><hi rend="italic">sous la
                    domination</hi><hi rend="italic">des conquérants</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Germains—</hi> the second portion of a work which, when completed, was to have
                    consisted of three parts, the first on southern Gaul under the Roman dominion,
                    and the third and most important embracing the period from the dismemberment of
                    the empire of Charlemagne to the end of the 13th century, and including the
                    brilliant though premature spring-time of early literature and culture which for
                    a short period relieved the sterile winter that had so long overshadowed the
                    intellect of Europe. In 1837 Fauriel published, along with an introduction, a
                    translation of the Provençal poem on the war of the Albigenses, and in 1839 he
                    became a member of the commission of the Histoire littéraire de la France, to
                    which work he contributed a number of articles on the writers of the 13th
                    century. He died 15th July 1844. After his death appeared, in 1846, <hi
                    rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de la littérature provençale,</hi>
                    which formed his course of professorial lectures for 1831-32, and may be
                    regarded as a portion of the third part of the great work which he had sketched
                    out on the history of southern Gaul. In these lectures he sought to prove that
                    from the embers of the. civilization of Greece and Rome, which, by a peculiar
                    combination of circumstances, had been transferred not wholly quenched to the
                    foreign soil of Provençe, was lighted the spark which originated the greater
                    part of the romances of chivalry (that is, not only those of the cycle of
                    Charlemagne, but of the cycle of the Round Table), and thus kindled the
                    civilization of modern Europe. Various opinions have been formed as to the
                    amount of truth in this theory, and it must at least be admitted that Fauriel
                    has been somewhat hampered and biased in his inquiry by preconceived
                    conclusions; butin any case he must be allowed the merit of having first fully
                    revealed the importance of the epoch of which he treats, and having supplied the
                    greater part of the materials for the solution of the problems which it presents
                    for discussion. Indeed, the distinguishing quality of his writings is their
                    suggestiveness, and their value is therefore scarcely lessened even when their
                    conclusions are disputed. The statement of Renan, made in 1855, that he is the
                    man of our times who has put in circulation the greatest number of new ideas,
                    can scarcely, however, be accepted, even when we remember his indirect influence
                    on the contemporary writers of France; but none was more than he <hi
                    rend="italic">en rapport</hi> with the spirit of the 19th century, or has done a
                    more important work in reference to those problems which are strictly literary
                    or historical. The professorial lectures of Fauriel for 1833-34 were published
                    in 1854, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Dante</hi><hi rend="italic">et les
                    origines</hi><hi rend="italic">de la langue</hi><hi rend="italic">et de la
                    littérature italiennes</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and among his miscellaneous
                    writings the most important are his examination of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Système</hi><hi rend="italic">de M. Raynouard</hi><hi rend="italic">sur
                    l’origine des langues romanes,</hi> contributed to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bibliothèque</hi><hi rend="italic">de l</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">École des
                    Chartes,</hi> and his lives of Dante and Lope de Vega in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Revue</hi><hi rend="italic">des Deux Mondes ior</hi> October 1834 and September
                    1839 respectively.</p>
                <p>The best and fullest account of Fauriel is that by Sainte-Beuve in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Portraits</hi><hi rend="italic">Contemporains,</hi> vol. iv. See
                    also the review of FaurieΓs work on Provençal literature by H. Fortoul in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux Mondes</hi> for May 1846, and the short notice
                    of his work on Dante by Renan in the <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux
                    Mondes</hi> for December 1855.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
