<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0247-0238-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FIRE-CLAY, FIRE-BRICKS (9th edition, volume 9, page
                    238)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z981">Abbots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s46h773">Columbates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29d7c">Bricks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wm7s">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9h942">Coaling</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925173">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838614">Bricks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865087">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865671">Coaling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:794221">Abbots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n247/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FIRE-CLAY, FIRE-BRICKS</label>. Fire-clays may be defined as
                    native combinations of hydrated silicates of alumina, mechanically associated
                    with silica and alumina in various states of subdivision, and sufficiently free
                    from silicates of the alkalies and from iron and lime to resist vitrification at
                    high temperatures; the absence of the vitrifiable element is, however, merely a
                    question of degree, as no native clays are wholly free from iron, the alkalies,
                    lime, and the other alkaline earths.</p>
                <p>Fire-clay may be looked upon as a special term for the grey clays of the
                    Coal-Measures, interstratified with, and generally in close proximity to, the
                    seams of coal, in beds varying from a few inches to many yards in thickness.
                    They are locally known as “clunches” and “underclays,” and are supposed to
                    represent the soil that produced the vegetation from which the coal was
                    formed.</p>
                <p>The association of coal with the fire-clays of the carboniferous formation has
                    localized the manufacture of firebricks, and by far the larger proportion are
                    produced in the Coal-Measure districts, especially at Stourbridge, celebrated
                    for producing a highly refractory brick, Broseley, Benthall, Madeley and
                    Coalbrookdale in the Shropshire coal-field, and in the Midland, Yorkshire, North
                    and South Wales, Durham, and the Scotch coal-fields; but in later years the area
                    of fire-brick manufacture has much widened. There has been an extensive
                    production since about 1850 from the Eocene clays in the neighbourhood of Poole
                    and Wareham in Dorsetshire; and a more limited supply from the Miocene between
                    Bovey Tracey and Newton Abbot in Devonshire.</p>
                <p>Still more recently Cornwall has become the seat of the manufacture, where, as at
                    Calstock, Tregoning Hill near Breage, St Ednor near St Columb, and Lee Moor,
                    fire-bricks of fine quality are made from china-clay refuse and disintegrated
                    granite. Mr Argall of the Tregoning Hill Company states that the locality was
                    one of the first seats of china-clay mining between the years 1730 and 1750, and
                    that in 1862 the present company commenced to make fire-bricks and tiles from
                    the refuse of the clays, taking about two-thirds of silica and one-third of
                    mica, which are mixed together in a pug mill, moulded and burnt in round ovens
                    holding about 16,000 bricks, and that a very superior fire-brick is made from
                    clay direct from the “stopes,” containing</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Silica</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>40’00</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>per cent.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Alumina</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>37’00</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Magnesia</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2’00</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Potash</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9’00</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Water</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12’00</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>&gt;9</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>which are employed by founders, smelters, gas companies, &amp;c. The price paid
                    at the works is from 50s. to 55s. per 1000. The source of the materials is
                    decomposed granite, of which Tregoning Hill consists.</p>
                <p>The Hingston Down fire-clay deposit, near Calstock, supplying the Calstock
                    fire-brick works, the Phaenix works, and the Tamar works in the same
                    neighbourhood, consists of a range of decomposed granite with an average width
                    of three-quarters of a mile, running east and west for 3 or 4 miles, extending
                    to an ascertained depth of from 300 to 400 feet, and intersected by mineral
                    lodes. The Calstock Fire-Brick Company (limited), superintended by Mr C. B.
                    Evate, commenced operations in the year 1870, and manufactured from the
                    decomposed granite fire-bricks of a highly refractory character, which are
                    delivered free on board at the port of Calstock at from 50s. to 60s. a thousand,
                    weighing about 3¾ tons. Another source of firebrick material, scarcely yet
                    developed, is the pockets or depressions occurring in the mountain limestone of
                    North Wales, Derbyshire, and Ireland, containing white refractory clays and
                    sands, the insoluble remnants from the local dissolution of the limestone,
                    intermixed with the debris of the overlying millstone grit. These clays and
                    sands when evenly mingled are sufficiently adhesive to <hi rend="subscript">
                        k</hi> be moulded, and their small contractility and highly refractory
                    character render them pre-eminently suitable for fire-brick manufacture.
                    Fire-brick works have already been established on the estate of Captain Cooke of
                    Colomendy Hall, near Mold, and the refractory clays and sands are largely
                    employed for lining furnaces, 3000 tons having been sold for this purpose alone
                    in the year 1877.</p>
                <p>The fire-clays of the Coal-Measures vary as regards their refractory character,
                    not only in the different coal-fields, but the individual strata in close
                    alternation often present sudden variations, refractory beds being
                    interstratified with useless strata largely charged with disseminated carbonate
                    of iron. The grey colour of the Coal-Measure clays is partially due to the
                    presence of this mineral, which, whether disseminated through the mass or
                    otherwise occurring in excess as concretionary nodules, is prejudicial to the
                    clays as a material for fire-bricks. Carbonaceous matter is also present in
                    variable proportions, colouring the clay from a slaty-black to a pale grey, but
                    as this is eliminated in the earlier stages of the burning of the bricks, its
                    presence in no way influences their refractory character.</p>
                <p>The relative proportion of silica and alumina which some manufacturers have laid
                    undue stress upon as indicating heat-resisting quality is of little moment, as
                    both these constituents, whether occurring in combination as silicates of
                    alumina, or as free alumina and silica, are essentially the refractory elements
                    of all good fire-bricks, being unvitrifiable <hi rend="italic">per se,</hi>
                    excepting when associated with the alkalies, lime, or oxides of iron. The
                    plastic character of refractory clays is also of limited influence on their
                    suitability for fire-brick manufacture; extreme plasticity, which is generally
                    accompanied by excessive contractility and vitrifiability, is prejudicial. As a
                    rule few clays or <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n248/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0248-0239"/> materials used in the manufacture of
                    fire-bricks are insufficiently plastic to prevent their being easily moulded,
                    and in the manufacture by the <hi rend="italic">dry process,</hi> or the
                    compression of the brick out of nearly dry pulverized clay, plasticity is not so
                    essential a quality. As regards chemical composition the following analyses
                    indicate its general character, and the variability of the proportion of the
                    constituents of some of the more important fire-clays :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">Coal-Meas,</hi></p><p>A. <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Stourbridge Clay.</hi> (Omitting the water.)</p><p>Silica
                                70'60</p><p>Alumina 26'60</p><p>Oxide of iron 2 0</p><p>Lime... »
                                Γ40</p><p>Magnesia - traces.</p><p>C. <hi rend="italic">Glass House
                                    Pot Clay,</hi><hi rend="italic">Tintanι</hi><hi rend="italic"
                                    >Abbey, Stourbridge.</hi> (Analysis by A. W.
                                Wills.)</p><p>Silica 73∙82</p><p>Alumina 15'88</p><p>Protoxide of
                                iron 2'94</p><p>Alkalies....» 0'90</p><p>Water .. 6 45</p><p>E. <hi
                                    rend="italic">Fire-Brick Clay from Newcastle.</hi> (Analysis by
                                H. Taylor. )</p><p>Silica 55'50</p><p>Alumina
                                27'75</p><p>Sesquioxide of iron 2'01 '</p><p>Lime
                                0'67</p><p>Magnesia 0'75</p><p>Alkalies 2'63</p><p>Water
                                10'53</p><p>G. <hi rend="italic">Clay from Glasgow,</hi> used for
                                saggars, glass house pots, bricks, &amp;c. (Percy’s <hi
                                    rend="italic">Metallurgy.)</hi></p><p>Silica ....„ ..
                                6616</p><p>Alumina 22'54</p><p>Protoxide of iron 5'31</p><p>Lime
                                1∙42</p><p>Water 314</p><p>J. <hi rend="italic">Fire-Clay from
                                    Dowlais.</hi></p><p>(Analysis by J. E. Rily.) Silica
                                67'13</p><p>Alumina 21 18</p><p>Sesquioxide of iron 1'85</p><p>Lime
                                ....„ 0'32</p><p>Magnesia 0'84</p><p>Alkalies 2'02</p><p>Organic
                                matter 0'90</p><p>water....« 6∙21</p><p><hi rend="italic"
                                    >Note.—</hi> In comparing the percentages be noticed that some
                                of the analyses cx&lt; <hi rend="italic">Tertiary Clays of Dorset
                                    and Devo</hi></p><p>L. <hi rend="italic">White Clay, Branksea
                                    Island, Dorset.</hi> (Analysis by Professor Way.)</p><p>Silica
                                —, 65'49</p><p>Alumina 21'28</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">ure Clays.</hi></p><p>B. <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Stourbridge Clay.</hi> (Analysis by Richardson.)</p><p>Silica
                                70'50</p><p>Alumina 25'46</p><p>Protoxide of iron
                                2'04</p><p>Magnesia 1'05</p><p>D. <hi rend="italic">“Best Clay,”
                                    Tamworth.</hi></p><p>(Analysis by A. W. Wills. )</p><p>Silica
                                .... 71'40</p><p>Alumina 21'17</p><p>Protoxide of iron
                                0'91</p><p>Lime 0'04</p><p>Alkalies 0'82</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Water 606</p><p>F. <hi rend="italic">Fire-Clay from Newcastle.</hi>
                                (Excluding the water.)</p><p>Silica 69'25</p><p>Alumina
                                17'90</p><p>Oxide of iron 2'97</p><p>Magnesia 1'30</p><p>Lime
                                7'58</p><p>H. <hi rend="italic">Dinas Fire-Clay, South Wales.</hi>
                                (Excluding the water.) Silica 91'95</p><p>Alumina 8'05</p><p>With
                                traces of iron.</p><p>K. <hi rend="italic">Welsh Fire-Clay.</hi>
                                (Excluding the water. )</p><p>Silica 8010</p><p>Alumina...» »
                                17'90</p><p>Oxide of iron 10</p><p>Lime 1'0</p><p>! of the
                                individual constituents, it must :lude the water.</p><p><hi
                                    rend="italic">n used for Fire-Brick Manufacture.</hi></p><p>Μ.
                                    <hi rend="italic">Black Clay, Branksea Island, Dorset.</hi>
                                (Analysis by Professor Way.)</p><p>Silica „ 72∙23</p><p>Alumina »
                                23*25</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Oxides of iron 1'26</p><p>Alkalies and alkaline earths ....
                                7'25</p><p>Sulphate of lime 4'72</p><p>N. <hi rend="italic">Beacon
                                    Hill Clay, near Poole.</hi></p><p>Lower Bagshot
                                Beds.</p><p>Silica 63'00</p><p>Alumina .................
                            33'50</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Oxides of iron 2'54</p><p>Alkalies and alkaline earths.....
                                Γ78</p><p>O. <hi rend="italic">Beacon Hill Clay, near
                                Poole.</hi></p><p>Lower Bagshot Beds.</p><p>Silica
                                53'52</p><p>Alumina....»..« ........... 33'68</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Oxide of Iron Γ00</p><p>Magnesia..... 2'00</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Lime 0'76</p><p>Magnesia 0'14</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>P. <hi rend="italic">Blue Ball Clay, Borey Tracy, Devon.</hi>
                                Miocene Lignite Formation.</p><p>Silica 47 00</p><p>Alumina 48
                                00</p><p>Oxides of iron 1∙5</p><p>Magnesia 2'0</p><p>Water, dec
                                1∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Oxide of iron 0'52</p><p>Alkalies 004</p><p>Water 1Γ34</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The above analyses indicate a preponderance of silica in the Coal-Measure
                    fire-clays compared with the Tertiary clays of Devon and Dorset, in which a
                    larger proportion of alumina occurs. The latter character is accompanied by
                    tenacity and plasticity, and greater contraction in drying and burning, which,
                    when excessive, is counteracted by mingling with the clay sand and ground burnt
                    clay or sherds.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Contractility.—</hi> The contraction in burning (excluding the
                    contraction in drying) of several Coal-Measure fire-clays pressed out of nearly
                    dry pulverized clay was ascertained by the writer to be as follows:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="3"><p>Fire-clay occurring between the “Penystonc Measure”
                            )</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>and “Vigors clay, Shropshire coal-measures, near;</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>► 1 percent.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Broseley</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Two-foot coal” fire-clay, Shropshire coal-measures...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Ganie coal” fire-clay, Shropshire coal-measures</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Bewdley Forest fire-clay, from the works of Mr Mob-j</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>h</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>berley, Bewdley, No. 1 1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>í</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>»</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Do. do. No. 2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">4</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Do. do. No. 3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Stourbridge fire-clay, from Messrs Fisher Brothers,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>∣ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“The Hayes,” Stourbridge, No. 1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>i <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>n</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Do. do. No. 2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>j ,</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Best” fire-clay, from the earl of Dudley’s pits near</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1 2</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>•Dudley</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>∣</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">99</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Seconds” and offal, from same</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Fire-clay, Maryport, Cumberland</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">99</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The average contraction of the Coal-Measure fire-clays is thus little over two
                    per cent. A brick manufactured from the best Stourbridge clay without admixture
                    of burnt material contracted seven-eighths of an inch in nine inches, but this
                    would probably represent the contraction both in drying and burning. The
                    contraction in burning of the Tertiary fire-clays used for the manufacture of
                    fire-bricks in Devon and Dorset is much more than that of the Coal Measure
                    clays</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="3"><p><hi rend="italic">Contractility of Devonshire
                                Clays.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Best pipe-clay,” Miocene Lignite Formation, Bovey Tracey, from the
                                works of Messrs</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>&gt;12 per cent.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Watts, Blake, Bearne, &amp; Co</p><p>“Cutty clay”</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>’ 8</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Household clay”</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Stoneware clay”</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Alum-makers’ clay”</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>‘ ‘ Drain pipe clay”</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Blue ball clay”</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Black ball clay”</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>11</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Brown ball clay”</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>11</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Black carbonaceous clay”</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">99</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Average contraction a little under 9 per cent.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="3"><p><hi rend="italic">Contractility of Dorsetshire Clays.</hi>
                                Lower Bagshot (Eocene)</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Beds.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“White clay” from Messrs Pike’s works, )</p><p>Wareham j</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>10 per cent.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“T” clay</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>11</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“V”clay</p><p>“Black” clay</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">99</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“Blue” clay</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>18</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“H” clay</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>15</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“P”clay</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>15</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">99</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>“S” clay</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">99</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Mottled sandy clay, Lower Bagshot Beds, )</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Wareham ∣</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">99</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Clay from Upper Plant Bed, Lower Bagshot í</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>A</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Beds, Studland Bay, Dorset j</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>O</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>&gt;&gt;</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The clays above enumerated are not exclusively used for fire-brick manufacture,
                    but fairly indicate the general character of the Tertiary fire-brick clays,
                    which, compared with the Coal-Measure fire-clays, are characterized by a
                    preponderance of alumina, tenacity of texture, contractility in the kiln, and an
                    absence of iron and the alkalies, &lt;fcc., which tend to vitrification.
                    Tenacity of texture in a fire-brick material is, however, a mechanical
                    condition, which, <hi rend="italic">caeteris paribus,</hi> assists
                    vitrification, a coarse open body being more refractory than a close homogeneous
                    brick of similar chemical composition. A well manufactured brick should be of a
                    pale cream or clear buff colour, uniform throughout its mass, and burnt to the
                    full extent of its contractility.</p>
                <p>The chemical changes which take place in the burning consist, first, of the
                    destruction of the disseminated carbonaceous matter, the dehydration of the
                    silicates of alumina, destroying their plastic character, and the decomposition
                    of the disseminated carbonate of protoxide of iron, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n249/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0249-0240"/> converting it into anhydrous sesquioxide, to
                    which the yellow colour of the burnt brick is due; if the burning is carried to
                    a high state of vitrification the yellow tint is replaced by a dull grey, due to
                    the partial reduction of the sesquioxide of iron and its conversion into
                    silicate of protoxide or minutely disseminated particles of metallic iron; any
                    alkalies present also form vitreous combinations with the silica during the
                    latter stages of the burning. The paleness of colour of a fire-brick is not
                    always a safe indication of the absence of iron, as the presence of a large
                    proportion of carbonaceous matter in the clay tends to bleaching by the
                    reduction of the colouring sesquioxidc to a lower oxide preserved as a silicate
                    in a comparatively colourless condition. Again, the presence of lime and the
                    other alkaline earths, which are disadvantageous fluxing elements, will cloak
                    the colouring power of a large pér-centage of oxide of iron by the formation of
                    a pale double silicate of lime and iron. This is taken advantage of in the
                    manufacture of buff building bricks by mixing ground chalk with ferruginous
                    clays which would otherwise burn dark red.</p>
                <p>A properly burnt brick, uniform in colour throughout its mass, can only be
                    obtained by slow progressive firing; a broken brick that has been too quickly
                    burnt, though pale on the surface, presents a darker central patch and
                    concentric rings of various shades of colour, due mainly to the different states
                    of oxidation of the iron, and partly to the presence of unconsumed carbonaceous
                    matter; but the chemistry of this colour-variegation is not clearly
                    understood.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Durability of Fire-Bricks.—</hi> The destruction and wearing
                    out of a fire-brick in its ordinary uses takes place in different ways. First,
                    it may waste by crumbling and shattering; this occurs only when the brick is
                    unnecessarily porous in texture, or from the presence of extraneous lumps of
                    foreign materials, such as small pebbles and fragments of lime and iron-stone,
                    which the manufacturer endeavours to get rid of by sifting or crushing before
                    the clay is moulded. Secondly, the gradual vitrification of the brick under the
                    pressure of the superimposed structure distorts its form, and the semiplastic
                    red-hot or white-hot mass is gradually squeezed out of shape, and has to be
                    periodically replaced in the hotter parts of the furnaces and kilns. However
                    completely a brick has been burnt, bringing its dimensions almost to the limit
                    of contractility, constant exposure to long-continued heat still further reduces
                    its bulk, causing the displacement of the mass of which it forms a part, aud
                    necessitating replacement and repairs. Thirdly, there is the gradual fretting
                    away of the exposed brick surface by vitrification, however refractory a brick
                    may be; when it lines flues and furnaces, the fumes and ashes incessantly
                    carried into contact with it bring foreign accessions, which vitrify the exposed
                    portions and form a coating of viscid slag, which eats into the brick surface,
                    creeping down and clogging the flues and fire-holes with a vitreous mass. In the
                    case of blast-furnaces the fretting away of the surface of the fire-brick
                    linings gradually enlarges their capacity, the surface destruction decreasing
                    from the tweers upwards, the faces opposite the impact of the blast being
                    distinctly excavated beyond the outline of the enlarged circumference. In one of
                    the furnaces of the Madeley Wood Company, Madeley, Shropshire, “blown in” in
                    1867 and “blown out” in 1874, the diameter at the base, originally 3 feet, had
                    been enlarged to about 7 feet 6 inches, and at the widest part, a little below
                    the middle, from 12 feet, its original diameter, to 13 feet. In another furnace,
                    after ten years’ blast, the original diameter of 4 feet 5 inches at the base had
                    been enlarged to 9 feet 6 inches; at a third of its height from 9 feet 11 inches
                    to 12 feet; and half way up, from 11 feet 9 inches to 12 feet 10 inches, the
                    destruction of bnck-surface gradually decreasing towards the top, where the
                    increase of size was but trifling. This would represent a consumption of
                    brick-surface of from 3 to 4 inches a year at the tweers, and about
                    three-quarters of an inch a year towards the middle of the furnace.</p>
                <p>It is beyond the scope of this article to enter into the details of fire-brick
                    manufacture, which in its main features resemble the manufacture of building
                    bricks, except that fire-bricks are rarely if ever burnt in clamps.</p>
                <p>Properly constructed ovens on the “down draft” principle, with the outlet from
                    the bottom into a tall chimney, are now almost universally employed, as they
                    ensure greater regularity in the burning than in the old form of kiln, with a
                    direct escape from the top, as well as economy in fuel. The consumption of coal
                    varies from 9 to 15 cwt. per 1000 bricks, exclusive of the coal used in the
                    drying stoves.</p>
                <p>Coal-Measure fire-clays are often mined in an almost rocky condition, requiring
                    long exposure to the weather to effect their disintegration. The softer clunches
                    or clays are sometimes prepared for the moulder by “weathering,” but the more
                    common practice is to grind the fire-clay just as it comes from the pit under
                    heavy “runners” or rollers, effecting a granular texture which is a desirable
                    quality in a refractory brick. It is now becoming a common practice to grind up
                    with the raw clay from onefourth to one-third of its weight of broken burnt
                    sherds or fire-bricks. All waste materials are thus utilized, and the
                    excessively contractile character of highly plastic clays such as those of
                    Dorsetshire is counteracted. Silicious sand is also sometimes mixed with the
                    more plastic clays to reduce their contractility.</p>
                <p>The ground clay is either brought into a plastic state with water in a pug-mill
                    and moulded by hand, or by brickmoulding machinery generally connected with the
                    pug-mill outlet; or the partially moist ground-clay dust is compressed into
                    bricks in iron moulds by steam power, a modification of Prosser’s well-known
                    process. More shapely bricks are thus produced than by plastic moulding, and
                    their perfectly true flat sides enable a minimum of jointing materials to be
                    employed—a circumstance of importance in the stability of fire-brick masonry, as
                    thick fireclay jointing contracts in the firing, tending to shatter tho
                    structure.</p>
                <p>In addition to the use of fire-clay for the bedding of all fire-brick structures,
                    it forms the materials of gas retorts, crucibles, and every kind of potter’s
                    kiln furniture, such as saggars, cranks, slip kiln bottoms, enamel kiln linings,
                    &amp;c. These have been up to within the last year or two moulded out of plastic
                    clay, but by processes and machinery recently patented by Mr A. Maw, saggars,
                    cranks, and every kind of kiln furniture can be moulded out of nearly dry
                    pulverized clay, at a great reduction in cost below that of the plastic process,
                    and the exact regularity of form attained effects a large saving of space in the
                    ovens and kilns. Moreover, the even bearing on each other of the
                    regularly-shaped saggars when piled up in the oven, reduces the “wear and tear”
                    and breakage to a minimum. Fire-bricks vary much in price in the different
                    producing districts,— about 40s. per 1000 may now be looked upon as a minimum,
                    ranging up to 70s. and 80s., further augmented by the cost of carriage to other
                    districts. A thousand fire-bricks weigh from 3¾ to 4 tons. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >(g. μ.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
