<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0871-0836-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FUR (9th edition, volume 9, page 836)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:936387">Fur</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833880">Blacks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933481">Foxes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010806">Martens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90g4n">Fur</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40r9m93h">Martens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f70c">Mink</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205075">Ohio</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n871/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FUR</label>. Certain animals, which inhabit the colder
                    climates, have a covering upon the skin called fur, lying alongside of another
                    and longer covering, called the overhair. The fur differs from the overhair in
                    that it is soft, silky, curly, downy, and barbed lengthwise, while the overhair
                    is straight, smooth, and comparatively rigid. These properties of fur constitute
                    its essential value for felting purposes, and mark its difference from wool and
                    silk; the first, after some slight preparation by the aid of hot water, readily
                    unites its fibres into a strong and compact mass; the others can best be managed
                    by spinning and weaving.</p>
                <p>On the living animal the overhair keeps the fur filaments apart, prevents their
                    tendency to felt, and protects them from injury—thus securing to the animal an
                    immunity from cold and storm; while, as a matter of fact, this very overhair,
                    though of an humbler name, is most generally the beauty and pride of the pelt,
                    and marks its chief value with the furrier. We arrive thus at two distinct and
                    opposite uses and values of fur. Regarded as useful for felt it is denominated
                    staple fur, while with respect to its use with and on the pelt it is called
                    fancy fur. For the one purpose the Russian hare skin is more valuable than the
                    Russian sable, while for the other the sable may be valued at one thousand times
                    the former.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> The manufacture of fur into a felt is of
                    comparatively modern origin, while the use of fur pelts as a covering for the
                    body, for the couch, or for the tent is coeval with the earliest history of all
                    northern tribes and nations. They were not simply a barbarous expedient to
                    defend man from the rigours of an arctic winter; woven wool alone cannot, in its
                    most perfect form, accomplish this. The pelt or skin is requisite to keep out
                    the piercing wind and driving storm, while the fur and overhair ward off the
                    cold; and they are as much a necessity to-day among more northern peoples as
                    they ever were in the days of barbarism. With them the providing of this
                    necessary covering became the first purpose of their toil; subsequently the
                    article grew into an object of barter and traffic, at first among themselves,
                    and afterwards with their neighbours of more temperate climes; and with the
                    latter it naturally became an article of fashion, of ornament, and of luxury.
                    This, in brief, has been the history of its use in China, Tartary, Russia,
                    Siberia, and North America, and at present the employment of fancy furs among
                    the civilized nations of Europe and America has grown to be more extensive than
                    at any former period. The supply of this demand in earlier times led to such
                    severe competition as to terminate in tribal pillages and even national wars;
                    and in modern times it has led to commercial ventures on the part of individuals
                    and companies, the account of which, told in its plainest form, reads like the
                    pages of a romance. Furs have constituted the price of redemption for royal
                    captives, the gifts of emperors and kings, and the pecular badge of state
                    functionaries. At the present day they vie with precious gems and gold as
                    ornaments and garniture for wealth and fashion; but by their abundance, and the
                    cheapness of some varieties, they have recently come within the reach of men of
                    moderate incomes. The history of furs can be read in Marco Polo, as he grows
                    eloquent with the description of the rich skins of the khan of Tartary; in the
                    early fathers of the church, who lament their introduction into Rome and
                    Byzantium as an evidence of barbaric and debasing luxury; in tho political
                    history of Russia, stretching out a powerful arm over Siberia to secure her rich
                    treasures; in the story of the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n872/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0872-0837"/> French occupation of Canada, and the ascent
                    of the St Lawrence to its source in Lake Superior, and the subsequent contest to
                    retain possession against England; in the early settlements of New England, New
                    York, and Virginia; in Irving’s <hi rend="italic">Astoria,</hi>; in the records
                    of tho Hudson’s Bay Company; and in the annals of the fairs held at
                    Nijni-Novgorod and Leipsic. Here it may suffice to give some account of the
                    present condition of the trade in fancy furs. The collection of skins is now
                    chiefly a matter of private enterprise. Few, if any, monopolies exist. The
                    Alaska Commercial Company, now about ten years old, enjoys some special
                    privilege for the taking of seal skins on the Pribiloff Islands, and some
                    peculiar restrictions exist in Russia in relation to certain peltries, but
                    beyond this, the trade in furs is a free one the world over. Individual
                    enterprise, skill, forecast, and capital, have an open field. The Hudson’s Bay
                    Company, with its chief office in London, still maintains its organization, but
                    conducts its affairs in North America under no special or royal grant, and
                    competes in the open market with individual traders throughout Canada, Labrador,
                    Manitoba, and Columbia. Its collection of peltries is offered to the highest
                    bidder at public auction in London, in January, March, and September of each
                    year.</p>
                <p>Private collectors and dealers throughout Canada and the United States forward
                    their furs to the seaboard, chiefly to New York, for sale there, or for
                    consignment principally to London and to Leipsic. The latter town still
                    maintains the custom of spring and autumn fairs, at which most kinds of wares
                    are sold or exchanged with dealers from Turkey, Austria, and Russia.
                    Nijni-Nυvgorod is the chief fair for European Russia, though very important
                    fairs are also held in Kasan and in Irbit among the Ural Mountains. The most
                    important fair for eastern Siberia is held at Kiachta, on the borders of China,
                    where an extensive exchange of furs is carried on with the Celestials. Japan has
                    added but little to the activity or extension of the fur trade, though her
                    northern shores have furnished many a fine fur seal and sea otter to the hardy
                    navigator. Staple furs, or those used chiefly in the manufacture of hats, are
                    those of the have and the rabbit, collected mainly in Russia, Germany, France,
                    and England, dressed, carroted, and cut from the skin in western Germiny,
                    France, Belgium, and England, and thence distributed to the manufacturing
                    centres of the world; and here it may be added that the clippings and cuttings
                    of fancy furs from the workshops of furriers are all saved, and find their way
                    to the machinery which utilizes the waste and transforms them into hatters’
                    furs. But of all these fur marts that of London is the chief, for thither tend
                    by the laws of trade, not only much of the produce of Asia and Europe, but also
                    the fine peltries of Chili and Peru, the nutria from Buenos Ayres, the fur seal
                    of Cape Horn and South Shetland, the hair seal from Newfoundland, as well as the
                    inferior peltries of Africa. To prepare fur skins in a way to endure this long
                    transportation is a simple and easy matter. When stripped from the animal the
                    flesh and fat are carefully removed, and the pelts hung in a cool place to dry
                    and harden; nothing is added to protect them. Care is taken that they do not
                    heat after packing, and that they are occasionally beaten to destroy worms. A
                    marked exception is the case of the fur seal, which is best preserved by liberal
                    salting and packing in hogsheads. All other raw furs are marketed in bales.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Kinds and Quantities—</hi> Few kinds of animals furnish a pelt
                    of suitable weight and pliability, and all of them differ widely in elegance of
                    texture, delicacy of shade, and fineness of overhair, and it is these
                    differences which determine their place in the catalogue of merchandise. These
                    few animals are not very prolific, and many of them attain their greatest beauty
                    in wild and uncultivated regions. To this remark there are some notable
                    exceptions. Being thus few in kind, and limited in quantity, one might fear the
                    extinction of the several choice varieties through the persistent energy of the
                    trapper. But here the fickleness of fashion steps in, and does for the fur trade
                    what the law of supply and demand does for the more staple articles of commerce.
                    Fashion, fastidious and fickle, neglects the use of certain kinds for a season;
                    the market price of the pelt no longer repays the outfit of the trapper; the
                    hunt is intermitted, and in two or three years the animal regains its numbers
                    and strength. The annual collection of furs is thus a matter of ceaseless
                    change; but the following may be relied on as an estimate correct enough for all
                    practical purposes :—∙</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">Average Annual Collection.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Badger</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5,0∞</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Bear</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Europe and Asia</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>60,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>15,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Europe and Asia</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Beaver</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Asia</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>20,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Buffalo</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>200,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>100,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Chinchilla</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Peru and Chili</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>100,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Cat, Wild</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>10,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>„ House</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>1,000,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Ermine</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Asia and Europe</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>400,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Fisher</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Fitch</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Europe</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>600,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Fox, Silver</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Asia and America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>,, Cross</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Asia and America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>,, Blue</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Europe and America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>,, White</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Arctic</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>75,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>„ Red</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Asia and Europe</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>300,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>60,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>,, Gray</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>30,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>,, Kitt</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>America...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>40,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Hamster</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Europe</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>200,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Hare</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Asia and Europe</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,500,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Kolinsky</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Asia</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>80,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Lamb</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Persian</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>100,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Astrakhan</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>600,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>European</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,000,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Lion</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>500</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Lynx</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>50,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Marten</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>130,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>,, Stone...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Europe</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>150,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>,, Baum...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Europe</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>60,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>,, Russian Sable</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>100,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Mink</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>250,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Russia</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>50,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Monkey</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Africa</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>40,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Musk Rat</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,000,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Russia</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>100,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Nutria</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>South America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,000,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Opossum</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>250,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Otter, Land</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>40,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>,, Sea</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>North Pacific</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Rabbit</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Europe</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5,000,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Raccoon</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>500,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Seal, Hair</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Atlantic</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,000,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>„ Fur</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Pacific</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>200,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Skunk</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>550,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Squirrel</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Siberia</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6,000,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Tiger</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Bengal and North China</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>500</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>∙∖Volf</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>25,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Wolverin</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>3,500</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>For the habits of these animals, and their modes of life, reference must be made
                    to the separate articles, and to such works as those of Cuvier and Brehm. But a
                    brief account may be given here of the different qualities of the pelts, with
                    some general remarks as to their average value and their customary uses.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Badger.</hi> —Size, 1 by 2 feet; overhair coarse, 3 to 4 inches
                    long, black with silver spots. The German are the best. Fur woolly. American
                    have softer overhair. Used for robes, military trappings, and brashes. Value of
                    prime, from 2s. to 6s. per skin..</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bear, Blade.—</hi> Size, 3 by 6 feet; overhair 6 to 8 inches
                    long, fine, flowing, and glossv; fur thin. Best are American. Used for robes,
                    military caps, and mats. The finest are the cubs. Value of prime, from £1 to £4.
                    . „ , .</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bear, Brown.—</hi><hi rend="italic">Sxa</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >∖</hi><hi rend="italic">e</hi> size as the black, and very fine in
                    overhair.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n873/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0873-0838"/>
                <p>Found only in the Hudson s Bay territory. Used for muffs and garniture. Value of
                    best prime, £15. Quantity very small.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bear, Grizzly.—</hi> Larger than the black; coarse hair; thick
                    heavy pelt. Only found in western part of United States. Used as robes. Value,
                    £1 to £2. <hi rend="subscript"> ¶</hi><hi rend="italic">Bear, White.—</hi>
                    Largest of the bear family; hair short and ngid; pelt thick. Found only in the
                    Arctic regions. The best pure white are used for robes. Value from £10 to
                    £20.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Beaver.</hi><hi rend="italic">~~</hi>-Size, 2 by 8 feet;
                    overhair 3 inches long, coarse and brown in colour; fur thick, fine, and dark
                    grey. Best are from Labrador and Moose Fort. Used in every form and fashion in
                    all northern countries; highly prized in Russia and China. Value from 4s. to
                    12s. per pound in the raw parchment state.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Buffalo.—</hi> Size, 8 to 12 feet’long; hair coarse, colour dun
                    brown. Only found on the western and northern American prairies. Best are from
                    the region of the Saskatchewan river. Prime are used as robes; coarse and
                    unprime as leather for moccasins. Value 12s. to £2.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Chinchilla.—</hi> Two kinds, real and bastard. Size of real, 8
                    by 12 inches; overhair and fur of equal length—about 1⅜ inches long, very fine,
                    and like wool may be spun and woven; colour silver grey and dark. Best are from
                    Peru. Used for muffs, boas, and borders on garments; value from 4s. to 12s. The
                    bastard are from Chili (chinchilla means the Chilian skin), short in fur, small
                    in size, weak in pelt, and are worth from 5d. to 10d.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cat, Wild.—</hi> Overhair and fur thin and coarse; colour grey;
                    value and uses very limited. Civet cats are sometimes admired for their singular
                    marks, but are in poor demand. House cats are too well known to require a
                    description. Their colours are black, grey, red, and mottled. Best come from
                    Holland; the poorest from Russia. Used very generally for fur work. Price of
                    best black 4s. to 8s.; other sorts nominal.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ermine. —</hi> Size, 4 by 10 inches; overhair and fur fine,
                    soft, and close; pelt thin and tough; colour pure white, the tip of the tail
                    black. Best are from Barabinsk and? Ischim, in Siberia. Used for muffs,
                    garments, and linings. Value variable; the best have been as high as 6s., and as
                    low as 7d.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fisher.—</hi> Size, 15 by 30 inches; overhair very fine,
                    glossy, dark, and durable, 2 inches long; fur close; tail 12 inches long, bushy,
                    and dark. A right noble skin. Best from British America. Value from £2 to
                    £4.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fitch.—</hi> Size about that of the American mink; overhair
                    fine, 1⅛ inches long, with dark points; fur a golden yellow. Best from Germany,
                    Holland, and Denmark; smallest from Russia. Used for ladies’ furs according to
                    the prevalent fashion. Value from 2s. to 6s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fox, Silver.</hi> —Size, 2 by 4 feet; overhair thick and fine,
                    3 inches long, varied in colour from pale silver to a brilliant blue black; fur
                    fine and curly; its beauty places it at the head of all fancy furs; the tail is
                    a royal brush. The choicest are from Labrador and Moose Fort; those*of Russia
                    are more woolly and less valuable. Used for muffs, boas, and linings of robes.
                    Price from £10 to £40.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fox, Cross. —</hi> Not quite so large as the silver, with fine
                    overhair, but a shade of red at the points, and from the paleness of the fur
                    making a distinct dark cross at the shoulders. Best are from the Hudson’s Bay
                    territory, and valued from £2 to £8.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fox, Blue. —</hi> Size the same as the cross, with grey-blue
                    overhair, and a woolly fur. The finest are from Archangel on the White Sea, and
                    from Greenland. Value from £2 to £4.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fox, White.</hi> —Size the same as the cross, with pure white
                    overhair and fur. The best are from Labrador, the poorest from Asia. Value from
                    4s. to 12s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Pox,</hi><hi rend="italic">Rcd.-JWeW</hi> known to all northern
                    nations; abundant in Europe, but in size and beauty inferior to the American
                    family. The former fetch 4s., while those from Labrador are valued at 16s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fox, Grey.—</hi> Only found in the United States. Overhair is
                    grey, sprinkled with silver on the back, the sides are yellow, and the tail an
                    ashen grey. Value from 4s. to 8s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fox, Kitt.—</hi> Found in north-west America and in Tartary.
                    Overhair fine; the back is a pure grey, the sides yellow, and the belly white.
                    In size it is the smallest of the foxes. Price from Is. to 3s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hamster.—</hi> Size, 3 by 5 inches; hair short and close, back
                    grey and the sides yellow. A great trouble to the farmers in Germany, who spare
                    no pains to exterminate them. The pelt is made into finings for cloaks.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hare.—</hi> Overhair fine; fur very long, fine, abundant, and
                    strong; pelt weak; colour grey and white. Best are from Russia. This skin is
                    largely used by furriers, but its fur is among the best for hatters purposes.
                    Value from 5d. to Is.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Kolinsky.—</hi> Found only in Asia, and attains the size of the
                    American mink; overhair a golden red, 1⅜ inches long. The tails make excellent
                    pencils for painters. Value from 2s. to 4s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lamb.—</hi> The finest, dark, close curled skins come from
                    Persia; the next grade from the Crimea, and are grey in colour; inferior skins
                    from Astrakhan. All these are used by furriers for caps, borders, and garments.
                    The finest Persian are worth 12s. to £1, the bnmean 6s., and the Astraklιan from
                    Is. to 2s. The lambskins of western Europe are used for lining gloves. Angora
                    sheep are sometimes in demand, and are coloured red, blue, grey, and orange to
                    suit the fashion for fringes and borders. Their value is from 12s. to £2.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lion.—</hi> The finest from Asia. Specimens are rare, and price
                    variable.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lynx.</hi> —Size, 2 by 3⅜ feet; overhair fine and flowing, of a
                    clear silver blue shade, sprinkled with black; length of overhair 3 to 4 inches.
                    Best are from Sweden and Labrador. Value from 8s. to £1.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Marten, American.—</hi> Size from 5 by 15 inches to 8 by 20
                    inches; overhair fine and flowing, 1 to 2 inches long; fur close and thick;
                    colour of best a dark coffee brown, of poorest a pale yellow. The finest are
                    from the Great Whale River and Labrador. Always a choice and valued pelt. Price
                    of best £5, of poorest 2s. The tips of the tails are highly prized for artists’
                    brushes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Marten, Stone.—</hi> Found in Europe; the best from Hungary and
                    Turkey. Colour a dull grey, overhair coarse, and fur woolly. Value of best
                    prime, 8s. to 12s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Marten, Baum.—</hi> Found in Europe and Asia, of fine overhair,
                    but woolly fur, of a brownish colour, approaching that of the American marten,
                    and furnished with a long and bushy tail. Value from £1 to £2.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Marten, Russian Sable.—</hi> These skins are in the highest
                    estimation with furriers. Size about the same as the American marten, but the
                    overhair is much more fine and flowing, of a rich bluish dark shade, and from 1⅜
                    to 2⅛ inches long; the pelt is very soft, tough, and durable. The best are from
                    Yakutsk in Siberia, the next from the Lena river, and the poorest from the lower
                    Amoor. Very choice grades, but of a browner shade, are furnished by Kamchatka.
                    Value of the poor Saghalien from 4s. to 8s.; while the darkest from Okhotsk will
                    command £30.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Mink, American.—</hi> This valuable skin has nearly the size of
                    the size of the marten, with an overhair that is shorter and slightly more
                    rigid, but vies with the marten in elegance of lustre, the choicest having a
                    dark blue shade that is always admired in furs. The best’are from Nova Scotia,
                    the State of Maine, and the Labrador coast. It is most abundant in the middle
                    and north-western States. Value of the best, from 12s. to £2.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Mink, Russian.—</hi> Of smaller size than the American, and
                    inferior in all other respects, but still a valuable pelt. Price of prime, from
                    2s. to 6s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Monkey.—</hi> From the west coast of Africa; has a long, thin,
                    flowing hair; of various colours, chiefly black and dun grey. Has a limited use
                    with furriers, fetching from 2s. to 6s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Musk-Rat.—</hi> A well-known fur in North America. Size 8 by 12
                    inches; overhair coarse and light brown; fur fine, thick, and silky; in general
                    favour with furriers, and available for a great variety of purposes. Best are
                    from New England and New York; very prolific in cultivated regions. The price is
                    very fluctuating, and as the annual collection varies from three to five
                    millions of skins, it is difficult to forecast the market value. Price for
                    prime, from 6d. to 3s. A variety of black coloured musk-rat from Delaware and
                    Maryland fetches double these prices.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Nutria.—</hi> From the La Plata, South America; in size and
                    value between the beaver and the musk-rat; overhair coarse and rigid; fur short
                    and fine; pelts too often unsound, and hence the value of the fur is chiefly for
                    hats. Price of dry skins from Is. to 2s. per pound.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Opossum.—</hi> Chiefly from the United States, but some also
                    from Australia. Overhair long, coarse and whitish grey; fur woolly. Best from
                    Ohio. Value from 5d. to 2s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Otter.—</hi> Comes from all northern countries. Size of best, 2
                    by 5 feet; overhair thick and close; colour brown black. Best are from Labrador
                    and Canada. The skin is in high reputation and general use with furriers. Value
                    of best, £1, 10s. to £3.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Otter, Sea.—</hi> Found only in the North Pacific Ocean, on the
                    coasts of Alaska, Kamchatka, and Japan. Size, 2 by 6 feet; overhair exceedingly
                    fine, and extending but little beyond the fur, which itself is very thick,
                    close, fine, and silky; colour dark brown, occasionally with silver points
                    regularly interspersed; pelt pliable and firm. The poorest skins are not more
                    valuable than those of the beaver; but the fine choice specimens command from
                    £20 to £100. They are in high repute with the Russians and Chinese.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Rabbit.—</hi> Size, 10 by 16 inches; fur thick and fine; pelt
                    weak; colour all shades from black to white. Best are found in England, but the
                    purest come from Poland. The best coloured skins are used by furriers, but much
                    the larger portion is cut for hatters’ fur. The animal is largely bred in
                    warrens, and its flesh used as food; the pelts thus become of secondary
                    importance, and, being abundant, supply a cheap fur.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Raccoon.—</hi> One of the peculiar and valuable pelts of the
                    United States, and flourishing best in cultivated regions. Size, 1 by 2 feet;
                    overhair not fine, but bright in colour, 3 inches long, thick, and flowing; fur
                    resembling that of the beaver; colour from silver blue to grey brown and coffee
                    brown. Best are from Michigan and Ohio. Average value of prime, 4s. Some
                    specimens vie with the fisher in its peculiar shade, and some even with the
                    silver fox, and such rare skins bring from £1 to £4.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n874/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0874-0839"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Seal, Hair.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> Chiefly from the North
                    Atlantic. Size from 3 to 6 feet; hair coarse and rigid; no fur; divided into
                    white coats, blue backs, mottled, and ordinary. Used for saddlery and military
                    purposes. Average price, 2s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Seal, Fur. —</hi> Found only in the Pacific and in the South
                    Atlantic. Size of the wigs, 4 by 8 feet; of the large, 3 by 6 feet; middling, 2⅛
                    by 5 feet; small, 2 by 4 feet; the pups vary in length from 2 to 4 feet.
                    Overhair coarse and rigid; fur fine, thick, silky, and very uniformly
                    distributed. Pelt thin, pliable, and of light weight. The largest number come
                    from Alaska, whence 100,000 are allowed by law to be brought annually. The best
                    of these are the prime middling pups. Value varies from £1 to £3 in the salted
                    state. A few fane skins come from the coast of British Columbia, and being
                    caught in winter are in prime condition. The choicest skins are taken on the
                    South Shetland and South Georgia Islands in the Antarctic Ocean. Fur fine beyond
                    comparison; pelt very pliable, light, and thin and firin. Value salted, from £2
                    to £10.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Skunk.—</hi> Another peculiar production of North America.
                    Size, 10 by 16 inches long; overhair fine, 3 inches long, dark blue and coffee
                    brown, thick, glossy, and flowing. Many have two white stripes, more or less
                    broad, extending from the head to the tail. It is now easy to deodorize the
                    skin, and the fur is a popular one in all countries. The best are from New York
                    and Ohio; value of best prime black, from 4s. to 10s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Squirrel. —</hi> Only those of northern Europe and Asia have a
                    value as merchandise. American are worthless. Size, 3 by 6 inches; overhair and
                    fur equally fine; colour from pale blue to clear dark blue; best are from
                    eastern Siberia; palest and poorest from European Russia; bellies white; tails
                    long and bushy. This finis in universal demand among furriers for muffs and
                    linings, as well as for large garments. Pelt pliable and tough; fur durable,
                    close, and fine. The tails are made into boas and brushes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Tiger.—</hi> Specimens are rare. Those from Bengal are large
                    and short in hair, but well marked; while those from northern China have hair 2
                    to 3 inches long, and frequently measure 10 to 14 feet in length. Value of the
                    latter, from £10 to £20.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Wolf.—</hi> The largest are from Labrador, measuring from 4 to
                    6 feet long, chiefly grey-brown in colour, with long, flowing, coarse overhair.
                    The finest are from Fort Churchill, and fetch a high price. The American prairie
                    wolf is a variety inferior in every respect. Price of best, £2; of the inferior,
                    4s. The wolf is very destructive of the fur-bearing animals, and is an object of
                    extermination with all trappers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Woloerin.—</hi> From Russia, Norway, and Hudson’s Bay. Colour a
                    clear dark brown, overhair coarse, 2⅜ inches long. Value from 12s. to 24s.</p>
                <p>Of the fur-bearers, those that seek their food in water have their finest but
                    shortest fur on the belly, and longer fnr upon the back; while those that avoid
                    the rivers have their longest and finest fur upon the back, and their bellies
                    clothed with fine, long, flowing overhair.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Dressing.</hi> —-Raw furs are made ready for use by softening
                    the pelt with pure butter or olive oil, trampling them in tubs filled with fine
                    hardwood sawdust at about blood heat, drawing the pelt over a sharp knife to
                    remove every particle of flesh, and finally trampling them again in clean
                    sawdust. The pelt thus becomes soft and pliable like the fine kid used for
                    gloves. They are then ready for the furrier, who assorts the skins as to colour
                    and overhair, and cuts them in various ways to bring them to the pattern of the
                    article required. Having been sewed together with a close, fine overseam, the
                    article is damped, and stretched upon a smooth pine board after a pattern
                    marked, then nailed along its edges and left to dry. After removal from the
                    board the article is trimmed, and softened by rubbing, and is then ready for the
                    liner. The skill of the furrier lies in the taste exhibited in the arrangement
                    of the furs, and in the economy of use of material.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Dyeing.—</hi> Furs are dyed in a variety of ways to make them
                    uniform in colour, and adapt them to the fashion and taste of the time.
                    Ordinarily this is a cheap and ready process, and only becomes an art when
                    employed upon fine skins, from which the overhair has been first removed by
                    plucking, leaving the fur alone to receive the dye-stuff. Among these are the
                    skins of the musk rat, beaver, otter, and especially the fur seal; the last has
                    received very careful attention, as its entire value depends upon the perfection
                    and success of the process. Unprime fur seals part with their overhair very
                    reluctantly, while the seasoned skins are very readily unhaired, leaving the fur
                    in all its smoothness; thus the best grades are likely to be very good, while
                    the rest rank only from ordinary to very common. Λ subsequent process is the
                    removal of all grease from the fur, which is effected by repeated washings in
                    softened water; if this is imperfectly done, the colour will be uneven and not
                    permanent. The final work is to prepare a dye of suitable strength, and apply it
                    in a suitable way, to infuse the colouring matters into the fur, without
                    suffering too much of it to reach the pelt, whereby its durability might be
                    ruined. London claims to have accomplished this for the sealskin in a manner
                    that distances all competition; and it certainly enjoys a wide popularity, as
                    well as the substantial fruits of the sale of its production of coloured seals.
                    ButAmerica also has its successful dyers of seals, one of the most important of
                    the results they have achieved being the giving to the fur seal a fine deep
                    brown colour, without injuring or burning the fur, while leaving the pelt soft,
                    light, and durable.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Prices of Fancy Furs.—</hi> The market value of dressed and
                    manufactured furs is at the mercy of fickle fashion and the weather. The
                    production of any one variety is very limited, and consequently those that are
                    in fashion during a cold winter command full and even extravagant prices, while
                    others, of equal intrinsic merit, have a merely nominal value. The consumer is
                    not more responsible for this than are the furrier and the fur merchant. It
                    was’the remark of an old and successful fur dealer that “furs when wanted are
                    diamonds, when not wanted are charcoal.” This fact renders the trade an
                    extremely hazardous one, and tends to make the venture in it a matter of
                    speculation rather than of provident enterprise; and while the consumer
                    occasionally may have to pay a very extravagant price for some few varieties of
                    furs for a short period, it happens far more frequently that the fur dealer is a
                    severe sufferer by reason of sanguine anticipations of advance in values, which
                    in nine cases out of ten are doomed to disappointment. <hi rend="smallcaps">(μ.
                        μ. b.)</hi></p>
                <p>The foregoing article is reprinted, by permission of Messrs Little, Brown, and
                    Co., Boston, Mass., from <hi rend="italic">Fur and the Fur Trade,</hi> by Μ. Μ.
                    Backus, Boston, 1879.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
