<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0098-0089-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FERID-EDDIN-ATHAR (9th edition, volume 9, page
                    89)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137253">Sufis</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048144">Orientalists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1056116">Pearls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093763">Religion</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h9v">Pearls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sg0z">Druggists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n98/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FERID-EDDIN-ATHAR</label> (1119-1229), or <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Farid Uddin Attar,</hi> a Persian poet and mystic, was born
                    at Kedken, near Nishapur, 513 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.</hi> (1119 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">a.d.),</hi> and was put to death 627 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >a.h.</hi> (1229 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.),</hi> thus having reached the
                    age of 110 years. His real name was Muhammed ben Ibrahim, and Ferid Eddin was
                    simply an honourable title equivalent to Pearl of Religion. He followed for a
                    time his father’s profession of druggist or perfumer, and hence the name of
                    Athar or Attar, which he afterwards employed as his poetical designation.
                    According to the account of Doulat Shah, his interest in the great mystery of
                    the higher life of man was awakened in the following way. One day a wandering
                    fakir gazed sadly into his shop, and, when ordered to be gone, replied: “It is
                    nothing for me to go; but I grieve for thee, O druggist, for how wilt thou be
                    able to think of death, and leave all these goods of thine behind thee?” The
                    word was in season; and Muhammed ben Ibrahim the druggist soon gave up his shop
                    and began to study the mystic theosophy of the Sufis under Sheikh Rekenuddin. So
                    thoroughly did he enter into the spirit of that religion that he was before long
                    recognized as one of its principal representatives. He visited Mecca, and on his
                    return was invested with the Sufi mantle by Sheikh Majduddin of Eaghdad. The
                    greater portion of his life was spent in the town of Shadyakh, but he is not
                    unfrequently named Nishapuri, after the city of his boyhood and youth. The story
                    of his death is a strange one. Captured by a soldier of Jenghiz Khan, he was
                    about to be sold for a thousand dirhems, when he advised his captor to keep him,
                    as doubtless a larger offer would yet be made; but when the second bidder said
                    he would give a bag of horse fodder for the old man, he asserted that he was
                    worth no more, and had better be sold. The soldier, irritated at the loss of the
                    first offer, immediately slew him. A noble tomb was erected over his grave at
                    Shadyakh, and the spot acquired a reputation for sanctity. Ferid Eddin was a
                    voluminous writer, and has left no fewer than 120,000 couplets of poetry, though
                    in his later years he carried his asceticism so far as to deny himself the
                    pleasures of poetical composition. His most famous work is the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Maηtic Uttαir</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> or language of birds,
                    an allegorical poem containing a complete survey of the life and doctrine of the
                    Sufis. It is extremely popular among Mahometans both of the Sunnite and Shiite
                    sects, and the manuscript copies are consequently very numerous. The birds,
                    according to the poet, were tired of a republican constitution, and longed for a
                    king. As the lapwing, having guided Solomon through the desert, best knew what a
                    king should be, he was asked whom they should choose. The Simorg in the
                    Caucasus, was his reply. But the way to the Caucasus was long and dangerous, and
                    most of the birds excused themselves from the enterprise. A few, however, set
                    out; but by the time they reached the great king’s court, their number was
                    reduced to thirty. The thirty birds <hi rend="italic">{si morg)</hi> wing-weary
                    and hunger-stricken, at length gained access to their chosen monarch the Simorg;
                    but only to find that they strangely lost their identity in his presence—that
                    they are he, and lie is they. In such strange fashion does the poet image forth
                    the search of the human soul after absorption into the divine.</p>
                <p>The text of the <hi rend="italic">Mantie Uttair</hi> was published by Garcin de
                    Tassy in 1857; a summary of its contents by the same Orientalist appeared in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Revue Contemporaine,</hi> t. xxiv., and was reprinted as
                        <hi rend="italic">La poésie philosophique et religieuse chez les
                        Persans,</hi> 1856; and this was succeeded by a complete translation in
                    1860. Among Ferid-Eddin’s other works may be mentioned his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pend Nameh,</hi> or Book of Reflection, of which a translation by Silvestre
                    de Sacy appeared in <hi rend="italic">Les mines de l'orient,</hi> vol. ii.; <hi
                        rend="italic">Bulbul Nameh,</hi> or Book of the Nightingale; <hi
                        rend="italic">Wasalet Nameh,</hi> or Book of Conjunctions; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Khusru ra Gul,</hi> the King and the Rose; and <hi rend="italic">Τezkiret
                        al Aulia.</hi> See Sir Gore Ouseley, <hi rend="italic">Biographical Notices
                        of Persian Poets,</hi> 1846; Von Hammer Purgstall, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">der schonen Redekünste Persiens,</hi> p.
                    140; <hi rend="italic">The Oriental Collections,</hi> vol. ii., 1798; Palmer,
                        <hi rend="italic">History of Sufism.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
