<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0782-0747-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FREE IMPERIAL CITIES (9th edition, volume 9, page
                    747)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950757">Hamburgers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130034">Spires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:803903">Aix</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139824">Swabians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4p01z">Spires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z77x">Swabian</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p527">Basel</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n782/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FREE IMPERIAL CITIES</label> is the ordinary English
                    translation of <hi rend="italic">Freie Reichs-Städte,</hi> a technical
                    expression in German history. In Germany, as in other countries of Europe, a
                    considerable number of towns succeeded, in the midst of the dynastic confusion
                    of the Middle Ages, in maintaining or acquiring more or less complete
                    independence of the state or sovereign within whose territory they were
                    situated. This they effected partly by forming defensive leagues with each
                    other, and partly by procuring, in return for service or money, privileges and
                    protection from the successive occupants of the imperial throne. Of these free
                    towns a certain proportion rose by commerce and industry to a position of great
                    influence, and ultimately took rank along with kingdoms and principalities as
                    integral members of the body politic of the empire. They first appear distinctly
                    in this character in the reign of Henry VII. (1308- 1313). Their number was
                    continually fluctuating, for their liberties were almost as easily lost as they
                    were with difficulty acquired. Most of them had to maintain a continual conflict
                    by war or diplomacy with the ecclesiastical or secular potentates of their
                    district, and not unfrequently their interests were betrayed by the emperors
                    themselves. Mainz, which in the 13th century was at the head of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Rheinisches Städtebund,</hi> or confederation of the cities of
                    the Rhine, was conquered in 1462, and subjected to the bishop’s see; Zwickau,
                    Altenburg, and Chemnitz, put in pawn first by Frederick II. and afterwards by
                    several of the later emperors, thus fell into the hands of the dukes of Saxony;
                    other free cities placed themselves of their own accord under the control of
                    prince or bishop; some, as Donauworth, were deprived of their privileges by the
                    emperors on account of real or alleged offences; others again were separated
                    from the empire by foreign conquest, as Hainault or Hagenau, Colmar,
                    Schlett-stedt, Weissenburg, Landau, and Besançon by Louis XIV.; and Basel
                    notably preferred to cast in its lot with the rising confederation of
                    Switzerland. At the diet of Augsburg in 1474 the free imperial cities divided
                    themselves for the first time into two benches, the Rhenish and the Swabian, the
                    former also including those of Alsace, Wetterau, Thuringia, and Saxony, and the
                    latter those of Franconia. They were formally constituted the third collegium of
                    the diet by the peace of Westphalia in 1648. At the time of the French
                    Revolution they still numbered 51,—the Rhenish bench comprising Cologne,
                    Aix-la-Chapelle or Aachen, Lübeck, Worms, Spires, Frankfort-on-the-Main, Goslar,
                    Bremen, Hamburg, Mühlhausen, Nordhausen, Dortmund, Friedberg, and Wetzlar; and
                    the Swabian bench, Ratisbon or Regensburg, Augsburg, Nuremberg, Ulm, Esslingen,
                    Reutlingen, Nördlingen, Rothenburg on the Tauber, Schwäbisch-Hall, Roth weil,
                    Ueberlingen, Heilbronn, Gmünd, Memmingen, Lindau, Dinkelsbühl, Biberach,
                    Ravensburg, Schweinfurt, Kempten, Windsheim, Kaufbeuem, Weil, Wangen, Isny,
                    Pfullendorf, Offenburg, Leutkirchen, Wimpfen, Weissenburg in the Nordgau,
                    Giengen, Gengenbach, Zeíl on the Hammerbach, Buchhorn, Ahlen, Buchau, Bopfingen.
                    A large proportion of these towns had then at least as little claim to their
                    exceptional position as the pocket-burghs of England before the passing of the
                    Reform Act. By the decision of the imperial deputation of 1803 <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Reichsdeputationshauptschluss)</hi> Cologne, Aix-la-Chapelle, Worms, and
                    Spires were assigned to France; only six, Hamburg, Lübeck, Bremen, Augsburg,
                    Frankfort-on-the-</p>
                <p>Main, and Nuremberg were allowed to retain their <hi rend="italic"
                        >Reichsfreiheit,</hi> or, in other words, to hold directly of the empire. On
                    the dissolution of the empire in 1806, Augsburg and Nuremberg were given to
                    Bavaria, and Frankfort was made the seat of Count Dahlberg, the archbishop and
                    electoral prince of Mainz, who was appointed primate of the confederation of the
                    Rhine. On the establishment of the German confederation in 1815, Hamburg,
                    Lübeck, Bremen, and Frankfort were recognized as free cities, and the first
                    three still hold that position in the new German empire; but Frankfort, in
                    consequence of the part it took in the war of 1866, has been degraded to the
                    rank of an ordinary Prussian town.</p>
                <p>In the earlier centuries of their existence the free cities of the empire were
                    under the jurisdiction of two imperial officers, one of whom, the imperial
                    advocate or <hi rend="italic">Reichsvogt,</hi> took charge of criminal cases,
                    and the other, the imperial procurator or <hi rend="italic"
                        >Reichs-Schultheiss</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Schuldheiss,</hi> dealt with
                    the civil cases. As time went on many of the cities purchased the right of
                    filling these offices with members of the principality; and in several instances
                    the imperial authority fell practically into desuetude except when it was roused
                    into action by peculiar circumstances, such as a dispute between the citizens
                    and their magistrates. The internal constitution of the cities was organized
                    after no common type; but there w ere several of them whose privileges were
                    drawn up in imitation of those of Cologne, which had been one of the very first
                    to assert its independence.</p>
                <p>See J. J. Moser, <hi rend="italic">Rcichsstädtisches</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Handbuch,</hi> Tübingen, 1732; D. Hänlein, <hi rend="italic">Anmerkungen
                        über</hi><hi rend="italic">die</hi><hi rend="italic">Geschichte der
                        Reichsstädte,</hi> Ulm, 1775; Á. Wendt, <hi rend="italic">Beschreibung der
                        kaiserl. freien Reichsstädte,</hi> Leipsic, 1804; G. W. Hugo, <hi
                        rend="italic">Die Mediatisirung</hi><hi rend="italic">der deutschen
                        Reichsstädte,</hi> Carlsruhe, 1838; <hi rend="italic">Ñ adz,
                        Deutsche</hi><hi rend="italic">Verfassungsgeschichte.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
