<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0882-0847-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FURNITURE (9th edition, volume 9, page 847)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s26r">Chest</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:853874">Chests</term>
                    <term ref="fast:853827">Chest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n882/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FURNITURE</label> is the name, of obscure origin, used to
                    describe the chattels and fittings required to adapt houses, churches, ships,
                    &amp;c., for use. The sculptures, paintings, and metal work of antiquity, of the
                    Middle Ages, and of the Renaissance, now kept iu museums and private
                    collections, have, with few exceptions, formed part of decorations or of
                    furniture made for temples, churches, or houses. Most of our ancient bronzes, if
                    not images taken from ancient shrines, are pieces of mirrors, tripods, altar
                    vessels, even the dishes and pans of the kitchen. Wood, ivory, precious stones,
                    bronze, silver, and gold have been used from the most ancient times in the
                    construction or for the decoration of seats, chests, tables, and other
                    furniture, and for the shrines and altars of sacred buildings.</p>
                <p>The kind of objects required for furniture have varied according to the changes
                    of manners and customs, as well as with reference to the materials at the
                    command of the workman, in different climates and countries. Of the furniture of
                    the ancient Egyptians there remain several examples. The British Museum contains
                    six chairs, about the same in height as those now used. One is of ebony, turned
                    in the lathe and inlaid with collars and dies of ivory. It is low, with a back;
                    and both back and legs are strengthened with rails of cane. The seat is of
                    plaited cane slightly hollowed. Another is shaped out of two frames of four
                    pieces of wood each, hinged in the centres of the longer sides, the lower ends
                    carved into the form of the heads of animals; the seat has been made of skin or
                    other flexible material so as to fold flat. Some Egyptian couches and seats had
                    the legs carved like those of panthers; some had the arms or seat supported by
                    figures representing slaves or captives taken in war. They were upholstered with
                    rich stuffs and are accurately represented in wall paintings (see the great
                    French work, <hi rend="italic">Description de</hi><hi rend="italic">l</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">Egypte).</hi> Workmen’s
                    tables, massive blocks of wood with four plain legs, and head rests hollowed
                    out, standing 9 or 10 inches high, are preserved in the British Museum,— some
                    being of alabaster, probably for the sake of coolness. Painted wooden chests,
                    with convex lids (not hinged), and mummy cases can be seen both in the British
                    Museum and in the Louvre in Paris.</p>
                <p>The excavations of;Nineveh have brought to light sculptured representations of
                    Assyrian seats. They were massive, the ends of the seat frame projected in the
                    shape of rams’ heads; in some instances figures of captives support the arms; in
                    one described by Sir H. A. Layard, two horses resting on the lower bars from
                    front to back support the seat. The seats were cushioned or upholstered with
                    rich materials. An elaborate piece of carved ivory, with depressions to hold
                    coloured glass, agate, &amp;c., from Nineveh, now in the British Museum, has
                    been inlaid into a throne, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n883/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0883-0848"/> —showing that such objects were sometimes
                    richly decorate! The carving is apparently of Egyptian origin. The furniture of
                    the Assyrians was more massive, and less varied and elegant in execution, than
                    that of the Egyptians.</p>
                <p>Greek seats <hi rend="italic">(thronoi)</hi> are sculptured in the Parthenon
                    frieze now in the British Museum. They resemble turned wood structures, though
                    perhaps representing bronze. The arms are low and straight, and the backs
                    upright. A curious chair of this kind is represented on one of the bas reliefs
                    from Xanthus (British Museum). In the same collection will be seen statues
                    seated in chairs framed in square bars, the horizontal pieces morticed into the
                    upright, and these details are carefully represented in marble. Certain
                    far-famed gold and ivory statues of colossal size, at Olympia and other places,
                    were represented seated. The bars and frames of the chairs, and of the
                    footstools and pedestals, were constructed of cedar wood, coloured and inlaid
                    with plates of sculptured ivory, and of gold and other precious materials. A
                    sacred chest with carved lid, a table covered with ivory carvings, and other
                    objects in these shrines are described by Pausanias. Unfortunately we have but
                    his verbal accounts of them (see Q. de Quincy, <hi rend="italic">Jupiter</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Olympien,</hi> in which careful engravings are given of their
                    probable shapes). Chairs of the shape in general use .forty or fifty years ago
                    (the front and back legs curved outwards, with a plain piece of wood curved to
                    fit the shoulders for the top rail of the back) are not uncommon in paintings on
                    vases. The vase rooms of the British Museum and the Louvre give frequent
                    illustrations of chairs, couches, &amp;c , as well as of the stuffs used in
                    upholstering them. Sumptuous Greek furniture, during the last two centuries B,c
                    , was made of bronze, damascened with gold and silver.</p>
                <p>The Romans employed Greek artists and workmen. Their chairs, couches, and seats
                    were of similar shape to those of the Greeks. During meals men reclined on
                    couches each made to hold three persons; a low rail protected the back; three of
                    these couches surrounded the table at entertainments, leaving the fourth side
                    open for service. The decoration consisted of rich coverings, constantly changed
                    to suit the season, or in honour of the guests. Women sat during meals. The <hi
                        rend="italic">sella</hi><hi rend="italic">curulis,</hi> a folding
                    cross-shaped seat, was carried in the chariot, and used in the forums, baths,
                    lecture halls, &amp;c. It was often inlaid with ivory. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sellae,</hi> square seats of bronze, were also often carried about, as well
                    as footstools, the former raising the sitter above the heads of humbler persons.
                    Couches, covered with tilts and curtains, could be carried by slaves, and used
                    as litters. Four silver figuresof the 4th century, representing the capital
                    cities of the empire, now in the British Museum, are considered to have
                    ornamented the ends of the poles or shafts of a litter. Tables were of marble,
                    resting on sphinxes or other animals. Dining tables were of wood, curiously
                    veneered, to which a high value was often attached, They rested on tripods or
                    frames of four or of six legs, ornamented with figures, busts, animals, &amp;c.,
                    in bronze. Tables were changed with each course. Tables were sometimes protected
                    by rims or borders, sometimes rested on feet of carved ivory. Books and other
                    property were kept in <hi rend="italic">scrinia,</hi> round chests that could be
                    fastened. Clothes and provisions had special rooms to hold them. In the later
                    ages of the empire, in Rome, and afterwards in Constantinople, gold and silver
                    were plentiful for furniture; even cooking and common house vessels were
                    occasionally made in those metals.</p>
                <p>The chair of St Peter in Rome, a solid square seat, with pedimental back and
                    panelled with carved ivory, that of St Maximian in the cathedral of Ravenna,
                    round backed, with arms also panelled with carved ivory, and many
                    representations on carved ivory diptychs or tablets, will give the student a
                    correct notion of the furniture of the divided empire. The character of the
                    curule chair survived and may be recognized in the Bayeux tapestry (St Edward’s
                    seat), and in many mediaeval paintings. The architectural features so prominent
                    in much of the mediaeval furniture begins in these Byzantine and late Roman
                    thrones. These features became paramount as Pointed architecture became general
                    in Europe, and scarcely less so during the Renaissance. Most of the mediaeval
                    furniture, chests, seats, trays, àc., of Italian make were richly gilt and
                    painted. In northern Europe carved oak was more generally used. The coronation
                    chair in Westminster Abbey, made for Edward I. in the 13th century, has a gabled
                    and crocketed back, is panelled with tracery work, and rests on carved
                    lions,—the whole gilt and painted. State seats in feudal halls were benches with
                    ends carved in tracery, backs panelled or hung with cloths (called cloths of
                    estats), and canopies projecting above. Bedsteads were square frames, the
                    testers of panelled wood, and resting on carved posts. Chests of oak carved with
                    panels of tracery, or of Italian cypress (when they could be imported), were
                    used to hold and to carry clothes, tapestries, &lt;fcc., to distant castles and
                    manor houses; for house furniture had to be moved from place to place. A chest
                    of the reign of John is kept in the castle of Rockingham. Many can be seen in
                    old parish churches, and in the South Kensington Museum, the Louvre, and many
                    other Continental galleries. Carved stalls covered by elaborate tabernacle work
                    remain in many cathedrals and churches. The Hôtel de Cluny in Paris contains
                    numerous examples of this kind of wood work. Altars were backed by paintings in
                    canopied frames, closed byshutters, which werealso painted insideand outside. In
                    some German churches, e.^.,the cathedrals of Hildesheim and of Münster in
                    Westphalia, the entire picture (as well as the shutters) was made to open out,
                    showing ingenious receptacles for reliquaries within. Copes and other vestments
                    were kept in semicircular chests with ornamental lock plates and iron hinges; an
                    example is preserved in Wells cathedral. The splendour of most feudal houses
                    depended on pictorial tapestries which could be packed and carried from place to
                    place. Wardrobes were rooms fitted for the reception of dresses, as well as for
                    spices and other valuable stores. Excellent carving in relief was executed on
                    caskets, which were of wood or of ivory, with painting and gilding, and
                    decorated with delicate hinge and lock metal work. The general subjects of
                    sculpture were taken from legends of the saints or from metrical romances.</p>
                <p>Renaissance art made a great change in architecture, and this change was
                    exemplified in furniture. Cabinets and panelling took the outlines of palaces
                    and temples; sometimes they were actually constructed in perspective, <hi
                        rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> a small theatre front at Vicenza, the work of the
                    younger Palladio. Curious internal fittings were arranged in cabinets, still
                    following the details of architectural interiors. In Florence, Rome, Venice,
                    Milan, and other capitals of Italy, sumptuous cabinets, tables, chairs, chests,
                    &lt;fcc., were made to the orders of the native princes. Vasari <hi
                        rend="italic">(Lives of Painters)</hi> speaks of scientific diagrams and
                    mathematical problems illustrated in costly materials, by the best artists of
                    the day, on furniture made for the Medici family. The great extent of the rule
                    of Charles V. helped to give a uniform training to artists from various
                    countries resorting to Italy, so that cabinets, &amp;c., which were made in vast
                    numbers in Spain, Flanders, and Germany, can hardly be distinguished from those
                    executed in Italy. Francis I. and Henry VIII. encouraged the revived arts in
                    their respective dominions. Examples of 16th-century chests, cabinets, tables,
                    seats, sideboards, &lt;tc., can be seen in museums, and in many private houses.
                        <hi rend="italic">Pietra</hi><hi rend="italic">dura,</hi> or inlay of hard
                    pebbles, agate, lapis, lazuli, and other stones, ivory carved and inlaid, carved
                    and gilt wood, marquetry or veneering with thin woods, tortoiseshell, brass,
                    &amp;c., were <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n884/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0884-0849"/> used in making sumptuous furniture during the
                    first period of the Renaissance. A folding chair of wrought iron (made at
                    Augsburg), with numerous groups of figures in complete relief, is preserved at
                    Longford Castle, Wiltshire. Mirrors, caskets, and other objects in damascened
                    iron (Milan) are shown in the South Kensington Museum. Subjects of carving or
                    relief were generally drawn from the theological and cardinal virtues, from
                    classical mythology, from the seasons, months, &amp;c. Carved altarpieces and
                    woodwork in churches partook of the change in style. The stalls of the cathedral
                    of Amiens, of the Certosa of Pavia, the cathedral of Siena, and a great number
                    of churches in Venice, Florence, Rome, Perugia, and other Italian cities,
                    illustrate first the transition, then the full change from Gothic to classic
                    detail in ecclesiastical furniture.</p>
                <p>The elegance of form and perfection of detail, which are noticeable in the
                    furniture of the 16th century, declined during the 17th all over Europe. The
                    framework became bulky and heavy, and the details coarse. Silver furniture was
                    made in considerable quantities by the Spaniards in Spain and Italy, and it was
                    used in the courts of the French and English kings. A few examples of silver
                    tables, mirrors, &amp;c., now in Windsor Castle and at Knole, in Kent, are
                    reproduced in electrotype in the South Kensington Museum. To this period belongs
                    the name of André Charles Boule, who furnished the palace of Versailles. He
                    invented or perfected a beautiful system of veneering with brass and
                    tortoiseshell, brass and ebony, occasionally using white metal besides. Examples
                    of this buhl or boule are shown in the Apollo gallery of the Louvre.</p>
                <p>The system of veneering, or coating common wood with slices of rare and costly
                    woods, fastened down with glue by screw presses made to fit the surface to be
                    covered, came into general use in the 18th century. Marquetry is veneer of
                    different woods, forming a mosaic of pictorial or ornamental designs. In Italy,
                    in Spain, and throughout the dominions of Charles V. and his successors, figure
                    subjects, architectural views, and quaint interiors were represented in these
                    materials. Usually two or three woods were employed; they were tinted by means
                    cf heated sand in iron frames, and the tints graduated to the utmost nicety.
                    Sometimes these effects were produced by splitting and laying slices of the same
                    wood with the grain running in different directions. The fine marquetry of the
                    last century was made of tulip wood or mahogany, with lime, pear, holly, beech,
                    and other light-coloured woods; sometimes in ebony and ivory, in Italy
                    particularly; or ebony and mother-of-pearl, the latter in Holland. Woods were
                    occasionally stained green, blue, and other colours, but these tints were
                    sparingly employed by the more famous makers. Curiously grained specimens of
                    mahogany, known as letter wood and by other names, were used for veneering late
                    in the century by the <hi rend="italic">ciseleurs</hi> or makers of rich brass
                    and gilt metal edgings, which that wood shows off to perfection. The
                    golden-coloured satin wood, which was imported towards the end of the last
                    century, was much used as a ground in English marquetry.</p>
                <p>Looking-glasses in large sheets began to be exported from Venice at the end of
                    the 17th century; some were engraved with figures on the backs. The manufacture
                    was established at Tourlaville, then in Paris, and about the same time at
                    Battersea on the Thames—under Government protection in both countries. The light
                    fantastic frames which came into fashion in France were called <hi rend="italic"
                        >rococo</hi> (from <hi rend="italic">roquaille, coquaille,</hi> rock and
                    shell work). Carved and gilt furniture was made in Italy, where it was best
                    designed, and all over Europe till late in the 18th century. Robert Martin, who
                    used fine lac polish, gave the name of “Vernis Martin” to painted and polished
                    furniture of all kinds, from carriages and wardrobes to fans and snuff-boxes. He
                    died in 1763. The discovery of Herculaneum and Pompeii about the middle of the
                    last century turned attention to the elegant designs of the Greco-Roman period.
                    Riesener, David Roentgen (known as David), and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >ciseleur</hi> Gouthière are well known names of French cabinetmakers;
                    Chippendale, Lock, Sheraton, and Heppelwhite were Englishmen of the same
                    period—the last half of the 18th century. James and Robert Adam designed
                    beautiful satin wood and other furniture at that date. Medallions of porcelain
                    were sometimes inlaid in cabinet fronts. Most of these manufactures came to an
                    end during the French Revolution and the long war. The “empire” style, a stiff,
                    affected classicalism, prevailed in France during the reign of Napoleon. It is
                    shown in the metal mounts of veneered mahogany furniture, and in the carvings of
                    chair legs and backs.</p>
                <p>A return has been made during recent years to mediaeval designs. In England there
                    is a going back to the fashions prevalent during the first fifty years of the
                    last century. The elegant Louis XVI. style is more popular in France.</p>
                <p>As regards furniture of the day, and the proprieties which ought to be observed
                    in form and decoration, it is a matter of regret that no definite style is
                    recognized in Europe; there cannot but be some consequent waste of power and
                    uncertainty of aim. A few general principles, however, are held to be applicable
                    to the shape and arrangements of furniture of whatever style.</p>
                <p>Bedsteads are now very generally made of iron in most countries of Europe. They
                    are plain; the portions not covered with hangings are made in brass, or coated
                    with enamelled paint In most cases no attempt is made to decorate them. They are
                    clean, and easily taken to pieces and moved. They need no criticism. Bedroom
                    furniture is no longer as rich or costly as when it was the fashion to include
                    state bed-chambers among suites of rooms thrown open for the entertainment of
                    guests. Wardrobes, chests of drawers, toilet tables, are only required to be of
                    suitable size, and as conveniently arranged inside as possible, in order that
                    light and heavy objects may be put away so as to be got at with the least
                    possible exertion. Such pieces of furniture should have no projections of
                    cornices or ornaments which do but take up space. Light-coloured woods, with the
                    simplest decorations, are preferred, on account of their freshness and
                    cheerfulness. Common timber, such as pine, ash, oak, maple, &amp;c., French
                    polished, with coloured lines sparingly employed, are much used by London makers
                    for bedroom furniture; but they are less durable than mahogany. Imitations of
                    graining are general—indeed the practice was common even in ancient Rome. But
                    the Japanese methods of staining, powdering with gold dust, and polishing common
                    timber without hiding the grain, deserve adoption; and efforts have latterly
                    been made in London to bring them into use.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Chairs.—</hi> The good construction of chairs is a test of
                    workmanship. If the wood is well seasoned, the tenons and mortices cut with
                    exactness, the glue hot and good, and proper pressure used in putting them
                    together, the various parts of chairs should be as perfectly united as if the
                    wood had grown in the form required. Sir G. Wilkinson speaks of the admirable
                    skill of the makers of Egyptian chairs, which required no cross bars to the
                    legs. Lightness is another requisite. Very light chairs made of white wood with
                    plaited grass seats are made at Chiavari in Italy. Large manufactories of chairs
                    are carried on at High Wycombe, and other places where beech timber is easily
                    obtained. If chairs are carved, the carving should be so subordinate to the
                    outline and the comfort of the sitter as not to interfere with the dress, or be
                    liable to breakage from having salient points, masses, or ornaments. The <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n885/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0885-0850"/> mahogany carved chairs of Chippendale and
                    Sheraton are often copied, but the repetitions have not the spirit of the
                    originals. The slight irregularities and variations made by carvers, who never
                    absolutely repeat themselves in a series or set of such pieces, save them from
                    the monotony so often seen in copies.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Couches.—</hi> In ancient times couches were used as actual
                    beds. A cast of an antique bronze couch can be seen in the South Kensington
                    Museum. The general shape has not changed in modern times. It is the chair
                    without arms elongated or the arm chair widened. The proprieties observed in
                    such furniture are such as are applicable to chairs. If parts of the furniture
                    of state rooms, they are generally framed in wood, carved and gilt or painted.
                    The seats, backs, and ends are stuffed and upholstered with rich materials, like
                    the chairs,—the most costly material being tapestry, formerly woven in fanciful
                    designs after Boucher, Fragonard, and other “genre” painters, in the looms of
                    Beauvais, or, in England, of Mortlake and Soho. Such tapestries can seldom be
                    procured now. Inferior imitations of these designs are still produced. Couches
                    or sofas of this kind are made for conversation rather than repose, and admit of
                    the backs being shaped in curves or carved at the top, provided that the
                    inequalities are but slight (a rule often violated in cheap modern furniture),
                    and the carvings so arranged as not to interfere with the comfort of sitters, or
                    of those who may occasionally lean on them. The ends should generally be square.
                    In rooms not intended for receptions shallow couches, with rounded ends, and
                    awkward showy carvings on the backs, are out of place. Another kind of couch,
                    thickly stuffed on the back, ends, and seat, may be considered as the Oriental
                    divan raised on legs. It is practically a framework of fixed cushions, intended
                    for repose. Its excellence depends on the upholstery, as does that of the modern
                    stuffed arm chair.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Tables.—</hi> Good workmanship and careful regard for comfort
                    and use are absolutely necessary in making tables. They are to be firm, and
                    easily moved, and the legs or supports out of the way of persons sitting at
                    them; their proper ornamentation is veneer of fine grained wood, split and
                    arranged in patterns or buhl and other marquetry. Carved and gilt tables with
                    marble tops, made as ornaments to galleries and halls, should have the carvings
                    so arranged as not to interfere with the general look of support, or be too
                    liable to breakage. The same may be said of sideboards. Much skilful carving on
                    such pieces is either too close an imitation of nature, and looks as if it were
                    hung on, not part of, the structure, or is crowded and not arranged in parts in
                    which it would be subordinate to leading lines of division, panels, borders,
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cabinets.—</hi> Cabinet fronts are flat, with metal edgings, or
                    shallow and delicate carvings; or they are subdivided by architectonic members,
                    columns, deep mouldings, &amp;c. In divisions protected by these salient
                    features carvings of regular figure compositions are in place. The interiors may
                    be subdivided into any varieties of quaint and ingenious drawers and
                    receptacles. It is to cabinets that the greatest skill is devoted. The perfect
                    fitting of small interior drawers, &amp;c., is a test of excellence in
                    workmanship. On cornices, brackets, and other projections, busts, figures, and
                    carving of the finest kind can be placed effectively,—great care being taken not
                    to break up running mouldings, cornices, and other members that mark the
                    structure, or form lines of division. The French, and after them the Italians,
                    are the first masters of this kind of carving. London cabinetmakers rarely
                    attempt the figure. A cabinet by Fourdinois (No. 721 ’ 69) in the South
                    Kensington Museum, purchased from the exhibition of 1867, may be referred to for
                    careful observation of these proprieties; even the mouldings of the panelling
                    are covered with carving, but so delicate as not to interfere with their general
                    outlines or surfaces. An example of flat carving may also be seen in a Flemish
                    17th century ebony cabinet in the same collection (No. 1651 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> -</hi> 56). As to the proper arrangements and colours of
                    marquetry decoration, there also the masses of the design should be symmetrical,
                    or balanced by compensating parts where absolute symmetrical arrangement is not
                    suitable. In marquetry, as in carving, there ought to be agreeable dispositions
                    of lines and masses of ornament, such as will look in proportion at distances at
                    which details are not distinguishable. The colours should be few and harmonious,
                    even when the materials are contrasted as decidedly as ebony with ivory, or
                    satin wood with mahogany. We may compare the crowded patterns and the garish
                    contrasts of colour of much modern marquetry with the work of Riesener. His
                    marquetry is laid out with diapers of two woods, or with medallions and pattern
                    work,—much space being left plain. A good example is in the large secrétaire now
                    in the Louvre, signed and dated 1769. The same may be said of Chippendale’s
                    furniture, and of that in satin wood designed by the brothers Adam in the last
                    century.</p>
                <p>The manufacture of furniture is, to a great extent, in the hands of large
                    factories both in England and on the Continent. Owing to the necessary
                    subdivision of labour in these establishments, each piece of furniture passes
                    through numerous distinct workshops. The master and a few workmen formerly
                    superintended each piece of work, which, therefore, was never far removed from
                    the designer’s eye. Though accomplished artists are retained by the
                    manufacturers of London, Paris, and other capitals, there can no longer be the
                    same relation between the designer and his work. Many operations in these modern
                    factories are carried on by steam. Even the carving of copies and repetitions of
                    busts, figures, and ornaments is done in some instances by a special machine.
                    This, though an economy of labour, entails loss of artistic effect. The chisel
                    and the knife are no longer in such cases guided and controlled by the sensitive
                    touch of a human hand.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Collections of Furniture.—</hi> 1. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Antique.—</hi> British Museum; Louvre; Vatican; Royal Museum, Naples. 2.
                        <hi rend="italic">Mediaeval and</hi> 16ZÄ <hi rend="italic">century.—</hi>
                    Musée de Cluny, Paris; S. Kensington Museum; Sauvageot Collection, Louvre;
                    National Museum, Nuremberg; Museum of Madrid. 3. 18ZΛ <hi rend="italic"
                        >century.—</hi> Louvre Galleries; collection of Sir R. Wallace, Manchester
                    Square, London. Fine examples have been exhibited from Windsor Castle.
                    Carriages, in the royal palaces at Lisbon and Vienna.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Books.—Description</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">V</hi><hi rend="italic">Égypte;</hi> Wilkinson, <hi
                        rend="italic">Ancient Egyptians·,</hi> Layard, <hi rend="italic">Nineveh,
                        Ac.;</hi> Hamilton’s <hi rend="italic">Vases;</hi> Wright’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Homes of our Forefathers;</hi> Agincourt, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de TArt;</hi> Du Sommerard, <hi
                        rend="italic">Arts</hi><hi rend="italic">Somptuaires;</hi> Viollet-le-Duc,
                        <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire du Mobilier;</hi> Jacquemart, <hi
                        rend="italic">History of Furniture;</hi> Pollen, <hi rend="italic">Furniture
                        and Woodwork,</hi> where references to books will be found and notes on
                    materials and construction. (J. H. P. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
