<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0764-0729-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FREDERICK I</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 729</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:999328">Lions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1734554">Lion</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:884318">Crowns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t32v">Lion</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n764/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FREDERICK I</label>. (1123-1190), surnamed by the Italians
                    Barbarossa, Holy Roman emperor, and one of the greatest of German sovereigns,
                    was the son of Frederick the One-eyed of Hohenstaufen, duke of Swabia, and of
                    Judith, daughter of Henry the Black, duke of Bavaria, and was born most probably
                    in 1123. He succeeded his father as duke of Swabia in 1147, and in the same year
                    accompanied his uncle Conrad III. on his disastrous crusade. As in addition to
                    his exceptional personal qualities Frederick possessed the advantage of uniting
                    in himself the blood of the two great rival families, the Guelphine and the
                    Ghibelline, Conrad III., though possessing an infant son, nominated him as his
                    successor. On the death of Conrad this choice was unanimously ratified by the
                    assembly at Frankfort, March 4 or 5, 1152, and on the 9th of the same month
                    Frederick received the crown of Germany at Aix-la-Chapelle. During the reign of
                    Conrad, the Italian and imperial rights claimed by the German kings had been
                    almost in abeyance, and it was to establish their reality that Frederick devoted
                    the chief energies of his life. After settling various disputes among the German
                    princes, and making arrangements for an alliance with Manuel emperor of the East
                    against King William of Sicily, he, in October 1154, descended with his army
                    through the vale of Trent to hold the diet of his imperial feudatories on the
                    plains of Roncaglia. Before this diet the Milanese had treated with contempt his
                    messenger sent to warn them against continuing to oppress the citizens of Lodi;
                    and when he witnessed afterwards, on his march to Piedmont, the desolation that
                    had been caused by the Milanese, he began to sack and burn their dependencies,
                    and after crossing the Po razed Tortona to the ground. Then having appeared,
                    with the iron crown on his head, in the church of St Michael’s, Pavia, he set
                    out over the Apennines to receive the imperial crown at Rome. After apprehending
                    Arnold of Brescia as an earnest of his intentions to support the papal cause,
                    and adjusting certain ceremonial differences with the pope, he was crowned
                    emperor June 18, 1155; but immediately after quelling the insurrection in Rome
                    which followed his coronation, he was compelled, by the sudden appearance of a
                    pestilence in his army, to march towards Lombardy, and without accomplishing
                    more than the capture of Spoleto he disbanded his troops and returned home.</p>
                <p>For the next three years a great variety of matters detained him in Germany.
                    Immediately on his return from Italy he put vigorous measures into execution
                    against the robber knights; and in September 1156 he reconciled Henry the Lion
                    by the restoration of the duchy of Bavaria, while at the same time he pacified
                    Henry <hi rend="italic">Jasomi,rgott,</hi> his rival, by raising Austria to the
                    rank of a duchy. Adelaide, whom he’married in 1147, he had divorced in 1153 on
                    the pretext of kinship; and, having in 1156 married Beatrice, daughter of the
                    count of Burgundy, he received at Besançon in 1157 the homage of the Burgundian
                    nobles. In the same year he was successful in compelling King Boleslaus of
                    Poland to acknowledge him as his feudal lord, obtained by persuasion the same
                    allegiance from King Geisa of Hungary, and rewarded Duke Ladislaus of Bohemia
                    for his faithful services by giving him the rank of a king. About this time he
                    published a manifesto against the pretensions of the Pope to confer <hi
                    rend="italic">beneficia</hi> upon him; and when Frederick in the beginning of
                    1158 was preparing for a second campaign in Italy, the pope sent an embassy to
                    explain that he did not use the word in its feudal sense.</p>
                <p>Frederick’s chief purpose in this expedition was to quell the pride of Milan.
                    Descending into Italy by four différent roads, with an army of 100,000 foot and
                    15,000 horse, he in 1158 laid siege to the city, which, after defying for a
                    month his persistent and furious attacks, w as compelled from scarcity of
                    provisions to surrender, and with humiliating forms to take the oath of
                    allegiance. He then held another diet at Roncaglia, at which, besides settling a
                    number of standing disputes, he recovered the right of instituting <hi
                    rend="italic">podestas</hi> to administer justice in the cities, assumed the
                    nomination of the consuls, and deprived the cities and barons of the right of
                    going to war. The adoption of these regulations —which if within the legal
                    prerogatives of the emperor had nevertheless fallen into abeyance, and were
                    utterly opposed to the strong spirit of independence struggling into existence
                    in the cities—may be said to mark the first stage of his waning influence in
                    Italy. And a second stage was reached when, on the death of Pope Adrian IV. in
                    1159, he determined to support the anti-pope Victor IV.; for from that time he
                    had to contend wñth the ceaseless opposition and intrigues of Pope Alexander
                    III., who fulminated against him a sentence of excommunication, March 24, 1160.
                    It is true that Frederick in 1162 was able to spread terror throughout Lombardy
                    by the capture and demolition of Milan; butin 1164 the cities of Verona,
                    Vicenza, Padua, Treviso, and Venice formed a defensive league, and expelled the
                    <hi rend="italic">podestas</hi> and other foreign oppressors from their
                    territories. In 1163 Frederick had punished the rebellion of Mainz against its
                    archbishop by razing its walls and filling up its trenches; but having, on the
                    death of Victor IV., promoted the election of the new anti-pope f Pascal III.,
                    he was detained by fresh religious and political contentions in Germany till the
                    end of 1166. Disregarding the embers of conflagration in the north of Italy, he
                    now pushed on towards Rome, to which Alexander had returned the previous year.
                    Doubtful as to the propriety of at once attacking the city, he laid siege to
                    Ancona; but when he learned that the Roman citizens had rashly allowed
                    themselves to be defeated at Tusculum, he raised” the siege, and going to Rome
                    took forcible possession of part of the Leonine city, and attacked and captured
                    the Vatican. On the following Sunday (August 1, 1167) the empress received in St
                    Peter’s the imperial diadem from Pascal III., and Frederick the circlet of gold
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n765/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0765-0730"/> which was the sign of patrician dignity.
                    Meanwhile behind him the cities of Lombardy had formed their famous league; even
                    Lodi was forced to yield its assent to the alliance; and Milan springing into
                    existence almost as by the wand of an enchanter, gave evidence of its defiant
                    and unquenchable hostility by the demolition of the castle of Trezzo, which
                    contained the emperor’s treasure. Even at Rome his position was far from
                    enviable, for Alexander HL, having taken refuge in the Colosseum, was prepared
                    to offer a desperate resistance. Accordingly Frederick fell upon the curious
                    expedient of proposing that both Alexander and Pascal should resign, and another
                    pope be elected. The citizens clamorously supported the proposal, but Alexander
                    prevented its accomplishment by suddenly leaving Rome for Benevento. Immediately
                    on his departure, and, to the superstitious fancies of the time, as if in token
                    of the wrath of heaven at his expulsion, and at the sacrilegious violence done
                    to the most sacred edifice of the holy city, suddenly, in the midst of a day of
                    burning and sultry splendour, the whole German army with scarcely an exception
                    was smitten by a pestilence of unexampled virulence, to which the terrors of
                    superstition imparted both additional horror and a more deadly fatality.
                    Frederick led the haggard and terror-stricken crowd of survivors with great
                    difficulty to Pavia, whence at the end of the year he set out for Germany
                    attended by about 30 horsemen; and at Susa he only saved himself from death at
                    the hands of the citizens by escaping during the night on foot accompanied by
                    two followers. For nearly seven years after this luckless flight he remained in
                    Germany. On the death of Pascal III. in September 1168 he supported the new
                    anti-pope Calixtus III., but by doing so he only lent additional vigour to the
                    Lombard league, who this year had founded the city which in honour of their
                    patron Alexander III. they named Alexandria; and in 1173 they took an oath not
                    to leave off waging war against the emperor till they drove him out of Italy.
                    Resolved, however, on a final effort, Frederick, having collected an immense
                    army, set out in October 1174 on his fifth and last Italian expedition. He
                    burned Susa to the ground, and captured Asti; but failing in a treacherous
                    attack on Alexandria, made after he had granted it a truce, he endeavoured to
                    negotiate a peace with the League. Final terms could not, however, be agreed
                    upon, and notwithstanding the crushing blow which his fortunes at this time
                    sustained through the defection of Henry the Lion, he resolved when recruited by
                    a new army from Germany to risk the battle at Lignano, which resulted in his
                    total defeat, 29th May 1176. Having in this battle been crushed beneath his
                    horse, he was believed to have fallen, either wounded or dead, into the hands of
                    the confederates; but on the third day afterwards he arrived at Pavia unhurt,
                    but so worn out by hunger and fatigue as to be scarcely recognizable. Finding
                    his case now desperate, he at last agreed to acknowledge the pontificate of
                    Alexander, and also at Venice, 25th July 1177, concluded a truce of six years
                    with the cities. He then turned his attention to Henry the Lion, who owned
                    himself vanquished in 1181, and was banished to England. On the expiry of the
                    treaty of Venice, the famous treaty of Constance was signed, 25th June 1183, by
                    which, while the supremacy of the empire was formally recognized, the
                    independent jurisdiction of the cities was substantially guaranteed. Henceforth,
                    Frederick resolved to rule Italy more by conciliation than by compulsion, and
                    while re-establishing his influence in Lombardy by granting such favours to the
                    Milanese as secured their lasting alliance and friendship, he virtually placed
                    Sicily under his immediate government by arranging a marriage between Constance,
                    heiress of that kingdom, and Henry his eldest son, who, having been elected King
                    of the Romans in his infancy, received the crown of Italy on the day of his
                    marriage, 27th June 1186, from the patriarch of Aquileia.</p>
                <p>Having thus at last brought his long life-struggle to an honourable if not very
                    triumphant close, it might have been expected that Frederick would now have been
                    content to doff his armour, and to pass his remaining days in peace. But hearing
                    in 1187 of the victorious progress of Saladin against the Christians in Syria,
                    his martial ardour was again kindled, and he resolved to enter the lists against
                    the redoubtable Saracen conqueror. This purpose he was, however, unable to carry
                    fully out, for after two successful battles in Asia Minor, he was drowned before
                    reaching Syria while crossing a small river in Pisidia, June 10, 1190.</p>
                <p>Frederick I. is said to have taken Charlemagne as his model; but the contest in
                    which he engaged was entirely different both in character and results from that
                    in which his great predecessor achieved such a wonderful temporary success.
                    Though Frederick failed to subdue the republics, the failure can scarcely be
                    said to reflect either on his prudence as a statesman or his skill as a general,
                    for his ascendency was finally overthrown rather by the ravages of pestilence
                    than by the might of human arms. In Germany his resolute will and sagacious
                    administration subdued or disarmed all discontent, and he not only succeeded in
                    welding the various rival interests into a unity of devotion to himself against
                    which papal intrigues were comparatively powerless, but won for the empire a
                    prestige such as it had not possessed since the time of Otto the Great. The wide
                    contrast between his German and Italian rule is strikingly exemplified in the
                    fact that, while he endeavoured to overthrow the republics in Italy, he held in
                    check the power of the nobles in Germany, by conferring municipal franchises and
                    independent rights on the principal cities. Even in Italy, though his general
                    course of action was warped by wrong prepossessions, he in many instances
                    manifested exceptional practical sagacity in dealing with immediate difficulties
                    and emergencies. Possessing great physical beauty, frank and open manners,
                    untiring and unresting energy, and a prowess which found its native element in
                    difficulty and danger, he seemed the embodiment of the chivalrous and warlike
                    spirit of his age, and was the model of all the qualities which then won highest
                    admiration. Stern and ambitious he certainly was, but his aims can scarcely be
                    said to have exceeded his prerogatives as emperor; and though he had sometimes
                    recourse when in straits to expedients almost diabolically ingenious in their
                    cruelty, yet his general conduct was marked by a clemency which in that age was
                    exceptional. His quarrel with the papacy was an inherited conflict, not
                    reflecting at all on his religious faith, but the inevitable consequence of
                    inconsistent theories of government, which had been created and could be
                    dissipated only by a long series of events. His interference in the quarrels of
                    the republics was not only quite justifiable from the relation in which he stood
                    to them, but seemed absolutely necessary. From the beginning, however, he
                    treated the Italians, as indeed was only natural, less as rebellious subjects
                    than as conquered aliens; and it must be admitted that in regard to them the
                    only effective portion of his procedure was, not his energetic measures of
                    repression nor his brilliant victories, but, after the battle of Lignano, his
                    quiet and cheerful acceptance of the inevitable, and the consequent complete
                    change in his policy, by which if he did not obtain the great object of his
                    ambition, he at least did much to render innoxious for the empire his previous
                    mistakes.</p>
                <p>The principal contemporary authorities for the reign of Frederick I. are the
                    chronicle of Otto bishop of Freisingen, to which is prefixed a letter of
                    Frederick containing a summary of the early events of his reign; the
                    continuation of this chronicle from 1158 to 1160 <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n766/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0766-0731"/> by Radevic, one of the canons of Otto; the
                    chronicle of Otto Morena of Lodi, continued from 1162 to 1167 by his son
                    Acerbus; and the life of Pope Alexander III. by the cardinal of Aragon. The
                    chief modern writers are Mutatori, <hi rend="italic">Annali</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">d'</hi><hi rend="italic">Italia;</hi> Sismondi, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histoire des Républiques Italiennes</hi>; H. v. Biinau, <hi rend="italic">Leben
                    und Thaten Friedrichs</hi><hi rend="italic">I.,</hi> Leipsic, 1722; Chenier, <hi
                    rend="italic">Histoire de la lutte des papes et des empereurs de la maison de
                    Souabc,</hi> &amp;c., 2d edition, Paris, 1856; F. von Raumer, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geschichte der Hohenstaufen und ihrer Zeit,</hi> 4thed., Leipsic, 1871; P.
                    Scheffer-Boichorst, <hi rend="italic">Friedrichs letzter Streit mit der
                    Curie,</hi> Berlin, 1866; K. Fischer, <hi rend="italic">Der Kreuzzug Friedrichs
                    L,</hi> Leipsic, 1870; H. l’rutz, <hi rend="italic">Kaiser Freidrich I.,</hi> 3
                    vols., Dantzic, 1871-73; Fr. X. Wegele, <hi rend="italic">Kaiser Friedrich I.
                    Barbarossa, ein Vortrag,</hi> Nordlingen, 1871; Dettloff, <hi rend="italic">Der
                    erste Römerzug Kaiser Friedrichs I.</hi> Göttingen, 1877; Bryce, <hi
                    rend="italic">Holy</hi><hi rend="italic">Roman Empire;</hi> Mihnan, <hi
                    rend="italic">History of</hi><hi rend="italic">Latin</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Christianity</hi>; 0. Vignati, <hi rend="italic">Storia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >diplomatica della lega Lombarda,</hi> Milan, 1866; Teste, <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of the Wars of Frederick I. and the Communes of Lombardy,</hi> English
                    translation, 1877; and E. A. Freeman in his first series of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Essays.</hi> (T. F. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
