<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0149-0140-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FICTIONS (9th edition, volume 9, page 140)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46970190">Fiction</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:923709">Fiction</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964412">Husbands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n149/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FICTIONS</label>, in law, or legal fictions, are false
                    averments, the truth of which is not permitted to be called in question. English
                    law as well as Roman law abounds in fictions. Sometimes they are merely the
                    condensed expression of a rule of law,— <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> the fiction
                    of English law that husband and wife are one person, and the fiction of Roman
                    law that the wife is the daughter of the husband. Sometimes they must be
                    regarded as reasons invented in order to justify a rule of law according to an
                    implied ethical standard. Of this sort seems to be the fiction or presumption
                    that every one knows the law, which reconciles the rule that ignorance is no
                    excuse for crime with the moral common-place that it is unfair to punish a man
                    for violating a law of whose existence he was unaware. Again, some fictions are
                    deliberate falsehoods, adopted as true for the purpose of establishing a remedy
                    not otherwise attainable. Of this sort are the numerous fictions of English law
                    by which the different courts obtained jurisdiction in private business, removed
                    inconvenient restrictions in the law relating to land, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>What to the scientific jurist is a stumbling-block is to the older writers on
                    English law a beautiful device for reconciling the strict letter of the law with
                    common sense and justice. Blackstone, in noticing the well-known fiction by
                    which the Court of Queen’s Bench established its jurisdiction in common pleas
                    (viz., that the defendant was in custody of the marshal of the court), says,
                    “These fictions of law, though at first they may startle the student, he will
                    find upon further consideration to be highly beneficial and useful; especially
                    as this maxim is ever invariably observed, that no fiction shall extend to work
                    an injury; its proper operation being to prevent a mischief or remedy an
                    inconvenience that might result from the general rule of law. So true it is that
                        <hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">fictione</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >juris semper</hi><hi rend="italic">subsistit</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >oequitasf</hi> Austin, on the other hand, while correctly* assigning as the
                    cause of many fictions the desire to combine the necessary reform with some show
                    of respect for the abrogated law, makes the following harsh criticism as to
                    others :—“Why the plain meanings which I have now stated should be obscured by
                    the fictions to which I have just adverted I cannot conjecture. A wish on the
                    part of the authors of the fictions to render the law as <hi rend="italic"
                        >uncognoscible</hi> as may be is probably the cause which Mr Bentham would
                    assign. I judge not, I confess, so uncharitably; I rather impute such fictions
                    to the sheer imbecility (or, if you will, to the active and sportive fancies) of
                    their grave and venerable authors, than to any deliberate design, good or evil.”
                    Bentham, of course, saw in fictions the instrument by which the great object of
                    his abhorrence, <hi rend="italic">jwdiciary law,</hi> was produced. It was the
                    means by which judges usurped the functions of legislators. “A fiction of law,”
                    he says, “may be defined as a wilful falsehood, having for its object the
                    stealing legislative powers by and for hands which could not or durst not openly
                    claim it, and but for the delusion thus produced could not exercise it.” A
                    partnership, he says, was formed between the kings and the judges against the
                    interests of the people. “Monarchs found force, lawyers fraud; thus was the
                    capital found” <hi rend="italic">{Historical Preface to the second edition of
                        the Fragment on Government),</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>In the same essay Bentham notices the comparative rarity
                            of fictions in Scotch law. As to fiction in particular, compared with
                            the work done by it in English law, the use made of it by the Scotch is
                            next to nothing. No need have they had of any such clumsy instrument.
                            They have two others “of their own making, by which things of the same
                            sort have been done with much less trouble. <hi rend="italic"
                                >Nobile</hi><hi rend="italic">officium</hi> gives them the creative
                            power of legislation; this and the word desuetude together the
                            annihilative.” And he notices aptly enough that, while the English
                            lawyers declared that James II. had abdicated the throne (which
                            everybody knew to be false), the Scotch lawyers boldly said he bad
                            forfeitedit.</p></note></p>
                <p>Sir H. Maine <hi rend="italic">{Ancient Law)</hi> supplies the historical element
                    which is always lacking in the explanations of Austin and Bentham. Fictions form
                    one of the agencies by which, in progressive societies, positive law is brought
                    into harmony with public opinion. The others are equity and statutes. Fictions
                    in this sense include, not merely the obvious falsities of the English and Roman
                    systems, but any assumption which conceals a change of law by retaining the old
                    formula after the change has been made. It thus includes both the case law of
                    the English and the <hi rend="italic">Responsa</hi><hi rend="italic">P</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">rudentum</hi> of the Romans. “At a particular stage of social
                    progress they are invaluable expedients for overcoming the rigidity of law; and,
                    indeed, without one of them, the fiction of adoption, which permits the family
                    tie to be artificially created, it is difficult to understand how society would
                    ever have escaped from its swaddling clothes, and taken its first steps towards
                    civilization.”</p>
                <p>The bolder remedial fictions of English law have been to a large extent removed
                    by legislation, and one great obstacle to any reconstruction of the legal system
                    has thus been partially removed. Where the real remedy stood in glaring contrast
                    to the nominal rule, it has been openly ratified by statute. In ejectment cases
                    the mysterious sham litigants have disappeared. The bond of entail can be broken
                    without having recourse to the collusive proceedings of fine and recovery.
                    Fictions have been almost entirely banished from the procedure of the courts.
                    The action for damages on account of seduction, which is still nominally an
                    action by the father for loss of his daughter’s services, is perhaps the only
                    fictitious action now remaining· <hi rend="subscript"> -</hi></p>
                <p>Fictions which appear in the form of principles (like that of the unity of
                    husband and wife) are not so easily dealt with by legislation. To expel them
                    formally from the system would require the re-enactment of vast portions of law.
                    A change in legal modes of speech and thought would be more effective. The legal
                    mind instinctively seizes upon concrete aids to abstract reasoning. Many hard
                    and revolting fictions must have begun their career as metaphors. In some cases
                    the history of the change may still almost be traced. The conception that a
                    man-of-war is a floating island, or that an ambassador’s house is beyond the
                    territorial limits of the country in which he resides, was originally a figure
                    of speech designed to set a rule of law in a striking light. It is then gravely
                    accepted as true in fact, and other rules of law are deduced from it. Its
                    beginning is to be compared with such phrases as “an Englishman’s house is his
                    castle,” which have had no legal offshoots, and still remain mere figures of
                    speech.</p>
                <p>Constitutional law is of course honeycombed with fictions. Here there is hardly
                    ever anything like direct legislative change, and yet real change is incessant.
                    The rules defining the sovereign power and fixing the authority of its various
                    members are in most points the same as they were at the last revolution,—in many
                    points they have been the same since the beginning of parliamentary government.
                    But they have long ceased to be true in fact; and it would hardly be too much to
                    say that the entire series of formal <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n150/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0150-0141"/> propositions called the constitution is
                    merely a series of fictions. The legal attributes of the king, and even of the
                    House of Lords, are fictions. If we could suppose that the effects of the two
                    Reform Acts had been brought about, not by legislation, but by the decisions of
                    law courts and the practice of House of Commous committees—by such assumptions
                    as that freeholder includes lease-holder, and that ten means twenty—we should
                    have in the legal constitution of the House of Commons the same kind of fictions
                    that we find in the legal statement of the attributes of the crown and the House
                    of Lords. Here, too, fictions have been largely resorted to for the purpose of
                    supporting particular theories,—populärer monarchical,—and such have flourished
                    even more vigorously than purely legal fictions, <hi rend="smallcaps">(e.
                        r.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
