<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0376-0363-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FONTAINEBLEAU</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 363</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:919892">Fairs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:933357">Fountains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b46t0h03c">Exports</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v436">Shoes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xw4804p">Fairs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vq1n">Fountains</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n376/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FONTAINEBLEAU</label>, a town of France, at the head of an
                    arrondissement, in the department of Seine-et-Marne, about 37 miles S.E. from
                    Paris on the railway to Lyons, in 48° 24' 23" N. lat. and 2° 42' 1" E. long. It
                    stands in the midst of the forest of Fontainebleau, is well built, and has
                    broad, clean, handsome streets. Among the more important buildings and
                    institutions are the hotel de ville, the barracks, the court-house, two
                    hospitals, a college, and a public library. The Pompadour mansion, and a portion
                    of that which belonged to the cardinal of Ferrara, are still preserved; and a
                    statue of General Damesme adorns the principal square. Wood-turning and the
                    manufacture of porcelain and earthenware are the chief industries; and wine,
                    grapes, garden produce, and paving stones are articles of export. The population
                    in 1871 was 11,545. In the immediate vicinity of the town is the celebrated
                    palace of Fontainebleau—one of the largest, and in the interior one of the most
                    sumptuous, of the royal residences of France. The origin of the name and of the
                    building are equally unknown; but the old manor-house was used by Louis VII. in
                    the latter part of the 12th century, and continued a favourite residence of
                    Philip Augustus and St Louis. The existing edifice was begun by Francis I., who
                    laid out immense sums of money in its erection, employing Primaticcio, a famous
                    Italian architect, to draw the plans, and commissioning Leonardo da Vinci,
                    Andrea del Sarto, and Benvenuto Cellini to expend the resources of their arts in
                    making it a truly royal residence. Henry IV. doubled the area of the buildings
                    and gardens, adding among other portions the great Diana gallery, the Court of
                    the Princes, and the Galerie des Cerfs. A canal which he constructed was
                    afterwards filled up by Louis XIV. With Louis XV. the palace fell into
                    disfavour, and for a time it was used as a military school. Napoleon I. restored
                    it with great splendour, at a cost of 6 million francs, and often resided in it;
                    but after the return of the Bourbons it was again allowed to fall into
                    disrepair. Louis XVIII. and Louis Philippe both did somewhat to its restoration.
                    The congeries of buildings is very extensive, the roofing, it is said, covering
                    no less than 14 acres. There are five great courts, distinguished as the Court
                    of the White Horse, the Court of the Fountain, the Oval or Donjon Court, the
                    Court of Princes, and the Court of the Kitchens or of Henry IV. The first is
                    also called the Court of Adieux in memory of the parting scene between Napoleon
                    and his Old Guard in 1814, at the foot of the Horse Shoe staircase. The chapel
                    of the Holy Trinity was built under Francis I., and the chapel of St Saturnin
                    dates from the same period, and occupies the site of an older building which was
                    consecrated by Thomas à Becket. It is impossible to do more than mention a few
                    of the historical events which have taken place at Fontainebleau. Philip the
                    Fair, Henry III., and Louis XIII. were all boru in the palace, and the first of
                    these kings died there. James V. of Scotland was there received by his intended
                    bride; and Charles V. of Germany was entertained there in 1539. Christina of
                    Sweden lived there for years, and the gallery is still shown where she caused
                    her secretary Monaldeschi to be murdered, or, as she regarded it, executed. In
                    1685 Fontainebleau saw the signing of the revocation of the edict of Nantes, and
                    in the following year the death of Condé. In the 18th century it had two
                    illustrious guests in Peter the Great of Russia and Christian VII. of Denmark;
                    and in the early part of the 19th it was twice the residence of Pius VII.,—in
                    1804, when he came to consecrate the emperor, and in 1812-1814, when he was that
                    emperor’s prisoner. It was within its walls that the sentence of divorce was
                    passed against Josephine. The forest of Fontainebleau is one of the most
                    beautiful wooded tracks in France, and for generations it has been the chosen
                    haunt of French landscape painters. The most celebrated spots are the Vallée de
                    la Solle, the Gorge au Loup, the Gorge d’Apremont, and the Fort 1’Empereur. The
                    whole area extends to 81,740 acres, and it is traversed by 12,000 miles of road
                    and pathway.</p>
                <p>See Pfnor, <hi rend="italic">Monographie</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Fontainebleau,</hi> with text by Champollion Figeac, Paris, 1866.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
