<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0361-0348-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FLOWERS, Artificial</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 348</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kw6x">Flowers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b40c4st3m">Shopping</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kn24">Glass</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4251fv6s">Wire</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1116884">Shopping</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:927866">Flowers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:998642">Lighting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210278">Belgium</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n361/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FLOWERS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Artificial</hi></label>. There
                    are few branches of ornamental work used in the decoration of ladies’ apparel
                    which have more increased in importance than that of artificial flower making,
                    in which, both in France and in England, large numbers of workpeople are
                    engaged. Not only has the trade itself greatly extended within the last few
                    years, but the improvement in the manufacture is very marked, and the bouquets
                    and wreaths used in the trimming of dresses may be almost said to rival nature,
                    so truly and delicately are the individual flowers manipulated. Artificial
                    flower making is almost entirely done by hand, giving occupation principally to
                    young women and children, the majority of whom work at home or in small shops.
                    The numbers employed at the time of the census of 1871 were returned as 4886, of
                    whom 1740 were under twenty years of age. In France the numbers are much larger,
                    for ten years ago it was estimated that there were at least 2000 shops where
                    artificial flowers were made, and it is probable that now these have been
                    increased to 3000. It is not entirely a woman’s work, however, for men are
                    employed, particularly in Paris, in cutting out the material for the flowers by
                    a stamp machine, in which 16 or 20 folds are operated upon at once, the folds
                    being coloured green, blue, crimson, according to the flower which is to be
                    imitated. Each piece is taken up separately by a girl armed with a pair of
                    pincers, who, with one dexterous movement, moulds it, as it were, roughly into
                    the shape of the flower, and then passes it on to another who gives a more
                    precise form to the petal. A third girl attaches each petal to a very fine wire,
                    thread having been previously twisted round this wire to form the stalk; while
                    the remaining operations consist in goffering the petals and leaves to give them
                    a curl, and finally gumming or waxing them over, or dusting them with fine
                    powdered glass or potato flour to represent the bloom. The rapidity and accuracy
                    with which these various processes are completed are very remarkable. A new
                    style of artificial flower has lately come into vogue, in France more
                    especially, made by the “enamel process,” in which a young girl sits by a jet of
                    flame, holding in her hand a stick of prepared glass. A momentary application to
                    the flame makes the end of the stick red hot, and while it is still in a pasty
                    state, the operator pulls out a short length, and immediately rolls it up into
                    the form of the petal or leaf, and passes it on to the painter for the proper
                    colouring. The remaining processes are similar to those of the ordinary
                    artificial flowers. These enamel flowers, though wondrously true and pretty, are
                    more suited for room decoration than for dress. While apparently a light and
                    pleasant work, artificial flower making is not one of the healthiest of our
                    trades, partly for the reason that it is so often carried on in small household
                    shops, where ventilation is of the scantiest. It has, however, been much
                    improved in this respect,’since it has come under the supervision of the Factory
                    Acts. There is always a certain amount of dust and colouring matter flying about
                    the room, which is more or less injurious, though the use of Scheele’s green and
                    sulphate of copper (verdigris blue) is almost discontinued, and with it a train
                    of symptoms that usually accompany arsenical poisoning. Weak eyes are a common
                    source of complaint, especially the form called asthenopia, which is
                    particularly induced when white flowers are made by gas light. In the
                    manufacture of the flowers, the net cost is about three-fifths of the whole for
                    material, and the remaining two-fifths for the labour. In France the earnings of
                    the men who cut the folds are from 4 to 5 francs per day, of the workwomen from
                    2⅜ to 3J, according to ability. In England a skilful flower worker will earn
                    from 20s. to 25s. per week, though there is a drawback in its being a season
                    trade, which is very brisk about the spring and fall of the year, and as
                    inactive during the other times. Besides the very large number of artificial
                    flowers made in England, the following table shows how great is the importation,
                    principally from France :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1866...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>...£293,306</p><p>...
                            304,440</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1870...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>...£266,502</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1874...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>...£447,351</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1867...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1871...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>... 367,186</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1875...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>... 510,800</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1868...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>... 341,176</p><p>...
                            365,407</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1872...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>.. 411,540</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1876...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>... 496,987</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1869...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1873...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>... 449,320</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1878...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>... 544.625</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Belgium and Holland likewise supply Great Britain but to a much smaller
                    extent.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n362/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0362-0349"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
