<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0311-0300-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FLEA (9th edition, volume 9, page 300)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn8f">Diptera</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g73738k">Aptera</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206536">Tasmania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:894485">Diptera</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n311/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FLEA</label>, an Anglo-Saxon name, probably derived from
                    fleogan,” to fly, typically applied to <hi rend="italic">Pulex irritans,</hi> a
                    blood-sucking insect-parasite of man and other mammal =≈, remarkable for its
                    powers of leaping, and unfortunately too well known, even in our own temperate
                    climate. Its position in classification has long been somewhat undecided; a
                    separate order was erected for it and its allies under the various names of <hi
                        rend="italic">Suctoria, Siphonaptera, Ropfhoteira,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Aphaniptera,</hi> by De Geer, Latreille, Clairville, and Kirby
                    respectively; and it is included in the <hi rend="italic">Aptera</hi> of
                    Lamarck, MacLeay, and others, and in the <hi rend="italic">Rlιyngota</hi> of
                    Fabricius. Various affinities have also been attributed to the group, which has
                    been supposed to have relations with the <hi rend="italic">IIymenoptera,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Hemfiptera,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Anoplura,</hi> and even
                    with the <hi rend="italic">Coleoptera</hi> (beetles). As regards the latter
                    order, it is noteworthy that a recently discovered allied group, <hi
                        rend="italic">Platypsyllidae,</hi> founded upon a parasite on the beaver
                    (and considered as a separate order by Westwood, under the name <hi
                        rend="italic">Achreioptera'),</hi> has been with considerable show of reason
                    referred to the beetles by so sound an entomologist as Dr Leconte. As regards
                    the flea, however, it is now generally accepted that its true affinities are
                    with the <hi rend="italic">Diptera</hi> or two-winged flies, as suggested by
                    Lamarck and Strauss Durckheim. In that order, it is by some held to occupy, as a
                    family <hi rend="italic">PuUcidae</hi> (with the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Platypsyllidai),</hi> the position of a sub-order, at the end, under the
                    name <hi rend="italic">Aplιaniptera</hi> (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Diptera,</hi>
                    vol. vii. p. 2δ6); but by others it is placed <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n312/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0312-0301"/> before the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mycetophilidae,</hi> at the head of the tribo <hi rend="italic"
                        >Encephala</hi> of the Nematocerous section of the great division <hi
                        rend="italic">Orthorhapha.</hi> The community of parasitic habits with the
                        <hi rend="italic">Ilippoboscidae</hi> (forest-flies and sheep-ticks) is to a
                    certain extent the reason for the former position; but the earlier
                    transformations seem to indicate a stronger relationship with the <hi
                        rend="italic">Encephala.</hi> The general characters have been given under
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Diptera;</hi> but the structure of the mouth of the
                    perfect insect may be specified. The labrum is obsolete; the mandibles are
                    represented by two flat and long processes, strengthened by a mid rib, and
                    having very finely toothed edges, and uniting with the slender central lingua to
                    form a puncturing lancet. When not in use, this is protected by the labial
                    palpi, which form a sort of tube. The maxillae are small leathery plates, and
                    their palpi, which are four-jointed and large, have been mistaken for antenuae.
                    The power of leaping, as well known, is very great; but there is no apparent
                    development of the hind femora to account for it (as in many jumping beetles),
                    although the posterior legs are saltatorial. The great muscular power of fleas
                    has been long turned to account by public exhibitors in all countries, who have,
                    under the pretence of taming or educating these miuute creatures, made use of
                    various contrivances to render the natural efforts of the insect to escape
                    assume the appearance of trained action. An account of the methods employed will
                    be found in the <hi rend="italic">American Naturalist,</hi> vol. xî. p. 7, from
                    the pen of Mr W. H. Dall. In some cases the steady carriage of the flea is to be
                    traced to fracture of its jumping legs. The female flea lays a few oblong white
                    eggs, in dirty places on floors frequented by domestic animals. The larvae,
                    before hatching, have a frontal point, used in breaking the shell of the egg.
                    They are long and worm-like, without feet, but with two small hooks at the tail,
                    and short antennae and mouth organs at the head. They are very active, and
                    apparently feed upon animal substances, forming, when full grown, a silky
                    cocoon. Many species are known, parasitic upon various animals aud birds. They
                    have been recorded as infesting the inside of rabbits’ ears, and the neck of a
                    fowl, from hedgehog, marmot, cat, dog, bat, squirrel, dormouse, ferret, weasel,
                    hare, rabbit, rat, mouse, field-mouse, shrew, moor-hen, jackdaw, thrush,
                    missel-thrush, blackbird, jay, bullfinch, chaffinch, yellow-hammer, pipit,
                    blackcap, whitethroat, skylark, willow-wren, long-tailed titmouse, siskin,
                    stock-dove, woodpigeon, common pigeon, starling, swallow, &amp;c. (though it is
                    by no means certain that these are all necessarily of distinct specific value);
                    and a species has been described from the common fowl in Ceylon. A large species
                    is often found in sandy pits, near the openings of the nests of sand-martins,
                    and a very large one sometimes occurs in wet and marshy places, probably living
                    upon the mole. For the latter parasite, and others in which the antennae exhibit
                    certain supposed peculiarities, a separate genus, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ceratopsyllus,</hi> has been proposed. In another flea, also found on the
                    mole, no trace of eyes could be found, even under a high power. A very large
                    species has been found on the Australian porcupine iu Tasmania; and Kirby, in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Fauna Boreali-Americana,</hi> described as <hi
                        rend="italic">Pulex</hi><hi rend="italic">gigas</hi> a flea two lines long,
                    which he believed to be the largest known. This was taken in 65° N. lat.
                    Westwood has recorded 17 British species; and oddly enough the same number are
                    noted from the Netherlands by Ritsema. Any notice of these parasites would be
                    incomplete without a reference to the “jigger,” “chigoe,” “bicho de pé,”
                    “nigua,” or “earth-flea,”— <hi rend="italic">Dermatophilus, Sarcopsyllus,</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">Rhynchoprion penetrans,</hi> so well known as a burrower
                    into the naked feet of men, in sandy localities in the West Indies and South
                    America. So great is this pest, that serious trouble has been occasioned by it
                    even to military expeditions in South America; and the French army in Mexico was
                    much troubled by it. The entry is effected usually under the nail, by the
                    impregnated female, which thereupon becomes enormously distended with an immense
                    number of eggs. Inflammation and ulceration follow this attack, and unless great
                    care is taken in extracting the insect, serious illness and even death result. A
                    good plate of the metamorphoses of this species is given in the volume of the
                        <hi rend="italic">American Naturalist</hi> above quoted, p. 754. For an
                    account of the medical aspects, see Dr Laboulbène’s article on the.“Chique,” in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire Encyclopédique</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                        Sciences</hi><hi rend="italic">Médicales</hi> (Paris, 1875), p. 239; and for
                    an exhaustive history, Guyon’s memoir in the <hi rend="italic">Revue</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">et Magasin de Zoologie</hi> for 1868 and 1869. Much attention
                    does not appear as yet to have been paid to the <hi rend="italic">Pulicidae</hi>
                    by naturalists, except as regards the anatomy of the common species. Dugès’s
                    “Recherches sur les Caractères Zoologiques du genre Pulex,” in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Annales des Sciences Naturelles,</hi> vol. xxvii. (1832) p.
                    145, and J. Künckel’s observations in the <hi rend="italic">Annales de la
                        Société Entomologique de France,</hi> 5e sér. iii. p. 129, and, as regards
                        <hi rend="italic">P.</hi><hi rend="italic">irritans,</hi> W. H. Furlonge’s
                    descriptions in the journal of the <hi rend="italic">Quekett
                        Microscopical</hi><hi rend="italic">Club,</hi> 1871, p. 189, and 1873, p.
                    12, and C. Ritsema’s in the <hi rend="italic">Album</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >der</hi><hi rend="italic">Natuur,</hi> xi. (1872), p. 65, may be specially
                    noticed. The name “flea” is frequently erroneously applied to many jumping or
                    lively insects not allied to the <hi rend="italic">Pulicidae;</hi> for instance,
                    the “turnip-flea” is a small beetle, <hi rend="italic">Phylloſreta</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">undulata,</hi> one of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Halticidae.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(e. c. r.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
