<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0174-0165-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FILLMORE, Millard (9th edition, volume 9, page
                    165)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:840456">Buffaloes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:863821">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205805">Cuba</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j960b1w">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x40m">Buffaloes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx6494x">Attorneys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n174/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FILLMORE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Millard</hi></label>
                    (1800-1874), thirteenth president of the United States of America. His family
                    was of English stock, and had early settled in New England. His father,
                    Nathaniel Fillmore, made in 1795 a clearing within the limits of what is now the
                    town of Summer Hill, Cayuga co., New York, and there the future president was
                    born, January 7, 1800. The father went by the title of “the squire,” and served
                    as a justice in the beginnings of the settlements nearest to him, which were
                    very sparsely occupied. Millard, to the age of fourteen, could have shared only
                    the simplest rudiments of education, chiefly from his parents, with slight help
                    from a school. At that age he was apprenticed, for the usual term, to a fuller
                    and clothier, to card wool, and to dye and dress the cloth from the farmers’
                    houses. Two years before the close of his term, he, by a promissory note for
                    thirty dollars, bought the remainder of his time from his master, and entered a
                    retired lawyer’s office as a student and helper at the age of nineteen. He, of
                    course, received and accepted the usual honour extended to young men of his
                    proclivities, to deliver the Fourth of July Oration, before he was twenty-one
                    years of age. In 1820 he made his way to Buffalo,—then only the germ of the
                    present flourishing city,—and supported himself as a student in another law
                    office by teaching a school and aiding the postmaster. In 1823 he was admitted
                    an attorney in the court of common pleas, Erie co., and then took up legal
                    practice at Aurora, to which his father had removed. Hard study, temperance, and
                    integrity gave him a good reputation and moderate success, and he was made an
                    attorney and counsellor of the supreme court of the State. In 1826 he married
                    Abigail, daughter of the Rev. Lemuel Powers. Returning to Buffalo in 1830 he
                    formed a partnership with two lawyers, both afterwards distinguished in public
                    life, and became successful at the bar. From 1828 to 1831 he served as a
                    representative in the State legislature, coming in as an anti-mason. In the
                    single term of 1832-4 he was a representative of his district in the national
                    Congress, as antiJackson, or in opposition to the administration. From 1836 to
                    1842, when he declined further service, he represented his district as a member
                    of the Whig party. In Congress he opposed the annexation of Texas as slave
                    territory, was a warm advocate of internal improvements and a protective tariff,
                    supported J. Q. Adams in maintaining the right of offering anti-slavery
                    petitions, advocated the prohibition by Congress of the slave trade between the
                    States, and favoured the exclusion of slavery from the District of Columbia. His
                    speech and tone, however, were moderate on these exciting subjects, and he
                    claimed the right to stand free of pledges, and to adjust his opinions and his
                    course by the development of circumstances. The Whigs having the ascendency in
                    Congress during the latter part of his membership, he was made chairman of the
                    House Committee of Ways and Means. Against a strong opposition he carried an
                    appropriation of 30,000 dollars for Morse’s telegraph, and secured important
                    provisions in the new tariff measures of 1842. He found some supporters of his
                    proposed nomination as a candidate for vice-president in the Whig National
                    Convention at Baltimore. In May 1844, being the Whig candidate for the
                    governorship of New York, he was defeated by Silas Wright. In 1847 he was made
                    comptroller of the State of New York, an office of manifold responsibilities and
                    duties, which he resigned on his election, in November 1848, as vice-president
                    of the United States, Zachary Taylor being president. He presided over the
                    senate ably and impartially during the seven months of exciting debate and
                    agitation on the so-called “Compromise Measures,” and Mr Clay’s “Omnibus Bill,”
                    which, though finally defeated as a whole, substantially succeeded in its
                    general bearing on several matters of intense import to the nation as connected
                    with the subject of slavery.</p>
                <p>President Taylor died July 9, 1850, and the next day Fillmore, according to the
                    special provision of the consti-tion, took the oath and acceded to the highest
                    office, being then fifty-one years old. The cabinet which he called around him,
                    contained many distinguished men, as Webster, Corwin, Crittenden, Graham, Hall,
                    and Kennedy. On the death of Webster in 1852, Edward Everett succeeded him as
                    secretary of state. The president sent a force to protect New Mexico in the
                    dispute as to its boundaries with Texas. The critical matter which gave its
                    historic significance to his administration was that chief one of the class of
                    “compromise” measures, the enactment of the Fugitive Slave Law, to make
                    effective a provision of the constitution for the rendition of “fugitives from
                    labour or service.” Being instructed by Crittenden, his attorney-general, that
                    the bill was not inconsistent with the constitutional sanction of the Habeas
                    Corpus, the president signed the bill, and issued a proclamation calling upon
                    Government officials to enforce it. These measures roused the most passionate
                    opposition and animosity, among Whigs as well as anti-slavery men. The attempt
                    to enforce the odious law was restricted by mobs in various free States, and was
                    made, for the most part, wholly ineffectual, the people being resolved to regard
                    it as annulled by the “higher law.” The fact that the president had signed and
                    sought to enforce the law, though he might plead for himself constitutional
                    obligation, and a purpose of patriotic fidelity in the exercise of his best
                    judgment, made a breach between him and his party. But few questioned the
                    sincerity and purity of his intentions, or his own full persuasion that the
                    measures were of vital necessity to pacify the nation. Still, as the result was
                    a sharp and embittered variance among his previous supporters, his
                    administration was regarded as inglorious, if not as a failure.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n175/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0175-0166"/>
                <p>In many other matters of high public concern, his official course, as indicated
                    by his appointments, the recommendations in his messages, and the projects which
                    he devised, was characterized by sound discretion, by humane promptings, and
                    practical wisdom. His advice, however, even on these matters, was not always
                    followed by Congress. That body 1 ιaving approved a plan for the extension of
                    the Capitol, the president, on July 4,1851, laid the corner-stone of the new
                    edifice, Daniel Webster being the orator of the occasion. In the same year he
                    interposed promptly and effectively in thwarting the projects of the
                    “filibusters,” under Lopez, for the invasion of Cuba. Commodore Perry’s
                    expedition to Japan, that of Lieutenant Lynch to Africa, and that of Ringgold to
                    the Chinese Seas, with the exploration of the valley of the Amazon by Herndon
                    and Gibbon, may be referred to as engaging the executive ability and
                    wide-forethought of the president. His term closed March 4, 1853. In the
                    preceding autumn he had been an unsuccessful candidate for nomination for the
                    presidency by the Whig National Convention, and he yielded his place to Franklin
                    Pierce. Three weeks before the close of his term his wife died in Washington,
                    and he quietly returned, with a son and a daughter, to private life in Buffalo.
                    In 1854, he travelled extensively through the southern and western States, and
                    in 1855-6 he visited Europe, moving from place to place in a quiet and
                    unostentatious way, but receiving much courteous attention. He declined the
                    proffered honour of D.C.L. from Oxford. While in Rome lie was informed of his
                    nomination for the presidency by the “Native American” party, the nominees of
                    the other parties being Buchanan and Fremont. In 1858 he married Mrs Caroline
                    MΙntosh of Albany, a lady of fortune and culture. Retiring to his home in
                    Buffalo, he enjoyed a studious retirement among his books and friends, taking no
                    public share in political affairs. He took great interest in the Buffalo
                    Historical Society, of which he was the president. His life closed March 8,
                    1874, in his seventyfifth year. All who knew him in any relation accorded in
                    regarding him as an upright and conscientious man, blameless, loving simple
                    ways, and heartily devoted to the best interests of his country. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">(g. e. e.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
