<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0169-0160-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FILE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 160</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1145710">Teeth</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:857974">Chisels</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1132472">Steel</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1078061">Processions</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1078016">Process</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4j09wd22">Teething</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c56c">Teeth</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xj9j">Steel</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4b853m90">Processions</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4930p29x">Process</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n169/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FILE</label>, a bar of steel having sharp teeth on its
                    surface, and used for abrading or smoothing hard substances. Some uncivilized
                    tribes polish their weapons with such things as rough stones, pieces of shark
                    skiu, or fishes’ teeth. The operation of filing is recorded in 1 Sam. xiii. 21;
                    and, among other facts, the similarity of the name for the filing instrument
                    among various European peoples points to an early practice of the art. A file
                    differs from a <hi rend="italic">rasp</hi> (which is chiefly used for working
                    wood, horn, and the like) in having its teeth cut with a chisel whose straight
                    edge extends across its surface, while the teeth of the rasp are formed by
                    solitary indentations of a pointed chisel. According to the form of their teeth,
                    files may be <hi rend="italic">single-cut</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >double-cut;</hi> the former have only one set of parallel ridges (either at
                    right angles or at some other angle with the length); the latter (and more
                    common) have a second set cut at an angle with the first. The double-cut file
                    presents sharp angles to the filed surface, and is better suited for hard
                    metals. Files are also classed according to fineness of teeth, being known (in
                    order of increasing fineness) as <hi rend="italic">rough, bastard, second-cut,
                    smooth,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">superfine</hi> or <hi rend="italic">dead
                    smooth.</hi> The shapes of files present almost endless varieties. Common forms
                    are—the <hi rend="italic">fiat</hi> file, of parallelogram section, with uniform
                    breadth and thickness, or tapering, or “bellied”; the <hi rend="italic"
                    >four-square</hi> file, of square section, sometimes with one side “safe,” or
                    left smooth; the so-called <hi rend="italic">three-square</hi> file, having its
                    cross section an equilateral triangle, the <hi rend="italic">half-round</hi>
                    file, a segment of a circle, the <hi rend="italic">round</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">rat-tail</hi> file, a circle; these are generally tapered. The <hi
                    rend="italic">float</hi> file is like the <hi rend="italic">flat,</hi> but
                    single-cut. There are many others. Files vary in length from three-quarters of
                    an inch (watchmakers’) to two or three feet and upwards (engineers’). The length
                    is reckoned exclusively of the spike or tang which enters the handle. Most files
                    are tapered; the <hi rend="italic">blunt</hi> are nearly parallel, with larger
                    section near the middle; a few are parallel. The <hi rend="italic">rifflers</hi>
                    of sculptors and a few other files are curvilinear in their central line.</p>
                <p>Cast-steel is the material chiefly used for files, though the larger and rougher
                    varieties are sometimes made from blister-steel. In manufacture, the blanks are
                    forged from bars that have been tilted or rolled as nearly as possible to the
                    sections required. They are then annealed with great care, and when sufficiently
                    softened are taken out, straightened, if necessary, with hand hammers, and then
                    reudered clean and accurate in form by filing or grinding. They are now ready
                    for cutting. In this process, as performed by hand, the cutter sits before a
                    square stake or anvil, on which the blank, slightly greased, is held (having its
                    tang towards him) by means of two leather straps passed round its ends, and held
                    fast below, one by each foot. He holds in his left hand a short chisel (the edge
                    of which always exceeds the width of the file), placing it on the blank with a
                    slight inclination from him, and beginning near the further end. He strikes the
                    chisel sharply with a hammer, an indentation is thus made, and the steel,
                    slightly thrown up on the side next the tang, forms a ridge. The chisel is then
                    transferred to the uncut surface, and slid from the operator till it reaches the
                    ridge just made; thus the position of the next cut is determined; the chisel is
                    again struck, and so on. (The end part of the file is dealt with separately.)
                    The workman seeks to give his blows as uniformly as possible. Sixty to eighty
                    cuts are made in one minute. After finishing. the first <hi rend="italic">course
                    of</hi> cuts, he proceeds, if the file is to be double-cut, to make the second
                    course, the cuts of the latter being generally somewhat finer. Thus the surface
                    is covered with teeth inclined towards the point of the file. If the file is
                    flat and is to be cut on the other side, it is turned over, and a thin plate of
                    pewter placed below it to protect the teeth. Triangular and other files are
                    supported in grooves in lead. In cutting round and half-round files, a straight
                    chisel is applied as tangent to the curve. The round face of a half-round file
                    requires eight, ten, or more courses to complete it.</p>
                <p>The file is next hardened. Being first covered with a paste to protect the teeth
                    from the direct action of fire, Ac. <hi rend="italic">(e.g.,</hi> passed through
                    beer-grounds to make it sticky, then through a mixture of common salt with
                    roasted and pounded cow’s hoof), it is heated to an even red heat, and then
                    suddenly cooled by plunging in cold water or brine. It is removed before cooling
                    throughout, that it may be straightened if necessary (which is done by
                    pressure). Then it is cooled in oil. The tang is next submitted to a softening
                    process, and the file, after being wiped, and the teeth brushed clean, is ready
                    for fixing into the handle and for use.</p>
                <p>In England files are chiefly made in Sheffield and Warrington, those of the
                    latter place being generally known as Lancashire files. It is remarkable that
                    while many other operations that appear more difficult than file-cutting are now
                    effected by machinery, and while numerous file-cutting machines have been
                    invented, the work continues (in England) to be largely done by hand. This is
                    perhaps partly due to strong opposition on the part of operatives to
                    introduction of machinery, and also to a foolish prejudice in favour of hand-cut
                    files (machine-cut files, indeed, are not unfrequently sold as hand-cut), but
                    probably also to the problem of cutting files by machinery being really somewhat
                    difficult. In most of the machines invented for that purpose, the idea has been
                    to construct an iron arm and hand to hold the chisel, and a hammer to strike the
                    blow, and so to imitate, as closely as possible, the manual process. Barnot’s
                    machine is an improvement on this. In it the blow is given by pressure of a flat
                    steel spring pressing on the top of a vertical slide, at the lower end of which
                    the chisel is firmly fixed. The slide is acted on by a cam making about one
                    thousand revolutions a minute, and the chisel consequently strikes that number
                    of blows per minute. The vibration is thus lessened. The history of file-making
                    by machinery in America (where it has been extensively practised) seems to
                    indicate that much of the failure experienced has been due to the fatal defect
                    in. the machinery used, of producing extreme regularity in the teeth. This gives
                    rise to complaints by artisans about files “running in grooves,” “chattering,”
                    &amp;c. The grooves produced by the file (if double-cut especially) at the
                    beginning of its movement are deepened as it is moved further. With irregular
                    teeth, on the other hand, such as are found in all hand-made files, the grooves
                    made in the first instance have their sides cut away as the file is advanced.
                    The Nicholson File Company, in Providence, Rhode Islaud, have used, with large
                    and increasing success, a machine which imitates, to some extent, this irregular
                    result of the hand process, cutting the file so that no two spaces are found
                    exactly alike in the entire length.</p>
                <p>The filing of a flat surface perfectly true is the test of a good filer; and this
                    is no easy matter to the beginner. The piece to be operated upon is generally
                    fixed about the level of the elbow, the operator standing, and, except in the
                    case of small files, grasping the file with both hands, the handle with the
                    right, the further end with the left. The great point is to be able to move the
                    file forward with pressure in horizontal straight lines; from the tendency of
                    the hands to <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n170/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0170-0161"/> move in arcs of circles, the heel and point of
                    the file are apt to be alternately raised. This is partially compensated by the
                    bellied form given to many files (which also counteracts the frequent warping
                    effect of the hardening process, by which one side of a flat file may be
                    rendered concave and useless). In bringing back the file for the next thrust it
                    is nearly lifted off the work. Further, much delicacy aud skill are required in
                    adapting the pressure and velocity, ascertaining if foreign matters or filings
                    remain interposed between the file and the work, &amp;c. Files can be cleaned
                    with a peace of the so-called <hi rend="italic">cotton-card</hi> (used in
                    combing cotton wool) nailed to a piece of wood. In <hi rend="italic"
                    >draw-filing,</hi> which is sometimes resorted to to give a neat finish, the
                    file is drawn sideways to and fro over the work. New files are generally used
                    for a time on brass or cast-iron, and when partially worn they are still
                    available for filing wrought iron and steeL</p>
                <p>An interesting application of the sandblast to sharpening the ~ teeth of files
                    has recently been made by M. Tilghmann. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. b. μ.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
