<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0317-0306-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FLEURY, Claude</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 306</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rj8h">Berries</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc9k">Indexes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v395">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:968979">Indexing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:830788">Berries</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n317/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FLEURY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Claude</hi></label> (1640-1723),
                    the famous ecclesiastical historian, was born at Paris, December 6, 1640.
                    Destined for the bar by his father, he was placed at the college of Clermont
                    (now that of Louis-le-Grand), where the sons of the first families of France
                    were educated. After passing brilliantly through the regular collegiate studies,
                    he was nominated an advocate to the parliament of Paris in 1658, and continued
                    during nine years to pursue the legal profession. Feeling a strong desire to
                    enter the church, being fond of solitude, but especially influenced by the
                    religious sentiments which he had imbibed during his early education, he
                    renounced the law—which, with history and literature, up to this time had formed
                    the principal objects of his study—in order to devote himself to theology
                    exclusively. He had already been some time in holy orders, when Louis XIV., in
                    1672, selected him as tutor of the princes of Conti; and so well did he acquit
                    himself in this office, that the king intrusted to him afterwards the education
                    of the count of Vermandois, one of his natural sons; and at the death of the
                    young prince, Fleury received as recompense for his services the abbey of
                    Loc-Dieu, in the diocese of Rhodez. Five years after this (1689) he was
                    appointed sub-preceptor of the dukes of Burgundy, of Anjou, and of Berri. He
                    thus became intimately associated with Fénelon, the chief preceptor of his royal
                    pupils. In 1696 he was selected to fill the place of La Bruyère in the French
                    Academy; and on the completion of the education of the young princes, the king
                    bestowed upon him the rich priory of Argenteuil, in the diocese of Paris (1706).
                    On assuming this benefice he resigned that of the abbey of Loc-Dieu, thus
                    setting an example of rare disinterestedness. It was about this time that he
                    decided, according to the suggestions of his friends, on commencing his great
                    work, for which he had been collecting materials for thirty years —the <hi
                    rend="italic">Histoire Ecclésiastique.</hi> Hitherto France did not possess any
                    work of equal merit in this department of literature. There existed many works
                    more or less voluminous on matters of doctrine and discipline; but no one had
                    written a history of the church,—a complete and scientific exposition of the
                    progress of Christian society, of its organization and its primitive doctrine,
                    of its varied changes in connexion with the state, of the successive development
                    of its institutions, of all the modifications introduced into its symbols and
                    its rites. Fleury had evidently the intention of writing a history of the church
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n318/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0318-0307"/> for all classes of society; but at the time in
                    which his great work appeared it was less religion than theology that absorbed
                    the attention of the clergy and the educated public; and his work, as well as
                    all those that had been published previously, is therefore more a work for the
                    student than one for the people, dwelling as it does very particularly on
                    questions of doctrine, of discipline, of supremacy, and of rivalry between the
                    priesthood and the imperial power, while it notices very slightly general
                    questions affecting religion and morality. This fault, which was then looked
                    upon as a merit, secured to the <hi rend="italic">Histoire Ecclésiastique</hi> a
                    very great success. The first edition, printed at Paris in 20 volumes 4to, 1691,
                    was followed by many others, among which may be mentioned that of Brussels, in
                    32 vols. 8vo, 1692, and that of Nismes, in 25 vols. 8vo, 1778 to 1780. The work
                    of Fleury only comes down to the year 1414. It was continued by J. Claude Fabre
                    and Goujet down to 1595, in 16 vols. 4to. In consulting the work of Fleury and
                    its supplement, the general table of contents, published by Rondel, Paris, 1758,
                    1 vol. 4to, will be found very useful. Translations have been made of the entire
                    work into Latin, German, and Italian. The Latin translation, published at
                    Augsburg, 1758-59, 85 vols. 8vo, carries the work down to 1684. Fleury, who had
                    been appointed confessor to the king in 1716, died in 1723.</p>
                <p>Fleury left many works besides his <hi rend="italic">Histoire
                    Ecclésiastique.</hi> The following deserve special mention :— <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">du Droit</hi><hi rend="italic">français,</hi>
                    1674, 12mo; <hi rend="italic">Catéchisme historique,</hi> 1679, 12mo; <hi
                    rend="italic">Moeurs des Israélites,</hi> 1681, 12mo; <hi rend="italic">Moeurs
                    des Chrétiens,</hi> 1682, 12mo; <hi rend="italic">Traité du choix et de la
                    méthode des études,</hi> 1686, 2 vols. 12mo; <hi rend="italic">Institution du
                    Droit ecclésiastique,</hi> 1687, 2 vols. 12mo <hi rend="italic">; Les Devoirs
                    des maîtres et des domestiques,</hi> 1688, 12mo. The Roman Congregation of the
                    Index has condemned the <hi rend="italic">Catéchisme historique</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Institution du Droit</hi><hi rend="italic">ecclésiastique.</hi>
                    The books to be specially consulted on Fleury’s biography are—Chr. Ernst
                    Simonetti, <hi rend="italic">Der</hi><hi rend="italic">Character</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">eines Geschichtsschreibers</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dem Leben und aus den Schriften des Abbts C. Fleury,</hi>
                    Göttingen, 1746, 4to; J. F. Lehret, <hi rend="italic">Dissertatio</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de C. Flcuryo, Gallo-catholico an acatholico,</hi> Tübingen, 1800,
                    4to; Chr. F. Ph. Jaeger, <hi rend="italic">Notice</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >sur</hi><hi rend="italic">C. Fleury,</hi><hi rend="italic">considéré comme
                    historien de V Église,</hi> Strasburg, 1847, 8vo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
