<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0729-0694-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FRANCIS BORGIA, St (9th edition, volume 9, page
                    694)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4610vs0f">Archbishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110522">Sebastianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:843075">Butlers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:909415">Empresses</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n729/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FRANCIS BORGIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">St</hi></label>
                    (1510-1572), duke of Gaudia, and afterwards general of the Jesuit order, was the
                    son of John, duke of Gandia, a scion of the well-known family of Borgia or Borja
                    to which Popes Calixtus III. and Alexander VI. had belonged, and of Joanna of
                    Aragon, daughter of Alphonso, a natural son of Ferdinand the Catholic. He was
                    born at Gandia (Valencia), on the 10th of October 1510, and from his infancy was
                    remarkable for his piety. Educated from his twelfth year at Saragossa under the
                    charge of his uncle the archbishop, he had begun to show a strong inclination
                    towards the monastic life, when his father, wishing to divert his thoughts
                    elsewhere, sent him in 1528 to the court of Charles V. Here he soon
                    distinguished himself greatly by his diligence and fidelity; and on his marriage
                    with Eleanor de Castro, a Portuguese lady of high rank, he was created by the
                    emperor Marquis of Lombay, and at the same time received the appointment of
                    master of the horse to the empress. He accompanied Charles on his African
                    expedition in 1535, and also into Provence in 1536; and on the death of the
                    empress in 1539 he was deputed to convoy the body to the burial place in
                    Granada. Circumstances connected with the funeral obsequies there deepened in
                    his mind long-cherished impressions as to the vanity of all worldly things, and
                    fixed his determination to leave the court betimes, and also, should he survive
                    his consort, to embrace the monastic life. On his return to Toledo, however, new
                    honours were thrust upon him, much against his will; he was made viceroy of
                    Catalonia and commander of the order of St James. At Barcelona, the seat of his
                    government, he lived a life of great austerity, but discharged his official
                    duties with energy and efficiency until 1543, when, having succeeded his father
                    in the dukedom, he at length obtained permission to resign his viceroyalty, and
                    to retire to a more congenial mode of life at Gandia. Having already held some
                    correspondence with Loyola, he now encouraged the recently founded order of
                    Jesuits to the utmost of his power. One of his first cares at Gandia was to
                    build a college for them; and on the death of Eleanor in 1546, he resolved to
                    become himself a member of their society. The difficulties arising from
                    political and family circumstances were removed by a papal dispensation, which
                    allowed him, in the interests of his young children, to retain his dignities and
                    worldly possessions for four years after he should have taken the vows. In 1550
                    he visited Rome, where he was received with every mark of distinction, and where
                    he furnished the means for building the Collegium Romanum. Returning to Spain in
                    the following year, he, with the emperor’s consent, formally resigned his rank
                    and estate in favour of his eldest son, laid aside his ducal robes,, assumed the
                    Jesuit habit, was ordained as a priest, and entered upon a life of penance and
                    prayer. At his own earnest request, in which he was seconded by Loyola, a
                    proposal that he should be created a cardinal by Julius III. was departed from;
                    and at the command of his superior he employed himself in the work of itinerant
                    preaching. In 1554 he was appointed commissary-general of the order in Spain,
                    Portugal, and the Indies, in which capacity he showed great activity, and was
                    successful in founding many new and thriving colleges. In 1556, shortly after
                    the retirement from public life of his old master Charles, Borgia had an
                    interview with him. Charles, unfavourable to all innovation, and looking with
                    distrust upon Jesuit pretensions, endeavoured<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n730/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0730-0695"/>, it is said, to induce the commissary to
                    transfer his allegiance to the older order of Jeronymites. This attempt, though
                    unsuccessful, did not disturb the old relations of confidence and friendship
                    between the two men, as was shown some time afterwards when Borgia was employed
                    by Charles to conduct some delicate negotiations with reference to a project
                    which was to secure for Don Carlos of Spain the succession to the Portuguese
                    crown in the event of the death of his cousin Don Sebastian. On the death of
                    Lainez in 1565, Francis Borgia was chosen to succeed him as third general of the
                    Jesuits. In this capacity he showed great zeal and administrative skill; and so
                    great was the progress of the society under his government that he has sometimes
                    been called “its second founder.” It is to be noticed, however, that the
                    peculiarities which are understood to be most characteristic of the order have
                    been derived from Loyola and Lainez rather than from Borgia, whose ideal was a
                    pure and simple monasticism rather than a life of manifold and influential
                    contact with the world. His death took place at Rome towards midnight on the
                    30th of September 1572. He was beatified by Urban VIII. in 1624, and canonized
                    by Clement X. in 1671, his festival being afterwards (1683) fixed by Innocent
                    XI. for the 10th of October.</p>
                <p>Several works by St Francis Borgia have been published, the principal of these
                    being a series of <hi rend="italic">Exercises</hi> similar to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Exercitia, Spiritualia</hi> of Loyola, and a treatise <hi
                        rend="italic">Rhetorica Condonandi.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Opera
                        Omnia</hi> were published at Brussels in 1675. His life was written by his
                    confessor Ribadeneira. See also Butler’s <hi rend="italic">Lives of the
                        Saints,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Breviarium Romanum</hi> (second
                    nocturn for 10th October).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
