<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0368-0355-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FOLEY, John Henry</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 355</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:830184">Bells</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1109473">Sculptors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2td33">Goldsmithing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47659k3h">Goldsmiths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41834b98">Wards</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hg87">Sculptors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19s90">Students</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n368/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FOLEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Henry</hi></label>
                    (1818-1874), sculptor, R.A., was born at Dublin, May 24, 1818. Through a distant
                    relative, a sculptor in the city, his attention was early directed to the
                    profession which was to occupy his life, and at thirteen he began to study
                    drawing and modelling at the schools of the Royal Dublin Society, where he took
                    several first-class prizes. In 1834 he proceeded to London, and in 1835 was
                    admitted a student in the schools of the Royal Academy. He first appeared as an
                    exhibitor in 1839 with his Death of Abel and Innocence. Ino and Bacchus,
                    exhibited in 1840, gave him immediate reputation, and the work itself was
                    afterwards commissioned to be done in marble for the earl of Ellesmere.
                    Conceived entirely without classical or other affectation, this work has the
                    charm of rare simplicity and grace. Lear and Cordelia and Death of Lear were
                    exhibited in 1841, Venus rescuing Aeneas and The Houseless Wanderer in 1842,
                    Prospero and Miranda in 1843. In 1844 Foley sent to the exhibition at
                    Westminster Hall his Youth at a Stream, and was, with <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n369/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0369-0356"/> Calder Marshall and John Bell, chosen by the
                    commissioners to do work in sculpture for the decoration of the Houses of
                    Parliament. Statues of John Hampden and Selden were executed for this purpose,
                    and received liberal praise for the propriety, dignity, and proportion of their
                    treatment. Commissions of all kinds now began to come rapidly, and without going
                    out of his way to seek it, Foley had from this time until his death work
                    sufficient to occupy not only the whole of his own time, but also that of the
                    numerous assistants and pupils whom he trained. Fanciful works, busts,
                    bas-reliefs, tablets, and monumental statues were in great numbers undertaken
                    and executed by him with that steady equality of worthy treatment which is
                    perhaps the next best thing to the inspiration of great genius. In 1849 he was
                    made an associate and 1858 a member of the Royal Academy; but although until his
                    death his name remained on the list of Royal Academicians, he, after 1861,
                    owing, it is said to some misunderstanding with the hanging committee of that
                    year, ceased not only to exhibit but also to hold any communication with the
                    body of which he was a member. Among his numerous works the following may be
                    noticed, besides those mentioned above :—The Mother; Egeria, for the Mansion
                    House; The Elder Brother in Cornus, his diploma work; The Muse of Painting, the
                    monument of James Ward, R. A.; Caractacus, for the Mansion House; Helen Faucit
                    (Mrs Theodore Martin); Goldsmith and Burke, for Trinity College, Dublin;
                    Faraday; Reynolds; Barry, for Westminster Palace Yard; John Stuart Mill, for the
                    Thames embankment; O'Connell and Gough, for Dublin; Clyde, for Glasgow; Clive,
                    for Shrewsbury; Hardinge, Canning, and Outram, for Calcutta; Hon. James Stewart,
                    for Ceylon; the symbolical group Asia, as well as the statue of the prince
                    himself, for the Albert Memorial in Hyde Park; and Stonewall Jackson, for South
                    Carolina. The statue of Outram is probably his masterpiece, and certainly
                    displays more imaginative fire than any other of his works, while well
                    exhibiting that perfect sanity of conception as well as that full mastery of the
                    means of his art by which all his works are characterized. Foley’s early
                    fanciful works have some charming qualities; but he will probably be always best
                    remembered for the workman-like and manly style of his monumental portraits. His
                    life was entirely devoted to his art, and he seems to have addressed himself to
                    it with all the workday docility of a craftsman, and at the same time with
                    strong feelings of duty and responsibility. Of great modesty, and rather
                    reserved in manner, he was open to all that influences a refined nature; in
                    poetry and music he was not only a student and admirer, but a composer and
                    performer. He died at Hampstead of a pleuritic effusion after a short illness,
                    preceded by a long indisposition, August 27, 1874, and was on the 4th of
                    September buried in St Paul’s Cathedral. He left his models to the Royal Dublin
                    Society, his early school, while a great part of his property goes eventually to
                    the Artists’ Benevolent Fund.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
