<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0722-0687-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FRANCHE COMTÉ</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 687</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:919892">Fairs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:803903">Aix</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:938950">Gates</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:863204">Claims</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xw4804p">Fairs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40k26h3v">Lombards</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4t727h76">Claims</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n722/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FRANCHE COMTÉ</label>, from 1674 till the great Revolution
                    one of the provinces of France, was bounded on the E. by the principality of
                    Montbéliard or Mömpelgard and Switzerland, S. by Bresse, Bugey, and Gex, N. by
                    Lorraine, and W. by the duchy of Burgundy and Champagne. It lay to the west of
                    the Jura, and included the valley of the upper Saône and the greater part of the
                    valley of the Doubs. In earlier history it is usually called the countship of
                    Burgundy or Upper Burgundy; in later French history, on the other hand, it is
                    frequently mentioned as the countship (la Comté) <hi rend="italic">par
                    excellence.</hi> The countship probably took its rise in the 10th century as a
                    fief of the kingdom of Burgundy, which was dependent on the empire. It was held
                    in the beginning of the 11th by Otto William, the warlike son of the king of the
                    Lombards; his son and successor Reinhold or Reinaud I. ventured to refuse his
                    homage to his suzerain Henry III., and his example was followed about a century
                    afterwards by Reinhold III., who took up a position of independence against the
                    emperor Lothar. In neither case was the attempt to throw off the yoke permitted
                    to succeed, but on the latter occasion at least the prestige of the countship
                    was improved, and according to one theory the honourable title of Free Countship
                    <hi rend="italic">(ſlFrei-grafochaft)</hi> was then acquired. After Lothar’s
                    death Reinhold again refused homage to the emperor Conrad, and though the
                    emperor consequently bestowed his countship on Conrad of Zähringen, Reinhold was
                    still in actual possession at his death in 1148. His daughter and heiress
                    Beatrix was married to Frederick Barbarossa in 1156; and on her decease in 1185
                    Frederick bestowed the countship on his third son Otto, and raised Besançon to
                    the rank of a free imperial city. Otto’s daughter Beatrix married Duke Otto of
                    Meran, and was succeeded first by their son Otto and afterwards by their
                    daughter Alix. Otto, the son of Alix, offended the emperor Rudolph I., and his
                    city Besançon was consequently besieged by the imperial troops in 1289; but it
                    made a successful defence, and peace was soon afterwards concluded. A treaty was
                    made with Philip the Fair of France, by which Otto’s daughter Johanna was to
                    marry Philip of Poitiers the king’s second son, and the suzerainty of France was
                    to be recognized by Franche Comté. The marriage took place in due course in
                    1307, and the importance attached by the king to his claims on Franche Comté is
                    shown by the leniency with which the charges against the princess Johanna or
                    Jeanne were enforced when her sisters-in-law were degraded and imprisoned and
                    their paramours tortured and executed. On Philip’s death in 1322 the countship
                    passed to Otto IV. duke of Burgundy, and it was successively held by Philip de
                    Rouvre, Margaret of France, Louis de Male, and Charles the Bold. On Charles’s
                    death, Louis XL of France claimed the protectorate <hi rend="italic">“for</hi>
                    the good of the country and the lady of Burgundy, and in favour of the marriage
                    of the dauphin with that lady.” By feudal law the countship still held of the
                    empire, being a German and a female fief; but the states accepted the French
                    protection (February 1477), and the claims of Maximilian were appeased by the
                    promise of the hand of Charles of France for his daughter Margaret. In April,
                    however, a rebellion broke out; the emperor recalled the people to their
                    allegiance, and the Swiss hastened to support the popular cause. The French were
                    constrained to withdraw; but in 1479 the Sire de Chaumont invaded the country,
                    captured Dole in spite of a vigorous defence, in which the students of the
                    university displayed a desperate but resultless valour, and forced the people to
                    submit. Besançon, the free imperial city, recognized the French king on the same
                    conditions which it had demanded from the dukes of Burgundy, and promised to pay
                    over half the product of its taxes. The parliament of Dole was transferred to
                    Salins, and the university to Besançon. When Charles VIII. refused to marry
                    Maximilian’s daughter, the people of Franche Comté rose in revolt, and the king
                    relinquished his claims by the treaty of Senlis, May 23,1493. Along with the
                    rest of the domains of the house of Burgundy the countship was bestowed on
                    Philip, Maximilian’s son, and passed to the crown of Spain. As a Spanish
                    territory its position was a peculiar and isolated one; and it was consequently
                    treated with great leniency by the Spanish Government. It paid a “gratuitous
                    gift” of not more than 200,000 livres every three years, and furnished very few
                    soldiers to the royal army. Under the nominal authority of the governor-general
                    of the Low Countries, it was practically "governed by the parliament of Dole and
                    a governor chosen from the ranks of its own nobility. In 1668 Louis XIV. cast
                    his eyes on the province, and Condé effected its conquest in fifteen days. On
                    the 14th of February the king swore at Dole to preserve the liberties of the
                    town and province as count palatine of Burgundy, and the parliament issued an
                    edict against those who refused to submit to his authority. By the peace of
                    Aix-la-Chapelle, which almost immediately followed, Franche Comté was restored
                    to Spain; but in 1674 Louis made a new invasion. Besançon was taken after a
                    lengthened siege, at which Vauban and the king were both personally present;
                    Dole shared the same fate; and by the 4th of July the whole country was again in
                    the hands of the French. To celebrate the conquest the triumphal arch of the
                    Saint Martin gate at Paris was erected. The count <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n723/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0723-0688"/> ship now became a French province; its gratuitous
                    donation became a regular impost, which was soon after increased in amount; and
                    the chief authority was placed in the hands of a governor-general. Instead of
                    three great bailiwicks, as formerly, there were four :—Amont, Aval, Besançon,
                    and Dole—their chief towns being Vesoul, Salins, Besançon, and Dole. See Clerc,
                    <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la Franche Comté.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
