<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0727-0692-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FRANCIS, St (9th edition, volume 9, page 692)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n727/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FRANCIS, <hi rend="smallcaps">St</hi></label> (1182-1226), a
                    well-known saint of the Roman Catholic Church, the founder of the great order of
                    Franciscans, was born at Assisi in the year 1182. His father was a trader in
                    goods which he appears chiefly to have purchased in the south of France, to
                    which he made frequent journeys; and his son was born during one of these
                    journeys, and in consequence received from the grateful father on his return the
                    name of Francesco. His mother had wished to call him, it is said, Giovanni or
                    John. The youth grew up very much like any other boy of his class. He received
                    but little learning from the priest of the parish, and does not seem to have
                    manifested any special love for school instruction. He was by nature a
                    merry-hearted and careless fellow, and developed early an inclination for fine
                    clothes and street amusements with other boys of his class. His parents,
                    indulgent to his gaieties, saw with pride the higher tastes and bright
                    intelligence of their son, and would sometimes say to one another, “He is like
                    the son of a prince.” The father formed expectations of α successful courtly
                    career; but the mother, seeing more into the boy’s heart, would say to her
                    neighbours, “If he lives like the son of a prince now, he shall hereafter be a
                    child of God.”</p>
                <p>Soon a great change came to him. At the age of twenty-five Francis was seized
                    with a severe illness. Reflections came to him on his sick-bed, and he rose from
                    it an altered man. Henceforward, says one of his biographers, “he held that in
                    contempt which he had hitherto held in admiration and love.” The ardour of his
                    natural character flamed forth first in the idea of military devotion, and then
                    in a consuming spirit of self-sacrifice for the good of others. All his love of
                    amusement and worldly display disappeared. He began to speak of poverty as his
                    bride; and the poor and the sick and the leper became the objects of his
                    peculiar care. He would seek out the lepers, hitherto abhorred by him as by the
                    popular feeling, and kiss them and minister to their wants. He made a pilgrimage
                    to Rome, and in his enthusiasm for poverty flung all he had on the altar of St
                    Peters, joined himself to a troop of beggars, and gave himself up to a wandering
                    life of almsgiving and charity. His mother guessed something of the feelings
                    that were struggling in her son’s heart; but his father, not unnaturally, was
                    greatly concerned at his conduct. At last matters came to an open rupture
                    between them; and the saint’s severance of the parental tie for the sake of his
                    divine mission is a significant incident in his career with all his biographers.
                    It happened in this wise. There was an old church or small chapel of the name of
                    St Damian in the neighbourhood of Assisi which had fallen into ruins. The spot
                    was a favourite one with the youthful enthusiast for meditation and prayer; and
                    one day as he sat in meditation among the ruins he seemed to hear a voice saying
                    to him clearly, “Francis, seest thou not that my house is in ruins; go and
                    restore it for me.” To hear was to obey. The divine voice, as with some other
                    enthusiasts, seemed to silence every other voice in his heart, even the voice of
                    conscience. He returned home, saddled his horse, took a bale of his father’s
                    goods, and repairing to Foligno he sold both horse and goods, and rushed to the
                    priest of St Damian with the money to pay for the restoration of the church. The
                    good priest was startled; his father heard with indignation of bis son’s
                    conduct, and at length with blows and curses securely imprisoned him from any
                    further freaks. But his father’s harshness overshot the mark. Released by <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n728/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0728-0693"/> the tenderness of his mother, and summoned to
                    restore the goods he had taken away and renounce all his patrimonial rights, the
                    popular feeling, which had previously sided with his father against him, now
                    turned in the youth’s favour. The bishop, before whom the case finally came,
                    discovered the youth’s vocation to a religious life, and induced him to restore
                    the value of the goods to his father. The money had been all the while lying
                    neglected amidst the ruins of the church. This accomplished, Francis renounced
                    all dependence upon his father, and gave himself up to the profession of a
                    religious mendicant, “I have but one, a Father in heaven, now,” he said. The
                    people were melted to tears by his devotion, and the good bishop took him for a
                    time under his own charge.</p>
                <p>Gradually Francis found his full vocation, not only in a life of entire devotion
                    and poverty for himself, but in founding an order of mendicants devoted to the
                    service of the church. It was in the old scene of his earlier inspiration that
                    the new idea came to him. Once more the divine voice was heard sounding in his
                    ears: “Provide neither gold nor silver nor brass in your purses, nor scrip for
                    your journey, neither two coats, nor yet staves.” This was about the year 1208
                    or 1209, when, therefore, the saint was about twenty-six years of age. He was
                    henceforth a preacher as well as an exemplar of poverty. He essayed to reproduce
                    the picture of the divine life on earth, having not where to lay his held, going
                    about doing good, and preaching the gospel of the kingdom. “Sell all that thou
                    hast, and give to the poor; then thou shalt have treasure in heaven.” Gradually
                    there gathered round his cell, which he had fixed outside the town near a little
                    church, the St Maria degli Angeli, better known as the Portiuncula, a band of
                    disciples as enthusiastic as himself. “Fear not,” he said to them, “because you
                    are small and seem foolish. Have confidence in the Lord who has vanquished the
                    world. Some will receive you. Many proud will resist you. Bear all with
                    sweetness and patience. Soon the wise and the noble will be with us. The Lord
                    hath given me to see this. I have in my ears the sounds of the languages of all
                    the people who will come to us,—French, Spaniards, Germans, English. The Lord
                    will make us a great people, even to the end of the earth.”</p>
                <p>In this insignificant manner was laid the foundation of the great Franciscan
                    order. At first there were only seven, himself the eighth, but all were animated
                    by the same spirit, and all followed the same rule of life. As he sent them
                    forth he said, “Go and preach two and two. Preach peace and patience; tend the
                    wounded: relieve the distressed; reclaim the erring; bless them wlιich persecute
                    you, and pray for them that despitefully use you.” The gospel of divine poverty
                    was proclaimed everywhere. The spirit of self-renunciation spread by-and-by like
                    wildfire, and multitudes were added to the order day by day. It may seem to our
                    modern imagination a fantastic dream, but the gospel of St Francis met a
                    congenial root in the social and spiritual life of the 13th century, and rapidly
                    grew into great results. The sanction and blessing of the papacy, however, were
                    necessary to give the order ecclesiastical position and influence. Francis
                    himself undertook a new journey to Rome, and suddenly appeared before the great
                    Innocent III. as he was walking one day on the terrace of the Lateran. The
                    startled pope dismissed the mean stranger with mingled pity and contempt; but
                    the same night a vision came to him of the marvellous growth of a palm tree from
                    meanness to magnificence; and, as he pondered the meaning of the vision, a
                    divine whisper reached him that thus powerful on behalf of the church was to
                    prove the poor man whose appearance had startled him. The natural conclusion
                    followed. The poor man was recalled, his projects were submitted to the judgment
                    of the Vatican, and the result was that the papal sanction was formally extended
                    to the order,—a few years before the same sanction was given to the great rival
                    order headed by the learned and noble Dominic. The founders of the two great
                    mendicant orders are said to have met afterwards at Rome, and again at a great
                    meeting of the Franciscans in 1219. St Dominic is credited with the most
                    friendly greetings offered to his brother saint. “Thou art my companion; thy
                    work and mine is the same.” It is said also that he looked with amazement at the
                    second meeting on the remarkable fascination which the simple-minded Francis
                    exerted over his followers. But it is difficult to know whether these reputed
                        <hi rend="italic">rapprochements</hi> of the great leaders were not an
                    afterthought of their biographers, interested in promoting the idea of the
                    friendliness of the two powers which were destined for a time to divide the
                    influence of the church between them.</p>
                <p>Francis founded an order of poor sisters as well as poor brothers, known by the
                    name of Poor Claras or Clarisses. The origin of the sisterhood is encircled in a
                    halo of romance, such as everywhere surrounds the footsteps of St Francis. Clara
                    was a young lady of the neighbourhood, who, either attracted by the saint’s
                    preaching, or enamoured of his life of poverty, or both, resolved to devote
                    herself to self-sacrifice as he and his companions had done. He is said to have
                    “poured into her ears the sweetness of Christ.” The result was that she forsook
                    her home, fled to the Portiuncula, and, being first a member of the order, was
                    then placed in a female convent. From this questionable beginning sprang the
                    sisterhood nearly as famous in its history as the great brotherhood, and which
                    survives till this day. There was a third order also sprung up in the course of
                    the saint’s lifetime. So marvellous were the consequences of his preaching that
                    whole populations, it is said, wished to devote themselves to consecrated
                    poverty. But many, of course, had no real vocation to such a service, and
                    Francis, visionary as he was, saw that the excesses of his system might prove
                    its ruin. So he arranged to receive persons of this class into an order of what
                    was called Tertiaries or Brethren of Penitence, who retained their social
                    position and their customary employments in the world, while coming under
                    general vows to abstain from worldly dissipations, such as the theatre, and
                    otherwise to be scrupulous in all their conduct. Women were not admitted to this
                    order without the consent of their husbands. Its members did not wear silk or
                    other costly materials, but they had no special costume, and otherwise were at
                    liberty. His conduct in this matter is sufficient to prove that, amidst all the
                    apparently childlike enthusiasm of the saint, he possessed, as indeed cannot be
                    doubted, no inconsiderable vein of shrewd discernment and of practical ability.
                    This order was established in 1221.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile Francis was unceasing in his personal labours. It is not easy to trace
                    the chronology of his age or his adventures; but the same spirit of
                    self-sacrifice, of burning ardour and spiritual industry, is everywhere
                    conspicuous. He made long missionary journeys to Illyria, to Spain, and even to
                    the East, to preach to the Mahometans. He gained access to the sultan, it is
                    said, and proclaimed to him the gospel of poverty. He was for some time in the
                    Holy Land, and everywhere he gained multitudes of disciples. The atmosphere of
                    miracle everywhere accompanied him, and his fame was spread throughout
                    Christendom. Whatever we may think of many events of his life, and impossible as
                    it is now to disentangle the legendary thread of the supernatural from its more
                    credible texture, there are many traits of the saint’s character which are in no
                    sense doubtful, but show with a clear and life-like impress what sort of a man
                    he was. He was passionately fond of all living things, and found his chief
                    happiness in ministering to the needs of his fellowcreatures or the enjoyment of
                    the lower creatures around him. His love for animals of all kinds was one of his
                    most <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n729/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0729-0694"/> remarkable and winning features. Of the birds
                    in the woods, the sheep in the fields, the ass on which he rode, the bees, the
                    hares, the rabbits, he always spoke as his brothers and sisters. When the birds
                    sang he said, “Our sisters, the birds, are pleasing God.” A little rabbit ran to
                    him for protection; it was received into his bosom, as one of his biographers,
                    the famous general of the order Bonaventura, says, “as if it had some hidden
                    sense of the perfection of the father’s heart.” The very wolves, which all men
                    were afraid to encounter, were tamed by him, and came like lambs and crouched at
                    his feet. So at least it is related in one memorable case in the legends of the
                    “Fioretti di San Francesco” (the “Little Flowers of St Francis,”—a collection of
                    marvellous stories about the saint very popular in Italy to this day). There may
                    be much in these stories that exceeds the limits of credibility; the amount of
                    accurate fact lying beneath them can no longer be traced; but noue can hesitate
                    to believe the beautiful depth of love which they reveal in the character of St
                    Francis, and the fascination of personal influence which they show to have been
                    possessed by him.</p>
                <p>Connected with his love of nature and all living things was his poetry—for St
                    Francis was not only saint but poet. The stream of Italian song, so soon to
                    swell into the full volume of Dante (1265-1321), began to flow in the rugged but
                    touching verse of the great preacher of Assisi. In him the troubadour
                    inspiration, dying out in its original seat, was transmuted into a spiritual
                    minstrelsy—hardly poetry, so imperfect is its form, but a lyrical cry, as Ozanam
                    says (in his volume <hi rend="italic">Les poètes franciscains,</hi> 1852), the
                    first broken utterance of a new voice which was soon to fill the world. The most
                    characteristic of his songs is a <hi rend="italic">Cantico</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >delle</hi><hi rend="italic">Creature</hi> (Song cf the Creation), which has
                    been translated in Mrs Oliphant’s interesting life of the saint.</p>
                <p>Marvellous as is the life of St Francis, the marvel that followed his death is
                    more astonishing than any that marked his earthly career. It is said that when
                    his naked body was visible after death, there was found upon it legibly
                    impressed the marks of our Lord’s passion; and the sacred story is that one day
                    as he prayed in the solitude of Mount Averno, near the sources of the Tiber and
                    the Arno, there appeared to him the vision as of a seraph with the arms extended
                    and the feet as if fixed to a cross; and as he thought in his heart what the
                    vision might mean, there were revealed on his hands and feet the signs of nails
                    as in the Crucified One. This is well known as the famous miracle of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Stigmata</hi> or wounds of our Lord. There seems to be no
                    doubt that some such marks were found on the dead body of the saint, whatever
                    explanation the phenomena may admit of. That there was anything really
                    supernatural in the phenomena will be so readily discredited by the modern
                    reader that it is unnecessary we should attempt any elaborate solution of the
                    marvel. An interesting analysis of all the facts, and such historical
                    explanation as they seem to admit of, will be found in Hase’s life of the saint,
                    and an article, founded upon the analysis there given, in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Good</hi><hi rend="italic">JΓords</hi><hi rend="italic">for</hi> 1867, p.
                    38 (“History of a Miracle”). St Francis, worn out by his many labours and
                    consuming zeal, died on 4th October 1226.</p>
                <p>“Of all saints,” says Milman <hi rend="italic">{Hist, of Latin Christ.,</hi> vol.
                    iv. 268), “St Francis was the most blameless and gentle. He was emphatically the
                    saint of the people,—of a poetic people like the Italians.” And to this day the
                    name, the life, and the longsuffering of the popular saint live in the hearts of
                    the poorer and devout Italians.</p>
                <p>Of what may be called more or less original biographies of the saint there are in
                    the well known <hi rend="italic">Acta Sanctorum</hi> no fewer than three :—(1)
                    The <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> by Thomas of Celano (whose name is also
                    associated with the composition of the famous <hi rend="italic">Dies Tree),</hi>
                    written only three years after the saint’s death; (2) the <hi rend="italic">Life
                        of the</hi><hi rend="italic">Tres Socii,</hi> three companions of the saint
                    written in 1247; and, lastly, (3) the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> by
                    Bonaventura, Platonic schoolman and general of the order in 1263. The works of
                    the saint have been collected and edited by Job. de la Haye, <hi rend="italic"
                        >S. Francisci Opera,</hi> 1739 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> There is an
                    elaborate biography by Malan, <hi rend="italic">Hist, de S. François
                        d'Assisi,</hi> 1841; and notices are also to be found in Helyot’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Hist,</hi><hi rend="italic">des Ordres Religieux,</hi> t.
                    vii., and Butler’s <hi rend="italic">Lives of the Saints.</hi> There are two
                    recent lives, both of special interest, by the German divine, Hase, and by Mrs
                    Oliphant in Macmillan’s Sunday Library series. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Franciscans.</hi> (j. <hi rend="smallcaps">t.)</hi> J</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
