<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0157-0148-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FIESOLE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 148</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1010918">Martyrs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:984609">Judgments</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:984572">Judgment</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1103658">Saints</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw1m">Martyrs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f45m">Judgments</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4057cr7r">Convents</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n157/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FIESOLE</label> (1387-1455). Il Beato Fra Giovanni Angelico
                    da Fiesole is the name given to a far-famed painter-friar of the Florentine
                    state in the 15th century, the protagonist, beyond all other men, of pietistic
                    painting. He is often, but not accurately, termed simply “Fiesole,” which is
                    merely the name of the town, noticed above, where he first took the vows; more
                    often, Fra Angelico. If we turn his compound designation into English, it runs
                    thus—“the Beatified Friar John the Angelic of Fiesole.” In his lifetime he was
                    known no doubt simply as Fra Giovanni, or Friar John; “the Angelic” is a
                    laudatory term which got assigned to him at an early date,—we find it in use
                    within thirty years after his death; and, at some period which is not defined in
                    our authorities, he was beatified by due ecclesiastical process. His surname was
                    Guido: his original Christian name—Giovanni being only his name in religion— is
                    not known. He was born at Vicchio, in the Tuscan province of Mugello, of unknown
                    but seemingly well-to-do parentage, in 1387 (not 1390, as sometimes stated); in
                    1407 he became a novice in the convent of S. Domenico at Fiesole, and in 1408 he
                    took the vows and entered the Dominican order. Whether he had previously been a
                    painter by profession is not'certain, but may be pronounced probable. The
                    painter named Lorenzo Monaco may have contributed to his art-training, and the
                    influence of the Sienese school is discernible in his work. According to Vasari,
                    the first paintings of this artist were in the Certosa of Florence; none such
                    exist there now. His earliest extant performances, in considerable number,
                    marked to some extent by the influence of Masolino, are at Cortona, whither he
                    was sent during his noviciate, and here apparently he spent all the opening
                    years of his monastic life. His first works executed in fresco were probably
                    those, now destroyed, which he painted in the convent of S. Domenico in this
                    city; as a fresco-painter, he may have worked under, or as a follower of,
                    Gherardo Stamina. From 1418 to 1436 he was back at Fiesole; in 1436 he was
                    transferred to the Dominican convent of S. Marco in Florence, and in 1438
                    undertook to paint the altarpiece for the choir, followed by many other works;
                    he may have studied about this time the renowned frescoes in the Brancacci
                    chapel in the Florentine church of the Carmine, and also the paiutings of
                    Orcagna. In or about 1445 he was <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n158/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0158-0149"/> invited by tne pope to Rome. The pope who reigned
                    from 1431 to 1447 wasEugenius IV., and he it was who in 1445 appointed another
                    Dominican friar, a colleague of Angelico, to be archbishop of Florence. If the
                    story (fir3t told by Vasari) is true—that this appointment was made at the
                    suggestion of Angelico only after the archbishopric had been offered to himself,
                    and by him declined on the ground of his inaptitude for so elevated and
                    responsible a station— Eugenius, and not (as stated by Vasari) his successor
                    Nicholas V., must have been the pope who sent the invitation and made the offer
                    to Fra Giovanni, for Nicholas only succeeded in 1447. The whole statement lacks
                    authentication, though in itself credible enough. Certain it is that Angelico
                    was staying in Rome in the first half of 1447; and he painted in the Vatican the
                    Cappella del Sacramento, which was afterwards demolished by Paul III. In June
                    1447 he proceeded to Orvieto, to paint in the Cappella Nuova of the cathedral,
                    with the co-operation of his pupil Benozzo Gozzoli. He afterwards returned to
                    Rome to paint the chapel of Nicholas V. In this capital he died in 1455, and he
                    lies buried in the church of the Minerva.</p>
                <p>According to all the accounts which have reached us, few men to whom the
                    distinction of beatification has been conferred could have deserved it more
                    nobly than Fra Giovanni. He led a holy and self-denying life, shunning all
                    advancement, and was a brother to the poor; no man ever saw him angered. He
                    painted with unceasing diligence, treating none but sacred subjects: he never
                    retouched or altered his work, probably with a religious feeling that, such as
                    divine providence allowed the thing to come, such it should remain. He was wont
                    to say that he who illustrates the acts of Christ should be with Christ. It is
                    averred that he never handled a brush without fervent prayer, and he wept when
                    he painted a Crucifixion. The Last Judgment and the Annunciation were two of the
                    subjects he most frequently treated.</p>
                <p>Bearing in mind the details already given as to the dates of Fra Giovanni’s
                    sojournings in various localities, the reader will be able to trace
                    approximately the sequence of the works which we now proceed to name as among
                    his most important productions. In Florence, in the convent of S. Marco (now
                    converted into a national museum), a series of frescoes, beginning towards 1443.
                    In the first cloister is the Crucifixion, with St Dominick kneeling; and the
                    same treatment recurs on a wall near the dormitory; in the chapterhouse is a
                    third Crucifixion, with the Virgin swooning, a composition of twenty life-sized
                    figures—the red background, which has a strange and harsh effect, is the
                    misdoing of some restorer; an Annunciation, the figures of about three-fourths
                    of life-size, in a dormitory; in the adjoining passage, the Virgin Enthroned,
                    with four saints; on the wall of a cell, the Coronation of the Virgin, λvith
                    Saints Paul, Thomas Aquinas, Benedict, Dominick, Francis, and Peter Martyr; two
                    Dominicans welcoming Jesus, habited as a pilgrim; an Adoration of the Magi; the
                    Marys at the Sepulchre. All these works are later than the altarpiece which
                    Angelico painted (as before mentioned) for the choir connected with this
                    convent, and which is now in the academy of Florence; it represents the Virgin
                    with Saints Cosmas and Damian (the patrons of the Medici family), Dominick,
                    Peter, Francis, Mark, John Evangelist, and Stephen: the pediment illustrated the
                    lives of Cosmas and Damian, but it has long been severed from the main subject.
                    In the Uffizi gallery, an altarpiece, the Virgin (life-sized) enthroned, with
                    the Infant and twelve angels. In S. Domenico, Fiesole, a few frescoes, less fine
                    than those in St Marco; also an altarpiece in tempera of the Virgin and Child
                    between Saints Peter, Thomas Aquinas, Dominick, and Peter Martyr, now much
                    destroyed. The subject which originally formed the predella of this picture has,
                    since 1860, been in the London National Gallery, and worthily represents there
                    the hand of the saintly painter. The subject 13 a Glory, Christ with the banner
                    of the Resurrection, and a multitude of saints, including, at the extremities,
                    the saints or beati of the Dominican order; here are no fewer than 266 figures,
                    or portions of figures, many of them having names inscribed. This predella was
                    highly lauded by Vasari; still more highly another picture which used to form an
                    altarpiece in Fiesole, and which now obtains world wide celebrity in the
                    Louvre—the Coronation of the Virgin, with eight predella subjects of the
                    miracles of St Dominick. For the church of S. Trinita, Florence, Angelico
                    executed a Deposition from the Cross, and for the church of the Angeli a Last
                    Judgment, both now in the Florentine academy; for S. Maria Novella, a Coronation
                    of the Virgin, with a predella in three sections, now in the Uffizi,—this again
                    is one of his masterpieces. In Orvieto cathedral he painted three triangular
                    divisions of the ceiling, portraying respectively Christ in a glory of angels,
                    sixteen saints and prophets, and the virgin and apostles: all these are now much
                    repainted and damaged. In Rome, in the chapel of Nicholas V., the acts of Saints
                    Stephen and Lawrence; also various figures of saints, and on the ceiling the
                    four evangelists. These works of the painter’s advanced age, which have suffered
                    somewhat from restorations, show vigour superior to that of his youth, along
                    with a more adequate treatment of the architectural perspectives. Naturally,
                    there are a number of works currently attributed to Angelico, but not really
                    his; for instance, a St Thomas with the Madonna’s girdle, in the Lateran museum,
                    and a Virgin enthroned in the church of S. Girolamo, Fiesole. It has often been
                    said that he commenced and frequently practised as an illuminator; this Î3
                    dubious, and a presumption arises that illuminations executed by Giovanni’s
                    brother Benedetto, also a Dominican, who died in 1448, have been ascribed to the
                    more famous artist. Benedetto may perhaps have assisted Giovanni in the frescoes
                    at S. Marco, but nothing of the kind is distinctly traceable. A folio series of
                    engravings from these paintings was published in Florence in 1852. Along with
                    Gozzoli already mentioned, Zanobi Strozzi and Gentile da Fabriano are named as
                    pupils of the Beato.</p>
                <p>We have spoken of Angelico’s art as “pietistic”; this is in fact its predominant
                    character. His visages have an air of rapt suavity, devotional fervency, and
                    beaming esoteric consciousness, which is intensely attractive to some minds, and
                    realizes beyond rivalry a particular ideal —that of ecclesiastical saintliness,
                    and detachment from secular fret and turmoil. It should not be denied that ho
                    did not always escape the pitfalls of such a method of treatment, the faces
                    becoming sleek and prim, with a smirk of sexless religiosity which hardly eludes
                    the artificial or even the hypocritical; on other minds, therefore, and these
                    some of the most masculine and resolute, he produces little genuine impression.
                    After allowing for this, Angelico should nevertheless be accepted beyond cavil
                    as an exalted typical painter according to his own range of conceptions,
                    consonant with his monastic calling, unsullied purity of life, and exceeding
                    devoutness. Exquisite as he is in his special mode of execution, he undoubtedly
                    falls far short, not only of his great naturalist contemporaries such as
                    Masaccio and Lippo Lippi, but even of so distant a precursor as Giotto, in all
                    that pertains to bold or life-like invention of a subject, or the realization of
                    ordinary appearances, expressions, and actions—the facts of nature, as
                    distinguished from the aspirations or contemplations of the spirit. Technically
                    speaking, he had much finish and harmony of composition and colour, without
                    corresponding mastery of light and shade, and his knowledge of the human frame
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n159/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0159-0150"/> was restricted. The brilliancy and fair light
                    scale of his tints is constantly remarkable, combined with a free use of
                    gilding; this conduces materially to that celestial character which so
                    pre-eminently distinguishes his pictured visions of the divine persons, the
                    hierarchy of heavçn, and the glory of the redeemed. (w. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >μ.</hi> Ji.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
