<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0507-0476-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FOUCHÉ, Joseph</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 476</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f1p">Jacobins</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:899352">Dues</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n507/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FOUCHÉ, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi></label> (1763-1820),
                    duke of Otranto, minister of police under Napoleon I., was born in a small
                    village near Nantes, 26th May 1763. He was the son of a ship captain, and at the
                    age of nine years began the study of mathematics at the college of his native
                    place, with the view of entering the merchant marine. That such a calling would
                    have proved congenial to him is not very probable, and at any rate it presented
                    so little attraction to his youthful fancy that he induced his father to consent
                    to the abandonment of this intention, and to permit him to continue his studies
                    at Paris under the superintendence of the principal of the oratory. He
                    afterwards taught successively iu the colleges of Juilly, Arras, and Vendome;
                    and at the time of the Revolution he was <hi rend="italic">préfet</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des études</hi> at Nantes. He now renounced his connexion with the
                    ecclesiastical profession, and in 1792 succeeded in being chosen one of the
                    national deputies for Loire-Inférieure. In this capacity he made a violent
                    speech in support of the execution of Louis XVI., without respite and without
                    appeal to the people, taunting those who hesitated to adopt such an extreme
                    measure with “trembling before the shade of a king.” In the midst of the
                    political chaos he determined to “ride on the whirlwind and direct the storm :”
                    though he had little or no interest in moral speculation, he became an ardent
                    asserter of atheism; and, though devoid of all political predilections, and
                    actuated in his political purposes simply by a cool calculation of advantages
                    that was seldom if ever surprised or ruffled even by the most critical
                    contingencies, he soon manifested a zeal for republicanism which exceeded that
                    of the wildest enthusiasts of that exceptional time. Having at the end of 1793
                    been commissioned to put in operation the law <hi rend="italic">des
                    suspects</hi> in the department of Nièvre, then one of the centres of the
                    royalist sympathizers, he not only succeeded in completely crushing all
                    insurrectionary symptoms, but initiated the movement for the spoliation of the
                    churches, by which the treasury was supplied with money for the campaign of
                    1794; and he also further inaugurated the age of reason by suppressing the
                    priests and causing to be inscribed on the doors of the cemeteries a sentence
                    afterwards generally adopted for this purpose— <hi rend="italic">La mort est un
                    sommeil éternel.</hi> In November of the same year he was appointed, along with
                    Collot d’Herbois, to execute the decree of the convention against the royalist
                    city of Lyons; and here he vied with his colleague in a mania for destruction
                    and bloodshed, inditing bombastic regrets that the mine and the guillotine did
                    their work too slowly to accord with the impatience of the republic, or to
                    express the omnipotence of the people. This devoted enthusiasm for freedom led
                    to his being elected president of the Jacobin Club, 4th June 1794, soon after
                    his return to Paris. He now so far allowed his audacity to overcome his
                    discretion as to make some derisive allusions to the part played in the fête de
                    1’Être Supreme by Robespierre, who on that account denounced him as an impostor
                    and peculator, and procured his expulsion from the society. Fouché had erred,
                    however, only by a too quick anticipation of public opinion, for the execution
                    of Robespierre followed on the 25th July. The star of Fouché was thus for a
                    short time again in the ascendant; but having awakened distrust by some new
                    intrigues, he was denounced as a terrorist, expelled the convention 9th August
                    1795, and placed under arrest. He obtained his freedom by the amnesty of the
                    26th October following; and having obtained the confidence of the socialist
                    Babeuf, and revealed his conspiracy to Barras, then president of the directory,
                    he was rewarded by an interest in the contracts of the army, and by being
                    appointed in 1798 ambassador to the Cisalpine republic. Soon afterwards his
                    intrigues against the directory of Milan led to his recall, but when the party
                    of Barras again came into power he was appointed to the Hague. There he remained
                    only a few months, returning to Paris to enter upon his famous career as
                    minister of police. In this capacity he for some years exercised an influence on
                    the internal affairs of France perhaps greater than that of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n508/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0508-0477"/> any one else; and it was chiefly owing to his
                    well-chosen measures of repression, his ready and dexterous use of expedients,
                    his almost omniscient faculty of detection, and his just appreciation of
                    political contingencies, that at this critical period of France’s history the
                    reign of anarchy was averted. Recognizing the necessity of a new political
                    departure, he suppressed the Jacobin clubs and newspapers, and was concerned in
                    instigating the beginning of a reaction towards monarchical principles. Though
                    he failed to effect an understanding between Barras and Napoleon, he resolved
                    rather to desert his patron than to share his overthrow, and exerted all his
                    powers of management and finesse to bring the <hi rend="italic">coup F état</hi>
                    of the 18th Brumaire to a successful termination. Besides taking an important
                    though carefully guarded share in the preliminary negotiations, he suspended in
                    the name of the directory the twelve municipalities of Paris, tranquillized the
                    citizens by posting on the walls reassuring intimations, and took the precaution
                    of shutting the gates of Paris to prevent the fugitive deputies from reentering
                    the city.</p>
                <p>Under the consulate, Fouché, notwithstanding the opposition of Sieyès, was
                    continued minister of police, partly because he was to be dreaded as an
                    opponent, and partly because no one else could bear comparison with him in
                    fitness for the office. Its duties he discharged, not only with unequalled tact
                    and discretion, but with a justice and mildness rendered possible only by his
                    perfect confidence in his superior cunning. At the same time there was
                    necessarily attached to it a very great irresponsible power, and far from
                    neglecting to make undue use of this he took care to lend an additional
                    appearance of necessity and value to his services by a continual supply of
                    political fomentations. If his audacity and assumption aroused the jealousy of
                    Napoleon, his cool impenetrability no less disconcerted him, and matters were
                    not improved by the ludicrous blunders of the secret police which Napoleon had
                    the folly to employ, in order both to test his minister’s fidelity and render
                    him less indispensable. Actuated therefore most probably by a regard to his own
                    position, Fouché endeavoured to prevent a too rapid abandonment of the lines of
                    republicanism, and deprecated as imprudent the means that were being used
                    towards the establishment of a monarchical government. Such advices doubtless
                    increased Napoleon’s irritation and distrust, and on becoming consul for life in
                    1802 he determined to rid himself of the galling fetters of his minister’s
                    ascendency. He did this, however, with great caution and respect; and while he
                    suppressed the office as no longer necessary, he conferred on Fouché the dignity
                    of a senator, and presented him with half the police reserve funds. The
                    association of the functions of the old office with those of the ministry of
                    justice did not prove a happy arrangement; and Fouché by maintaining for his own
                    purposes the same system of espionage as formerly, was able, by revealing the
                    Georges conspiracy to reassert his influence in the affairs of state. Divining
                    Napoleon’s secret wishes and intentions, he now took every opportunity to press
                    upon him the advisability of immediately assuming the monarchical crown, and
                    applied himself to the furtherance of this object with an ostentatious zeal that
                    was doubtless meant to suggest that he was almost 'the sole agent in determining
                    events towards that end. And indeed he might, after Napoleon, justly claim the
                    chief merit of that great political change, for at any rate the smoothness with
                    which it was accomplished was greatly due to Fouché’s skilful management.</p>
                <p>After Napoleon’s coronation Fouché was therefore reinstalled in his old office,
                    4th July 1804, uniting with its functions those of the ministry of the interior.
                    In this position he took a very prominent part in the rule of France under
                    Napoleon, and to some extent rivalled his master in influence; for if the empire
                    gained glory by Napoleon’s achievements, it owed its internal harmony to Fouché,
                    who had for a time the entire direction of its administration. On the revival of
                    the titles of nobility he was created duke of Otranto, and it appeared as if his
                    tenure of office were indissolubly connected with the empire’s stability. The
                    bond between him and the emperor was, however, solely one of interest, and the
                    very antipodes of one of affection and mutual esteem. His imperturbable
                    self-control, his connexion with the old republicans, the obscurity and mystery
                    in which he shrouded his intentions, and his power of secret strategy gained him
                    almost a kind of mastery over the arbitrary spirit of Napoleon, but it was a
                    mastery borne both with impatience and with resentment. Apart from this, his
                    cold and vulgar ambition and his cynical contempt for all unsubstantial glory
                    irritated the sensitive egoism of Napoleon, whose magnificent projects he often
                    pierced with shafts of truth that were too painfully effective, and whom he
                    somewhat imprudently tormented with warnings as to the necessity of limiting his
                    designs of conquest. When matters were in this critical condition, they were
                    brought to a crisis by a proclamation of Fouché calling on France—then
                    threatened by the English invasion—to prove that Napoleon’s presence was not
                    necessary to scatter his enemies. The proclamation was effectual; but on
                    Napoleon’s return to Paris Fouché was deprived of the ministry of the interior.
                    Shortly afterwards he sent an agent to England to carry on negotiations with the
                    English Government, in ignorance that Napoleon had sent another for the same
                    purpose; and the English minister, suspecting a trick, declined all further
                    negotiations. This mischance completed Fouché’s disgrace; he ceased to be
                    minister of police, 3d June 1810; and to secure his absence from France, he was
                    appointed governor of Rome. While delaying his departure he was requested to
                    deliver up the autograph letters of Napoleon and other Government documents in
                    his possession; and lιis answer that they were all destroyed was deemed so
                    little satisfactory that he found it expedient to go into voluntary exile. On
                    delivering up the papers the destruction of which he had asserted, he was
                    afterwards permitted to return to his estate at PontCarré; but in 1813 Napoleon
                    judged it prudent to appoint him governor of Illyria, after which he was sent to
                    Rome to watch the movements of Murat. Being recalled to France some time before
                    the entrance of the allies into Paris, he in anticipation of events came to an
                    understanding with Talleyrand, and becoming one of the principal members of the
                    provisional Government, proposed that a deputation should be sent to the Comte
                    d’Artois, brother of Louis XVIII. He afterwards wrote letters to the king
                    recommending the adoption of certain measures fitted to reconcile the opponents
                    of the Bourbon dynasty, and on the 25th April addressed a letter to Napoleon at
                    Elba, advising him, instead of making an effort to remount the throne of France,
                    to seek a sphere for his ambition in America, “where his genius would be admired
                    without being feared.” On the news of Napoleon’s escape from Elba the Government
                    of Louis offered Fouché the portfolio of police, but he declined it on the
                    ground that the Government could no longer hold its position. Next day he was
                    ordered to be arrested, but deluding by a clever stratagem the officers sent for
                    that purpose, he escaped to the hôtel of Hortense Beauharnais, and received on
                    the following day his old office from the hands of Napoleon. He now determined
                    merely to prepare for Napoleon’s downfall, which he saw to be imminent; and
                    besides securing the confidence of both patriots and royalists, he opened a
                    communication with the allies. After the battle of Waterloo it was therefore to
                    him that all eyes turned for guidance; and, becoming the bead of the provisional
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n509/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0509-0478"/> Government, he succeeded in producing the
                    impression that his skilful diplomacy had saved Paris from extreme humiliation.
                    Having played such an important part in this political crisis, his name could
                    not be omitted from the list of the new Government, and he received his old
                    office from the king, of whose brother’s death he had been one of the principal
                    instigators. His dexterity, however, had now set itself a task for which it was
                    incompetent; and gradually finding his position untenable, he resigned office 19
                    th September 1815. As a kind of solatium he was appointed ambassador to Dresden;
                    but on the passing of the law of banishment against those who had voted for the
                    death of Louis XVI., he retired to Prague. He became a naturalized Austrian
                    subject in 1818, and died at Trieste, 25th December 1820., in possession of
                    enormous wealth.</p>
                <p>Fouché, notwithstanding his equivocal expression of countenance and his known
                    untrustworthiness, had a peculiar faculty of captivating the eminent politicians
                    with whom he came into contact. This was due at once to his instinctive
                    divination of their weak point, and to his wonderful knowledge of the varying
                    conditions of the political barometer. Though somewhat boastful, his
                    conversation was remarkably agreeable and interesting, and was frequently
                    lighted up by terse and sarcastic witticisms which would have done credit to
                    Talleyrand. His temperament was too cold to enable him to achieve success as an
                    orator, but his writings, though sometimes bombastic, must be allowed the merit
                    of cleverness, and are often characterized by a graphic felicity. His
                    unparalleled political career is to be accounted for not perhaps so much by his
                    peculiar intellectual abilities as by the apparent fact that he was, as Μ.
                    Thiers has expressed it, completely “indifferent to good and evil ”—that he was
                    influenced neither by the impulses of passion nor by the dictates of conscience.
                    His private life was virtuous compared with that of many of his contemporaries,
                    and his political life—apart from his connexion with the death of Louis XVI.,
                    and the atrocities of Nantes and Lyons—was not only unstained by heinous crime,
                    but to an unenlightened spectator seemed wholly devoted to the public interest.
                    Inhabiting a region beyond the influence of party bias, he appeared when a
                    political crisis was at hand almost in the character of the guardian angel of
                    France, cherishing no remembranceof past ingratitude, but benevolently
                    proffering for her acceptance the only aid that could save her from disaster. He
                    was, if not the leading actor, at least the principal wire-puller and prompter
                    in many of the great events of his time; but his only important legacy to
                    posterity is the grand spy-system which he brought almost to perfection, and
                    which has since exercised such a baneful influence on European politics. Next to
                    his love of intrigue, his main motive in all his purposes was something
                    resembling avarice; but in all probability he did not love even money, and
                    sought to lay hold of it chiefly as the one stable rock amid the billows and
                    quicksands of political life. Though his purposes were not held in check by any
                    moral principle, yet so strong was his self-control, and so calm his estimate of
                    possibilities, that he never committed himself irrevocably to a conspiracy that
                    was not successful. The atrocities, however, which inaugurated his political
                    career, and at the close of it his acceptance of office under Louis XVΠI., were,
                    though widely separated in time, so incompatible with each other that he at last
                    completely lost the confidence of all parties in the state, and his past career
                    was placed in a light so strongly sinister as to render its character
                    unmistakable. Many politicians of his own time had been guilty of equally
                    heinous crimes; but few of any age have so consistently and uninterruptedly
                    sacrificed every political and moral consideration, including that of
                    self-respect, to a temporary success.</p>
                <p>Fouché is the author of <hi rend="italic">PJflcxions</hi><hi rend="italic">sur le
                    jugement de Louis</hi><hi rend="italic">Capet,</hi> 1793; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Réflexions sur Téducation publique,</hi> 1793; <hi rend="italic">Rapport et
                    projet de loi relatifs aux collèges,</hi> 1793; <hi rend="italic">Rapport sur la
                    situation de Commune-Affranchie,</hi> 1794; <hi rend="italic">Lettre aux
                    préfets,</hi><hi rend="italic">concernant</hi><hi rend="italic">les
                    prêtres,</hi> &lt;t∙c., 1801; two <hi rend="italic">Rapports au Roi</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Notes aux ministres étrangers,</hi> 1815, where he ably discusses
                    the condition of France at the time; and <hi rend="italic">Lettre au duc de
                    Wellington,</hi> 1817. He is said to have been the author of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Précis de la</hi><hi rend="italic">vie</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >publique</hi><hi rend="italic">du due</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">Otrantc,</hi> published at
                    London and Leipsic in 1816. The <hi rend="italic">Mémoires de Fouché,</hi>
                    Paris, 1824, were declared by his family to be a forgery, but although their
                    naïveté is often too pronounced to be compatible with their authenticity, they
                    are evidently founded on original sources of information. See also <hi
                    rend="italic">Vie</hi><hi rend="italic">de Fouché,</hi> 1821; Bourrienne, <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of Napoleon</hi>; Desmarest, <hi rend="italic">Témoignages
                    historiques, ou quinze Ans de haute police sous Napoléon,</hi> 1833; Martel, <hi
                    rend="italic">Étude sur Fauché et sur le communisme dans le pratique en</hi>
                    1793, 1873, which contains a number of documents never before published; and an
                    interesting account of an interview with Fouché by Earl Stanhope, in Lord
                    Brougham’s collected works, vol. v. (T. F. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
