<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0119-0110-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FERRIER, Susan Edmonston</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 110</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1115813">Shepherds</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:991740">Landlords</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:888134">Daughters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pt4b">Novels</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dn7s">Witnesses</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n119/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FERRIER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Susan Edmonston</hi></label>
                    (1782-1854), Scottish novelist, born in Edinburgh in 1782, was the aunt of the
                    subject of last notice. Her father was James Ferrier, for some years factor to
                    the duke of Argyll, and at one time one of the clerks of the court of session
                    with Sir Walter Scott. Her mother was a Miss Coutts, the beautiful daughter of a
                    Forfarshire farmer. Miss Ferrier’s first novel, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Marriage,</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n120/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0120-0111"/> was begun in concert with a friend, Miss
                    Clavering, grand-daughter of the duke of Argyll; but this lady soon relinquished
                    her share in the work, and <hi rend="italic">Marriage,</hi> completed by Miss
                    Ferrier alone, appeared in 1818, when its authoress was between five and six and
                    thirty. It was followed in 1824 by <hi rend="italic">The Inheritance,</hi> a
                    better constructed and more mature work; and the last and perhaps best of her
                    novels, <hi rend="italic">Destiny,</hi> dedicated to Sir Walter Scott (who
                    himself undertook to strike the bargain with the publisher Cadell), appeared in
                    1831. All these novels were published anonymously; but, with their clever
                    portraiture of contemporary Scottish life and manners, and even recognizable
                    caricatures of some social celebrities of the day, they could not fail to become
                    popular north of the Tweed, and many were the conjectures as to their
                    authorship, which was by some attributed to Scott himself. Thus, in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Nodes Λmbrοsiance</hi> (November 1826), the Shepherd mentions <hi
                    rend="italic">The Inheritance,</hi> and adds, “which I aye thought was written
                    by Sir Walter, as weel’s <hi rend="italic">Marriage,</hi> till it spunked out
                    that it was written by a leddy.” Scott himself gave Miss Ferrier a very high
                    place indeed among the novelists of the day. In his diary (March 27, 1826),
                    criticizing a new work which he had been reading, he says, “The women do this
                    better. Edgeworth, Ferrier, Austen, have all given portraits of real society far
                    superior to anything man, vain man, has produced of the like nature.” Another
                    friendly recognition of Miss Ferrier is to be found at the conclusion of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Tales of my Landlord,</hi> where Scott calls her his
                    “sistershadow,” the still anonymous author of “the very lively work entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Marriage.''</hi></p>
                <p>Lively, indeed, all Miss Ferrier’s works are,—written in a clear, brisk English,
                    and with an inexhaustible fund of humour. It is true her books portray the
                    eccentricities, the follies, and foibles of the society in which she lived,
                    caricaturing with terrible exactness its hypocrisy, boastfulness, greed,
                    affectation, and undue subservience to public opinion. Yet Miss Ferrier wrote
                    less to reform than to amuse. With an honest aversion to these things herself,
                    she wished, not to lecture her readers, but to laugh with them. In this she is
                    less like Miss Edgeworth than Miss Austen. Miss Edgeworth was more of a
                    moralist; her wit is not so involuntary, her caricatures not always so
                    good-natured. But Miss Austen and Miss Ferrier were genuine humorists, and with
                    Miss Ferrier especially a keen sense of the ludicrous was always dominant. She
                    could be serious, she could be pathetic, she could even touch some of the finest
                    chords in human nature; but she never interfered with the depths of human
                    wickedness and misery. She liked best to laugh; she turned naturally to the
                    humorous, and her humorous characters are always her best. It was no doubt
                    because she felt this that in the last year of her life she regretted not having
                    devoted her talents mere exclusively to the service of religion, not taking into
                    account then how much good she had involuntarily done, and how much harmless
                    pleasure she had distributed about her; for, if she was not a moralist, neither
                    was she a cynic; and her wit, even where it is most caustic, is never
                    uncharitable.</p>
                <p>Miss Ferrier lived till 1854, more than twenty years after the publication of her
                    last work. The most pleasant picture that we have of her is in Lockhart’s
                    description of her visit to Scott in May 1831. She was asked there to help to
                    amuse the dying master of Abbotsford, who, when he was not writing <hi
                    rend="italic">Count Robert of Paris,</hi> would talk as brilliantly as ever.
                    Only sometimes, before he had reached the point in a narrative, “it would seem
                    as if some internal spring had given way.” He would pause, and gaze blankly and
                    anxiously round him. “I noticed,” says Lockhart, “the delicacy of Miss Ferrier
                    on such occasions. Her sight was bad, and she took care not to use her glasses
                    when he was speaking; and she affected to be also troubled with deafness, and
                    would say, ‘ Well, I am getting as dull as a post; I have not heard a word since
                    you said so-andso,’—being sure to mention a circumstance behind that at which he
                    had really halted. He then took up the thread with his habitual smile of
                    courtesy—as if forgetting his case entirely in the consideration of the lady’s
                    infirmity.”</p>
                <p>Miss Ferrier died, November 5, 1854, at her house No. 38 Albany Street,
                    Edinburgh. She left among her papers a short unpublished article, entitled
                    “Recollections of Visits to Ashestiel and Abbotsford.” This is her own very
                    interesting account of her long friendship with Sir Walter Scott, from the date
                    of her first visit to him and Lady Scott at Ashestiel, where she went with her
                    father in the autumn of 1811, to her last sad visit to Abbotsford in 1831. It
                    contains some impromptu verses written by Scott in her album at Ashestiel.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
