<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0846-0811-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FUGGER (9th edition, volume 9, page 811)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1139824">Swabians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1172973">Wealth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100524">Roses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173194">Weavers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:999105">Linen</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z77x">Swabian</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7712k">Wealth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw4857c">Weavers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n846/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FUGGER</label>, the name of a Swabian family which, by
                    remarkable energy in industry and commerce, acquired enormous wealth, and rose
                    to high rank in the state. The founder of the family was John Fugger, a
                    respectable master-weaver at Graben, near Augsburg. His eldest son, John,
                    associated trade in linen with weaving in Augsburg, of which he became a citizen
                    by marriage in 1370. Here he rose to an honourable position, being one of the
                    twelve councillors of the guild of weavers, and an assessor of the Fehmgericht,
                    the much dreaded secret tribunal of Westphalia. He died in 1409, leaving a
                    fortune of 3000 florins. His eldest son, by a second marriage, Andrew, was known
                    as “the rich Fugger,” and became the founder of a noble line, Fugger vom Reh,
                    which died out in 1583. Jacob Fugger, the second son of John, was the first of
                    the family who possessed a house in Augsburg, where he greatly extended the
                    business he inherited, and was made head of the guild of weavers. After his
                    death in 1469, his three sons, Ulrich, George, and Jacob, who were men of
                    unusual resource and industry, added immensely to the riches he had left them.
                    Ulrich devoted himself to trade, and his operations were so varied that even the
                    works of Albert Dürer reached Italy by his means. Jacob worked the mines of
                    Tyrol, and his profits were vast enough to enable him, without difficulty, to
                    lend the archduke of Austria 150,000 florins, and to build (in Tyrol) the
                    splendid castle of Fug-gerau. The three brothers married ladies of noble
                    families, and were themselves raised to noble rank by the emperor Maximilian,
                    who, being always in need of money, was delighted to honour subjects whose power
                    of aiding him was so extensive. In return for 70,000 gulden he mortgaged to them
                    the county of Kirchberg and the lordship of Weissen-horn; and afterwards, in
                    carrying on war with Venice, he received from them, at the request of Pope
                    Julius II., a subsidy of 170,000 ducats. An evidence of the generous use to
                    which they put their wealth still survives in the Fuggerei at Augsburg,—a
                    collection of more than 100 small houses built by the brothers and let by them
                    at low rents to poor tenants. Jacob and the two sons of Ulrich died without
                    heirs, so that the possessions of the family descended to the sons of George. Of
                    these the eldest, Marcus, became a priest, and died in 1511. His two brothers,
                    Raimund and Antonius, then represented the house, and their names were soon well
                    known far beyond the limits of Germany, for they had commerical relations with
                    nearly every part of the civilized world. They were vehement opponents of the
                    Reformation, and freely spent money in support of the church. During the famous
                    diet of Augsburg in 1530, Charles V. enjoyed the splendid hospitality of
                    Antonius in his house in the Weinmarkt; and there is a story that the merchant
                    astonished the emperor by lighting a fire of cinnamon with an imperial bond for
                    money due to him. According to another anecdote, Charles remarked at a later
                    time, when the treasury of the king of France was being shown to him, “There is
                    a linen-weaver in Augsburg who could pay all that out of his own purse.” Whether
                    these things are true or not, the emperor was certainly impressed by the
                    extraordinary resources of the two citizens. He not only made over to them the
                    mortgaged properties of Kirchberg and ΛVeissenhorn, but created them <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n847/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0847-0812"/> counts and invested them with princely
                    privileges. In return for the help they gave him in his expedition against the
                    pirates of Algiers in 1535, he conferred on them the right of issuing a gold and
                    silver coinage of their own; and the right was repeatedly exercised. Their
                    princely rank did not prevent them from continuing their mercantile career, and
                    when Antonius died in 1560 he left six million gold crowns, besides a vast
                    amount of property of various kinds in Europe, Asia, and America. He and his
                    brother Raimund (who died in 1535) were the founders of two great lines which
                    are still continued. The privileges conferred on the family by Charles V. were
                    confirmed and increased by Ferdinand II.; and since that time, although no
                    member either of the Raimund or the Antonius line has risen to the highest
                    distinction in any department, many of them have done honourable service to the
                    state, and have been famous for their liberality. The fortunes of the family are
                    often cited in evidence of the prosperity of Germany before the country was
                    nearly ruined by the Thirty Years’ War. In 1593 a collection of portraits of the
                    chief representatives of the Fugger race, engraved by D. Custos of Antwerp, was
                    issued at Augsburg. Editions with 127 portraits appeared at Augsburg in 1618 and
                    1620, the former accompanied by α genealogy in Latin, the latter by one in
                    German. An edition which was published at Ulm in 1754 includes 139
                    portraits.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
