<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0058-0049-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FATHERS OF THE CHURCH</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 49</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:828168">Basil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1144248">Teachers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kz4v">Teachers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m3m">Caves</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n58/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FATHERS OF THE CHURCH</label>. Ecclesiastically the word
                    “father” is used in a variety of secondary significations. In the Old Testament
                    even, we find the name applied to priests (Judg. xvii. 10, xviii. 19), and to
                    prophets (2 Kings ii. 12, vi. 21, xiii. 14), as well as to kings (2 Kings v.
                    13); and in the days of later Judaism there was a definite office which was
                    known as that of the Father of the Synagogue.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See the rescript of Constantine (in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Codex Theodorianus)</hi> referred to and discussed by Vitringa,
                    <hi rend="italic">De Syn. Vet.</hi> lib. ii. c. 5.</p></note> In the Christian
                    church almost every kind of spiritual relationship in which age or authority was
                    in any way implied came to be expressed by some word denoting paternity. Thus we
                    find such names as abba, papa, pater, bestowed occasionally upon godfathers,
                    confessors, instructors, and almost invariably upon bishops and heads of
                    monasteries The decrees of the council of Nice are often referred to as those of
                    the 318 fathers. The expression “church fathers” (patre3 ecclesiastici),
                    however, has come to be used in a comparatively definite and restricted sense,
                    as denoting in the aggregate those teachers of the ancient church who, from the
                    close of the apostolic age onwards, either orally or in writing expounded and
                    defended the orthodox faith, and came to be acknowledged, either by tacit
                    consent or by express declaration of the church, as duly qualified exponents of
                    her doctrines. The title of father is generally held to imply soundness of
                    doctrine, holiness of life, the approval of the church, and undoubted antiquity
                    (Perrone). The word itself is fitted to suggest the idea of age, and also some
                    such notion as that which is expressed in 1 Cor. iv. 15.</p>
                <p>The patristic period of the church’s history is generally held to begin with the
                    close of the apostolic age; but historians are not agreed as to the date at
                    which it may be said to have closed. Some Roman Catholic writers speak of
                    Bernard, who died in 1153, as having been the “last of the fathers,” while Greek
                    patristic is often brought down so far as to the council ofFlorence. But it is
                    usual to speak of the scholastic period as having begun with Anselm; and there
                    seems to be no good reason for removing Bernard from the list of the schoolmen.
                    As no very important author either in Latin or in Greek can be assigned to the
                    centuries immediately preceding Anselm, it may therefore be said, roughly
                    speaking, that the patristic period practically closed for the Eastern Church
                    with Joannes Damascenus, and for the Western with Gregory the Great.</p>
                <p>The patri.stic canon has never been quite definitely fixed, and no precise line
                    of demarcation can be drawn between those ancient teachers of Christianity who
                    are and those who are not entitled to be reckoned “fathers.” The name is often
                    bestowed on some whose title when viewed from the standpoint of rigid orthodoxy
                    cannot but be regarded as somewhat doubtful. While Arius and Eusebius of
                    Nicomedia have obviously no title to be called “fathers,” it has not been
                    thought necessary to withhold the honourable appellation from Origen or
                    Tertullian.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Perrone,
                    <hi rend="italic">Loci Theologici,</hi> p. ii. sect. ii. cap. ii., De sanctis
                    patribus.</p></note> The authors usually named as fathers may be arranged
                    according to chronology into three groups, called respectively the apostolic,
                    the primitive, and the post-Nicene. The apostolic fathers, that is to say, the
                    fathers who were to some extent contemporary with the apostles, are Clement of
                    Rome, Ignatius, Polycarp, the author of the <hi rend="italic">Shepherd of
                    Hernias,</hi> and the author of the <hi rend="italic">Epistle of Barnabas</hi>
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Apostolic Fathers).</hi> The chief primitive or
                    ante-Nicene fathers are Irenaeus, Justin <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n59/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0059-0050"/> Martyr, Origen, Clement of Alexandria, Cyprian,
                    Tertullian, Gregory Thaumaturgus. Among the post-Nicene fathers may°be mentioned
                    Ambrose, Athanasius, Augustine, Basil, Chrysostom, Cyril of Jerusalem, Cyril of
                    Alexandria, Epiphanius, Gregory of Nazianzum, Gregory of Nyssa, Gregory the
                    Great, Hilary, Jerome, and Leo. A distinction is usually recognized between the
                    patres and those who were merely scriptores ecclesiastici, and it is to the
                    latter category that such writers as Eusebius and Socrates the historians most
                    properly belong. The Eastern and the Western Church have each four authors of
                    note whom they recognize as fathers <hi rend="italic">par excellence.</hi> Those
                    of the Eastern are Athanasius, Basil, Chrysostom, and Gregory of Nazianzum.
                    Those of the Western are Jerome, Ambrose, Augustine, and Gregory,—the fathers
                    respectively of her monastic system, of her sacerdotal authority, of her
                    scientific theology, and of her popular religion (Milman, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Latin Christianity,</hi> b. it c. 4).</p>
                <p>The study of the fathers has sometimes been regarded as constituting a distinct
                    discipline called patrology or patristic, which, however, practically resolves
                    itself into the church history of the first six centuries. For information on
                    the individual fathers and on the influence they exerted upon one another and
                    upon the thought and life of the church the reader is referred to the various
                    articles, biographical, archaeological, and historical, relating to that
                    period.</p>
                <p>The much-disputed question as to the authority of the fathers resolves itself
                    into the more general one as to the place of tradition considered as a source of
                    dogma and a rule of life apart from the scriptures (see vol. v. p. 759). There
                    seems to be no sufficient evidence for the statement made by Turrettin and
                    others to the effect that some Catholic writers set the writings of the fathers
                    individually on a level with the canonical scriptures; and it is certainly an
                    exaggeration to say that Cardinal Cajetan regarded them as having no authority
                    at all.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Turrettin, loc.
                    ii. qu. 21. Möhler, <hi rend="italic">Symbolik,</hi> sec. 42.</p></note> The
                    Tridentine doctrine is that no one is entitled to interpret scripture in a sense
                    contrary to the interpretations of holy mother church or to the <hi
                    rend="italic">unanimoιιs</hi> consent of the fathers.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Cone. Trid., sess. iv. Compare the Forma
                    juramenti professionis fidei prepared by Pius IV.</p></note> Roman Catholic
                    writers accordingly as a rule attach comparatively little weight to the
                    peculiarities of individual fathers, and hold themselves committed to nothing
                    that is not established by what they consider to be unanimous and unvarying
                    tradition. They distinguish, moreover, between the function of the fathers as
                    witnesses and their function as instructors. As witnesses to the tradition and
                    teaching of the church, they give testimony which is binding on the Catholic
                    conscience; as independent teachers, they are entitled to be listened to with
                    deference and respect, but their interpretations and arguments are to be freely
                    accepted or as freely rejected according to their merits.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Möhler, <hi rend="italic">ut sup.;</hi>
                    Perrone, <hi rend="italic">ui sup.</hi></p></note> Protestant writers, while
                    fully admitting the merits, literary and other, of many of the fathers, usually
                    dwell much upon the admitted fact of their fallibility, and strive to show that
                    the attempt to establish an unambiguous tradition by their means is in very many
                    cases much more illusory than Catholic writers are disposed to allow.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Chemnitz, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Examen Concilii</hi><hi rend="italic">Tridentini,</hi> De traditionibus;
                    Daille, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> usu</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">patrum;</hi> Barbeyrac, <hi rend="italic">De la Morale</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Pères,</hi> and others.</p></note> They do not, however, deny
                    that on many important points there is such a thing as a consensus patrum; but
                    this they regard as having at best no other authority than what is merely human
                    and ecclesiastical, the Bible alone being the supreme rule of faith and life.
                    The fundamental Protestant antithesis to the Tridentine doctrine according to
                    which the canonical books and the traditions preserved by the church are to be
                    received and reverenced “pari pietatis effectu ac reverentia”</p>
                <p>is very clearly expressed in the sixth Article of the Church of England which
                    declares that “Holy Scripture containeth all things necessary to salvation; so
                    that whatsoever is not read therein nor may be proved thereby is not to be
                    required of any man that it should be believed as an article of faith, or be
                    thought requisite or necessary to salvation.”</p>
                <p>The first writer in patrology may be said to have been Jerome, himself one of the
                    greatest of the fathers. His work, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Viris Illustribus, sive Catalogus scriptorum ecclesiasticorum,</hi> was
                    reprinted, along with the similar works of Gennadius of Marseilles, Isidore of
                    Seville, and lldefonso of Toledo, by Fabricius in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bibliotheca</hi><hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastica</hi> (1718). Among modern
                    writers on this subject Mohler <hi rend="italic">(Patrologie,</hi> 1842), Alzog
                    <hi rend="italic">(Grundriss der Patrologie,</hi> 1866), Engelhardt <hi
                    rend="italic">(Littcrarische</hi><hi rend="italic">Leitfaden zu Vorlesungen über
                    die Patristik,</hi> 1823), and J. E. L. Danz <hi rend="italic">(Initia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">doctrinae patristicoe,</hi> 1839) may be referred to. See also
                    Cave’s <hi rend="italic">Apostolici</hi> (1677) and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ecclesiastici</hi> (1683), Ittigii <hi rend="italic">Tractatus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de Bitt. Patr.</hi> (Lips.. 1707), and Dowling’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Notitia Scriptorum</hi><hi rend="italic">SS.</hi><hi rend="italic">Patrum</hi>
                    (Oxon. 1839). The most important collective editions of the fathers are the
                    Latin <hi rend="italic">Magna Bibliotheca</hi><hi rend="italic">Veterum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Patrum of</hi> De la Bigne (Paris, 1575), of which the <hi
                    rend="italic">Maxima Bibliotheca</hi> (Lyons, 1677) is an improved reprint, and
                    the exhaustive <hi rend="italic">Patrologies</hi><hi rend="italic">cursus
                    completus</hi> of Migne, in which the collection of Latin authors, brought down
                    to the time of Innocent III., occupies 221 volumes (Paris, 1844-1855), while the
                    Greek division, extending to the council of Florence, is completed in 166 vols.
                    (Paris, 1857-1866). (J. S. BL.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
