<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0168-0159-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FILANGIERI, Gaetano</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 159</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bv7b36b">Reformers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93d6n">Bar</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wk9g">Reformation</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j0b03x">Constants</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20m3b">Moralities</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40k55d">Morals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1092555">Reformation</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1092647">Reformers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n168/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FILANGIERI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Gaetano</hi></label>
                    (1752-1788), au eminent Italian publicist, was born at Naples on the 18th of
                    August 1752. He was the third son of Caesar prince of Arianiello, and through
                    his mother he was connected with the ducal house of Fragnito. Gaetano was from
                    his infancy destined for the profession of arms; when only seven years of age he
                    received a military appointment, and at fourteen he began actual service. His
                    early years gave no promise c f future distinction; he seems originally to have
                    manifested a positive dislike for the classics, while his interest in the exact
                    sciences, it is said, was first awakened at a comparatively mature age by a
                    trivial circumstance. His brother’s tutor had made a mistake in the solution of
                    a mathematical problem; Gaetano had been acute enough to discover and rectify
                    the error. From that day his great intellectual powers began to develop rapidly,
                    and such was his diligence that, at twenty years of age, besides being well
                    grounded in mathematical science, he had acquired a competent knowledge of
                    Isatin and Greek, of ancient and modern history, as well as of the principles of
                    law, and, moreover, had composed a couple of essays, one on “Educational Reform”
                    and another on the “Morals of Princes.” Meanwhile he had quitted the military
                    service, and, yielding to the wishes of his friends rather than to his own
                    inclinations, had entered on the profession of the law. At the bar his knowledge
                    and eloquence soon secured his success, and special circumstances still further
                    helped his advancement. In the year 1774 King Charles III. of Naples, at the
                    instance of his minister Tanucci, had issued a much-needed ordinance for the
                    reform of abuses in the administration of justice. Although this reform had been
                    generally welcomed, it had excited the murmurs of the bar. Filangieri now became
                    the advocate of the court, and published a defence of the royal decree founded
                    upon the most enlarged views of law and equity. The extensive knowledge and
                    matured judgment displayed in this performance called forth the warm
                    commendation of Tanucci, who encouraged its author to pursue the course in which
                    he had already acquired so much distinction. Through this influence and that of
                    his uncle the archbishop of Palermo he received, in 1777, several honourable
                    appointments at court; but his residence there neither broke in upon his regular
                    habits of life, nor interrupted the course of his studies; nor did he allow it
                    to interfere with the composition of the great work, <hi rend="italic"
                    >La</hi><hi rend="italic">Scienza della</hi><hi rend="italic">Legislatione,</hi>
                    on which he was engaged, and to which, rather than to practice at the bar, he
                    had all along been devoting his chief attention. The first and second books,
                    containing respectively an exposition of the rules on which legislation in
                    general ought to proceed, and a discussion of political and economic laws in
                    particular, appeared at Naples, 1780. Its success was great and immediate. Not
                    only in Italy, but throughout Europe at large, the author forthwith took rank
                    with the most celebrated publicists,— with his own countrymen Gravina, Vi <hi
                    rend="subscript"> b</hi> co, and Beccaria, and with the illustrious Montesquieu.
                    Although in the course of his observations he had found it necessary to point
                    out many faults committed by his own Government, so skilfully had he discharged
                    the delicate task of stating obnoxious truths without giving offence to those in
                    power that he was promoted by the king to a commandery in the royal order of
                    Constantine, In 1783 he was married to Caroline von Frendel, an Hungarian lady;
                    and in order that he might the more fully enjoy domestic happiness, and at the
                    same time have leisure for the composition of his work, on which he became every
                    day more intent, he, with the consent of the king, resigned all his military
                    appointments and his offices at court, and retired to a country seat at Cava,
                    some twenty miles from Naples. In the same year he published the third book of
                    his <hi rend="italic">Scienza,</hi> relating entirely to the principles of
                    criminal jurisprudence. Even his earlier volumes had not failed to rouse the
                    antipathies of an interested and influential class; but in this certain
                    suggestions which he had made as to the need for reform in the Roman Catholic
                    Church called forth the censure of the ecclesiastical tribunals, and his book
                    was condemned by the congregation of the Index in 1784. In the following year he
                    nevertheless published three additional volumes, dealing with education and
                    morals, these forming the fourth book of his great work. He was proceeding with
                    the preparation of the remaining three books, but his health was now
                    considerably impaired, owing to an excess of application, so that composition
                    advanced but slowly; and other interruptions soon followed. In 1787 the new
                    king, Ferdinand TV., summoned him to Naples to assist in the council of finance;
                    and there for a time he was wholly engrossed with this important public
                    business. But severe domestic misfortunes, combined with over-work, soon
                    compelled his withdrawal from office once more. He had just finished the first
                    part of his fifth book, in which he treats of the different systems of religion
                    which preceded Christianity, when he died on the 21st of July 1788. Of the
                    second part of the same book he had only made a rude sketch, in which were noted
                    down the principal subjects of discussion,—such as the advantages of
                    Christianity, and the dangers of superstition; the inconveniences of not
                    distinguishing the spiritual from the temporal power; the evils of an ignorant,
                    venal, excessively wealthy clergy. He was then to have considered the principles
                    of ecclesiastical jurisprudence; and a chapter on toleration was to have
                    completed the book. Tn the sixth book he proposed to treat of the laws relating
                    to property; and in the seventh and last, of those regarding the patria potestas
                    and the government of families. It is much to be regretted that the author was
                    not spared to complete his great work. Though unfinished, it has exercised
                    considerable influence on the thought and feeling of Europe, particularly in
                    Italy, where, at the time of its publication, the feudal system of legislation
                    was still in full force. In some portions, particularly in the chapters on
                    criminal law, it is not even now out of date. Filangieri had also other
                    important works in contemplation when he died. One, of which he had written a
                    short fragment, was to have been entitled <hi rend="italic">Nuova
                    Scienza</hi><hi rend="italic">delle</hi><hi rend="italic">Scieηze;</hi> another
                    was to have contained a system of universal history.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n169/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0169-0160"/>
                <p>His great work, <hi rend="italic">La Scienza della Legislazione,</hi> lias gone
                    through many editions, and has been translated into most of the languages of
                    Europe. The best Italian edition is perhaps that of Livorno, in 5 vols. 8vo
                    (1807). The Milan edition (1822) contains the <hi rend="italic">Opusculi</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">scelti</hi> and a life by Donato Tommasi. A French translation, by
                    Gallois, appeared in Paris in 7 vols. 8vo (1786-98); it was republished in
                    1822-24, with the addition of the <hi rend="italic">Opuscules</hi> and notes by
                    Benjamin Constant. <hi rend="italic">The Science of Legislation</hi> was
                    translated into English by Sir R. Clayton (London, 1806).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
