<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0401-0388-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FORBES, Duncan</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 388</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198938">Rebellion</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1093581">Relationism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n401/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FORBES, <hi rend="smallcaps">Duncan</hi></label> (1685-1747),
                    of Culloden, was born at Bunchrew or at Culloden near Inverness on the 10th of
                    November, 1685. After he had completed his studies at the universities of
                    Edinburgh and Leyden, he was admitted advocate at the Scottish bar in 1709. His
                    own talents and the influence of the Argyll family secured his rapid
                    advancement, which was still further helped by his loyalty to the Hanoverian
                    cause at the period of the rebellion in 1715. In 1722 Forbes was returned member
                    for Inverness, and in 1725 he succeeded Dundas of Arniston as lord advocate. He
                    inherited the patrimonial estates on the death of his brother in 1734, and in
                    1737 he attained to the highest legal honours in Scotland, being made lord
                    president of the Court of Session. As lord advocate, he had laboured to improve
                    the legislation and revenue of the country, to extend trade and encourage
                    manufactures, and no less to render the Government popular and respected in
                    Scotland. In the proceedings which followed the memorable Porteous mob, for
                    example, when the Government brought in a bill for disgracing the lord provost
                    of Edinburgh, for fining the corporation, and for abolishing the town-guard and
                    city-gate, Forbes both spoke and voted against the measure as an unwarranted
                    outrage on the national feeling. As lord president also he carried out some
                    useful legal reforms; and his term of office was characterized by quick and
                    impartial administration of the law. The rebellion of 1745 found him at his
                    post, and it tried all his patriotism. For some years before, he had repeatedly
                    and earnestly urged upon the Government the expediency of embodying Highland
                    regiments, putting them under the command of colonels whose loyalty could be
                    relied upon, but officering them with the native chieftains and cadets of old
                    families in the north. “If Government,” said he, “pre-engages the Highlanders in
                    the manner I propose, they will not only serve well against the enemy abroad,
                    but will be hostages for the good behaviour of their relations at home; and I am
                    persuaded that it will be absolutely impossible to raise a rebellion in the
                    Highlands.” Such a plan was afterwards successfully pursued by Chatham; but,
                    though Walpole is said to have approved of the scheme, it was not adopted by the
                    council. On the first rumour of the Jacobite rising Forbes hastened to
                    Inverness, and through his personal influence with the chiefs of Macdonald and
                    Macleod, those two powerful western clans were prevented from taking the field
                    for Charles Edward; the town itself also he kept loyal and well protected at the
                    commencement of the struggle, and many of the neighbouring proprietors were won
                    over by his persuasions. His correspondence with Lord Lovat, published in the
                    Culloden papers, affords a fine illustration of his character, in which the
                    firmness of loyal principle and duty is found blended with neighbourly kindness
                    and consideration. But at this critical juncture of affairs, the apathy of the
                    Government interfered considerably with the success of his negotiations.
                    Advances of arms and money arrived too late, and though Forbes employed all his
                    own means and what money he could borrow on his personal security, his resources
                    were quite inadequate to the emergency. It is doubtful whether these advances
                    were ever fully repaid. Part was doled out to him, after repeated solicitations
                    that his credit might be maintained in the country; but it is evident he had
                    fallen into disgrace in consequence of his humane exertions to mitigate the
                    impolitic severities inflicted upon his countrymen after their disastrous defeat
                    at Culloden. The ingratitude of the Government, and the many distressing
                    circumstances connected with the insurrection, sunk deep into the mind of
                    Forbes. He never fairly rallied from the depression thus caused, and after a
                    period of declining health he died on the 10th of December 1747, in the
                    sixty-third year of his age.</p>
                <p>Forbes was a patriot without ostentation or pretence, a true Scotsman with no
                    narrow prejudice, an accomplished and even erudite scholar without pedantry, a
                    man of genuine piety without <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n402/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0402-0389"/> asceticism or intolerance. His country long felt
                    his influence through her reviving arts and. institutions; and the example of
                    such a character in that coarse and venal age, and among a people distracted by
                    faction, political strife, and national antipathies, while it was invaluable to
                    his contemporaries in a man of high position, is entitled to the lasting
                    gratitude and veneration of his countrymen. In his intervals of leisure he
                    cultivated with some success the study ot philosophy, theology, and biblical
                    criticism. He is said to have been a diligent reader of the Hebrew Bible. His
                    published writings, some of them of importance, include— <hi rend="italic">A
                    Letter to a Bishop, concerning some Important Discoveries in Philosophy and
                    Theology</hi> (1732); <hi rend="italic">Some Thoughts concerning Religion,
                    natural and revealed, and the Manner of Understanding Revelation</hi> (1735);
                    and <hi rend="italic">Reflections on Incredulity</hi> (2d ed. 1750). His
                    correspondence was collected and published in 1815, and a memoir of him (from
                    the family papers) was written by Mr Hill Burton, and published along with a <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of Lord</hi><hi rend="italic">Loι∙at,</hi> in 1847. His
                    statue by Roubiliac stands in the Parliament House, Edinburgh.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
