<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0909-0502-0471-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FOSCOLO, Ugo (9th edition, volume 9, page 471)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1043867">Odes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n502/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FOSCOLO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Ugo</hi></label> (1778—1827),
                    the Italian writer who next to Alfieri has most contributed to free, the
                    literature of his country from the pedantries and affectations of the 17th and
                    18th centuries, was born at Zante on the 26th of January 1778. On the death of
                    his father, a physician at Spalatro, in Dalmatia, the family removed to Venice,
                    and in the university of Padua Foscolo prosecuted the studies begun in the
                    Dalmatian grammar school. The fact that amongst his Paduan masters was the Abbé
                    Cesarotti, whose version of Ossian had made that work highly popular in Italy,
                    was not without influence on Foscolo’s literary tastes, and his early knowſledge
                    of modern facilitated his studies in ancient Greek. His literary ambition
                    revealed itself by the appearance in 1797 of his tragedy <hi rend="italic"
                        >Tieste—</hi> a production which obtained a certain degree of success.
                    Foscolo, who from causes not clearly explained, had changed his Christian name
                    Niccolo to that of Ugo, now began to take an active part in the stormy political
                    discussions which the fall of the republic of Venice had provoked. He was a
                    prominent member of the national committees, and addressed an ode to Napoleon
                    the liberator, expecting from the military successes of the French general, not
                    merely the overthrow of the effete Venetian oligarchy, but the establishment of
                    a free republican government. The treaty of Campo Formio (17th Oct. 1797), by
                    which Napoleon handed Venice over to the Austrians, gave a rude shock to
                    Foscolo, but did not quite destroy his hopes. The state of mind produced by that
                    shock is reflected in the letters of Jacopo Ortis, a species of political
                    Werther,— for the hero of Foscolo embodies the mental sufferings and suicide of
                    an undeceived Italian patriot just as the hero of Goethe places before us the
                    too delicate sensitiveness embittering and at last cutting short the life of a
                    private German scholar. The story of Foscolo, like that of Goethe, had a
                    groundwork of melancholy fact. Jacopo Ortis had been a real personage; he was a
                    young student of Padua, and committed suicide there under circumstances akin to
                    those described by Foscolo. At this period Foscolo’s mind appears to have been
                    only too familiar with the thought of suicide. Cato and the many classical
                    examples of selfdestruction scattered through the pages of Plutarch appealed to
                    the imaginations of young Italian patriots as they had done in France to those
                    of the heroes and heroines of the Gironde. In the case of Foscolo as in that of
                    Goethe, <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n503/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0909-0503-0472"/> the effect produced on the writer’s mind by
                    the composition of the work seems to have been beneficial. He had seen the ideal
                    of a great national future rudely shattered; but he did not despair of his
                    country, and sought relief in now turning to gaze on the ideal of a great
                    national poet. At Milan, whither he repaired after the fall of Venice, he was
                    engaged iu other literary pursuits besides the composition of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ortis.</hi> The friendship formed there with the great poet Parini was ever
                    afterwards remembered with pride and gratitude. The friendship formed with
                    another celebrated Milanese poet soon gave place to a feeling of bitter enmity.
                    Still hoping that his country would be freed by Napoleon, he served as a
                    volunteer in the French army, took part in the battle of the Trebbia and the
                    siege of Genoa, was wounded and made prisoner. When released he returned to
                    Milan, and there gave the last touches to his <hi rend="italic">Ortis,</hi>
                    published a translation of and commentary upon <hi rend="italic">Calli~</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">machus,</hi> commenced a version of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Iliad,</hi> and began his translation of Sterne’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sentimental Journey.</hi> The result of a memorandum prepared for Lyons,
                    where along with other Italian delegates he was to have laid before Napoleon the
                    state of Italy, only proved that the views cherished by him for his country were
                    too bold to be even submitted to the dictator of France. The year 1807 witnessed
                    the appearance of his <hi rend="italic">Carme</hi><hi rend="italic">sui</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Sepolcri,</hi> of which the entire spirit and language may be
                    described as a sublime effort to seek refuge in the past from the misery of the
                    present and the darkness of the future. The mighty dead are summoned from their
                    tombs, as ages before they had been in the master-pieces of Greek oratory, to
                    fight again the battles of their country. The inaugural lecture on the origin
                    and duty of literature, delivered by Foscolo in January 1809 when appointed to
                    the chair of Italian eloquence at Pavia, was conceived in the same spirit. In
                    this lecture Foscolo urged his young countrymen to study letters, not in
                    obedience to academic traditions, but in their relation to individual and
                    national life and growth. The sensation produced by this lecture had no slight
                    share in provoking the decree of Napoleon by which the chair of national
                    eloquence was abolished in all the Italian universities. Soon afterwards
                    Foscolo’s tragedy of <hi rend="italic">Ajax</hi> was represented but with little
                    success at Milan, and its supposed allusions to Napoleon rendering the author an
                    object of suspicion, he was forced to remove from Milan to Tuscany. The chief
                    fruits of his stay in Florence are the tragedy of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ricciarda,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Ode to the Graces,</hi> left
                    unfinished, and the completion of his version of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sentimental Journey.</hi> His version of Sterne is an important feature in
                    his personal history. When serving with the French, he had been at the Boulogne
                    camp, and had traversed much of the ground gone over by Yorick; and in his
                    memoir of Didimo Cherico, to whom the version is ascribed, he throws much
                    curious light on his own character. He returned to Milan in 1813, until the
                    entry of the Austrians; thence he passed into Switzerland, where he wrote a
                    fierce satire in Latin on his political and literary opponents; and finally he
                    sought the shores of England at the close of 1816.</p>
                <p>During the eleven years passed by Foscolo in London, until his death there, he
                    enjoyed all the social distinction which the most brilliant circles of the
                    English capital confer on foreigners of political and literary renown, and
                    experienced all the misery which follows on a disregard of the first conditions
                    of domestic economy. His contributions to the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Quarterly</hi><hi rend="italic">Revieτvs,</hi> his
                    dissertations in Italian on the text of Dante and Boccaccio, and still more his
                    English essays on Petrarch, of which the value was enhanced by Lady Dacre’s
                    admirable translations of some of Petrarch’s finest sonnets, heightened his
                    previous fame as a man of letters. But his want of care and forethought in
                    pecuniary matters involved him in much embarrassment, and at last consigned him
                    to a prison; and when released, he felt bitterly the change in his social
                    position, and the coldness now shown to him by many whom he had been accustomed
                    to regard as friends. His general bearing in society—if we may accept on this
                    point the testimony of so keen an observer and so tolerant a man as Sir Walter
                    Scott—had unhappily not been such as to gain and retain lasting friendships. He
                    died at Turnham Green on the 10th of October 1827. Forty-four years after his
                    death, in 1871, his remains were brought to Florence, and with all the pride,
                    pomp, and circumstance of a great national mourning, found their final resting
                    place beside the monuments of Macchiavelli and Alfieri, of Michelangelo and
                    Galileo, in Italy’s Westminster Abbey, the church of Santa Croce. To that solemn
                    national tribute Foscolo was fully entitled. For the originality of his thoughts
                    and the splendour of his diction his country honours him as a great classic
                    author. He had assigned to the literature of his nation higher aims than any
                    which it previously recognized. With all his defects of character, and through
                    all his vicissitudes of fortune, he was an ill-judging but always a sincere and
                    courageous patriot. He was, if ever Italian deserved those titles, the precursor
                    and prophet of the unity and independence which his country now enjoys.</p>
                <p>Ample materials for the study of Foscolo’s character and career may be found in
                    the complete series of his works published in Florence by Le Monnier. The series
                    consists of <hi rend="italic">Prose lettcrarie,</hi> in 4 vols., 1850; <hi
                        rend="italic">Epistolario,</hi> in 3 vols., 1854; <hi rend="italic">Prose
                        pólitiche,</hi> 1 vol., 1850; <hi rend="italic">Poesie,</hi> 1 vol., 1856;
                        <hi rend="italic">Lettere di</hi><hi rend="italic">Ortis,</hi> 1 vol., 1858;
                        <hi rend="italic">Saggi di</hi><hi rend="italic">critici</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">storico-letterario,</hi> 1st vol. 1859, 2d vol. 1862. To this
                    series must be added the very interesting work published at Leghorn in 1876, <hi
                        rend="italic">Lettere inedite</hi><hi rend="italic">del Foscolo, del
                        Giordani, e della Signora di Stael, a Vincenzo Monti.</hi> The work
                    published at Florence in the summer of 1878, <hi rend="italic">Vita di Ugo
                        Foscolo, di Pellegrino Artusi,</hi> throws much doubt on the genuineness of
                    the text in Foscolo’s writings, as given in the complete Florence edition,
                    whilst it furnishes some curious and original illustrations of Foscolo’s
                    familiarity with the English language. (J. Μ. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
