<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0909-0229-0220-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">FINLAY, George</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 9, page 220</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bk43">Levant</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dj58k71">Enthusiasm</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:912699">Enthusiasm</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n229/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FINLAY, <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi></label> (1799-1875),
                    the historian of Greece “from its conquest by the Romans to the present time,”
                    was born of Scottish parents at Faversham, Kent, on the 21st of December 1799.
                    His father, Major John Finlay, RE, F.R.S., who had held for some time the post
                    of inspector of the Government powder-mills at Faversham and Waltham Abbey, died
                    when George was still very young (1802); but the boy has left on record how his
                    interest in historical studies was awakened at a very early age by the manner in
                    which his mother used to explain the history of England. On the second marriage
                    of his mother, he was sent to a boarding-school near Liverpool, where he spent
                    three years,—not very profitably, according to his own account. Afterwards his
                    education was continued in more favourable circumstances under a private tutor
                    in the house of his uncle, Mr Kirkman Finlay, who at that time sat as member of
                    parliament for the Glasgow district of burghs. While making good progress in his
                    literary education, he at the same time laid up pleasant and life-long memories
                    of the boating, fishing, and pedestrian excursions for which the picturesque
                    shores of the Firth of Clyde offer so many delightful facilities. At one time he
                    had entertained thoughts of entering the army; but having been dissuaded from
                    this by his friends, he ultimately, at the close of his university curriculum in
                    arts, made choice of the legal profession. He received his preliminary technical
                    training in a writer’s office in Glasgow, and, when little over twenty years of
                    age, went to Göttingen to complete his studies in Roman law. But before this
                    time he had begun to feel a deep interest in the contemporary affairs of Greece,
                    and ct the Hanoverian university he was wholly unable to withdraw<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit09newyrich/page/n230/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0909-0230-0221"/> his attention frorii the stirring drama which was
                    then being unfolded in the south-eastern corner of Europe. “I conversed much,”
                    he says, “with everybody I met who had visited Greece, read all the works of
                    modern travellers, and associated a great deal with the only Greek who was then
                    studying at Göttingen.” In 1823 he resolved to visit the country personally, in
                    order that ho might judge for himself of the condition of the people and the
                    prospects of the war. In November accordingly he arrived in Cephalonia, where he
                    first met Lord Byron, by whom, as well as by Sir Charles Napier, the British
                    resident, he was very kindly received. Shortly afterwards he was landed at
                    Pyrgos, and during the next fourteen months, which were spent partly at Athens
                    and partly at Missolonghi, he greatly improved his knowledge of the language,
                    history, and antiquities of the country. While soon led to form a very
                    unfavourable opinion of the rapacity, selfishness, and incompetency of the Greek
                    leaders, both civil and military, he by no means lost his enthusiasm for the
                    cause of Greek independence. A severe att ιck of fever, however, combined with
                    other circumstances to make a change of scene desirable in December 1824. The
                    rest of that winter accordingly and the spring of 1825 were spent in Rome,
                    Naples, and Sicily. After spending a summer at Castle Toward, Argyllshire, he
                    went to Edinburgh, where he attended classes in the university, and passed his
                    examination in civil law with a view to being called to the Scottish bar. His
                    unquenched enthusiasm for Greece, however, made it impossible for him to resist
                    the pressing invitation of his friend Hastings that he should return to that
                    country, and thenceforward, if we except a few brief journeys (one to England in
                    1826 in order to secure the services of some competent engineers), the remainder
                    of his life was wholly spent in the land of his adoption. He took part in the
                    unsuccessful operations of Lord Cochrane and Sir Richard Church for the relief
                    of Athens in 1827. When independence had been secured in 1829, under the
                    presidency of Capodistrias, he was induced by the prospect of peaceful progress
                    to buy a landed estate in Attica, hoping in this way to aid in putting the
                    country “into the road that leads to a rapid increase of production, population,
                    and material improvement.” These hopes were not realized; all his efforts for
                    the introduction of a better system of agriculture ended in failure; within a
                    very few years he found that he had lost his capital as well as his labour in
                    his generous but ill-rewarded enthusiasm. Only when it had become too plain to
                    him that Greece could be served in no other way, did he form the resolve of
                    giving himself to the literary work which occupied, somewhat sadly, all the
                    remainder of his life. “Had the hopes with which I joined the cause of Greece in
                    1823 been fulfilled, it is not probable that I should have abandoned the active
                    duties of life, and the noble task of labouring to improve the land, for the
                    sterile task of recording its misfortunes.” So he writes in. 1855. His first
                    publications were <hi rend="italic">The Hellenic Kingdom and the Greek
                    Nation</hi> (London, 1836); <hi rend="italic">Essai sur les principes de banque
                    appliquésà l'état actuel de la Grèce</hi> (Athens, 1836); and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Remarks on the Topography of</hi><hi rend="italic">Oropia and Diacria,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">with</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic">map</hi>
                    (Athens, 1838). The first instalment of his great historical work appeared in
                    1844 (the 2d edition in 1857) under the title <hi rend="italic">Greece under the
                    Romans: a Historical View of the Condition of the Greek Nation from the time of
                    its Conquest by the Romans until the Extinction of the Roman Empire in the
                    East.</hi> Meanwhile he had been qualifying himself still further for his task
                    by travel as well as by reading; he undertook several tours (one in the company
                    of Karl Ritter) to various quarters of the Levant; and as the result of one of
                    them he published a volume <hi rend="italic">On the Site of the Holy Sepulchre;
                    with a plan of Jerusalem</hi> (London, 1847). The <hi rend="italic">History of
                    the Byzantine</hi><hi rend="italic">and Greek Empires fromſſiXQ-ÌAoZ</hi> was
                    completed in 1854. It was speedily followed by the <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Greece under Othoman and Venetian Domination</hi> (1856), and by the <hi
                    rend="italic">History of the Greek Revolution</hi> (Edinburgh, 1861). In weak
                    health, and conscious of failing energy, he now gave the last years of hi life
                    to the task of revising, supplementing, and partly rewriting his great work.
                    From 1864 to 1870 he was also correspondent of the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>
                    newspaper, and at various periods he contributed articles to <hi rend="italic"
                    >Blackwood's Magazine,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum,</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Saturday Review.</hi> He was a member of several learned
                    societies; and in 1854 he received from the university of Edinburgh the honorary
                    degree of LL.D. He died at Athens on the 26th of January 1875. A new edition of
                    his <hi rend="italic">11</hi><hi rend="italic">ist</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >or</hi><hi rend="italic">y</hi>, “revised throughout, and in part rewritten,
                    with considerable additions, by the author, and edited by the Rev H. F. Tozer,
                    Μ. A.,” with a portrait by Jeens, was issued from the Oxford Clarendon press in
                    1877. It includes a brief but extremely interesting fragment of an autobiography
                    of the author. As an historian Finlay had the merit, which was also to some
                    extent the advantage, of entering upon a field of research that had been
                    previously wholly neglected by English writers, Gibbon alone being a partial
                    exception. He brought to his work many admirable qualities; as a student he was
                    laborious, as a scholar he was accurate, as a thinker he was both acute and
                    profound; and in all that he wrote he was unswerving in his loyalty to the
                    principles of constitutional government and to the cause of liberty and justice.
                    The portion of his work which extends from 146 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> to
                    1453 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> has been translated into German.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
