<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0836-0801-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">EXETER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 8, page 801</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198642">Conquest</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n836/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EXETER</label>, the chief town of Devonshire, in England, a
                    city which is a county in itself, and a municipal and parliamentary borough,
                    stands on the Exe, about ten miles northwest of the mouth of the river, where it
                    opens to the English Channel. The distance of Exeter from London is 194 miles.
                    The ancient city (round which suburbs have extended) occupies a broad ridge of
                    land, which rises steeply from the left bank of the Exe. At the head of the
                    ridge is the castle, on the site of a great British earthwork. This was the
                    stronghold of <hi rend="italic">Caer Isc</hi> (so named from the river Isc or
                    Exe, meaning water); and the British town became the <hi rend="italic">I sea
                    Damnoniorum</hi> of the Romans, just as Isea Silurum was the Roman name of
                    Caerleon on the <hi rend="italic">Usk,</hi> in South Wales. Roman coins,
                    tesselated pavements, pottery, and sepulchral urns have been found from time to
                    time, proving that the station was one of importance. It was one of the few
                    cities in Britain which were not deserted at the time of the Saxon Conquest; and
                    when Athelstan came westward about 926, he found <hi rend="italic"
                    >Exanceastβr,</hi> the “ehester” or fortified town on the Exe, as the Saxons
                    called it, occupied by Britons and Saxons <hi rend="italic">aequo jure.</hi> The
                    ground plan of the city indicates its</p>
                <p>Romano-British origin, since the principal streets cross each other nearly in the
                    centre. The main or High Street is, in fact, a portion of the Roman road which
                    extended from the eastern border of the county to the Tamar. Exeter was more
                    than once attacked by the Northmen; but the walls which had been constructed by
                    Athelstan greatly protected the “burgh;” and in 1050 the episcopal see of
                    Devonshire, which had been founded at Crediton about 910, was removed, for
                    greater security, to Exeter.</p>
                <p>The position of Exeter, and its importance as the principal city of the western
                    peninsula, have affected the whole course of its history, and led to its
                    numerous sieges. In 1068 the Conqueror appeared before Exeter, beleaguered it
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n837/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0837-0802"/> for eighteen days, and then received the
                    submission of its citizens. He afterwards founded the castle, known as
                    “Rougemont,” from the red colour of the rock on which it stands. The castle was
                    held for Matilda in 1137 by Baldwin de Redvers, earl of Devon; and King Stephen
                    took it after a siege of three months. Exeter was Lancastrian, and in 1469 held
                    out successfully against Sir William Courtenay and the Yorkists. In 1497 it was
                    besieged by Perkin Warbeck, and in 1549 for thirty-five days by the men of Devon
                    and Cornwall, who rose in defence of the “old religion.” The city was taken and
                    retaken during the civil war; and the queen gave birth there to the Princess
                    Henrietta, afterwards duchess of Orleans. After that period the most noticeable
                    event is the entry of the prince of Orange (William III.) in November 1688. His
                    “declaration” was then read by Burnet in the cathedral.</p>
                <p>The High Street of Exeter and its continuation, called Fore Street, are narrow,
                    but very picturesque, with many old houses of the 16th and 17th centuries. There
                    is a tangle of lesser streets within the wails, the line of which may be traced.
                    All the gates have been destroyed. The suburbs, which have greatly extended
                    since the beginning of the present century, contain many good streets, terraces,
                    and detached villas. The surrounding country is not only rich and fertile, but
                    is of great beauty. Extensive views are commanded in the direction of Haldon, a
                    stretch of high moorland which may be regarded as an outlier of Dartmoor. The
                    lofty mound of the castle has been laid out a3 a promenade, with fine trees and
                    broad walks. The city is the centre of the system of western railways. London
                    may be reached either by the Great Western (Bristol and Exeter) line, or by the
                    South-Western, passing by Salisbury and Basingstoke. The distance in both cases
                    is about the same. The North Devon railway runs from Exeter by Crediton to
                    Barnstaple and Ilfracombe; and the South Devon by Teignmouth and Totness to
                    Plymouth, and thence into Cornwall. There is also a line to Plymouth belonging
                    to the South-Western Company, which passes inland by Lidford and Tavistock.</p>
                <p>The population of Exeter in 1871 was 34,650 within the municipal limits. The
                    parliamentary borough contained 44,226 persons. The city, of which the earliest
                    recorded charter was granted by Henry I., has returned two members of parliament
                    since the reign of Edward L It is situated in the parliamentary division of East
                    Devon. Assizes for the county of Devon are held twice in the year at Exeter, in
                    the assize hall within the castle. The most important buildings in the city are
                    the cathedral, the guildhall, and the Albert Memorial museum; and the remains of
                    the castle are also of interest</p>
                <p>The cathedral, although not one of the largest in England, is inferior to none in
                    the great beauty of its architecture and in the richness of its details. With
                    the exception of the Norman transeptal towers, the general character is
                    Decorated, ranging from about 1280 to 1369. On the exterior the great
                    peculiarities are the towers mentioned above., and the west front, which is of
                    later date than the rest of the church (probably 1369-1394), and is adorned with
                    statues. Transeptal towers occur elsewhere in England only in the collegiate
                    church of Ottery, in Devonshire, where the cathedral served as a model. Within,
                    the points to be specially noted are—the long unbroken roof, extending
                    throughout nave and choir (there is no central tower or lantern); the beautiful
                    sculpture of bosses and corbels; the minstrel’s gallery, projecting from the
                    north triforium of the nave; and the remarkable manner in which the several
                    parts of the church are made to correspond. The window tracery is much varied;
                    but each window answers to that on the opposite side of nave or choir; pier
                    answers to pier, aisle to aisle, and chapel to chapel, while the transeptal
                    towers complete the balance of parts. A complete restoration of the cathedral,
                    under Sir G. G. Scott, was began in 1870 and completed in 1877. The new stall
                    work, the reredos, the choir pavement, of tiles, rich marbles, and porphyries,
                    the stained glass, chiefly by Clayton and Bell, and the sculptured pulpits in
                    choir and nave are of the highest merit. The ancient episcopal throne, a sheaf
                    of tabernacle work in wood, erected by Bishop Stapledon about 1320, has been
                    cleaned and renovated; and the organ, of which the pipes are of very nearly pure
                    tin, has been rearranged. The most interesting monuments are those of bishops of
                    the 12th and 13th centuries, in the choir and lady chapel. Some important MSS.,
                    including the famous book of Saxon poetry given by Leofric to his cathedral, are
                    preserved in the chapter house. The united sees of Devonshire and Cornwall were
                    fixed at Exeter from the installation there of Leofric (1050) by the Confessor,
                    until the re-erection of the Cornish see in 1876.</p>
                <p>The Guildhall in the High Street is a picturesque Elizabethan building, which
                    contains some interesting portraits. Among them are a full-length of General
                    Monk, duke of Albemarle, born in Devon (engraved in Lodge), and a full length
                    (given by Charles II.), of the Princess Henrietta. Both are by Sir Peter Lely.
                    The Albert Memorial Museum in Queen Street was designed by Hayward of Exeter
                    (1865). Devonshire materials have been chiefly used in its construction. The
                    building, which is of considerable size, contains a school of art, an excellent
                    free library, a reading room, and a museum of natural history and antiquities.
                    There is a good collection of local birds, and some remarkable pottery and
                    bronze relics extracted from barrows near Honiton or found in various parts of
                    Devonshire. Of the Castle the chief architectural remain is a portion of a
                    gateway tower which may be late Norman. Huge dykes and trenches of the British
                    period exist in an adjoining garden. The parish churches of Exeter are of small
                    importance, but the modern church of St Michael (1860) deserves notice. It is
                    sufficient to mention the Devon and Exeter Institution, founded in 1813, which
                    contains a large and valuable library; the diocesan training college and school;
                    and the grammar school, which dates from the reign of Henry VIII. There are two
                    market houses in the city, many hospitals, and many charitable institutions.</p>
                <p>Exeter has few manufactures; and Devonshire or Honiton lace, for which it is
                    celebrated, is made quite as much in the villages of the south coast as in and
                    around Exeter itself, although it is chiefly brought to the city for sale. There
                    is a considerable trade of a miscellaneous description. Hides from South
                    America, wines from Portugal and Spain, fruits and valonia from the
                    Mediterranean, and coal from the northern counties and Wales are imported.
                    Leather, paper, corn, and cider are sent to London and other parts of the
                    country. The woollen trade has quite passed away from Exeter, although it was at
                    one time so considerable that it was only exceeded by that of Leeds, and the
                    value of exported goods in 1768 exceeded half a million annually. The Ship
                    Canal, from Exeter to Topsham, in the estuary of the Exe, greatly assisted this
                    commerce. It was begun in 1564, enlarged in 1675, and again in 1827. Vessels of
                    300 tons can come up to the quay at Exeter; those of greater burden remain at
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n838/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0838-0803"/> Topsham; and those of the largest size lie at
                    Exmouth, at the outfall of the river.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi> Of older histories the most important is
                    Izacke’s <hi rend="italic">Antiquities of Exeter,</hi> 1681. The best later
                    authorities are <hi rend="italic">The History of the City of Exeter,</hi> by the
                    Rev. G. Oliver, 1861; <hi rend="italic">Lives of the Bishops of Exeter and
                    History of the Cathedral,</hi> by the Rev. G. Oliver, 1861; Archdeacon Freeman’s
                    <hi rend="italic">History of Exeter Cathedral,</hi> 1874; and Murray’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Handbook for the Southern Cathedrals of England</hi> (Exeter),—see
                    edition of 1876. (R. J. K. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
