<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0576-0555-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ESSEX, Robert Devereux, Second Earl of</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 8, page 555</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:825145">Bacon</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1066737">Plate</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65g52">Plating</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mn8h">Plate</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n576/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ESSEX, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Devereux, Second Earl
                    of</hi></label> (1567- 1601), son of the preceding, was born at Netherwood,
                    Herefordshire, November 10, 1567. He entered the university of Cambridge in
                    1577, and graduated in 1581. He appeared at court in 1584. In 1585 he
                    accompanied the earl of Leicester on an expedition to Holland, and greatly
                    distinguished himself at the battle of Zutphen. In 1587 he was appointed master
                    of the horse, and in the following year was made general of the horse, and
                    installed knight of the garter On the death of Leicester he succeeded him as
                    chief favourite of the queen, a position which injuriously affected his whole
                    subsequent life, and ultimately resulted in his ruin. While Elizabeth was
                    approaching the mature age of sixty, Essex was scarcely twenty-one. Though well
                    aware of the advantages of his position, and somewhat vain of the queen’s
                    favour, his constant attendance on her at court was irksome to him beyond all
                    endurance; and when he could not make his escape to the scenes of foreign
                    adventure after which he longed, he varied the monotony of his lifc at court by
                    intrigues with the maids of honour. In 1589, without the queen’s consent, he
                    joined the expedition of Drake and Norreys against Portugal, but on the 4th June
                    was compelled to obey a letter enjoining him at his *’ uttermost peril” to
                    return immediately. Soon after his return occurred his famous duel with Sir
                    Charles Blount, a rival favourite of the queen, in which the earl was disarmed
                    and <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n577/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0577-0556"/> slightly wounded in the thigh. In 1590 Essex
                    married the widow of Sir Philip Sidney, but in dread of the queen’s anger he
                    kept the marriage secret as long as possible. When it was necessary to avow it,
                    her rage at first knew no bounds, but as the earl did “use it with good temper,”
                    and “for her majesty’s better satisfaction was pleased that my lady should live
                    retired in her mother’s house,” he soon came to be “in very good favour.” In
                    1591 he was appointed to the command of a force auxiliary to one formerly sent
                    to assist Henry IV. of France against the Spaniards; but after a fruitless
                    campaign he was finally recalled from the command in January 1592. For some
                    years after this, most of his time was spent at court, where he held a position
                    of unexampled influence, both on account of the favour of the queen, and from
                    his own personal popularity. In 1596 he was, after a great many “changes of
                    humour” on the queen’s part, appointed along with Lord Charles Howard to the
                    command of an expedition, which was successful in defeating the Spanish fleet,
                    capturing and pillaging Cadiz, and destroying 53 merchant vessels. It would seem
                    to have been shortly after this exploit that the beginnings of a change in the
                    feelings of the queen towards him came into existence. On his return she chided
                    him that he had not followed up his successes, and though she professed great
                    pleasure at again seeing him in safety, and was ultimately satisfied that the
                    abrupt termination of the expedition was contrary to his advice and
                    remonstrances, she forbade him to publish auything in justification of his
                    conduct. She doubtless was offended at his growing tendency to assert his
                    independence, and jealous of his increasing popularity with the people; but it
                    is also probable that her strange infatuation regarding her own charms, great as
                    it was, scarcely prevented her from suspecting either that his professed
                    attachment had all along been somewhat alloyed with considerations of personal
                    interest, or that at least it was now beginning to cool. Francis Bacon, at that
                    time his most intimate friend, endeavoured to prevent the threatened rupture by
                    writing him a long letter of advice; and although perseverance in a long course
                    of feigned action was for Essex impossible, he for some time attended pretty
                    closely to the hints of his mentor, so that the queen “used him most
                    graciously.” In 1597 he was appointed master of the ordnance, and in the
                    following year he obtained command of an expedition against Spain. He gained
                    some trifling successes, but as the Plate fleet escaped him he failed of his
                    main purpose; and when on his return the queen met him with the usual
                    reproaches, he retired to his home at Wanstead. This was not what Elizabeth
                    desired, and although she about this time conferred on Lord Howard the earldom
                    of Nottingham for services at Cadiz, the main merit of which was justly claimed
                    by Essex, she ultimately held out to the latter the olive branch of peace, and
                    condescended to soothe his wounded honour by creating him earl marshal of
                    England. That nevertheless the irritated feelings neither of Essex nor of the
                    queen were completely healed was manifested shortly afterwards in a manner which
                    set propriety completely at defiance. In a discussion on the appointment of a
                    lord deputy to Ireland, Essex, on account of some taunting words of Elizabeth,
                    turned his back upon her with a gesture indicative not only of anger but of
                    contempt, and when she, unable to control her indignation, slapped him on the
                    face, he left her presence swearing that such an insult he would not have
                    endured even from Henry VIII. In 1599, while Ulster was in rebellion, the office
                    of lord deputy was conferred on Essex, but whether at his own express wish, or
                    only after he was persuaded against his will to accept it, has been disputed.
                    This point has an important bearing on the further question of the origin of
                    Essex’s treacherous designe. His campaign was an unsuccessful one, and by acting
                    in various ways in opposition to the commands of the queen and the council, and
                    suddenly leaving the post of duty with the object of privately vindicating
                    himself before the queen, he laid himself open to charges more serious than that
                    of mere incompetency. For these misdemeanours he was deprived of all his high
                    offices, and ordered to live a prisoner in his own house during the queen’s
                    pleasure. Chiefly through the intercession of Bacon his liberty was shortly
                    afterwards restored to him, but he was ordered not to return to court. For some
                    time he hoped for an improvement in his prospects, but when he was refused the
                    renewal of his patent for sweet wines, hope was succeeded by despair, and half
                    maddened by wounded vanity, he made an attempt to incite a revolution in his
                    behalf, by parading the streets of London with 300 retainers, and shouting, “For
                    the queen! a plot is laid for my life !” These proceedings awakened, however,
                    scarcely any other feelings than mild perplexity and wonder; and finding that
                    hope of assistance from the citizens was vain, he returned to Essex House, where
                    after defending himself for a short time he surrendered. After a trial—in which
                    Bacon, who prosecuted, delivered a speech against his <hi rend="italic"
                    >quondam</hi> friend and benefactor, the bitterness of which was quite
                    unnecessary to secure a conviction entailing at least very severe punishment—he
                    was condemned to death, and notwithstanding many alterations in Elizabeth’s
                    mood, the sentence was carried out 21st February 1601.</p>
                <p>Essex was in person tall and well proportioned, with a countenance which, though
                    not strictly handsome, possessed, on account of its bold, cheerful, and amiable
                    expression, a wonderful power of fascination. His carriage was not very
                    graceful, but his manners are said to have been “courtly, grave, and exceedingly
                    comely.” He was brave, chivalrous, impulsive, imperious sometimes with his
                    equals, but generous to all his dependants and incapable of secret malice; and
                    these virtues, which were innate and which remained with him to the last, must
                    be regarded as somewhat counterbalancing, in our estimation of him, the follies
                    and vices created by temptations which were exceptionally strong, and which
                    obtained additional power from the time and manner of their occurrence. He was
                    one of the most learned noblemen of his time, and his abilities were
                    considerable and mauy-sided, but a fatal want of prudence and self-government
                    made him almost the necessary victim of the difficult position in which from his
                    early manhood he had been placed, partly by circumstances, and partly by his own
                    pardonable vanity.</p>
                <p>Camden's <hi rend="italic">Life of Elizabeth; Secret History of Queen Elizabeth
                    and the Earl of Essex,</hi> by a “Person of Quality,” pub. at Cologne 1690, and
                    afterwards at London; Devereux, <hi rend="italic">Lives of the Earls of
                    Essex;</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bacon and Essex,</hi> by Edwin E. Abbott,
                    D.D., 1877. See also the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Bacon.</hi> (T. F. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
