<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0466-0447-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ENNIUS, Q</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 8, page 447</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1048651">Oscans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9rd17">Trojans</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n466/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ENNIUS, Q</label>. Although Enniusis known to us only from
                    fragments of his writings and from ancient testimony, yet there is sufficient
                    evidence from both sources to justify us in assigning to him a position of great
                    eminence and influence in Roman literature. Although not the creator of that
                    literature, for he is later in date, not only than Livius Andronicus and
                    Naevius, but than Plautus, yet he did more than any of the early writers to
                    impart to it a character of serious elevation, and thereby to make it truly
                    representative of Rome. The influence of Naevius was little felt by subsequent
                    writers; and, although the works of Plautus have enjoyed a happier fortune than
                    those of Ennius, yet Latin comedy was essentially an exotic product, and stood
                    in no direct relation to Roman life, nor to the deepest and most permanent moods
                    of the national mind. On the other hand, both Lucretius and Virgil may be
                    regarded as inheriting the spirit of Ennius; and in many fragments of his
                    various works we recognize his affinity with the genius of Roman history,
                    oratory, and satire.</p>
                <p>The circumstances of his life naturally fitted him to become the chief medium of
                    contact between the art and intelligence of Greece and the practical energy and
                    commanding character of Rome. He was born among the Calabrian mountains
                    (“Calabris in montibus ortus”) in the small town of Rudiae, in the year 239 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> one year after the date of the first dramatic
                    representation of Livius Andronicus, and two years after the end of the first
                    Punic war. Oscan was the language of the district in which Rudiae was situated;
                    but, as it is called by Strabo "Ελλτ/νις πόλις, and as Ennius is spoken of as
                    “semi-Graecus,” Greek was probably the language in common use among the
                    cultivated classes. Since the subjugation of Italy, and the settlement of Roman
                    and Latin colonies in the conquered districts, the knowledge of Latin must have
                    been spread among the allies who sent their contingents to the Roman armies.
                    Ennius testified to his appreciation of the intellectual gain derived from the
                    possession of various languages by using, in reference to his knowledge of
                    Oscan, Greek, and Latin, the expression that “he had three hearts” (Gell, xvii.
                    17), the word “cor” being used by him, as by many other Latin authors, as the
                    seat of intelligence. Through the access which these languages gave to the ideas
                    and sentiments of which they were the organs, Ennius was able to combine the
                    culture of Greece, the fresh feeling and inspiration of Italy, the elevated mood
                    and “imperial patriotism of Rome,” in laying the strong foundation of the
                    national literature.</p>
                <p>He is said (Serv. on <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi> vii. 691) to have claimed
                    descent from one of the legendary kings of his native district, the “Messapus
                    equurn domitor” who is introduced by Virgil (in recognition of the poetical fame
                    of his reputed descendant) as coming to the gathering of the Italian clans
                    accompanied by his followers, chanting their nativesongs,— “Ibant aequati numero
                    regemque canebant.”</p>
                <p>This consciousness of ancient lineage is in accordance with the high
                    self-confident tone of his mind, with his sympathy with the dominant genius of
                    the Roman republic, and with his personal relations to the members of her great
                    families. The exemption from war which his native district enjoyed during the
                    first twenty years of his life afforded him leisure to acquire the culture which
                    he turned to use in later life; and the vicinity of Tarentum afforded him
                    favourable opportunities for familiarizing himself w ith the dramatic art of
                    Greece. But of his early years nothing is directly known, and we first hear of
                    him in middle life as serving, with the rank of centurion, in Sardinia, in the
                    year 204 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> where he attracted the attention of the
                    Quaestor Cato, and was taken by him to Rome in that year. This personal service
                    in the second Punic war, the most momentous struggle in which Rome was ever
                    engaged, must have deepened his interest in the national fortunes, and
                    contributed to that knowledge of men, and especially of the soldierly character,
                    which was afterwards largely displayed in his epic and dramatic poetry. As Cato
                    made it a reproach to M. Fulvius Nobilior that he had taken Ennius, after he
                    became known as a poet, along with him in his Aetolian campaign (Cicero, <hi
                    rend="italic">Tusc. Bιsp.,</hi> i. 2), we may perhaps infer that it was the
                    personal qualities of the man rather than the genius or culture of the poet
                    which recommended the Messapian soldier to his regard.</p>
                <p>From the time of his arrival in Rome till his death in 169 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.,</hi> he devoted himself actively to various kinds of literary production,
                    and probably to giving instruction in Greek, for which a great demand existed
                    among the families of more liberal ideas among the Romau aristocracy. He lived
                    on the Aventine, “in a plain and simple way, attended only by a single
                    maid-servant” (to quote the words of Jerome in his continuation of the Eusebian
                    Chronicle), and enjoying the friendship of the foremost men in the state, such
                    as the great Scipio and M. Fulvius Nobilior, the conqueror of Aetolia. So strong
                    was the bond of friendship which united him to the former of these men, that a
                    bust of the poet was placed after death in the tomb of the Scipios, between
                    those of the conqueror of Hannibal and the conqueror of Antiochus. He
                    accompanied M. Fulvius Nobilior in his Aetolian campaign, in the year 189 B.C.,
                    and was present at the capture of Ambracia, which formed the subject of one of
                    his dramas. The representation of this drama probably took place at the
                    celebration of the general’s triumph two years later. Through the influence of
                    his son, the poet obtained the privilege of Roman citizenship, a fact
                    commemorated by him in a line of the <hi rend="italic">Annals—</hi></p>
                <p>“Nos sumu’ Romani qui fuvimus ante Rudini.”</p>
                <p>He died at the age of 70, immediately after producing the tragedy of <hi
                    rend="italic">Thyestes.</hi> In the last book of his epic <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n467/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0467-0448"/> poem, in which he seems to have given various
                    details of his personal history, he mentions that he was in his 67th year at the
                    date of its composition. He compared himself, in contemplation of the close of
                    the great work of his life, to a gallant horse which, after having often Avon
                    the prize at the Olympic games, obtained bis rest when weary with age. A similar
                    feeling of pride at the completion of a great career is expressed in the
                    memorial lines which he composed to be placed under his bust after death,—“Let
                    no one weep for me, or celebrate my funeral with mourning; for I still live, as
                    I pass to and fro through the mouths of men.”</p>
                <p>From the impression stamped on his remains, and from the testimony of his
                    countrymen, we think of him as a man of a robust, sagacious, and cheerful nature
                    (Hor. <hi rend="italic">Ep.</hi> ii. 1, 50; Cic. <hi rend="italic">De Sen.</hi>
                    5); of great industry and versatility; combining imaginative enthusiasm and a
                    vein of religious mysticism with a sceptical indifference to popular beliefs and
                    a scorn of religious imposture; and tempering the grave seriousness of a Roman
                    with a genial capacity for enjoyment (Hor. <hi rend="italic">Ep.</hi> i. xix.
                    7). We may realize the nature of his relation to such men as Fulvius Nobilior,
                    and his personal bearing towards them, by a passage quoted from his <hi
                    rend="italic">Annals</hi> (Gell. xii. 4), in which he is said, on the authority
                    of the grammarian Aelius Stilo (a contemporary of Lucilius, and one of Cicero’s
                    teachers), to have drawn his own portrait under the figure of a confidential
                    friend of the Roman general Servilius. This friend is introduced as being sent
                    for by Servilius during a battle, and is described as one “whom he (Servilius)
                    gladly made the sharer of his table, his talk, and his cares, when tired out
                    with speaking on great affairs of state in the broad forum and august
                    senate,—one with whom he could frankly speak about serious matters or jest about
                    trifles,—to whom he could safely confide all that he cared to utter, with whom
                    he had much hearty entertainment alone and in society,—one whose nature could
                    never be prompted to any baseness through levity or malice,—a learned, loyal,
                    pleasant man, contented and cheerful, of much tact and courtesy, choice in his
                    language, and of few words, with much old buried lore, with much knowledge of
                    men, and much skill in divine and human law,—who knew well when to speak and
                    when to be silent.”</p>
                <p>His career as a writer began at a great epoch of the national life, the end of
                    the second Punic war. The self confident and triumphant spirit produced by the
                    successful result of that struggle may be discerned in the exuberant vitality
                    and animal spirits of the comediee of Plautus, whose period of most vigorous
                    production falls in the years between the end of the war and his death in 184
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> Morenearly contemporary with Ennius was Caecilius
                    Statius, the Insubrian Gaul, whom Roman critics ranked as a greater comic
                    dramatist than Plautus or Terence. If weight may be attached to the phrase in
                    which Horace repeats the criticism of the Augustan age,—</p>
                <p>“Vincere Caecilius gravitate,”</p>
                <p>he must have resembled him in temper also more than the older dramatists. Till
                    the appearance of Ennius, Roman literature, although it had produced the epic
                    poem of Naevius and some adaptations of Greek tragedy, had been most successful
                    in comedy. Naevius and Plautus were men of thoroughly popular fibre. Naevius
                    suffered for his attacks on members of the aristocracy, and, although Plautus
                    carefully avoids any direct notice of public matters, yet the bias of his
                    sympathies is indicated in several passages of his extant plays. Ennius, on the
                    other hand, was by temperament in thorough sympathy with the dominant
                    aristocratic element in Roman life and institutions. Und?r his influence
                    literature became less suited to the popular taste, more specially addressed to
                    a limited and cultivated class, but at the same time more truly expressive of
                    what was greatest and most worthy to endure in the national sentiment and
                    traditions. With the many-sided activity which characterized him, he attempted
                    comedy, but with so little success that, in the canon of Volcatius Sedigitus he
                    is mentioned, solely as a mark of respect “for his antiquity,” tenth and last in
                    the list of comic poets. The names of only one or two of his comedies are known.
                    He may be regarded also as the inventor of Roman satire, in its original sense
                    of a “medley”or “miscellany,”although it was by Lucilius that the character of
                    aggressive and censorious criticism of men and manners was first imparted to
                    that form of literature. The word “satura” was originally applied to a rude
                    scenic and musical performance, exhibited at Rome before the introduction of the
                    regular drama. The saturae of Ennius were collections of writings on various
                    subjects, and written in various metres, and contained in four or, perhaps, six
                    books. Among these were included metrical versions of the physical speculations
                    of Epicharmus, of the gastronomic researches of Archestratus of Gela
                    (“Heduphagetica”), and, probably, of the rationalistic doctrines of Euhemerus.
                    It may be noticed that all these writers whose works were thus introduced to the
                    Romans were Siciliau Greeks. Original compositions were also contained in these
                    saturae, and among them the panegyric on Scipio, to which Horace refers in the
                    phrase “Calabrae Pierides” <hi rend="italic">(Od.</hi> iv. 8, 22). The satire of
                    Ennius seems to have resembled the more artistic satire of Horace in its record
                    of personal experiences, in the occasional introduction of dialogue, in the use
                    made of fables with a moral application, and in the didactic office which it
                    assumed.</p>
                <p>But the chief distinction of Ennius was gained in tragic and narrative poetry. He
                    was the first to impart to the Roman adaptations of Greek tragedy the masculine
                    dignity, pathos, and oratorical fervour which continued to animate them in the
                    hands of Pacuvius and Accius, and which, when set off by the acting of Aesopus,
                    called forth vehement applause in the age of Cicero. The titles of about
                    twenty-five of hi3 tragedies are known to us, and a considerable number of
                    fragments, varying in length from a few words to about fifteen lines, have been
                    preserved. These tragedies were for the most part adaptations and, in some
                    cases, translations from Euripides. One or two were original dramas, of the
                    class called “praetextatae/’ <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> i</hi> dramas founded on Roman history or legend. The heroes and
                    heroines of the Trojan cycle, such as Achilles, Ajax, Telamon, Cassandra,
                    Andromache, were prominent figures in some of those adapted from the Greek.
                    Several of the more important fragments are found in Cicero, who expresses a
                    great admiration of the manly fortitude or dignified pathos (“O poema tenerum et
                    moratum, atque molle”) of the passages which he quotes. Although it is more
                    difficult to judge, from unconnected fragments, of the genius of a dramatic than
                    of any other kind of poet, yet in these remains of the tragedies of Ennius we
                    can trace indica-tionsof strong sympathy with the noblerandbolderelements of
                    character, of vivid realization of impassioned situations, and of sagacious
                    observation of life. The frank bearing, fortitude, and self-sacrificing heroism
                    of the best type of the soldierly character find expression in the persons of
                    Achilles, Telamon, and Eurypylus; and a dignified and passionate tenderness of
                    feeling makes itself heard in the lyrical utterances of Cassandra and
                    Andromache. The language is generally nervous and vigorous, occasionally
                    vivified with imaginative energy. But it flows less smoothly and easily than
                    that of the dialogue of Latin comedy. It shows the same tendency to aim at
                    effect by alliterations, assonances, and plays on words. The rudeness of early
                    art is most apparent in the inequality of the metres in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n468/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0468-0449"/> which both the dialogue and the “recitative” are
                    composed.</p>
                <p>But the work which gained him his reputation as the Homer of Rome, and which
                    called forth the tribute of affectionate admiration from Cicero and Lucretius,
                    and that of frequent imitation from Virgil, was the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Annales,</hi> a long narrative poem in eighteen books, containing the record of
                    the national story from mythical times to the years during which the poem was
                    written. Although the whole conception of the work implies that confusion of the
                    provinces of poetry and history which was perpetuated by later writers, and
                    especially by Lucan and Silius, yet it was a true instinct of genius to discern
                    in the idea of the national destiny the only possible motive of a Roman epic.
                    The execution of the poem (to judge of it by the fragments, amounting to about
                    six hundred lines, which have been preserved) although rough, unequal, and often
                    prosaic, seems to have combined the realistic fidelity and freshness of feeling
                    of a contemporary chronicle with the vivifying and idealizing power of genius.
                    He prided himself especially on being the first to form the strong speech of
                    Latium into the mould of the Homeric hexameter. And although it took several
                    generations of poets to beat their music put to the perfection of the Virgilian
                    cadences, yet in the rude adaptation of Ennius the secret of what ultimately
                    became one of the grandest organs of literary expression was first discovered
                    and revealed. The inspiring idea of the poem was accepted, purified of all alien
                    material, and realized in artistic shape by Virgil in his national epic. He
                    deliberately imparted to that poem the charm of antique associations by
                    incorporating with it much of the phraseology and sentiment of Ennius. The
                    occasional references to Roman history in Lucretius are evidently reminiscences
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Annals.</hi> He as well as Cicero speaks of him with
                    pride and affection as “Ennius noster.” Of the great Roman writers Horace had
                    least sympathy with him; yet he testifies to the high esteem in which he was
                    held during the Augustan age. Ovid expresses the grounds of that esteem when he
                    characterizes him as</p>
                <p>“Ingenio maximus, arte rudis.”</p>
                <p>A sentence of Quintilian expresses the feeling of reverence for his genius and
                    character, mixed with distaste for his rude workmanship, with which the Romans
                    of the early empire regarded him:—·“Let us revere Ennius as we revere the sacred
                    groves, hallowed by antiquity, whose massive and venerable oak trees are not so
                    remarkable for beauty as for the religious awe which they inspire” <hi
                    rend="italic">(Inst. Or.</hi> X. i. 88). From his own application of the epithet
                    “sanctus” to poets, which may be compared to the application by Lucretius of the
                    same word to the great discoverers in philosophy, and to the “pii vates” of
                    Virgil, we may learn something of the earnest spirit in which he wrote for his
                    countrymen the great story of their fathers’ deeds.</p>
                <p>“Aspicite, 0 cives, senis Enni imagini’ formam;</p>
                <p>Hic vestrum panxit maxima facta patrum.”</p>
                <p>The best edition of his fragments is that of Vaiden, published in 1854. The
                    remains of his tragedies are edited also in Ribbcek’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tragicorum Latinorum</hi><hi rend="italic">Reliquioe,</hi> published in 1852.
                    These remains are critically discussed in the <hi rend="italic">Römische
                    Tragödie</hi> of the same author, published in 1875. (W. Y. S. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
