<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0160-0151-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ELM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 8, page 151</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96096v">Bark</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18t15">Seeds</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207555">Montana</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:827573">Bark</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:908187">Elm</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n160/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ELM</label>, the popular name for the trees and shrubs
                    constituting the genus Ulrnus, of the natural order Ulmacea. The Common Elm, U.
                    campestris, a doubtful native of England, is found throughout great part of
                    Europe, in North Africa, and in Asia Minor, whence it ranges as far cast as
                    Japan. It grows on almost all soils, but thrives best on a rich loam, in open,
                    low-lying, moderately moist situations, attaining a height of 60-100, and in
                    some few cases as much as 130 or 150 feet The branches are numerous and
                    spreading, and often pendulous at the extremities; the bark is rugged; the
                    leaves are alternate, ovate, rough, doubly serrate, and, as in other species of
                    Ulmus, unequal at the base (see vol. iv. p. 109, fig. 100); the flowers are
                    small, hermaphrodite, numerous, ip purplish brown tufts, and each with a fringed
                    basal bract, have a four-toothed campanulate calyx, four stamens, and two
                    styles, and appear before the leaves in March and April: and the seed-vessels
                    are green, membranous, one-seeded, and deeply-cleft. Unlike the wych elm, it
                    rarely perfects its seed in England, where it is propagated by means of suckers
                    from old trees, or preferably by layers from stools. In the first ten years of
                    its growth it ordinarily reaches a height of 25-30 feet. The wood, at first
                    brownish-white, becomes, with growth, of a brown colour having a greenish shade.
                    It is close-grained, free from knots, without apparent medullary rays, and is
                    hard and tough, but will not take a polish. All parts of the truuk, including
                    the sapwood, are available in carpentry. By drying, the wood loses over 60 per
                    cent, of its weight, and has then a specific gravity of 0 ’ 588. It has
                    considerable transverse strength, does not crack when once seasoned, and is <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n161/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0161-0152"/> remarkably durable under water, or if kept quite
                    dry; though it decays rapidly on exposure to the weather, which in ten to
                    eighteen months causes the bark to fall off, and gives to the wood a yellowish
                    colour—a sign of deterioration in quality. To prevent shrinking and warping it
                    may be preserved in water or mud, but it is best worked up soon after felling.
                    Analyses of the ash of the wood have given a percentage of 47 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 8 per cent, of lime, 21 ’ 9 per cent, of potash, and
                    13 7 per cent, of soda. In summer, elm trees often exude an alkaline gummy
                    substance, which by the action of the air becomes the brown insoluble body
                    termed ulmin. Elm wood is used for keels and bilge-planks, the blocks and
                    dead-eyes of rigging, and ships’ pumps, for coffins, wheels, furniture, carved
                    and turned articles, and for general carpenters’ work; and previous to the
                    common employment of cast-iron was much in request for waterpipes. The inner
                    bark of the elm is made into bast mats and ropes. It contains mucilage, with a
                    little tannic acid, and was formerly much employed for the preparation of an
                    antiscorbutic decoction, the decoctum ulmi of pharmacy. The bark of Ulmus fulva,
                    Michaux, the Slippery or Red Elm of the United States and Canada, serves the
                    North American Indians for the same purpose, and also as a vulnerary. The leaves
                    as well as the young shoots of elms have been found a suitable food for live
                    stock. For ornamental purposes elm trees are frequently planted, and in avenues,
                    as at the park of Stratfieldsaye, in Hampshire, are highly effective. They were
                    first used in France for the adornment of public walks in the reign of Francis
                    I. In Italy, as in ancient times, it is still customary to" train the vine upon
                    the elm—a practice to which frequent allusion has been made by the poets. Among
                    the small-leaved varieties of U. campestris are the species U. Berardi and U.
                    fastigiata; besides these there are several slender kinds with variegated
                    leaves.</p>
                <p>The Wych Elm, or Wych Hazel, U. montana, is indigenous to Britain, where it
                    usually attains a height of about 50 feet, but among tall-growing trees may
                    reach 120 feet. It has drooping branches, and a smoother and thinner bark,
                    larger and more tapering leaves, and a far less deeply notched seed-vessel than
                    U. campestris. The wood, though more porous than in that species, is a tough and
                    hard material when properly seasoned, and, being very flexible when steamed, is
                    well adapted for boat-building. Branches of the wych elm were formerly
                    manufactured into bows (see vol. ii. p. 372), and if forked were employed as
                    divining-rods. The Weeping Elm, the most ornamental member of the genus, is
                    regarded as a variety of this species. The Dutch or Sand Elm is a tree very
                    similar to the wych elm, but produces inferior timber. The Cork-Barked Elm, U.
                    suberosa, is distinguished chiefly by the thick deeply-fissured bark with which
                    its branches are covered. The American or White Elm, U. amencana, is a hardy and
                    very handsome species, of which the old tree of Boston Common (U.S.) was a
                    representative. This tree is supposed to have been in existence before the
                    settlement of Boston, and at the time of its destruction by the storm of the
                    15th February 1876 measured 22 feet in circumference.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="smallcaps">Arboriculture,</hi> vol. ii. p. 317; Loudon, Arboretum
                    Britannicum, vol. iii. 1838.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
