<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0632-0611-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ETHIOPIA, or Aethiopia</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 8, page 611</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39364">Monuments</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h12vb7j">Frontiers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tq5rj1x">Geez</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1205830">Ethiopia</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1025892">Monuments</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:915906">Ethiopians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:999835">Lists</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n632/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ETHIOPIA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Aethiopia</hi></label>, in
                    Greek At‰πια, the ancient classical designation of a country and kingdom of
                    Northeastern Africa, lying immediately to the S. of Egypt, and extending
                    eastward» to the Red Sea, but with no definitely marked boundaries in any other
                    direction. According to the “folk’s etymology” of the Greeks, the name was
                    equivalent to the “land of the scorched faces,” from α‰p, to burn, and <hi
                    rend="italic">ωψ,</hi> the countenance, and this supposed derivation doubtles3
                    reacted on the employment of the word, and increased the vagueness of its
                    meaning; but in all probability it was really, like the name of Egypt itself, a
                    corruption of some Egyptian original now unknown. The knowledge of this country
                    possessed by the earlier Greeks was extremely slight, and greatly corrupted by
                    mythical additions. To the generation among whom the Homeric poems took their
                    rise the Ethiopians were the remotest inhabitants of the world, and received the
                    gods themselves as familiar guests. They arc twice mentioned by Hesiod, who
                    calls their king by the Egyptian name of Memnon. Herodotus acquired a
                    considerable amount of information about their connexion with Egypt, and
                    Democritus is said to have travelled as far south as Meroe, and to have written
                    an account of its hieroglyphics; but it was not till the invasion of Ptolemy
                    Philadelphus that the Greeks began to be familiar with the country. From
                    Herodotus downwards we hear of a great many separate tribes, most of whom are
                    designated by Greek epithets descriptive of some real or supposed peculiarity,
                    as the Ichthyophagi or Fish-eaters, the Macrobii or Long-livers, the Troglodytes
                    or Cave-dwellers. To only a few of them can their proper geographical position
                    be assigned, and of none of them can we with certainty determine the
                    ethnographical affinities. The name Ethiopian, indeed, must be regarded not as
                    an ethnographical but as a politico-geographical designation. It has been
                    applied, both in ancient and modern times, to peoples of different race who have
                    occupied the country to the south of Egypt and the southwestern part of Arabia,
                    much in the same way as the name Englishman is used by foreigners for any native
                    of the British Islands, whether he be of Germanic or Celtic descent; and in this
                    respect it probably differs from the quasi-synonymous Cushite of Hebrew
                    ethnology and the An of the Egyptian inscriptions. The inhabitants of Meroe or
                    Southern Ethiopia were a reddish-brown people, and are so represented on the
                    monuments; but they were surrounded by, and perhaps intermingled with, a number
                    of dark-skinned tribes, whose effigies indicate affinity with the negro. Modern
                    research enables us to trace the main outlines of Ethiopian history, but with
                    the same indefiniteness of chronology which attaches to so much of the history
                    of Egypt. Of its earlier epochs we are profoundly ignorant. The Greeks had a
                    tradition that the Egyptians were indebted to the Ethiopians for the first
                    impulse of their civilization; but recent investigators maintain that the
                    relation between the two peoples must have been exactly the reverse of this, and
                    their view is supported by the fact that as we advance up the river the
                    monuments are evidently of later date and poorer workmanship, as if the southern
                    builders were only second-rate imitators of their northern predecessors <hi
                    rend="italic">(cf.</hi> Brugsch, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Aeyyp-</hi><hi rend="italic">ten's,</hi> 1877). The Pharaohs of
                    the XII. Egyptian Dynasty —the Usurtesens or Osortasens and Amenemhats— repulsed
                    the encroachments of the Ethiopians and invaded their country. By Usurtesen III.
                    a frontier fortress was erected at Semneh; and he forbade the people to the
                    south to enter Egypt except for the purpose of trading in cattle. During the
                    XVIII. Dynasty we find the kings of Egypt partly in friendly and partly in
                    hostile relations with their Ethiopian neighbours. Λahmes married an Ethiopian
                    princess, and received the assistance of her family in the expulsion of the
                    shepherd kings. Amenhotep (Amenophis) I. his son, and Thothmes (Tuthmosis) I.
                    his grandson, both <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n633/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0633-0612"/> extended the Egyptian dominion towards the south,
                    and the supremacy of Tuthmosis III. seems to have been widely acknowledged
                    throughout the Ethiopian region. When Amenhotep II., as we are informed by an
                    inscription in the Nubian temple of Amadas, brought back from his conqueste the
                    dead bodies of the kings he had slain, one of them was sent to adorn the walls
                    of Napata, the Ethiopian city now identified with Jebel Barkal. Amenhotep III.,
                    Horemhebi, and the more warlike Rameses or Ramessu I. are all mentioned as in
                    possession of the Ethiopian supremacy, but as engaged from time to time in wars
                    within the region. Amenhotep III. founded at Napata a great fortress-temple for
                    the god Amon-ra of Thebes. A general revolt took place against Ramses II. and
                    the importance of the wars that followed is shown by the extensive sculptures
                    and paintings in regard to them still preserved at Ipsambul (Abu-simbel) and
                    Beit Walli. During the XXII. Egyptian Dynasty the independence and power of the
                    principal Ethiopian potentate had increased so much that Azerch-Amen, of Napata,
                    the Zerah of the Biblical narrative, conquered all the valley of the Nile, and
                    advanced against Syria and Judah; the defeat, however, inflicted on him at
                    Zeρhathah by King Asa was so complete that he withdrew again within his original
                    frontiers. Piankhi Meriamen, the priest-king of Napata, whose family had an
                    Egyptian origin, took advantage of the confusion into which Egypt had fallen
                    during the XXIII. Dynasty, and succeeded in establishing his authority; and for
                    several generations Ethiopian influence was predominant in Egypt. Tirhakah
                    especially was a monarch of great power, as is attested by his monuments at
                    Napata and elsewhere. The great Egyptian Psametik was enabled by foreign
                    assistance to restore a native dynasty; but the excessive favour which he showed
                    to those who had helped him to his throne so displeased the Egyptian military
                    caste that they emigrated to Ethiopia to the number, according to Herodotus, of
                    240,000. At Ipsambul (Abu simbel) there is a Greek inscription on one of the
                    great colossi of Ramses purporting to have been engraved by the Greek
                    mercenaries who accompanied the expedition of Psametik against his runaway
                    subjects. The Persian invader Cambyses, who brought the Egyptian independence to
                    a close, failed in his attack on the Ethiopian kingdom; but the change in the
                    condition of Egypt helped to open up Ethiopia to Greek enterprise and influence.
                    Under the Ptolemies various Greek colonies—Dire-Berenices, Adulis, Arsinoe—were
                    established on the Ethiopian coast of the Red Sea, and Greek learning was
                    introduced into the Ethiopian court. Ptolemy Philadelphus invaded the country,
                    but came to terms with the king, Ergamenes or Arkamen, who is reported to have
                    relieved the royal power from the ecclesiastical bondage under which it had long
                    suffered, by putting the priests to death and plundering their temples.
                    Arkamen’s name occurs on the monuments at Debod or Tabet. In the reign of
                    Augustus, C. Petronius had to defend the Egyptian frontiers against an invasion
                    under Queen Candace: in the second campaign he extorted the submission of the
                    country, which continued nominally Roman till the reign of Diocletian. A
                    garrison was established at Primis or Ibrim, and a troop of German horse had its
                    head-quarters at Pselchis. There is still a very perfect Roman camp at Mehendi,
                    to the south of Hierasykaminos. About the 1st century of the Christian era a new
                    kingdom seems to have grown up at Axume. The king Zoskales is mentioned by the
                    author of the <hi rend="italic">Periplus</hi><hi rend="italic">of the Erythrean
                    Sea,</hi> who also tells us that he was acquainted with Greek; he may be
                    identified with the Za Hagalé or Hekla of the Ethiopian list of kings. In the
                    sixth century the Christians of Yemen, being oppressed by the dynasty of Jewish
                    proselytes who at that time held the throne of the Himyarites, asked and
                    obtained the assistance of the Axumite monarch; but the Ethiopian sovereignty
                    thus established only lasted for about seventy years.</p>
                <p>Compare <hi rend="smallcaps">Egypt,</hi> vol. vii. pp. 730-748; <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Abyssinia,</hi> vol. i., and the woιks of Salt, &amp;c., there
                    referred to; and in addition Lenormant, <hi rend="italic">Manuel de l'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">histoire orientale</hi><hi rend="italic">; Records of the
                    Past,</hi> vol. iv.; Vivien de Saint Martin, “Éclaire, geogr. et hist, sur
                    Γinscription d'Adulis,' ’ in <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Asiatique,</hi> 1863, published separately in 1864, and his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Le Nord de l'Afrique dans l’antiquité grecque et romaine,</hi> 1863.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ethiopian,</hi> or Geez, is the name given in modern
                    philology to a language of the Semitic family, which is still used in Abyssinia
                    for literary and ecclesiastical purposes. It shows the closest affinity in
                    grammatical structure with Arabic. The verb has ten conjugations, of which two
                    are peculiar, and the remaining eight analogous to as many of the ten Arabic
                    conjugations. The noun presents a greater similarity to the Hebrew noun, though
                    at the same time it has decidedly Arabic characteristics. There is no dual form
                    either in noun or verb. About a third of the vocables of the language have been
                    traced to Arabic roots, while others find their counterparts and kindred in
                    Aramaic and Hebrew. A considerable number of words have been imported from
                    foreign tongues—some as mere exotics by translators and scholars, but many
                    others through direct popular intercourse with foreign nations. Aramaic, Hebrew,
                    and Greek have been chiefly laid under contribution, the last especially for
                    words technical to Christianity. Of course it is often difficult to decide in
                    the case of Aramaic and Arabic vocables whether they are real borrowings since
                    the differentiation of the languages, or are part of the original common stock
                    of the Semitic. There are at least two modern languages which have sprung from
                    the ancient Geez, distinguished in modern philology by the conventional names of
                    Tigrina and Tigré, both derived from the native Tigraj, which is applied to
                    either indifferently. The Tigré, spoken by the half-nomadic races on the
                    frontiers of Nubia and Sennaaris, at least among one tribe, the Habab, extremely
                    like the parent speech; the Tigrina, on the other hand, is corrupt both in its
                    sounds, its inflexions, and its vocabulary, and bears evidence more especially
                    of Λmharic influence. Tigré has been very partially investigated: Merx
                    published, in 1868, a vocabulary and grammatical sketch; Munziger’s vocabulary
                    is printed in Dillmann’s <hi rend="italic">Lexicon;</hi> and a Tigré translation
                    of the gospel of Luke by Kugler and Isenberg exists in manuscript. The Tigrina,
                    or rather the Adoan dialect of the Tigrina, was treated pretty fully by Dr
                    Praetorius in hi3 <hi rend="italic">Grammatik der Tigijüa Sprache,</hi> 1872,
                    and he has since published, in the <hi rend="italic">Ztschrft. d.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Deut.</hi><hi rend="italic">Morg. Ges.,</hi> 1874, a paper on the
                    two dialects of Hamâsên and Tanben, which differ considerably in vocabulary as
                    well as in pronunciation, but are mutually intelligible. Another dialect mainly
                    of Ethiopie character is spoken by the people of Harrar, who form a small
                    Semitic enclave in the Hamitic population to the east of southern Abyssinia. Its
                    peculiarities have been investigated by Burton, <hi rend="italic">First
                    Footsteps in East Africa,</hi> 1856, and by Praetorius in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ztschr. d.</hi><hi rend="italic">Deut.</hi><hi rend="italic">Μorg. Ges.,</hi>
                    1869. The affinity of the Geez alphabet has given rise to no small discussion:
                    Ludolf brought it into comparison with the Samaritan, De Lacy with the Greek and
                    Coptic, and Lepsius with the Devanâgari, but in the opinion of most Semitic
                    investigators, its Semitic origin has been proved by the discovery of the
                    cognate Himyaritic alphabet or <hi rend="italic">musnad</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(cf.</hi> Renan, <hi rend="italic">Hist,</hi><hi rend="italic">des Langues
                    Sémitiques,</hi> p. 308).</p>
                <p>The literature of the Ethiopian language, like that of Armenian, is almost
                    exclusively Christian, and, indeed, with comparatively slight exceptions,
                    theological or ecclesiastical. Only a few inscriptions have been preserved of
                    the pre-Christian period, the most notable being those of Axum <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n634/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0634-0613"/> and Adulis, but it is not improbable that light
                    will be ob tained on the earlier times from the inscriptions of Southern Arabia,
                    which are beginning to receive special attention. The language of the Axum
                    inscriptions is the same as that of the Bible, and contains the Ambaric clement.
                    The forms of the letters vary, and the older forms are liker the Himyaritic.
                    Vowel signs are irregularly employed, and sometimes omitted, and the numeral
                    notation is peculiar. The work which forms the standard of a classical style is
                    the version of the Bible. According to native tradition it was made from the
                    Arabic, either by the first bishop Frumentius (Abba Salama) or by the “Nine
                    Saints” of the 5th century; but internal evidence goes to prove that it was
                    really derived from the Greek version in use in the Alexandrian church. In the
                    course of centuries it has undergone numberless alterations at the hands of
                    copyists; but even its most corrupted condition leaves it clear that it must
                    have been characterized by great fidelity to the Greek text. Among the MSS. of
                    the Old Testament Professor Dillmann distinguishes three classes: the first,
                    which seldom occurs, preserves in the main the original translation; the second,
                    and most numerous, contains a text revised according to the Greek; and the third
                    has been improved by comparison with the Hebrew. Besides the ordinary canonical
                    books of the English Bible, and the ordinary apocryphal books, with the
                    exception of the Maccabees, the Ethiopian canon includes a number of works of
                    various interest and value, as the Kufale or Book of the Jubilees, the Book of
                    Enoch, and the Ascension of Isaiah,—concerning which consult <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Apocalyptic Literature,</hi> vol. ii. The books of the
                    Maccabees were either never translated or have been lost, but their place has
                    been supplied by spurious productions of the same name. Several apocryphal books
                    are also incorporated with the New Testament, which is usually reckoned to
                    contain 35 altogether. It was printed in <hi rend="italic">2</hi> vols, at Rome,
                    1548, in the London Polyglot, and in 1830 by the London Bible Society, under the
                    editorship of Th. P. Platt. Dillmami published the Octateuch, Leipsic, 1853, the
                    four books of the Kings, Leipsic, 1861-1871, Enoch, 1851, and the book of the
                    Jubilees, 1859; and R. Lawrence published the <hi rend="italic">Ascensio</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">desa ice,</hi> 1819, and the <hi rend="italic">Apocalypse of
                    Ezra,</hi> 1820, at Oxford. <hi rend="italic">(Cf.</hi> Dillmann’s article on
                    the <hi rend="italic">Aethiopische</hi><hi rend="italic">Bibelübersetzung</hi>
                    in Herzog’s <hi rend="italic">Real</hi><hi rend="italic">Encyclopädie,</hi> 2d
                    edition, 1877.) Of the numerous works which rank as ecclesiastical authorities
                    in the Ethiopian church, it is sufficient to mention the <hi rend="italic"
                    >CyrUlns,</hi> which contains, not only several dogmatie treatises of Cyril of
                    Alexandria, but also similar productions of several others of the fathers; the
                    <hi rend="italic">Synodus,</hi> which includes, <hi rend="italic">inter
                    alia,</hi> the constitutions and statutes of the apostles, the canons of the
                    councils of Ancyra, Neocaesarea, Sardis, Antioch, and Nicaea, an exposition of
                    the Nicene creed, and an exposition of the Decalogue; the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mafshafa</hi><hi rend="italic">kidân</hi><hi rend="italic">za egziena
                    Iyasus,</hi> or the Testament of our Lord Jesus (usually quoted as the Kidân),
                    which treats of various ecclesiastical, liturgical, and eschatological matters;
                    the <hi rend="italic">Genzai</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Mafshafa Genzat,</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Mafshafa Kedr,</hi> containing respectively the burial
                    service and other sections of the ritual; the <hi rend="italic">Philexmιs,</hi>
                    a monastic treatise, probably translated into Ethiopie in the 14th century, and
                    deriving its name from Philoxenus of Manbig. Among the poetic works are a
                    collection of hymns in honour of the saints of the Ethiopian calendar, entitled
                    <hi rend="italic">Erziabkhαη uagsa,</hi> or “May God reign,” and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Orgaηoηa Maryams</hi> eulogy of the Virgin in rhythmic prose. The
                    MSS. of the <hi rend="italic">Mavaséet</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Antipkonαry</hi> sometimes contain an interesting musical notation, which,
                    according to native tradition, was introduced by a saint who lived in the 6th or
                    7th century. Certain works called <hi rend="italic">Savasev</hi> or guides are
                    devoted to the illustration of the Ethiopian language, but they are very poor,
                    and make no distinction between grammatical, lexicographical,
                    andhistorico-scientific information, standing thus on the same level with such a
                    work as Elyot’s <hi rend="italic">Latin Dictionary.</hi> The historical works,
                    as for example those concerning Alexander of Macedon, are of little moment; and
                    the real value of the lists of early kings of Ethiopia is still a matter of
                    dispute. According to Praetorius, one of the most recent investigators <hi
                    rend="italic">(Ztschr. d. Dent. Morg. Ges.,</hi> 1870), all the statements made
                    in Ethiopian literature about the earlier history of the country have been in
                    the main derived from Arabic legends not earlier than the 14th century, and then
                    reconstructed with the assistance of the king lists, which alone have some
                    degree of historic credibility. The European libraries which possess the richest
                    collections of Ethiopian MSS. are the British Museum, the Bodleian, the Royal
                    Library at Vienna, and the National Library at Paris. Ruppell·s collections are
                    preserved at Frankfort-on-the-Maine, and KrapfΓs at Tübingen and Würtemberg. The
                    Bodleian catalogue was published by Dillmann, 1858; D’Abbadie’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Catalogue</hi><hi rend="italic">raisonné</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    manuscripts</hi><hi rend="italic">éthiopiens</hi> appeared in 1859; and a list
                    of the Magdala collection in the British Museum, consisting of upwards of 300
                    MSS., was contributed to the <hi rend="italic">Ztschr. d.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Deut.</hi><hi rend="italic">Morg. Ges.,</hi> 1870, by William Wright. Ewald
                    gives a list of the Würtemberg MSS. in <hi rend="italic">Ztschr.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">für</hi><hi rend="italic">die</hi><hi rend="italic">Kunde des
                    Morgenlandes,</hi> 1843, and of the Tübingen MSS. in <hi rend="italic">Ztschr.
                    d.</hi><hi rend="italic">Deut.</hi><hi rend="italic">Morg. Ges.,</hi> 1847. Dorn
                    had already made known the few works possessed by the St Petersburg library, in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Bull, de l'Λcad.,</hi> May and October 1837. The Vienna
                    collection is dealt with by Fr. Midler in <hi rend="italic">Ztschr. d.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Deut.</hi><hi rend="italic">Mo) g.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Ges.,</hi> 1862. The first scholar who turned his attention to Ethiopian was
                    Potken of Cologne about 1513. A grammar and dictionary were published by Jacob
                    Wemmers, a Carmelite of Antwerp in 1638; and in 1661 appeared the first edition
                    of the great lexicon by Job Ludolf, who, in the 1702 edition, prefixed a <hi
                    rend="italic">Dissertatio</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >harmonia</hi><hi rend="italic">liηgu&lt;x cetk. cum. cel. orient.,</hi> and was
                    also the author of <hi rend="italic">Comment, de Hist, ceth.</hi></p>
                <p>Modern works connected with the subject are Hupfeldt, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Exercitationes</hi><hi rend="italic">Aethiopica,</hi> 1825; Dorn, <hi
                    rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">psalterio</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >alhiopicο,</hi> 1825; Tuch, <hi rend="italic">De Aethiop.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >lingua sonorum proprietatibus quibusdam,</hi> 1854, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">ath.</hi><hi rend="italic">lingua</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">son.</hi><hi rend="italic">sibilantium usu,</hi> 1854; Ewald, <hi
                    rend="italic">Ueber des athiop.</hi><hi rend="italic">Buch's Ηenοkh</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Entstehung,</hi> 1854; D’Abbadie, <hi rend="italic">Herma Pastor
                    Ethiopice,</hi> 1860; Schrader, <hi rend="italic">De Lingua</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Aethiopica</hi><hi rend="italic">indole,</hi> 1860; Ceriani, <hi
                    rend="italic">Monumenta</hi><hi rend="italic">sacra et profana</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">e codicibus</hi><hi rend="italic">Βibl.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Ambrosiana,</hi> Milan, 1861; Rodwell, <hi rend="italic">Aethiopic
                    liturgies</hi><hi rend="italic">and prayers,</hi> 1865; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Physiologies oethiopice,</hi> 187 <hi rend="italic">7.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
