<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0908-0502-0483-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EPIRUS, or Epeirc (9th edition, volume 8, page
                    483)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150446">Thrones</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1024954">Molossians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804157">Albanians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16p3t">Albanians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bv79x75">Coras</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xg2s">Boring</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pz51m4r">Borings</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1226682">Albania</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n502/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EPIRUS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Epeirc</hi></label><hi
                        rend="superscript                     smallcaps"> t</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >s,</hi> was that part of Northern Greece which stretched along the Ionian
                    Sea from the Acroceraunian promontory on the N. to the Ambracian gulf on the S.,
                    and was conterminous on the landward side with Illyria, Macedonia, and
                    Thessaly—thus corresponding to the southern portion of Albania. The name Epirus
                        <hi rend="italic">("Ήπειρος,</hi> or in the local dialects “Απειρος)
                    signified mainland, and was originally applied to the whole coast southward to
                    the Corinthian gulf, in contradistinction to the neighbouring islands, Corcyra,
                    Leucas, &amp;c. The country is all more or less mountainous, especially towards
                    the east, where the Pindus chain, in its main massif of Lacmon, feeds the
                    fountains of nearly all the great rivers of Northern Greece,—the Peneus, the
                    Achelous, the Arachthus, and the Aous. In ancient times it did not produce corn
                    sufficient for the wants of its inhabitants; but it was celebrated, as it has
                    been almost to the present day, for its cattle and its horses. According to
                    Theopompus, a writer of the fourth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> the
                    Epirots were divided into fourteen independent tribes, of which the principal
                    were the Chaones, the Thesproti, and the Molossi. The Chaones, identified by one
                    theory with the Chones who dwelt on the Tarentine gulf in Italy, inhabited the
                    northern portion of the country along the Acroceraunian shore, the Molossians
                    the inland district of which the lake of Pambotis or Yannina may be regarded as
                    the centre, and the Thesprotians the region to the north of the Ambracian gulf.
                    Aristotle places in Epirus the original home of the Hellenes, though the common
                    opinion among his countrymen traced them rather to Thessaly. In any case Epirus,
                    in spite of its distance from the chief centres of Greek thought and action, and
                    the fact that its inhabitants were hardly regarded as other than barbarians,
                    exerted even at an early period no small influence on Greece, by means more
                    especially of the oracle of Dodona. One of the earliest and most flourishing
                    settlements of the Greeks proper in Epirus λvas the Corinthian colony of
                    Ambracia, which give its name to the neighbouring gulf. The happy results of the
                    experiment appear to have tempted other Greek states to imitate the example, and
                    Elatria, Bucheta, and Pandosia bore witness to the enterprise of the people of
                    Elis. Among the other towns in the country the following were of some importance
                    :— in Chaonia—Palaeste and Chimaera, fortified posts to which the dwellers in
                    the open country could retire in time of war; Onchesmus or Anchiasmus, now
                    represented by Santi Quarante, or <hi rend="italic">ή σκάλα των</hi> 'Αγιων
                    Σάραντα, the Harbour of the Forty Saints; Phoenice, still so called, the
                    wealthiest of all the native cities of Epirus, and after the fall of the
                    Molossian kingdom the centre of an Epirotic League; Buthroton, the modern
                    Butrinto; Phanote, well known from its connection with the wars of the Romans;
                    and Hadrianopolis, founded by the emperor whose name it bore; in Thesprotia—the
                    Elean settlements already mentioned; Cassope, the <hi rend="italic">chef
                        lieu</hi> of the Cassopaeans, the most powerful of the Thesprotian clans;
                    Ephyra, afterwards Cichy-rus, a very ancient site, identified by Leake with the
                    monastery of St John three or four miles from Phanari, but by Bursian with the
                    ruins on the hill of K astri at the northern <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n503/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0908-0503-0484"/> end of the Acherusian Lake; and in
                    Molossia—Passaron, where the kings were wont to take the oath of the
                    constitution and receive their people’s allegiance; and Tecmon, Phylace, and
                    Horreum, all of doubtful identification. The Byzantine town of Rogus is probably
                    the same as the modern Luro, formerly known as Oropus.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> The kings or rather chieftains of the
                    Molossians, who ultimately extended their power over all Epirus, claimed to be
                    descended from Pyrrhus, son of Achilles, who, according to the legend, settled
                    in the country after the sack of Troy, and transmitted his kingdom to Molossus,
                    his son by Andromache. The early history of the dynasty is very obscure; but
                    Admetus, who lived in the 5th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> has become
                    famous for his hospitable reception of the banished Themistocles, in spite of
                    the grudge that he must have harboured against the great Athenian, who had
                    persuaded his countrymen to refuse the alliance tardily offered by the Molossian
                    chief when their victory against the Persians was already secured. He was
                    succeeded about 429 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> by his son or grandson,
                    Tharymbas or Arymbas I. who being placed by a decree of the people under the
                    guardianship of Sabylinthus, chief of the Atintanes, was educated at Athens, and
                    thus became at a later date the introducer of a higher kind of civilization
                    among his subjects. Alcetas, the next king mentioned in history, was
                    contemporary with Dionysius of Syracuse (about 385 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >b.c.)</hi> and was indebted to his assistance for the recovery of his
                    throne. His son Arymbas II. (who succeeded by the death of his brother
                    Neoptolemus) ruled with prudence and equity, and gave encouragement to
                    literature and the arts. To him Xenocrates of Chalcedon dedicated his four books
                    on the art of governing; and it is specially mentioned that he bestowed great
                    care on the education of his brother’s children. Troas, one of his nieces,
                    became his own wife; and Olympias, the other, was married to Philip of Macedon,
                    and had the honour of givipg birth to Alexander the Great. On the death of
                    Arymbas, his nephew Alexander, the brother of Olympias, was put in possession of
                    the throne by the assistance of Philip, who was afterwards assassinated on
                    occasion of the marriage of the youthful king with his daughter Cleopatra.
                    Alexander was the first who bore the title of King of Epirus, and he raised the
                    reputation of his country amongst foreign nations. His assistance having been
                    sought by the Tarentines against the Samnites and Lucanians, he made a descent,
                    332 B.o., at Paestum, near the mouth of the river Silarus, and reduced several
                    cities of the Lucaui and Bruttii; but in a second attack upon Italy he was
                    surrounded by the enemy, defeated, and slain, near the city Pandosia, in the
                    Bruttian territory.</p>
                <p>Aeacides, the son of Arymbas IL, succeeded Alexander, and espoused the cause of
                    Olympias against Cassander; but he was dethroned by his own soldiers, and had
                    hardly regained his position when he fell, 313 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi>
                    in battle against Philip, brother of Cassander. He had, by his wife Phthia, the
                    celebrated Pyrrhus, and two daughters, Deidamia and Troas, of whom the former
                    married Demetrius Poliorcetes. His brother Alcetas, who succeeded him, continued
                    the war with Cassander till he was defeated; and he was ultimately put to death
                    by his rebellious subjects, 295 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> The name of
                    Pyrrhus, who next ascended the throne, gives to the history of his country an
                    importance which it would never have otherwise possessed; but for an account of
                    his life we must refer to the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Pyrrhus.</hi></p>
                <p>Alexander, his son, who succeeded in 272 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi>
                    attempted to seize on Macedonia, and defeated Antigonus Gonatas, but was himself
                    shortly afterwards driven from his kingdom'by Demetrius. He recovered it,
                    however, and spent the rest of his days in peace. Two other insignificant reigns
                    brought the family of Pyrrhus to its close, and Epirus was thenceforward
                    governed by a praetor, elected annually in a general assembly of the nation held
                    at Passaron. It imprudently espoused the cause of Perseus in his ill-fated war
                    against the Romans, 168 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>;' and it was consequently
                    exposed to the fury of the conquerors, who destroyed, it is said, 70 towns, and
                    carried into slavery 150,000 of the inhabitants. It never recovered from this
                    blow. At the dissolution of the Achaean league, 146 B.c., it became part of the
                    province of Macedonia, receiving the name Epirus Vetus, to distinguish it from
                    Epirus Nova, which lay to the east.</p>
                <p>On the division of the empire it became the inheritance of the emperors of the
                    East, and remained under them until the taking of Constantinople by the Latins,
                    in 1204, when Michel Angelus Comnenus seized on Aetolia and Epirus. On the death
                    of Michel in 1216, these countries fell into the hands of his brother Theodore.
                    Thomas, the last of the direct line, was murdered in 1318 by his nephew Thomas,
                    lord of Zante and Cephalonia, and his dominions were dismembered. Not long
                    after, Epirus was overrun by the Samians and Albanians, and the confusion which
                    had been growing since the division of the empire was worse confounded still.
                    Charles II. Tocco, lord of Cephalonia and Zante, obtained the recognition of his
                    title of despot of Epirus from the emperor Manuel Comnenus, in the beginning of
                    the 15th century; but his family was deprived of their possession in 1431 by
                    Amurath II. In 1443, Scanderbeg, king of Albania, made himself master of a
                    considerable part of Epirus; but on his death it fell into the power of the
                    Venetians, from whom it passed again to the Turks, under whose domination it
                    still remains.</p>
                <p>Nauze, “Rech. hist, sur les peuples qui s'établirent en Épire,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Mém. de l'Acad. des</hi><hi rend="italic">∕nscr.,</hi> 1729;
                    wolfe, “observations on the Gulf of Arta,” in <hi rend="italic">Jour.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Roy.</hi><hi rend="italic">Geog. Soc.,</hi> 1834; Merleker,
                        <hi rend="italic">Darstellung</hi><hi rend="italic">des Landes</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">und der Bewohner von Epeiros,</hi> Königs., 1841; J. H. Skene,
                    “Remarkable Localities on the Coast of Epirus,” in <hi rend="italic">Jour.
                        R.</hi><hi rend="italic">G.</hi> 5.,1848; Bowen, <hi rend="italic">Athos,
                        Thessaly, and Epirus,</hi> 1852; ILιhι&gt;, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Albanesische</hi><hi rend="italic">Studien,</hi> 1854: Bursian, <hi
                        rend="italic">Geogr.</hi><hi rend="italic">von Griechenland,</hi> vol. i.,
                    1862; Major R. Stuart, * Οη Phys. Geogr. and Nat. Resources of Epirus," in <hi
                        rend="italic">J.</hi><hi rend="italic">R.</hi><hi rend="italic">G. S.,</hi>
                    1869; Guido Cora, in <hi rend="italic">Cosmos;</hi> Dumont, “Souvenirs de
                    l’Adriatique, de ΓEplre," &lt;fcc., in <hi rend="italic">Rev. des Deux
                        Mondes.</hi> 1872.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
