<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0490-0471-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">EPICTETUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 8, page 471</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:912601">Enteritis</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1133750">Stoics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:848002">Carters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:886086">Cynicism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:796264">Actium</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r753">Lying</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dj16">Stoics</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n490/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EPICTETUS</label> (the word means “acquired,” but no other
                    name ha≡ been handed down for him) was, according to the received account, born
                    at Hierapolis, a town in the southwest quarter of Phrygia. His life extends
                    between a date slightly anterior and a date slightly posterior to the second
                    half of the 1st century <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> While young, he was one
                    of the slaves of Epaphroditus, a freedman and courtier of the emperor Nero; and
                    while in that position, he managed to attend the lectures of Musonius Rufus, an
                    important and esteemed teacher of the Stoical system during the reigns of Nero
                    and Vespasian. Epictetus was lame—whether from birth or in consequence of an
                    accident or of his owner’s cruelty is unknown; he was also of weakly health.
                    That he was a free man in the later part of his life is evident, but the means
                    by which his liberty was obtained are unrecorded. In the days of Domitian he was
                    one of the recognised votaries and perhaps professors of philosophy; and in the
                    year 90, when that emperor, irritated by the support and encouragement which the
                    opposition to his tyranny found amongst the adherents of Stoicism, issued an
                    edict to all philosophers to quit Rome, Epictetus was amongst those who withdrew
                    into the provinces. For the rest of his life he settled at Nicopolis, a town of
                    southern Epirus, not far from the scene of the battle of Actium. There for
                    several years he lived, and taught by close earnest personal address and
                    conversation. According to some authorities he lived into the time of Hadrian;
                    he himself mentions the coinage of the emperor Trajan. His contemporaries and
                    the next generation held his character and teaching in high honour. According to
                    Lucian, the earthenware lamp which had belonged to the sage was bought by an
                    enthusiastic relic-hunter for 3000 drachmas. He was never married. He wrote
                    nothing; but much of his teaching was taken down with affectionate care by his
                    pupil Flavius Arrianus, the historian of Alexander the Great, and is preserved
                    in two treatises, of the larger of which, called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Discourses of Epictetus</hi><hi rend="italic">{'Επίκτητου</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ΔuxτpL-βaf),</hi> four books are still extant. The other treatise is a shorter
                    and has been a more popular work, the <hi rend="italic">Manual</hi> or
                    ’Εγχειρίδιου. It contains in an aphoristic form the main doctrines of the longer
                    work. There exists a tolerably extensive commentary on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Manual</hi> by Simplicius.</p>
                <p>The philosophy of Epictetus is stamped with an intensely practical character, and
                    exhibits a high idealistic type of morality. He is an earnest, sometimes stern
                    and sometimes pathetic preacher of righteousness, who despises the mere graces
                    of a literary and rhetorical lecturer and the subtleties of an abstruse logic.
                    He has no patience with mere antiquarian study of the Stoical writers. The
                    problem of how life is to be carried out well is the one question which throws
                    all other inquiries into the shade. “When you enter the school of the
                    philosopher, ye enter the room of a surgeon; and as ye are not whole when ye
                    come in, ye cannot leave it with a smile, but with pain.” True education ' lies
                    in learning to wish things to be as they actually are: it lies in learning to
                    distinguish what is our own from what does not belong to us. But there is only
                    one thing which is fully our own,—that is, our will or purpose. God, acting as a
                    good king and a true father, has given us a will which cannot be restrained,
                    compelled, or thwarted; he has <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> put it wholly in
                    our own power, so that even he himself has no power to check or control it.
                    Nothing external, neither death nor exile nor pain nor any such thing, is ever
                    the cause of our acting or not acting; the sole true cause lies in our opinions
                    and judgments. Nothing can ever force us to act against our will; if we are
                    conquered, it is because we have willed to be conquered. And thus, although we
                    are not responsible for the ideas that present themselves to our consciousness,
                    we are absolutely and without any modification responsible for the <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n491/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0491-0472"/> way in which we use them. Nothing is ours besides
                    our will. And the divine law which bids us keep fast what is our own forbids us
                    to make any claim to what is not ours; and while enjoining us to make use of
                    whatever is given to us, it bids us not long after what has not been given. “Two
                    maxims,” he says, “we must ever bear in mind,—that apart from the will there is
                    nothing either good or bad, and that we must not try to anticipate or direct
                    events, but merely accept them with intelligence.” We must, in short, resign
                    ourselves to whatever fate and fortune bring to us, believing, as.the first
                    article of our creed, that there is a god, whose thought directs the universe,
                    and that not merely in our acts, but even in our thoughts and plans, we cannot
                    escape his eye. In the world, according to Epictetus, the true position of man
                    is that of member of a great system, which comprehends God and men. Each human
                    being is thus a citizen of two cities. He is iu the first instance a citizen of
                    his own nation or commonwealth in a corner of the world; but he is also a member
                    of the great city of gods and men, whereof the city political is only a copy in
                    miniature. All men are the sons of God, and kindred in nature with the divinity.
                    For man though a member in the system of the world is more than a merely
                    subservient or instrumental part; he has also within him a principle which can
                    guide and understand the movement of all the members; he can enter into the
                    method of divine administration, and thus can learn—and it is the acme of his
                    learning—the will of God, which is the will of nature. Man, said the Stoic, is a
                    rational animal; and in virtue of that rationality he is neither less nor worse
                    than the gods, for the magnitude of reason is estimated not by length nor by
                    height, but by its judgments. Each man has within him a guardian spirit, a god
                    within him, who never sleeps; so that even in darkness and solitude we are never
                    alone, because God is within, and our guardian spirit. The body which
                    accompanies us is not strictly speaking ours; it is a poor dead thing, which
                    belongs to the things outside us. But by reason we are the masters of those
                    ideas and appearances which present themselves from without; we can combine
                    them, and systematize, and can set up in ourselves an order of ideas
                    corresponding with the order of nature.</p>
                <p>The natural instinct of animated life, to which man also is originally subject,
                    is self-preservation and self-interest. But men are so ordered and constituted
                    that the individual cannot secure his own interests unless he contribute to the
                    common welfare. We are bound up by the law of nature with the whole fabric of
                    the world. The aim of the philosopher therefore is to reach the position of a
                    mind which embraces the whole world in its view,—to grow into the mind of God
                    and to make the will of nature our own. Such a sage agrees in his thought with
                    God; he no longer blames either God or man; he fails of nothing which he
                    purposes and falls in with no misfortune unprepared; he indulges neither in
                    anger nor envy nor jealousy; he is leaving manhood for godhead, and in his dead
                    body his thoughts are concerned about his fellowship with God.</p>
                <p>The historical models to which Epictetus reverts are Diogenes and Socrates. But
                    he frequently describes an ideal character of a missionary sage, the perfect
                    Stoic—or, as he calls him, the Cynic. “The Cynic,” he says, “is a messenger sent
                    from God to men to show them the error of their ways about good and evil, and
                    how they seek good and evil where they cannot be found.” This missionary has
                    neither country nor home nor land nor slave; his bed is the ground; he is
                    without wife or child; his only mansion is the earth and sky and a shabby cloak.
                    It must be that he suffer stripes; and being beaten, he must love th03e who beat
                    him as if he were a father or a brother. He must be perfectly unembarrassed in
                    the service of God, not bound by the common ties of life, nor entangled by
                    relationships, which if he transgresses he will lose the character of a man of
                    honour, while if he upholds them he will cease to be the messenger, watchman,
                    and herald of the gods. The perfect man thus described will not be angry with
                    the wrong-doer; he will only pity his erring brother; for anger in such a case
                    would only betray that he too thought the wrong-doer gained a substantial
                    blessing by his wrongful act, instead of being, as he is, utterly ruined.</p>
                <p>The best edition of the works of Epictetus is that by Schweighäuser in 6 vols.
                    8vo, 1799-1800. There are at least two English translations,—an old one by
                    Elizabeth Carter, and a recent version by George Long. (W. W.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
