<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0908-0773-0738-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EVIDENCE (9th edition, volume 8, page 738)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2t79r">Digestion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h708385">Will</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49g84h">Wills</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058667">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058664">Personalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058861">Persons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:893579">Digestion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1175513">Wills</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n773/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EVIDENCE</label>. It is necessary to distinguish two common
                    meanings of the word evidence which are not unfrequently confused. Evidence
                    sometimes means the ascertained facts from which we infer the existence of some
                    other fact or principle. It also means the testimony of persons as to the
                    existence of facts, from which testimony we infer that these or other facts do
                    or do not exist. It is the latter sense alone which Î3 appropriate in speaking
                    of judicial evidence,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Sir James Stephen’s definition is—“Evidence means—(1) all statements
                            which the judge permits or requires to be made by witnesses in court in
                            relation to matters of fact under inquiry; such statements are called
                            oral evidence; and (2) all documents produced for the inspection of the
                            Court or judge; such documents are called documentary evidence.”— <hi
                                rend="italic">Digest of the Law of Evidence.</hi></p></note> The
                    rules of tile law of evidence are based chiefly on considerations relating to
                    human testimony. Their fundamental purpose is to guard and test the truthfulness
                    of statements as to matters of fact made in a court of justice. The further
                    question, what conclusion is to be drawn from the facts, supposing them to be
                    true, is the subject of few if any specific rules. The general theory oι
                    relevancy excludes testimony relating to facts from which no conclusion whatever
                    could be drawn with reference to the facts in issue. On the other hand, in the
                    case of what is called “conclusive proof,” the law directs that on certain
                    evidence the judge must regard some fact as proved and reject any evidence
                    offered against it. Between these two extremes the law leaveβ the relation
                    between facts in evidence and facts in issue to the unaided logic or common
                    sense of the tribunal.</p>
                <p>The theory of relevancy above alluded to lies at the root of the law of evidence,
                    and requires some preliminary explanation. The phrase is not one of common use
                    in English text books, and nothing like a statement of the general principle is
                    to be found in them. Roscoe, for instance <hi rend="italic">{Digest of the Law
                        of Evidence at Nisi Prius),</hi> simply states that, “as the object of
                    pleading is to reduce the matters in difference between the parties to distinct
                    and simple issues, so the rules of evidence require that no proof, oral or
                    documentary, shall be received that is not referrible to those issues. All
                    evidence of matters which the courts judicially notice, or of matters
                    immaterial, superfluous, or irrelevant, is therefore excluded.” And again, “In
                    general, evidence of collateral facts, not pertinent to the issue, is not
                    admissible,” We are left to collect from the abundant wealth of decided cases
                    what things are relevant and material, and what things are irrelevant and
                    superfluous. . A statement of the general result of the cases will be found in
                    Sir James F. Stephen’s recently published <hi rend="italic">Digest of the Law of
                        Evidence.</hi> In the introduction to an edition of the Indian Evidence Act,
                    by the same author, the theory of ιelevancy thus deduced from the decided cases
                    is fully explained, and its connexion with the general law’s of experimental
                    inquiry pointed out.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n774/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0774-0739"/>
                <p>The distinction sometimes drawn between direct and circumstantial evidence is of
                    popular rather than legal interest. The fact in issue may be proved either by
                    the testimony of persons who swear to it as a matter of personal knowledge, or
                    by the testimony of persons who swear to other facts from which the existence of
                    the fact in issue is inferred. In the former case the evidence is said to be
                    direct, in the latter circumstantial. The probative force of these two sorts of
                    evidence has been differently estimated. On the one hand, it has been said (and
                    this. we should think is the more popular view) that a conclusion arrived at
                    merely from inference is not so trustworthy as the positive assertion of a sane
                    and honest witness who testifies to what he has actually seen or heard. The
                    explanation would seem to be that men have less confidence in their own powers
                    of reasoning than in the assertione of others. It is hardly neceseary to
                    point.out that in both cases a process of inference is necessary— that we infer
                    the existence of the fact from the fact that the witness swears to it, and that
                    this inference like others 13 exposed to the chances of error. On the other
                    hand, the numberless instances on which positive direct testimony as to matters
                    of fact has been subsequently shown to be entirely false or erroneous, has led
                    to the opposite opinion that circumstantial is more trustworthy than direct
                    evidence. Apart from the possibility of deliberate falsehood in the witness,
                    there is the chance of his having been utterly and unaccountably mistaken.
                    Everybody can recall striking instances of this—especially in cases of personal
                        identity.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A very
                            remarkable example is given by Mr Wills in his essay on <hi
                                rend="italic">The Rationale of Circumstantial Evidence.</hi> Sir
                            Thomas Davenant, an eminent barrister, a gentleman of acute mind and
                            strong understanding, swore positively to the persons of two men whom he
                            charged with robbing him in the open daylight. But it was proved, on the
                            most conclusive evidence, that the men on trial were at the time of the
                            robbery at so remote a distance from where Sir Thomas was robbed that
                            the thing was impossible. The consequence was that the men were
                            acquitted: and some time afterwards the robbers were taken, and tho
                            articles stolen from Sir Thomas and his lady found upon them.</p></note>
                    Accordingly, it has been said, in the phrase of Paley, that “circumstances
                    cannot lie,” or, as it was put by Mr Justice Buller in Donnellau’s case, “a
                    presumption which necessarily arises from circumstances is very often more
                    convincing and more satisfactory than any other kind of evidence, because it is
                    not within the reach and compass of human ability to invent a train of
                    circumstances which shall be so connected together as to amount to a proof of
                    guilt without affording opportunities for contradicting a great part, if not all
                    those circumstances.” The facts in circumstantial evidence are, however, like
                    the facts in direct evidence, to be taken subject to the possibility of mistake
                    or falsehood on the person narrating them, and the process of inference has its
                    own peculiar dangers. The <hi rend="italic">anno</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >domini</hi> water-mark on writing paper has often been the instrument of
                    convicting persons of forgery; but “it is beyond a doubt,” says Mr Wills, “and
                    instances of the kind have recently occurred, that issues of paper have taken
                    place bearing the water-mark of the year succeeding their distribution.”
                    Circumstantial evidence corresponds to “facts relevant to the issue,” as defined
                    in this article.</p>
                <p>The English law of evidence is perhaps the most perfect example we possess of
                    what Bentham calls judge-made law. It is substantially the creation of
                    successive generations of judges in the courts of common law. It grew up as a
                    thing of custom and practice, and it is not so very long since different customs
                    prevailed on different circuits. Thus, .Lord Ellenborough, in one instance
                    quoted by Sir J. Stephen, spoke of the practice of the Northern and Western
                    Circuits as being different from that of the Oxford Circuit. It was made by
                    judges for juries, and this fact no doubt serves to explain many of its
                    peculiarities.</p>
                <p>Without adopting Bentham’s opinion that these were deliberately intended to
                    subserve the “sinister interests” of the lawyers, we may admit that they were
                    founded largely on distrust of the capacity of the tribunal to which the issues
                    of fact belong. Hence doubtless those numberless presumptions by which a
                    conclusion is imposed on the jury until positive evidence is offered to set it
                    aside. Hence also that monstrous system of exclusions by which any person whose
                    position was such as to make it in tho least degree likely or possible that he
                    would tell a falsehood, was withdrawn from the hearing of the jury. Only the
                    most contemptuous disbelief in the sagacity of jurymen can account for the
                    exclusion of the only witness cognizant of the transaction in question, simply
                    because he has a slight pecuniary interest in the result. It may be conjectured
                    that if trial by jury had not been the practice of the common law—if the judges
                    had acquired the power of deciding issues of fact as well of law—many of the
                    most obnoxious rules of evidence would never, have existed.</p>
                <p>The legislature has interfered mainly for the purpose of putting an end to these
                    exclusions. Certainly the most important of the statutes dealing with the law of
                    evidence are those which make classes of persons, formerly excluded, competent
                    to testify. The source of this continuous reform is to be found in the treatise
                    of Bentham, which, for the first time, examined the traditionary law by the
                    light of practical utility. Starting with the fundamental principle that the
                    great object in judicial evidence is the discovery of truth, he hunted down with
                    merciless rigour the artificial rules which closed out the surest sources of
                    evidence. The success of his attack has been complete. In 1843 the exclusion of
                    persons by reason of interest or crime was abolished (6 and 7 Vict. c. 85), but
                    the incapacity of the parties to an action was allowed to remain. This in turn
                    was abolished with certain exceptions by the 14 and 15 Vict. c. 99. By 32 and 33
                    Vict. c. 68, parties were allowed to give evidence in actions for breach of
                    promise (subject to the requirement of corroboration), and husbands and wives in
                    proceedings for adultery. The last Act of this sort was passed in 1877, and is a
                    curious instauce of the guarded way in which the legislature has approached this
                    subject. It simply provides that, on the trial of any indictment or other
                    proceeding for the non-repair of any public highway, bridge, or for a nuisance,
                    or of any other indictment or proceeding instituted for the purpose of trying or
                    enforcing a civil right only, every defendant to such indictment or proceeding,
                    and the wife or husband of any such defendant, shall be admissible witnesses,
                    and compellable to give evidence. Husband and wife are now excluded only in
                    purely criminal cases, and in course of time no doubt that exclusion also will
                    be brought to an end. Religious disabilities (enforced by the necessity of an
                    oath) have also been gradually got rid of by successive enactments, the most
                    important being the 24 and 25 Viet, c. 66, and 32 and 33 Vict. c. 68. With these
                    exceptions, the legislature has left the leading principles of the law
                    untouched.</p>
                <p>In attempting to give an outline of the law of evidence in this country we shall
                    follow in the main the division adopted by Sir J. Stephen in his very useful <hi
                        rend="italic">Digest</hi> English text books on the law of evidence owe
                    their enormous bulk to the introduction of rules which properly belong to the
                    substantive law, or to the rules of practice in the tribunals. Confining
                    ourselves to the general principles of evidence, we βhall notice shortly the
                    following heads :—1st, What facts may be proved in a court of law; 2d, By what
                    kind of evidence they must be proved; and,. 3d, By whom, and in what manner, the
                    evidence must be produced.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n775/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0775-0740"/>
                <p>1. Sir J. Stephen states the general rule as follows :— “Evidence may be given in
                    any action of the existence or non-existence of any fact in issue, and of any
                    fact relevant to any fact in issue, and of no others.” Relevant facts here means
                    simply facts (other than those in issue) which may be proved, and would include
                    cases of relevancy strictly so-called,— <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> facts
                    relevant in the sense that from their existence you may infer the existence of
                    the facts in issue. There are minor classes of facts, not being facts in issue,
                    and not being relevant facts in this sense, which nevertheless may be proved.
                    For example, “facts which, though not in issue, are so connected with facts in
                    issue as to form part of the same transaction,” and “facts which are necessary
                    to be known to explain or introduce a fact in issue,” may be proved; but to say
                    that they are relevant tends to obscure the theory of relevancy.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>^.] <hi
                                rend="superscript"> ater e</hi> ^ <hi rend="superscript"> lti</hi> θ
                                <hi rend="superscript"> n of t1ιe</hi><hi rend="italic">Digest,</hi>
                            the phrase “deemed to be relevant”</p><p>is substituted for
                            ‘‘relevant.”</p></note></p>
                <p>What facts, then, are to be regarded as relevant to facts in issue Î English law,
                    as we have seen, makes no attempt to answer this question otherwise than by the
                    enumeration of decided cases. The general definition of relevancy in Stephen’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Digest</hi> is the following :—Facts, whether in issue or
                    not, are relevant to each other when one is, or probably may be, or probably may
                    have been—the cause of the other, the effect of the other, an effect of the same
                    cause, a cause of the same effect,—or when the one shows that the other must or
                    cannot have occurred, or probably does or did exist, or that any fact does or
                    did exist or not, which in the common course of events would either have caused
                    or have been caused by the other.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>This definition is borrowed from a pamphlet on the <hi
                                rend="italic">Theory of ^</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                                u</hi><hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                                iciαl</hi><hi rend="italic">evidence,</hi> by George Clifford SeZ⅛H
                            Λκ <hi rend="superscript"> ay</hi> A,l∙. <hi rend="superscript"> Mr
                                Whitworth</hi> examines the case of Äΐί ϊ I <hi rend="superscript">
                                y in 1864</hi> &gt; <hi rend="superscript"> and shows how the iteras
                                0f</hi> relevancy <hi rend="superscript"> 1 t</hi> θ <hi
                                rend="superscript"> d</hi><hi rend="superscript"> &amp;</hi><hi
                                rend="superscript"> 1 u</hi> " <hi rend="superscript"> der</hi> °
                                <hi rend="superscript"> ne</hi> ° <hi rend="superscript"> τ other of
                                the above heads of</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>There is little doubt that this is a correct statement of the general principle
                    embodied in the decided cases of the law of England. Facts may be proved from
                    which legitimate inferences may be drawn as to the existence of the facts
                    disputed at the trial, and this inference depends on the existence of a causal
                    connexion between the two sets of facts. The theory of relevancy thus becomes,
                    as Sir James Stephen (Indian Evidence Act) has pointed out, a particular case of
                    the general theory of induction; and the question whether facts are relevant to
                    each other or not may become co-extensive with the entire field of human
                    knowledge. Bentham has pointed out, in his chapter on “Real evidence, or
                    evidence from things” <hi rend="italic">{Rationale of Judicial Evidence,</hi>
                    book v. c. 3), that</p>
                <p>“There is scarce an imaginable distinction or observation an indication of which
                    could, with reference to the subject of the present work, be charged with being
                    altogether irrelevant; for in one way or other, and even in each instance in
                    various ways, there is not an imaginable fact the existence of which is not
                    capable of being taken for the subject of inquiry in a court of judicature. If,
                    therefore, the whole encyclopaedia were to be crowded into the body of this
                    work, and into this part of it in particular, there is not a page of it that
                    would, strictly speaking, be irrelevant with regard to the subject of this
                    work.”</p>
                <p>It is perhaps hardly necessary to give instances in illustration of the general
                    definition of things relevant. The conduct of a person charged with an offence
                    is one of the most common and the most obvious cases. Thus, “any fact which
                    supplies a motive for such an act, or which constitutes preparation for it, any
                    subsequent conduct of such person which appears to have been influenced by any
                    such act, and any act done in consequence of any such act by or by the authority
                    of that person,” may obviously lead to inferences as to the act itself. One of
                    Sir James Stephen’s illustrations may be cited :—</p>
                <p>“The question is whether A wrote an anonymous letter threatening B, and requiring
                    B to meet the writer at a certain time and place to satisfy his demands. The
                    fact that A met B at that time and place is relevant, as conduct subsequent to
                    and affected by a fact in issue (an effect of that cause). The fact that A had a
                    reason unconnected with his letter is relevant as rebutting the inference
                    suggested by his presence (the effect of another cause. )”</p>
                <p>The limit of relevancy is sometimes expressed by the saying that collateral facts
                    are not admissible in evidence unless pertinent to the issue, but, as usual, we
                    are left to collect the meaning of collateral from the decided cases. The
                    typical case is perhaps that of Holcombe <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> Hewson (2
                    Campbell, 391), where, on a question whether the beer supplied by plaintiff to
                    defendant was good, the plaintiff was not allowed toprove that the beer he
                    supplied to his other customers was good. In Phillips <hi rend="italic">On
                        Evidenced</hi> is stated that an admission by a prisoner that he had
                    committed a similar offence at another time ought not to be received in
                    evidence. To an enumeration of such cases Roscoe <hi rend="italic">(Evidence at
                        Nisi Prius,</hi> p. 89) adds generally that all proof of facts which merely
                    tends to create an unjust prejudice, or unduly to influence the jury, or occupy
                    tbe time of the court in irrelevant inquiries, is inadmissible; but if the proof
                    be directly or indirectly pertinent to the issue, it will be admitted;—which
                    seems to come to this, that mere similarity in circumstances or coincidence in
                    time will not make one fact relevant to another unless some causal connexion
                    between them is made apparent. Thus, in the beer case above mentioned, the
                    evidence might have been made relevant by showing that the beer supplied to all
                    the customers was the same. Sir James Stephen’s <hi rend="italic">Digest</hi>
                    contains several headings of exceptions to the rule excluding collateral
                    evidence, but they will be found, we think, to be all cases of the general rule
                    of relevancy Some bond of connexion, as cause and effect, will be found to have
                    been established between them. Thus, when the intention of an act is in question
                    (as in the case of a man accused of setting fire to his house in order to get
                    insurance money), other instances of similar acts (as that the prisoner had
                    previously had two houses burnt, each being insured, and the insurance having
                    been paid) may be adduced.</p>
                <p>But it must not be supposed that the law admits as evidence all facts which are,
                    in a strictly logical sense, relevant. The most considerable and important
                    exception is that of <hi rend="italic">hearsay evidence.</hi> In ordinary life
                    we should regard a statement made to us at second hand not only as relevant to
                    the fact it asserts, but as sufficient and satisfactory proof, if both of our
                    informants are persons of creditable character and intelligence. In point of
                    fact, the immense bulk of our knowledge and belief on all sorts of subjects is
                    founded on hearsay evidence, many times more remote than in the case we have
                    supposed. The general rule of law excludes all such evidence. “The fact that a
                    statement was made by a person not called as a witness is not regarded as
                    relevant to the truth of the matter asserted thereby.” The reason is
                    sufficiently obvious. A deponent in court tells his story under securities for
                    its truthfulness. He may be cross-examined. He may be punished for telling lies.
                    But for these securities it would hardly be safe, considering the consequences
                    attaching to every issue in a court of justice, to act upon any testimony
                    whatever. These securities do not exist in the case of extra-judicial statements
                    by persons not called before the court, and accordingly, as a general rule, no
                    evidence can be offered regarding them. The extent, and perhaps the apparent
                    severity of the rule, may be illustrated by the case in which it was held that,
                    in a question of the validity of a will, the declaration of one attesting
                    witness, since deceased, that he forged it, cannot be offered in evidence.</p>
                <p>This rule, however, has its exceptions, which are classified in Stephen’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Digest</hi> under the heads of “admissions or confessions<pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n776/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0908-0776-0741"/>; statements by deceased declarant; evidence
                    given on a former occasion; statements made under special circumstances;
                    judgments of a court of justice.” An admission is defined to be a statement
                    suggesting any inference as to facts unfavourable to the conclusion contended
                    for by the person by whom or on whose behalf it is made, and may be given in
                    general in evidence against him. In civil actions, statements of this sort, made
                    without prejudice or on express condition that they are not to be used in
                    evidence, may not be admitted. An important class of admissions is that of
                    confessions in criminal cases. A voluntary confession may be used in evidence
                    against a prisoner, but a confession caused by “any inducement, threat, or
                    promise, proceeding from a person in authority,” is not admissible. But a
                    confession made under promise of secrecy, or in consequence of deception, may be
                    used in evidence. Dying declarations, made in immediate prospect of death, are
                    ad-missable in trials for the murder or manslaughter of the deceased.
                    Declarations made in the ordinary course of business or duty by deceased persons
                    are admitted as relevant to the matter to which they relate. And a declaration
                    by a deceased person is admissible “if he had peculiar means of knowing the
                    matter stated, if he had no interest to misrepresent, and if it was opposed to
                    his proprietary interest.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>In the leading case of Higham <hi rend="italic">ν.</hi> Ridgway, an
                            entry in the book of a deceased man-midwife, stating the birth of a
                            child on a certain day and the <hi rend="italic">payment</hi> of his fee
                            for attendance, was admitted in evidence to prove the birth on that day.
                            The acknowledgment of payment was held to be “against the declarant’s
                            interest,” and rendered the whole statement admissible. The distinctions
                            made by judges in cases of declarations by persons deceased nιn very
                            fine. A declaration made by a person in the course of his business or
                            duty will not let in anything but the statement it was his duty to make.
                            Thus a declaration by a deceased sheriff ’ s officer as to the time and
                            place of an arrest effected by him was admitted so far only as the <hi
                                rend="italic">time</hi> was concerned, because it was not his
                            official duty to make a note of the <hi rend="italic">place.</hi> If,
                            however, the statement had contained such a note as “received for the
                            same five shillings” (which would be a statement against interest), the
                            evidence as to place would have been admitted. Again, in the Sussex
                            Peerage case, it was held that a declaration made by a clergyman that he
                            had performed a marriage under circumstances which would make him liable
                            to pecuniary penalties was held not to be a “statement against interest”
                            within the meaning of the rule. On the other hand, a statement made by a
                            tenant that he paid rent for his house was -held to be admissible as
                            against interest, because it rebutted the presumption founded on the
                            fact of possession that it belonged to him in fee simple. The tendency
                            of judicial decisions since the principal case (Higham <hi rend="italic"
                                >ν.</hi> Ridgway) has been to limit the operation of the rule. In a
                            recent case, however (Leyden <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> Lord St
                            Leonards), the judges expressed an opinion that the best rule would be
                            to admit all declarations made by deceased persons, where they had
                            peculiar means of knowing the fact testified, and had no interest to
                            misrepresent it.</p></note> Declarations relating to public rights or
                    customs by competent persons may be used in evidence after their death. In
                    pedigree cases, statements by deceased blood-relations, made before litigation,
                    are to be admitted. The statutes 11 and 12 Vict. c. 42 and 30 and 31 Vict. c. 35
                    allow depositions of deceased witnesses to be used in certain criminal cases. In
                    civil cases the evidence of a deceased witness may be used at a subsequent trial
                    raising the same issues. Among the miscellaneous cases of admissible hearsay
                    evidence may be mentioned facts of a public nature recited in statutes and
                    proclamations. entries in public records, and statements in maps, and plans, and
                    accredited historical works. Judgments are conclusive proof of “the state of
                    things which they effect,” and as between parties of the facts actually in
                    issue.</p>
                <p>Another instance of departure from the logical theory of relevancy is the
                    evidence of opinion. The general rule, as enunciated by Stephen <hi
                        rend="italic">(Digest,</hi> part i. c. 5), is “that the fact that any person
                    is of opinion that a fact in issue or relevant to the issue does or does not
                    exist is not regarded as relevant to the existence of such fact.” A distinction,
                    which Sir J. Stephen does not notice, must be drawn between two senses in which
                    the word opinion may be used. In common parlance, the belief of a scientific
                    witness on some technical point, and the belief of an ordinary witness as to
                    some fact perceived by himself, would with equal propriety be described as
                    opinion. And it would not be difficult to show that psychologically they are the
                    same thing. The opinion in each case is the result of a process of reasoning. In
                    each case one reasons from a number of facts to a conclusion. The belief of a
                    witness in a question of personal identity is based on a number of facts as to
                    which he has no doubt, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                        t</hi> the size, the build, the gait, the clothes of the person in question.
                    The law, however, draws a broad distinction between this kind of inference and
                    the open and deliberate inference as to matters not directly perceived by the
                    senses. It distinguishes between facts and inferences, holding in disregard of
                    psychology that the former are directly perceived; but it does not insist upon
                    absolute certainty in the perception. A witness may “believe” or “think” or “be
                    of opinion” that he saw A. on a given day, or he may say positively that he did
                    see him. The strength of his persuasion will be considered by the tribunal, but
                    his evidence will not be rejected because his persuasion is weak. Or, as Mr
                    Taylor puts it, “the law does not require him to speak with such expression of
                    certainty as to exclude all doubt.” By opinion then is meant not merely a lower
                    degree of persuasion, a more feeble belief, but a belief held as the result of
                    inference and not of direct perception. There is nothing in the feebleness with
                    which a witness's belief in the existence of a fact is expressed or held to make
                    it irrelevant. But as a general rule, opinion in the other sense is not
                    admissible in evidence at all. It is the business of the tribunal of the jury to
                    form such opinions for themselves. Indeed, the exclusion of opinion in evidence
                    is put on this very ground in some of the decided cases. Thus, in an insurance
                    case, a new trial was granted because the opinion of a witness had been admitted
                    as to whether the communication of particular facts would have varied the terms
                    of the policy—the court holding that this was a question for the jury alone. But
                    the general rule has its exceptions, which may almost all be included “in the
                    opinion of experts.” In matters of science and skill requiring special study and
                    education, the opinion of persons so qualified (experts) may be given in
                    evidence. The law of a foreign country, and the examination of hand-writing, are
                    among such matters. But an expert cannot give an opinion as to the existence of
                    the facts oil which his opinion is based, although of course he may testify to
                    them if he has perceived them himself. Iu thus excluding opinion on all but
                    technical subjects, the law is stricter than the logic of ordinary life. The
                    opinion of others tells for something in the formation of our own opinions, and
                    no doubt ought to tell for something. This, however, is not the place for an
                    examination of the influence of authority in matters of reasoning. It is
                    sufficient to point out that in law it is reduced to a minimum.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">How facts that may be given in evidence are to be
                        proved.—</hi> First of all we must set aside a considerable class of facts
                    which need not be proved, because they are already supposed to be known to the
                    court. The judge takes “judicial notice” of them. These are for the most part
                    facts relating to the constitution, including, of course, the entire body of law
                    administered in all the courts of the country, from whatever source it may be
                    derived. The courts will also take judicial notice of the accession and sign
                    manual of the queen and her successors, of the existence and title of every
                    state and sovereign recognized by her Majesty, of the names, titles, functions,
                    signatures, Ac., of the judges of the supreme court, of the great seal, privy
                    seal, seals of the courte of justice, and of certain <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n777/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0908-0777-0742"/> corporations, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> of
                    London, of the universities, also of the beginning and termination of war, and
                    the articles of war, the extent of her majesty’s dominions, the divisions of
                    time, the meaning of English words, &amp;c. (see Stephen’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Digest,</hi> pt. ii. c. 7.) And, of course, facts which have been admitted
                    for the purposes of the trial by the parties or their agents need not be proved.
                    All other facts must be proved, either by oral or documentary evidence. Oral
                    evidence is the testimony of a witness delivered before the court as to what he
                    has himself actually seen or heard. All facts <hi rend="italic">may</hi> be
                    proved by oral evidence, except in some special cases where the law requires
                    documentary evidence. A “document,” in this sense, extends to any record,
                    whether expressed in writing or symbols, and no matter what may be the nature of
                    the substance on which it is recorded. A gold watch with an inscription on it,
                    or a tombstone, is a document.</p>
                <p>The most important rule in this branch of the subject is that which requires the
                    contents of a document to be proved by the document itself. The law requires the
                    “best evidence” procurable in each case, and if a document is in existence it is
                    better evidence than any second-hand account of its contents. This is called
                    primary evidence. But secondary evidence, either by means of written copies or
                    oral accounts, is to be admitted in certain casee. If it· is proved that the
                    instrument has been lost or destroyed, or that it is in the hands of the
                    opposite party, who, after notice, has refused to produce it, then “secondary”
                    evidence of its contents may be given. So when the original is of such a nature
                    that it cannot be easily moved (as, <hi rend="italic">β.g.,</hi> a libel written
                    on a wall), secondary evidence may be given. Secondary evidence includes
                    (besides oral accounts by persons who have seen the original)—(1) examined
                    copies, exemplifications, office copies, and certified copies; (2) other copies
                    made from the original and proved to be correct; (3) counterparts of documents
                    as against the parties who did not execute them (Stephen, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Digest,</hi> part ii., c. 9). Public documents in general must be proved
                    either by the production of the original or by the official copies in class (1)
                    above. Stephen states the rule requiring documentary evidence in special cases
                    as follows :—“When any judgment of any court or any other judicial or official
                    proceeding, or any contract or grant, or any other disposition of property, has
                    been reduced to the form of a document or a series of documents, no evidence may
                    be given except the document itself, or secondary evidence” where such is
                    admissible. The importance of this rule with reference to contracts will be at
                    once apparent. When the contract has been reduced to writing, parole (or oral)
                    evidence cannot be admitted to prove its contents. The writing itself, or
                    secondary evidence, must be produced, and no variation of its terms can be
                    proved by oral evidence. Thus, where goods were insured generally in ships from
                    a particular port, and the ship in which they were shipped was lost, evidence
                    could not be given that that particular ship was excepted from the policy. Γhe
                    mere fact that a memorandum was made, not intended to have effect as a contract,
                    will not exclude oral evidence of the transaction. And certain facts, collateral
                    to the contract, may be proved by oral evidence. Thus fraud, or want of
                    consideration, or any circumstances which would affect its validity, may be so
                    proved.</p>
                <p>Of course, in the interpretation of contracts containing doubtful, technical, or
                    unintelligible expressions, or using common words in a non-natural sense,
                    recourse must be had to oral evidence. Thus the expression a “bale of gambier,’
                    in a written contract, may be proved by verbal evidence to mean a compressed
                    package weighing two cwt. And where the expression “ten thousand rabbits”
                    occurred in a lease, evidence to show that a thousand, in relation to rabbits,
                    meant twelve hundred, was admitted. But when the document is utterly unmeaning
                    (as where a legacy is left to ), oral evidence cannot be resorted to for the
                    purpose of supplying a meaning. Where more than one meaning is possible,
                    reference may be to the surrounding circumstances, or the fact to which the
                    document was or may have been intended to refer. These rules, it need hardly be
                    said, apply only as between parties, and where the legal rights and obligations
                    dependent on the instrument are in question.</p>
                <p>Certain presumptions <hi rend="italic">(j.e.</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                        f</hi> conclusions of fact adopted until they are disproved) relating to
                    documents may be mentioned here. Thus a document is presumed to have been
                    executed on the day on which it bears date. Again, where a document is not
                    produced after due notice, it is presumed to have been duly stamped. And it is a
                    most important presumption w ith reference to documents purporting and proved to
                    be thirty years old, and produced from what appears to be the proper custody,
                    that the signatures, execution, and attestation are as they purport to be. Or,
                    as it is sometimes expressed, “when a deed is thirty years old, it proves
                    itself.” Alterations and interlineations in a deed are presumed to have been
                    made before execution; in a will they are presumed to have been made afterwards.
                    The nature of such presumptions is explained below.</p>
                <p>One more rule with regard to documentary evidence may be added. When the law
                    requires an instrument to be attested <hi rend="italic">(e.g.,</hi> a will), it
                    cannot be used in evidence unless one attesting witness is called to prove its
                    execution, if there be an attesting witness alive and capable of giving
                    evidence. If there be no such witness, the signature of at least one attesting
                    witness, and of the person executing the deed, must be proved to be in their
                    respective handwritings. This rule was said by Lord Ellenborough to be as
                    “fixed, formal, and universal as any that can be stated in a court of justice.”
                    It formerly extended to all documents actually attested, not merely to those
                    required to be attested by law.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Burden of proof, competency of witnesses, &lt;c∙c.—</hi> The
                    general rule is that the burden of proof lies on the person who asserts the
                    affirmative, or, as it is more accurately expressed by Sir J. Stephen, “whoever
                    desires any court to give judgment, as to any legal right or liability dependent
                    on the existence or non-existence of facts which he asserts or denies to exist,
                    must prove that these facts do or do not exist.” And the burden of proof, and
                    the right of beginning in an action, lie on the party against whom judgment
                    would be given if no evidence at all were offered in the case. Again, the effect
                    of a presumption <hi rend="italic">(presumptio</hi><hi rend="italic">facti,</hi>
                    as distinguished from <hi rend="italic">p&gt;resumptio juris</hi> or conclusive
                    proof) is to throw the burden of proof on the party who denies it as a matter of
                    fact. And here it may be convenient to say a word or two with reference to
                    presumptions. Writers on the law of evidence generally distinguish between
                    presumptions of law and presumptions of fact—the latter being, the former not
                    being, rebuttable by counter-evidence. The subject occupies a considerable space
                    in most books on evidence. Sir J. Stephen regards it as falling properly undeι
                    specific divisions of the substantive law. Thus the presumption that everybody
                    knows the law he regards as belonging to the criminal law and not to the law of
                    evidence. Presumptions of this sort <hi rend="italic">(presumptiones
                        juris</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">de jure,</hi> are au
                    indirect way of expressing some legal principle. In th&lt; last case the rule is
                    that ignorance of the law is no excus∙ for an illegal act, and the so-called
                    presumption looks lik&lt; an artificial and characteristic reason invented for
                    its ex planation. Presumptions of fact, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> conclusions
                    which 0∣ certain evidence must be adopted by the court until an unless they are
                    disproved by counter-evidence, are cases i which the task of inference is taken
                    out of the haud⅛ c <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n778/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0908-0778-0743"/> the jury altogether. They are strongly
                    objected to by Bentham <hi rend="italic">(Rationale of Judicial Evidence,</hi>
                    Introduction, c. 22) on this very ground. “On trial for a criminal offence,
                    amongst others murder, in this and that case the law presumes malice. Of the
                    presumption in this case, what is the plain English? That fearing that by a jury
                    the man would be acquitted, the determination of the judge is that he shall be
                    convicted.” If the presumption, however, is the safest conclusion to act on in
                    the circumstances, there would seem to be no harm in saving the jury the trouble
                    of drawing the inference for themselves.</p>
                <p>Besides these two classes of presumptions, and along with them, legal writers
                    often discuss the presumptions which are said to be within the province of the
                    jury itself. These are neither more nor less than various degrees of
                    probability, in cases of circumstantial evidence; thus the leading text book on
                    criminal practice (Archbold), following Coke and Blackstone, states that these
                    presumptions are of three kinds— <hi rend="italic">violent, probable,</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">light</hi> or <hi rend="italic">rash.</hi> A case of
                    violent presumption, generally given as an illustration, is where a person is
                    found in a house run through the body, and a man is seen running away with a
                    drawn sword in his hand, no other person being found about the premises. The
                    conclusion that this man is the murderer is irresistible. The other cases are
                    simply inferior degrees of probability established by circumstantial evidence,
                    the lowest degree being described as such that it ought to have no weight with
                    us at all. The distinctions are of no value, and are probably retained in text
                    books because they are described by the same name as the two classes of legal
                    presumptions above described—those, namely, which Sir J. Stephen distinguishes
                    as “conclusive proof” and “presumption” respectively.</p>
                <p>Presumptions of the second class abound in every branch of the law, and are to be
                    explained with reference to its peculiar principles. Of the more general
                    presumptions a number of examples have been collected in Stephen’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Digest,</hi> part iii. c. 14. One of the most common is the
                    presumption of death after seven years’· absence which has been a good deal
                    debated in the courts, but may now be considered to be settled. A person who has
                    not been heard of for seven years is presumed to be dead, unless the
                    circumstances are such as to account for his absence otherwise. But there is no
                    presumption as to his having been dead at any particular time, <hi rend="italic"
                        >e.g.,</hi> if a person was last heard of in 1860, the court in 1870
                    presumes that he is dead, but not that he was dead in 1867. The question of
                    survivorship, where two or more persons are shown to have perished by th.e same
                    catastrophe, as in cases of shipwreck, has been much discussed. It was at one
                    time thought that there might be a presumption of survivorship in favour of the
                    younger as against the older, of the male as against the female, &amp;c. But it
                    is now clear that there is no such presumption. Another common case is the
                    presumption of legitimacy in favour of persons born during the continuance of
                    lawful wedlock. The presumption of regularity in official proceedings <hi
                        rend="italic">(omnia esse rite acta)</hi> is also one of frequent
                    occurrence.</p>
                <p>The effect of presumptions may be compared with that of estoppel. The former
                    establishes against a party a conclusion which stands unless and until he
                    positively disproves it. By estoppel a party is prevented from disproving a fact
                    which he has actually or constructively asserted. For examples see article <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Estopγel.</hi></p>
                <p>With few exceptions all witnesses are now competent to testify in courts of
                    justice. The following are the chief exceptions :—(1) persons incapacitated by
                    extreme youth, or mental disease; and (2) in criminal cases the wife or husband
                    of a prisoner, except when the prosecution is for injury or violence to such
                    wife or husband. The old rules of exclusion have been noticed <hi rend="italic"
                        >supra.</hi></p>
                <p>Certain classes of facts are protected from disclosure on various grounds. Thus,
                    no person' can be compelled to disclose communications made to him by his wife
                    during marriage, and servants of the state cannot be compelled to give evidence
                    in official matters without the consent of the head of the department to which
                    they belong. But perhaps the most important case is that of communications
                    between lawyer and client. The lawyer is not allowed to disclose such
                    communications without the client’s assent, nor can the client be compelled to
                    disclose such communications himself. The rule, however, will not extend to
                    communications in furtherance of any crime or fraud. Medical men and clergymen
                    have no such privilege. There is, however, a general consensus of opinion in
                    favour of protecting confessions made by prisoners to their spiritual advisers;
                    and judges have from time to time expressed their reluctance to compel
                    disclosure in such cases. To this class also belongs the rule that no person can
                    be compelled to answer a question tending to criminate himself, although the
                    fact that the answer might expose him to a civil action will be no
                    protection.</p>
                <p>In some few cases the evidence of more than one witness is required. Thus, in
                    trials for treason, there must be at least two witnesses testifying to the same
                    act or to different acts of the same treason, except when the treason consists
                    in an attempt on the life or person of the queen. So in perjury, one witness,
                    unless corroborated by circumstances, will not be sufficient to convict the
                    prisoner. In actions for breach of promise of marriage, in affiliation cases,
                    and in prosecutions when the only witness is an accomplice, such corroboration
                    is also necessary. Otherwise in the law of England the testimony of one witness
                    is sufficient to prove any fact.</p>
                <p>The general rule is that testimony must be given on oath, but an oath is binding
                    if administered in any form which the witness declares to be binding. By recent
                    enactments, however, a person objecting on grounds of religious belief to the
                    taking of any oath may be permitted to make a solemn affirmation instead; and
                    any person who objects to take an oath, whether on religious grounds or not, or
                    is objected to as incompetent to take an oath, may ’ “solemnly promise and
                    declare.” In all cases the punishment of perjury attaches.</p>
                <p>At the trial a witness is first of all examined by the party producing him
                    (examination-in-chief); he is then cross-examined by the opposite party, and
                    re-examined by his own party. The re-examination must refer to matters arising
                    out of the cross-examination. There are certain questions which may be asked in
                    cross-examination only. Thus, in the examination-in-chief, leading questions <hi
                        rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> questions suggesting their own answer) are not
                    allowed; in cross-examination they are. So also in cross-examination a witness
                    may be asked any question tending to test his accuracy or credibility, or to
                    destroy his credit by injuring his character, and he must answer them, however
                    disgraceful may be the imputation they convey.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The unlimited licence of
                            cross-examination to character is the one flagrant abuse of the existing
                            law of evidence; and but for the restraint imposed upon counsel, partly
                            by public partly by professional opinion, would be a much more serious
                            evil than it is. The illustration in Stephen’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >Digest</hi> is a notorious but perfectly fair example. I he
                            question is whether A. committed perjury in swearing that be was R. I.
                            B. depones that he made tattoo marks on the arm of R. T., which at the
                            time of the trial were not and never had been on the arm of A. B. may be
                            asked and compelled to answer the question, whether .many years after
                            the alleged tattooing, and many years before the occasion on which he
                            was examined, he committed adultery with the wife of one of his
                            friends.” The Indian Evidence Act restricts the licence of
                            cross-examination by the following provisions :—(1) Such questions are
                            proper if they are of such a nature that the truth of the imputation
                            would seriously affect the opinion of the court as to the credibility of
                            the witness on the matter to which he testifies; (2) Such <pb
                                corresp="kp-eb0908-0779-0744" xml:id="pbn9744"/> questions are
                            Improper if the imputation would not affect, or would affect in a slight
                            degree, the opinion of the court as to the credibility of the witness on
                            the matter to which he testifies; (3) Such questions are improper if
                            there is a great disproportion between the importance of the imputation
                            made against the witness’s character and the importance of his
                            evidence,”</p></note> No <pb corresp="pbn9744"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n779/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0908-0779-0744"/> evidence, however, can be led to contradict
                    the answer in the latter case, unless it refer to a previous conviction, or to
                    circumstances tending to throw doubt on the impartiality of the witness. A
                    witness may in cross-examination, and a witness proving hostile or adverse to
                    the party calling him, may, in examination-in-chief, be asked whether he had not
                    on a former occasion made statements inconsistent with his present statements.
                    The credit of a witness may also be impeached by the other party calling
                    witnesses to swear that they believe him to be unworthy of belief, and
                    counter-evidence may be given in reply. The theory of the proceedings is that a
                    witness will tell his story in the most favourable way for the party calling him
                    and against his opponent.</p>
                <p>The improper admission or rejection of evidence was formerly a frequent ground
                    for applications for new trial; under the Judicature Act a new trial will only
                    be granted on such ground when some substantial wrong has been occasioned
                    thereby.</p>
                <p>The following are the most important writers on the law of evidence:—John Pitt
                    Taylor (two vols. 8vo, 6th edition, London, 1872); Henry Roscoe <hi
                        rend="italic">(Digest of the Law of Evidence on the trial of actions at Nisi
                        Prius,</hi> 13th edition, by Day and Powell, London, 1875); <hi
                        rend="italic">A.</hi> Μ. Best <hi rend="italic">(On the Principles of the
                        Law of Evidence, with elementary rules for the interrogation of
                        witnesses,</hi> 6th edition, London, 1875); Edmund Powell <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Principles and Practice of the Law of Evidence,</hi> 4th edition, London,
                    1875); Sir J. F. Stephen <hi rend="italic">(Digest of the Law of Evidence,</hi>
                    London, 1877); S. Greenleaf <hi rend="italic">(On the Law of Evidence,</hi> 3
                    vols. 13th edition, Boston, 1876). (E, R.)</p>
                <p>questions are Improper if the imputation would not affect, or would affect in a
                    slight degree, the opinion of the court as to the credibility of the witness on
                    the matter to which he testifies; (3) Such questions are improper if there is a
                    great disproportion between the importance of the imputation made against the
                    witness’s character and the importance of his evidence,”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
