<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0908-0838-0803-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EXHIBITIONS (9th edition, volume 8, page 803)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kn24">Glass</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:918096">Exhibitionism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:918123">Exhibitors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n838/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EXHIBITIONS</label>. National and International Exhibitions
                    may be ranked among the most remarkable features in the industrial records of
                    the world, and have taken their place as prominent instruments of civilization,
                    for by their means the diffusion of knowledge has been advanced and extended in
                    the most wonderful manner.</p>
                <p>It is to the Society of Arts that the credit is due of having originated national
                    exhibitions. So far back as the year 1761 that body offered prizes for
                    agricultural and other machines, and had an exhibition of these in its
                    apartments. In 1798 France began a series of national expositions under the
                    direction of Napoleon. The exhibitors at first numbered only 110, and a jury of
                    niue was appointed to decide upon their merits. A gold medal was offered to the
                    manufacturer who should deal the heaviest blow to English trade. The second
                    exposition took place in 1801, and was so successful that the third was fixed to
                    take place in 1802. Expositions were subsequently held in 1806, 1819, 1823,
                    1827, 1834, 1839, 1844, and in 1849, in which year there were 4494 exhibitors.
                    This last was the conclusion of the purely national displays in France before
                    the great London international exhibition of 1851. So exclusive were the French
                    at that time that a proposal made for the representation of foreign products in
                    1849 was deemed by the minister of commerce to have emanated from the enemies of
                    French industry.</p>
                <p>In 1820 a series of exhibitions were opened in various cities of Austria, and
                    national exhibitions were held at Vienna in 1835, 1839, and 1845, which last had
                    1865 exhibitors. In Germany there were national exhibitions at Berlin in 1822
                    and 1827, and in 1844 one with 3060 exhibitors. National exhibitions were held
                    in Saxony between 1824 and 1845, in which last year there were 6013 exhibitors.
                    Between 1837 and 1848 exhibitions were held at Lausanne, Berne, St Gall, and
                    Zurich in Switzerland; between 1835 and 1850 at Brussels and Ghent in Belgium;
                    between 1823 and 1844 at Stockholm in Sweden; between 1829 and 1849 at St
                    Petersburg, Moscow, and Warsaw in Russia; between 1844 and 1849 at Lisbon in
                    Portugal; between 1829 and 1855 in the kingdom of Sardinia; between 1827 and
                    1850 at Madrid; between 1828 and 1844 at New York and Washington in the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>In the United Kingdom industrial displays had to fight their way against much
                    apathy and prejudice. In 1828 an exhibition was formed in London under the
                    patronage of George IV., which dragged out an unfortunate existence till 1833,
                    when it was consigned to oblivion as an unsuccessful bazaar. In Ireland
                    exhibitions of native industry were held triennially in the rooms of the Royal
                    Dublin Society, commencing in 1829. In 1845, however, an exhibition of
                    manufactures held in Covent Garden, London, proved a great success; and in 1849
                    an exposition of industry was held at Birmingham, which was the most complete of
                    any held till that time in the country.</p>
                <p>After various proposals made by the Society of Arts between 1846 and 1849, it was
                    held that the great object of an international exhibition of industry was more
                    likely to be carried out than hitherto, and at last a royal commission was
                    issued to take steps for an industrial exhibition to be held in 1851. The
                    commissioners received a site of upwards of 18 acres in Hyde Park, and erected
                    the building known as the “Crystal Palace,” from the designs of Mr (afterwards
                    Sir) Joseph Paxton. Its general plan was a parallelogram 1848 feet long by 408
                    feet wide. There was also a projection on the north side 936 feet long, the
                    whole covering a space of 1,000,000 square feet. The exhibition had four great
                    departments,—raw material, machinery, manufactures, fine arts,—which were
                    subdivided into 30 classes; and this arrangement has been usually followed in
                    the great exhibitions since held. In allocating the space for the display of
                    objects one-half was given to England and the colonies, the other half to
                    foreign countries. The estimated value of the articles exhibited, excluding the
                    famous Koh-i-noor diamond, was £1,781,929. This exhibition was opened on 1st May
                    by Queen Victoria in person, and w as closed on I lth October following, and the
                    receipts exceeded the expenditure by a sum of £213,305. The building was
                    afterwards removed to Sydenham, where it forms the main part of the present
                    “Crystal Palace.”</p>
                <p>The success of the Great Exhibition of 1851 encouraged the repetition of similar
                    displays all over the world, a list of which will be found in the table given
                    below.</p>
                <p>In 1855 the great Paris international exhibition was held, which was opened by
                    the emperor of the French on 17th May. The buildings for this exhibition were of
                    various kinds. There were the palais d’industrie, the palais des beaux arts, and
                    the panorama; erections were afterwards added for agricultural implements,
                    carriages, minor articles, &amp;c. The main building, which was of. stone,
                    brick, and glass, was only 800 feet long by 350 feet wide. This exposition
                    brought together an assemblage of objects in the industrial and fine arts such
                    as had never been seen before. The distinguishing feature of the palais
                    d’industrie was its collection of the works of living artists, while the London
                    exhibition of 1851 was principally a display of manufactured goods. The
                    exposition was closed on the 15 th November, when the distribution of medals to
                    about 12,000 exhibitors took place.</p>
                <p>In 1862 the second great English international exhibition was held in London in
                    an immense brick erection adjoining the gardens of the Horticultural Society at
                    South Kensington. The building consisted of two vast domes of glass, 250 feet
                    high and 60 feet in diameter, larger than the dome of St Peter’s, connected by a
                    nave 800 feet long, 100 feet high, and 83 feet wide, with a closed roof lighted
                    by a range of windows after the manner of the clerestory of a Gothic cathedral.
                    The domes opened laterally into spacious transepts, and the nave into a wide
                    central avenue and interminable side aisles and galleries roofed with glass.
                    These apartments occupied 16 acres, but in addition there were two <hi
                        rend="italic">annexes</hi> which covered 7∣ acres. The ceremonial with which
                    this exhibition was inaugurated on 1st May was the most imposing public pageant
                    which had been seen in Britain for many years. The number of exhibitors iu the
                    industrial division was 26,348, besides 2305 in art, making in all 28,653. The
                    fine art collection was very extensive, comprising 901 pieces of sculpture, 1275
                    engravings, 983 architectural designs, and no less than 3370 paintings. The
                    classification of the objects was based upon that of 1851, and embraced 36
                    divisions, in addition to those of the fine arts.</p>
                <p>In April 1867∙a great international <hi rend="italic">exposition</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">universelle</hi> was opened in Paris in an immense oval
                    building erected in the Champ de Mars. It was arranged in twelve concentric
                    aisles, with a small open central garden. It covered no less than 37 acres, and
                    the total number of exhibitors was 42,000. It was intended to bring into notice
                    all the resources which industry can create for satisfying the requirements of
                    mankind, and it was divided primarily into groups corresponding with the leading
                    wants of the human family. A great feature was the display of actual examples of
                    the styles of dbmestic and palatial architecture of most <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n839/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0908-0839-0804"/> countries, even the tents of some of the
                    nomad tribes, such as the Kirghis Tartars, Samoyeds, Bedouin Arabs, &amp;c.,
                    being exhibited. In addition, all kinds of civil and military erections of
                    general importance were represented.</p>
                <p>In May 1873 an international exhibition was opened in the Imperial Park at
                    Vienna. The building in which it was held was of enormous size, covering about
                    40 acres. The principal part of the edifice was a grand nave nearly 1000 yards
                    long, in the midst of which rose a vast rotunda or dome of great height. In this
                    part of the building objects of a trophy character were exhibited, and presented
                    a <hi rend="italic">coup cl</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">oβil</hi> of surpassing
                    grandeur. An immense number of prizes and diplomas were distributed, and the
                    awards were shared by almost every nation in the world. This exhibition was
                    closed in November 1873. It was not a success financially, there being a
                    considerable deficit in the receipts. The building has been converted into a
                    national museum.</p>
                <p>In 1876, after five years of preparation, the great international exhibition of
                    America, a centennial celebration of the Declaration of Independence, was opened
                    in Fairmount Park, Philadelphia, on the 10th of May. The main building was in
                    the form of a parallelogram extending east and west, 1880 feet in length and 464
                    feet in width. Its central span, in which was situated the grand avenue, was
                    1832 feet long by 120 feet wide, being the longest of such a width ever
                    introduced into an exhibition building. The greater portion of the structure was
                    one story high, the interior height being 70 feet. In the centre were four
                    square towers 120 feet high. The frame work was of iron, filled in with glass
                    and wood; it covered 20Ό2 acres. With the other buildings attached to the
                    exhibition, a total space of 60 acres were covered. Besides the main building
                    there were the machinery hall, the horticultural hall (built in a Moorish
                    style), the agricultural hall, the memorial hall or art gallery, the Government
                    building, covering about 2 acres, in which were illustrated the functions of the
                    Government in time of peace and its resources as a war power. Besides these
                    there were the women’s pavilion, the judges’ hall, and a great many smaller
                    erections, including a Swedish schoolhouse, a timber-framed house somewhat in
                    the style of the 16th century, which formed the head-quarters of the British
                    commission. A structure having the homely designation of “department of public
                    comfort” was used as a place of rest and convenience. The total number of
                    buildings within the inclosure was over 160, and their cost was £1,600,000. The
                    number of exhibitors was 60,000, derived from 37 nations. The promenades in the
                    main building were 25 miles in length.</p>
                <p>In England, after the great displays of 1851 and 1862 a feeling began to gain
                    ground that as the activity and ingenuity of manufacturers and designers were
                    constantly directed to fresh efforts, universal expositions would attain such
                    gigantic proportions as to become quite unmanageable. A resolution was therefore
                    come to by the British commissioners, as trustees of the fund derived from the
                    proceeds of the great exhibition of 1851, that the objects suitable for
                    exhibition should be divided into groups, and that exhibitions of selections
                    from these groups should be held at more frequent intervals. A plan was then
                    arranged for a series of exhibitions of the fine arts, recent scientific
                    inventions and discoveries, and two or three branches only of manufactures,
                    providing at the same time for the representation of each distinct manufacture
                    once in ten years. Exhibitions were accordingly held in 1871, 1872, 1873, and
                    1874, but at last it was found that they lost the attractiveness of novelty, and
                    failed to draw the multitude of sight-seers who flocked to the great exhibitions
                    of 1851 and 1862.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding these views of the British commissioners, an <hi rend="italic"
                        >Exposition</hi><hi rend="italic">Universelle</hi> on a great scale was
                    opened in Paris on 1st May 1878 by the President, Marshal MacMahon. It is
                    expected to unite the civilized world, as the sciences are represented as well
                    as the arts. The building, or Industrial Palace, is an enormous erection in the
                    Champ de Mars, consisting of a series of rectangular galleries in which each
                    country has been allotted a division more or less important. Besides the main
                    building, there are about a dozen <hi rend="italic">annexes</hi> without the <hi
                        rend="italic">enceinte</hi> of the palace. Immediately across the Seine
                    there is a second palace situated in the Trocadero (so named from a Spanish fort
                    in the harbour of Cadiz, captured in 1823), amidst ornamental gardens with
                    cascades. This is devoted to the fine arts and music, and is to remain a
                    permanent monument of the exhibition. It contains a music gallery even larger
                    than the Albert Hall, London. The space occupied by the exhibition is about 140
                    English acres; and the total expense has been announced by the minister of
                    commerce as about £1,800,000 sterling.</p>
                <p>An international exhibition is proposed to be held in 1879 at Melbourne, a city
                    which in 1851 was a town of but 20,000 inhabitants.</p>
                <p>Of the London Great Exhibition of 1851 an official catalogue was published the
                    same year in 4 vols. 8vo, and in 1852 a volume of reports by the juries on the
                    subjects in the 30 classes into which the exhibition was divided, in royal 8vo.
                    A sumptuous edition of this catalogue on large paper was printed, of which
                    copies were presented to distinguished personages and public libraries. Of the
                    exhibition of 1862 an illustrated catalogue was printed by the commissioners the
                    same year in 4 vols. 8vo. Of the Paris exposition held in 1855 there was an
                    official catalogue published the same year; and a <hi rend="italic">Rapport sur
                        l’Exposition Universelle</hi> (also published) was presented by Prince
                    Napoleon to the emperor in 1857. Of the exposition of 1867 there was published
                    in London the same year a translation from the proof-sheets of the French
                    official catalogue. Of the Vienna exhibition of 1873 there was an official
                    illustrated general catalogue, with a large number of reports of the juries,
                    &amp;c. Of the Philadelphia exhibition there was an official catalogue printed
                    in four languages— English, French, German, and Spanish; a series of reports and
                    awards under the different groups into which the exhibition was divided is now
                    being published. Besides the general catalogues of the great international
                    exhibitions, there have been published an immense number of catalogues of the
                    exhibits of the different countries at each, which are to be found available for
                    reference in the South Kensington and other industrial museums. Various
                    beautifully illustrated books, representing the works of art exhibited, have
                    been published both in London and Paris; and one, <hi rend="italic">Études sur
                        l'Exposition de</hi> 1878, intended to be a complete record of the progress
                    made in all the arts up to the present date, is about to be issued under the
                    direction of E. Lacroix.</p>
                <p>The following table shows the statistics of the first six great international
                    exhibitions :— «</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Acres.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Exhibitors.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Cost.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Days open.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Receipts.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Number of Visitors.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>London of 1851</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>21</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>17,000</p><p>21,779</p><p>28,653</p><p>50,226</p><p>42,584</p><p>60,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>£292,794</p><p>1,000,000</p><p>460,000</p><p>800,000 2,200,000
                                1,600,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>144</p><p>200</p><p>171</p><p>217</p><p>186</p><p>159</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>£506,100</p><p>128,099</p><p>408,530</p><p>420,735</p><p>206,470</p><p>762,744</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6,039,195</p><p>5,162,330</p><p>6,211,103
                                10,200,000</p><p>7,254.687</p><p>9,910,966</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Paris of 1855</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24⅜</p><p>23⅛</p><p>37</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>London of 1862</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Paris of 1867</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Vienna of 1873</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Philadelphia of 1876</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>60</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n840/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0840-0805"/>
                <p>The following table shows the minor exhibitions which have been held in various
                    parts of the world from 1852 to the present time (1878) :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1852</p><p>1853</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Exhibition of Irish arts and manufactures. Do. do. with those of
                                other countries.</p><p>Industrial exhibition, which cost £200,000.
                                Native industry</p><p>Do. do</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Dublin</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>New York</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>New Brunswick... Madras</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1854</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Madrid</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Industrial arts.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Munich</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>German industry.</p><p>Norwegian arts and
                                manufactures.</p><p>Belgian arts.</p><p>Exhibition of Art
                                Manufacture Association.</p><p>Art treasures exhibition.</p><p>Swiss
                                arts and manufactures; 2050 exhibitors. Italian
                                industry.</p><p>American industry</p><p>Exhibition, with 296
                                exhibitors</p><p>Products of 12 northern departments of
                                France.</p><p>National exhibition, with 947
                                exhibitors.</p><p>Russian products.</p><p>1 Fine art in Tuscany and
                                Italian silk goods.</p><p><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> Dutch
                                industries.</p><p>Exhibition of articles of common
                                use.</p><p>Exhibition preliminary to London great exhibition of
                                1862.</p><p>Turkish produce, and foreign machinery</p><p>Dutch
                                produce, art, and industry.</p><p>Industries connected witlι corn
                                and wine.</p><p>Local art and industry.</p><p>Principally
                                agriculture</p><p>Do. do.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1856</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Christiania</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Brussels</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Edinburgh</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1857</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Manchester</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Bern</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1858</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Sardinia</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>New York</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1859</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Hanover</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Rouen</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Athens</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1860</p><p>1861</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>St Petersburg</p><p>Florence</p><p>Haarlem</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Brussels</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1863</p><p>1864</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Victoria -</p><p>Constantinople....</p><p>Amsterdam</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Bayonne</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Malta</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Calcutta</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Lucknow</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>London</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>First working men’s exhibition.</p><p>Arts and manufactures,
                                attracted 900,000 visitors. Agriculture and
                                horticulture.</p><p>International fishery
                                exhibition</p><p>Industrial exhibition.</p><p>Arts, manufactures,
                                and agriculture; 3911 exhibitors.</p><p>Colonial
                                produce.</p><p>Metals and trades.</p><p>Working men's industrial
                                exhibition.</p><p>Do. do.</p><p>Exhibition of industry, with 1451
                                exhibitors.</p><p>American produce.</p><p>Scandinavian
                                industries.</p><p>Raw produce, with 2590
                                exhibitors.</p><p>Intercolonial exhibition, rich in specimens of
                                minerals.</p><p>working men's exhibition.</p><p>Fishery
                                exhibition.</p><p>Industries of N.W provinces of
                                India.</p><p>International maritime exhibition.</p><p>Products of
                                Chili.</p><p>South London industrial classes
                                exhibition.</p><p>Netherland Society of Manufacturers; rich in
                                objects of domestic economy.</p><p>Exhibition of drawing
                                implements.</p><p>Italian products.</p><p>Russian industrial
                                exhibition.</p><p>Indian cotton.</p><p>Intercolonial exhibition,
                                with J914 exhibitors. Workmen’s international
                                exhibition.</p><p>First annual international exhibition at
                            South</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1865</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Dublin</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Cologne</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Boulogne</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Sieιτa Leone</p><p>Οροιίο <hi rend="italic">J</hi></p><p>Dunedin,
                                New &gt;</p><p>Zealand j</p><p>Birmingham</p><p>Vienna</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>London</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Stettin</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1866 <hi rend="subscript"> z</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Philadelphia</p><p>Stockholm</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>.. 1</p><p>1867</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Brazil, Rio de )</p><p>Janeiro
                            f</p><p>Melbourne</p><p>London</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>The Hague</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Agra</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1868</p><p>1869</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Havre</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Santiago</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>London</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1870</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Amsterdam!</p><p>Berlin</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Turin</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>«</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>St Petersburg</p><p>Gujerat</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Sydney</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>London</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1871</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Do J</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Milan</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Kensington.</p><p>Exhibition of selected branches of
                                industry.</p><p>International maritime exhibition.</p><p>Second
                                annual international exhibition.</p><p>Irish native produce and fine
                                arts.</p><p>Scandinavian art and industry; 4000 exhibitors.
                                Agriculture, Industrial products, and works of art.</p><p>Exhibition
                                on celebration of second centenary of Peter the Great, illustrative
                                of the progress of Russia in manufactures.</p><p>Products of South
                                America.</p><p>Third annual international exhibition.</p><p>Fourth
                                and last annual international exhibition Exhibition of fungi; 7000
                                specimens shown Industrial art.</p><p>Agricultural machines and
                                implements. Exhibition of needlework in Albert Hall. Exhibition of
                                bees, their produce, hives, and</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Naples</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1872</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>London</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Dublin</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>«</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Copenhagen ..</p><p>Lyons <hi rend="italic">J</hi></p><p>Moscow ..
                                5</p><p>Bogota</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1873</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>London.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Do</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1874</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Aberdeen</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Brussels</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1875</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Paris</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1876</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>London</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Do J</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Paris</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>bee furniture, in Alexandra palace. Applications of
                                electricity.</p><p>Exhibition of art and industry, and local
                                antiquities.</p><p>Exhibition of life-saving and hygienic apparatus.
                                Exhibition of silks, bronzes, casques, wearingapparel, Λc., being
                                the fifth of a series since 1872.</p><p>Loan collection of
                                scientific apparatus.</p><p>Caxton exhibition, illustrative of the
                                art of</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>’’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Thurso 1</p><p>Brussels</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1877</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Kioto, Japan....</p><p>London</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Do I</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Do I</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>printing.</p><p>westminster and Pimlico working classes
                            in-</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Cape Town -'</p><p>Hamburg</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>dustrial exhibition.</p><p>Intel-national exhibition of
                                manufactures of all kinds.</p><p>International dairy
                                exhibition.</p><p>Exhibition of Industrial Art.</p><p>International
                                exhibition. (J. SM.)</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Ghent</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1878</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ballarat</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
