<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0582-0561-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ESTHONIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 8, page 561</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205503">Finland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1000943">Livonians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1353199">Grammar</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198506">Mark</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1124682">Soils</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7f10g">Esthonians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qr5b">Livonians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45717n5r">Parrots</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n582/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ESTHONIA</label> (in German <hi rend="italic">∑sthland,</hi>
                    or more correctly <hi rend="italic">Ehstland,</hi> in the native language
                    JFtroma, “the frontier country,” or <hi rend="italic">∑ahwama,</hi> “the country
                    of the Rahwas or Esthonians,” in Lettish <hi rend="italic">Iggaun Senna,</hi>
                    probably “the land of the banished”), one of three Baltic or so-called German
                    provinces of Russia, is bounded on the N. by the Gulf of Finland, on the E. by
                    the government of St Petersburg, from which it is separated by the river Narowa,
                    on the S. by Livonia, and on the W. by the Baltic. Inclusive of the islands of
                    Dago, Mohn, and Oesel, it has an area of 7817 <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n583/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0583-0562"/> square miles. It consists essentially of a nearly
                    level plateau of Silurian limestone which presents to the Gulf of Finland a
                    precipitous coast from 49 to 120 feet in height, has a gradual slope inland to
                    the south, and is broken by three or four slightly marked terraces running E.
                    and W. Traces of glacial action are exceedingly abundant in the shape of drift
                    and boulders, both on the mainland and in the islands. A considerable portion of
                    the surface is occupied by stretches of sand, marsh, or pine forests; but other
                    parts afford a good arable soil. There are a great number of small lakes
                    throughout the country, and on the eastern frontier lies the Ozerδ Tchudskoye or
                    Peipus Lake, about 55 miles long and 30 broad. None of the rivers are large
                    enough to be of real commercial importance, The climate is severe with long
                    winters and frequent storms. Most of the population is engaged in agricultural
                    pursuits— cattle, barley, rye, hemp, flax, and tobacco receiving their chief
                    attention. With the exception of the distilling of brandy and the weaving of a
                    little linen and cloth there is no manufacturing industry, and foreign commerce
                    is almost entirely confined to Reval, Baltisch port, and Hapsal. The province is
                    administratively divided into the six districts of Reval, Wesenberg,
                    Weissenstein, Hapsal, Leal, and Kunda, and the city of Reval is the seat of the
                    principal Government officials. The national church is Lutheran; but it is
                    gradually losing ground before the encroachments of Greco-Russian proselytism
                    strongly supported by the political authorities. It divides the country into
                    eight dioceses, and places the centre of its administration in a consistorium at
                    Reval. In 1875 there were 578 schools, attended by 18,952 boys and 1G,227 girls,
                    or in other words, by 92 pupils out of every 1000 inhabitants. The higher
                    education under the influence of the nobility and clergy keeps for the most part
                    true to German traditions. Out of a population numbering 323,961 in 1870 about
                    one-thirteenth is of German race; and the province may be briefly characterized
                    as a country fundamentally Esthonian, with a Teutonic aristocracy and a Russian
                    government. The Esthonians proper belong to the Finnish family, and still
                    maintain their native language. Howorth, however, has recently endeavoured to
                    show that their settlement in the Baltic district is after all not of such high
                    antiquity. Perhaps none of the nationalities of Europe have maintained greater
                    purity of descent, and the general opinion is that they are the aboriginal
                    occupants of the soil. They are not confined to the country with which they are
                    nominally identified, but form more than a third of the population of Livonia or
                    Liefland, and are found in isolated districts in the governments of Vitepsk,
                    Pskoff, and St Petersburg. Altogether they are estimated at about G50,000. In
                    physical development they do not rank high and appear to bear the marks of
                    long-continued hardship and servitude. They are generally short in stature,
                    especially in the neighbourhood of Dorpat. The skull is angular and
                    brachycephalous, the forehead low, the space between the nostrils and mouth
                    short, the hair usually yellowish or brown, and the beard scanty. Their language
                    is rich in roots, and has no small flexibility of composition and structure.
                    There are two main dialects —the Dorpat or Werro Esthonian and the Reval
                    Esthonian —which are nearly as distinct from each other as Polish and Bohemian,
                    and can hardly be successfully treated in a common grammar. The latter, which
                    preserves more carefully the full inflexional forms, and pays greater attention
                    to the laws of euphony, is consequently recognized as the literary speech, and
                    has the wider domain. It breaks up again into two varieties, the one of which,
                    like the Livonian and Tchudish, uses strong forms of words, while the other,
                    like the literary Finnish, indulges iu weak forms. Minor varieties are
                    exceedingly numerous—almost every parish, according to Wiedemann, having
                    recognizable peculiarities. Thefirst publication inEsthonian was a Lutheran
                    catechism, prepared at the suggestion of Heinrich von Galen, master of the
                    Livonian order in the 16th century. In 1637 appeared an Esthonian grammar by
                    Stahl, and in 1648 a similar -work by Hutslev. A translation of the New
                    Testament by a learned society was printed at Reval in 1715, and in 1780 Hupei
                    published his Esthonian-German lexicon, with a grammar of the two principal
                    dialects. Between 1813 and 1832 there appeared at Pernau twenty volumes of <hi
                    rend="italic">Beitrage zur genauem</hi><hi rend="italic">Keηnt-niss</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">der</hi><hi rend="italic">Esthnischen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sprache,</hi> by Roseplänter, and from 1840 downwards A. von Jannau, Fr.
                    Fählmann, Aug. Heinrich Hansen, Knupffer, Haller, and others contributed
                    valuable papers on Esthonian subjects to the <hi rend="italic">Verhandlungen der
                    Gelehrten</hi><hi rend="italic">Esthnischen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Gesellschaft.</hi> In 1844 appeared Ahrens’s <hi rend="italic">Grammatik
                    der</hi><hi rend="italic">Esthnischen</hi><hi rend="italic">Sprache</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Revαlischen Dialects,</hi> which however, recognizes only the
                    weaker form of the dialect. More recently F. J. Wiedemann under the auspices of
                    the Imperial Academy of St Petersburg has devoted himself to the detailed
                    investigation of Esthonian, visiting the different parts of the country, and
                    registering all peculiarities on the spot. Reports of his labours are given iu
                    the <hi rend="italic">Bulletin oi</hi> the society, and his lexicon was
                    published in 1869. The popular songs and traditions of the Esthonian are
                    numerous and interesting; they have a close resemblance to the similar
                    productions of Finland, and many of them embody portions of an old heathen
                    mythology and cosmogony. The last professional rhapsodist is said to have died
                    in 1813. Rouss published a collection of <hi rend="italic">Esthnische</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Volkslieder</hi> in 1850-51, several of which may be found
                    translated in Latham’s <hi rend="italic">nationalities of Europe,</hi> vol. i.;
                    Dr Fr. Kreutzwald, with questionable judgment, united a number of the separate
                    songs into a connected poem (Helsingfors 1866); and his work has been translated
                    by Carl vonReinthal as <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Ehstnische</hi><hi rend="italic">Sage von Kalewipoeg,</hi> 1857, 1859. Still
                    more recently Jacob Hurt has commenced at Dorpat what is intended to be a
                    complete collection of Old. Esthonian popular poetry, under the title of <hi
                    rend="italic">Vaηα</hi><hi rend="italic">Kanal,</hi> or “The Old Harp.”</p>
                <p>The Esthonians are mentioned in the 11th century by Adam of Bremen, and in the
                    12th and 13th the name becomes quite familiar. They appear to have given no
                    small trouble to their Scandinavian neighbours by their piratical excursions,
                    and several of the Danish kings attempted to bring them into subjection. Canute
                    1V., or Knud Valdemarson, invaded their country with a fleet of 760 ships,
                    forced many of their number to submit to the rite of baptism, and erected
                    several Christian churches; but hardly had his shipe disappeared when the
                    churches were in ruins, and the conversions proved to be a pretence. In 1219
                    Valdemar Seier, or the Victorious, received the papal blessing, and undertook
                    another and more formidable crusade. The Danish soldiers vowed a vow that, if
                    victory was granted to their arms, every Dane of twelve years and upwards would
                    from henceforth hold a fast on St Laurence’s Eve. At first they were apparently
                    successful; but after they deemed their conquest secure, the Esthonians fell
                    upon them unawares, and pressed them so hard that, as the tale is told, their
                    defeat would have been inevitable, had not the archbishop, Anders Suneson, like
                    another Moses, ascended a hill and held up his hands in benediction and prayer.
                    The victory thus obtained was commemorated by the creation of thirty-five
                    knights on the field of battle, who, it may be noted, were the first members of
                    their order in Denmark. Though their country was incorporated with the Danish
                    kingdom, the Esthonians proved by no means submissive subjects, and we find
                    several of Valdemar’s successors obliged to suppress their insurrections by
                    force. At length Valdemar Atterdag, after the great rebellion <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n584/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0584-0563"/> of 1313, sold his troublesome possession in 1347
                    to the Knights of the Sword for 19,000 marks; and the history of Esthonia is in
                    consequence practically the history of that order till the 1Gth century. The
                    nobles and cities offered voluntary homage to Sweden in 1521, but the Swedish
                    kings found it no easy task to maintain their claim against the Russian
                    encroachments, which had begun as early as 1483. The foolish ambition of Charles
                    XII. decided the matter against them; and in 1721, by the peace of Nystadt,
                    Esthonia was formally ceded to Peter the Great, who did what he could to
                    conciliate the inhabitants, both Esthonians and Germans. Serfdom was abolished
                    in 1817 by Alexander I., but the condition of the peasants continued so
                    unsatisfactory that they rose in rebellion in 1859. The struggle between German
                    and Russian influences is still going on, but it can hardly end in anything else
                    than Russian domination.</p>
                <p>See, besides the works already mentioned, Hupei, <hi rend="italic">Topogra-
                    2&gt;hische</hi><hi rend="italic">Nachrichten,</hi> Riga, 1774-82; Petri, <hi
                    rend="italic">Esthland</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi rend="italic">die
                    Esther,</hi> 1802; Willigerod, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Esthlands,</hi> 1817; Merkel, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">freien Letten und</hi><hi rend="italic">Esthen,</hi> 1820; Ewer,
                    <hi rend="italic">Des Herzogthums Esthlands Ritterund Landrechte,</hi> Dorpat,
                    1821; T. L. von Parrot, <hi rend="italic">Liwen, Lättcn, Lasten,</hi> 1839; Joh.
                    Friedrich von Reck and Karl Eduard Napinsky, <hi rend="italic">Allgemeines
                    Schriftsteller-und Gelehrte. j-Lexicon der Provinzen Livland, Estland,</hi>
                    &amp;c.; Kohl, <hi rend="italic">Die Deutsch-Russischen Ostseeprovinzen,</hi>
                    1840; Rigby, “L’Esthonie,” in <hi rend="italic">Revue</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Britannique,</hi> 1841; <hi rend="italic">Letters from the Baltic,</hi> London,
                    1844; Possart, <hi rend="italic">Statistik und Geographie des Gouvernements
                    Esthlands,</hi> 1846; Kruse, <hi rend="italic">Urgeschichte des Esthnischen
                    Volksstamms,</hi> 1846; Milner, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Baltic,</hi> 1854; Mag. Fr. Schmidt, “Untersuchungen über die Erscheinungen der
                    Glacialformation in Estland und auf Oesel,” in <hi rend="italic">Bull, de l</hi>
                    ’ <hi rend="italic">Acad.</hi><hi rend="italic">Imp. de St Petersbourg,</hi>
                    1865; Von Richter, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der deutschen
                    Ostseeprovinzen,</hi> 1857-1858; Etzel, <hi rend="italic">Ostsee und
                    Küstenländer,</hi> 1859; Cröger, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte Liv-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Est-</hi><hi rend="italic">und Kurlands,</hi> 1867; Eckardt, <hi
                    rend="italic">Die Baltischen Provinzen Russlands,</hi> Leipsic, 1869—English
                    translation (“Modern Russia ”), 1870; F. Muller, <hi rend="italic">Beiträge
                    zur</hi><hi rend="italic">Orographie</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Hydrographie</hi><hi rend="italic">von Estland,</hi> 1870;
                    Hunfalvy, <hi rend="italic">Reisen in der Ostseeprovinzen Russlands,</hi> 1873;
                    ΛVeske, <hi rend="italic">Reise durch das Estenland im Sommer</hi> 1875, St
                    Petersburg, 1876; Fried. G. von Bunge, <hi rend="italic">Das Herzogthum Estland
                    unter der Herrschaft der Könige von Dänemark,</hi> Gotha, 1877.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
