<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0908-0687-0662-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EUGENIUS (9th edition, volume 8, page 662)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rz2q">Cistercians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4p01z">Spires</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1096431">Reunions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130034">Spires</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n687/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EUGENIUS</label>, the name of four popes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Eugenius</hi> I. was a native of Rome. Elected pope in 654,
                    on the banishment of Martin I. by the emperor Constans IL, he showed greater
                    deference than his predecessor to the emperor’s wishes, and made no public stand
                    against the patriarchs of Constantinople. He died in 657, and was canonized, his
                    day being the 2d of June, although according to Anastasius, he died on the 1st
                    of that month.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Eugenius</hi> II. was a native of Rome, and was chosen to
                    succeed Pascal I. in 824. Another candidate, Zinzinnus, was proposed by the
                    plebeian faction, and the presence of the emperor Lothair was necessary in order
                    to maintain the authority of the new pope. Lothair took advantage of this
                    opportunity to redress many abuses in the papal administration, to vest the
                    election of the pope in the nobles, and to confirm the statute that no pope
                    should be consecrated till his election had the approval of the emperor. A
                    council which assembled at Rome during the reign of Eugenius passed several
                    enactments for the restoration of church discipline, took measures for the
                    foundation of schools and chapters, and decided against priests wearing a
                    secular dress or engaging in secular occupations. Eugenius also adopted various
                    provisions for the care of the poor and of widows and orphans, and on that
                    account received the name of “father of the people,” an epithet not altogether
                    appropriate, if he was, as he is said to have been, the author of the “ordeal of
                    cold water.” He died in 827.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Eugenius</hi> III., a native of Pisa, was elected pope in
                    February 1145. When called to occupy this supreme position he was only abbot of
                    the Cistercians, and he owed his elevation partly to the fact that none were
                    eager to accept an office the duties of which were at the time so difficult and
                    dangerous, but chiefly to his being the friend and pupil of Bernard of
                    Clairvaux, the most influential ecclesiastic of the Western church, and a strong
                    assertor of the pope’s temporal authority. The choice had not, however, the
                    approval of Bernard, who remonstrated against the election on account of the
                    “innocence and simplicity” of Eugenius; but after the choice was made he took
                    advantage of the qualities in Eugenius which he objected to, so as virtually to
                    rule in his name. During nearly the whole of his pontificate Eugenius was unable
                    to reside in Rome. Hardly had he left the city to be consecrated in the
                    monastery of Farfa, when the citizens, under the influence of Arnold of
                    Brescia—the great opponent of the pope’s temporal power—established the old
                    Roman constitution, and elected Giordano to be “patrician.” Eugenius appealed
                    for help to Tivoli and to other cities at feud with Rome, and with their aid was
                    successful in making such conditions with the Roman citizens as enabled him for
                    a time to hold the semblance of authority in h⅛ capital; but as he would not
                    agree to a treacherous compact against Tivoli, he was compelled to leave the
                    city in March 1146. He stayed for some time at Viterbo and then at Siena, but
                    ultimately went to France. On hearing of the fall of Edessa, he had, in December
                    1145, addressed a letter to Louis VII. of France, calling on him to take part in
                    another crusade; and at a great diet held at Spires in 1146 the emperorConrad
                    III. also,and many of his nobles were,by the eloquence of Bernard, incited to
                    dedicate themselves to the holy warfare. After holding councils at Paris,
                    Rheims, and <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n688/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0908-0688-0663"/> Treves, Eugenius, in 1149, returned to Italy,
                    and took up his residence at Viterbo. In 1150, through the aid of the king of
                    Sicily, he was able again to enter Rome, but the jealousy of the republicans
                    soon compelled him to retire. The emperor Frederick Barbarossa had promised to
                    aid him against his revolted subjects, but the death of Eugenius, at Tivoli,
                    June 7, 1153, prevented the fulfilment of the engagement. Though the citizens of
                    Rome were jealous of the efforts of Eugenius to assert his temporal authority,
                    they were always ready to recognize him as their spiritual lord, and they
                    besides deeply reverenced his personal character. Accordingly he was buried at
                    the Vatican with every mark of respect, and his tomb soon acquired an
                    extraordinary fame for miraculous cures.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Eugenius</hi> IV. (1383-1447), born in 1383, was the son of
                    a Venetian merchant, and bore the name of Gabriel Condolmieri. His mother was
                    the sister of Gregory XII., and when Gregory mounted the papal throne in 140G,
                    Gabriel, then a Celestine monk, became bishop of Sienna. In 1408 he was made
                    cardinal, and on the death of Martin V. he was elected pope, March 3,1431.
                    Martin V. belonged to the house of Colonna, and the rich treasures which he had
                    accumulated during his pontificate remained in their hands. Eugenius, however,
                    claimed their possession, as the papal successor of Martin, and this being
                    refused, he, with the aid of the rival faction of the Orsini and the general
                    body of the Roman citizens, seized all the Colonnas who were in Rome, captured
                    their castles in the surrounding country, and compelled the prince of Salerno to
                    make humiliating terms. With the large sum of money acquired from the Colonnas
                    he was enabled soon afterwards to quell a revolt which had assumed serious
                    dimensions in the Roman states, and for a time his power was undisputed
                    throughout all his dominions. The augury thus presented of a pontificate of
                    exceptionable prosperity and influence was not, however, fulfilled, for the
                    after career of Eugenius was chiefly a succession of humiliations, and during
                    the greater part of it there existed the scandal of a church “divided against
                    itself.” It is doubtful whether even Martin V., if he had lived, could have
                    longer delayed the serious quarrel between pope and council which was the chief
                    feature of Engenius’s pontificate; but the latter had neither his predecessor’s
                    family influence; nor his practical prudence, personal popularity, or steadfast
                    will. He was a patron and friend of learning, and is admitted to have practised
                    with exemplary conscientiousness all the virtues of his order, but he can
                    scarcely be allowed any other commendation. At times he manifested a certain
                    degree of dexterity in gaining his end, but as he was ignorant of the world, and
                    unable to appreciate the motives and interests which exist beyond the pale of a
                    monastery, he was in a great measure necessarily deprived of the knowledge which
                    could guide him safely through complicated circumstances. In addition to this he
                    was a strong and hard dogmatist, bitter and relentless in his hatred of heresy,
                    and keenly suspicious of anything that in the faintest way seemed to cast a
                    doubt on the dignity, infallibility, and unlimited authority of his office. On
                    the very day that he was chosen pope the council appointed by his predecessor
                    met at Basel. Three principal subjects were to engage its attention,—the
                    reconciliation of the Hussites, the reform of the church, and the reunion of,
                    the Greek and Latin churches. A great victory gained by the Hussites a few weeks
                    after the council met seemed, in the opinion of the majority of the members, to
                    lend to the two former subjects an additional and supreme urgency, and they
                    actually arranged to receive a deputation of the Hussites for the purpose of
                    agreeing to a peaceable settlement of the points in dispute. Such a proposal,
                    however, at once excited the alarm of Eugenius,— alarm regarding his own
                    authority, and alarm at the manifestation of such signs of clemency towards
                    heretics. His fears were doubtless nourished by the Roman curia, who foresaw the
                    injury that would result to their own interests through the threatened reforms;
                    and on November 12, induced partly by his own misgivings and partly by their
                    advice, Eugenius wrote the cardinal Caesarini, president of the council,
                    ordering him to dissolve it, and summon another to meet two years afterwards at
                    Bologna. Against this command Caesarini strongly remonstrated, but Eugenius was
                    inflexible, and the council, obtaining the support of the emperor and the duke
                    of Milan, proceeded to act independently of the pope’s authority. He fulminated
                    letters of excommunication against all who should attend it, but the number of
                    its members went on increasing; and, gaining confidence by its accessions, it
                    cited him on April 20, 1432, to appear before it in less than three months, and
                    on September 6, as he did not obey the summons, declared him guilty of schism.
                    Eugenius, to gain the support of Sigismund, had granted him the imperial crown,
                    but since Sigismund remained faithful to the council, Eugenius was compelled to
                    yield, and in 1433 he revoked his bull of dissolution. In the following year the
                    Colonnas, aided by the Visconti, compelled Eugenius to flee from Rome. He
                    escaped in disguise to Florence, and afterwards, notwithstanding an otter of
                    assistance from the patriarch of Alexandria, took up his residence at Bologna.
                    Meantime the essential subjects of dispute between him and the council, so far
                    from being settled, were gradually leading to a crisis, and when finally the
                    council endeavoured to deprive him of the power of conferring benefices, he in
                    1437 sought to change the place of meeting to Ferrara, on the ground that the
                    latter place was more suitable for discussing the reunion with the Greek church.
                    The council replied by summoning him to appear before them within sixty days, at
                    the end of which time they, on his failing to appear, suspended him from his
                    functions. In January 10, 1438, the opposition council, supported by the emperor
                    and the patriarch, met at Ferrara, but on account of an outbreak of the plague,
                    the place of meeting was changed to Florence. Here the act declaring the reunion
                    of the Greek and Latin churches was published July 6, 1439. Meantime, the
                    council at Basel proceeded to elect as pope Amadeus duke of Savoy, under the
                    title of Felix V., and continued the work of reform until 1443. In October of
                    that year Eugenius, with the aid of Alphonso king of Aragou, whose claim to the
                    throne he had supported in opposition to René of Anjou, was enabled to enter
                    Rome; and in 1447, through the subtle but unprincipled craft of Aeneas Sylvius
                    Piccolomini, who had forsaken his old master Amadeus, the whole of Germany was
                    induced to declare against the antipope. The same day, however, that news
                    reached Eugenius of this diplomatic triumph, he was seized with a mortal
                    illness; and, after only lingering to sign the treaty of pacification, he died
                    23d February 1447. Nor does he appear to have gained much comfort from tlds
                    final act of his pontificate, regarding it rather as a necessary but
                    disagreeable compromise than as the means of attaining his original purpose, for
                    he is said to have exclaimed on his deathbed,—“O Gabriel, Gabriel, better would
                    it have been for you to have been neither pope, nor cardinal, nor bishop, but to
                    have finished your days as you commenced them, following peaceably in the
                    monastery the exercises of your order.”</p>
                <p>See Platina, <hi rend="italic">Vita</hi><hi rend="italic">Pontificum;</hi> Aeneas
                    Sylvius, <hi rend="italic">De Cοnciliο BasH-icnse,</hi> and various passages in
                    his other works; Muratori, <hi rend="italic">Ann. d'Italia;</hi> Artaud de <hi
                        rend="italic">Kontor,</hi><hi rend="italic">Ilistoiredes</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Souverains Pontifes romains;</hi> Gregorovius, <hi
                        rend="italic">Geschichte der Stadt Rom im Mittelalter;</hi> and Milman, <hi
                        rend="italic">History of Latin Christianity.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
