<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0849-0814-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">EYCK, Van</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 8, page 814</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:991032">Lambs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:827285">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1181450">Worship</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93k3f">Madonna</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n849/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EYCK, <hi rend="smallcaps">Van</hi></label>, the name of a
                    family of painters in whose works the rise and mature development of art in
                    western Flanders are represented. Though bred in the valley of the Meuse, they
                    finally established their professional domicile in Ghent and in Bruges.; and
                    there, by skill and inventive genius, they changed the traditional habits of the
                    earlier schools, remodelled the primitive forms of Flemish design, and
                    introduced a complete revolution into the technical methods of execution
                    familiar to their countrymen.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="smallcaps">Hubert Van Eyck</hi> was the oldest and most remarkable
                    of this race of artists. The date of his birth and the records of his progress
                    are lost amidst the ruins of the earlier civilization of the valley of the
                    Meuse. He was born about 1366, at Maeseyck, under the shelter or protection of a
                    Benedictine convent, in which art and letters had been cultivated from the
                    beginning of the 8th century. But after a long series of wars,—when the country
                    became insecure, and the schools which had flourished in the towns decayed,—he
                    wandered to Flanders, and there for the first time gained a name. As court
                    painter to the hereditary prince of Burgundy, and as client to one of the
                    richest of the Ghent patricians, Hubert is celebrated. Here, in middle age,
                    between 1410 and 1420, he signalized himself as the inventor of a new method of
                    painting. Here he lived in the pay of Philip of Charolais till 1421. Here he
                    painted pictures for the corporation, whose chief magistrates honoured him with
                    a state visit in 1424. His principal masterpiece, and the only picture that can
                    be traced to his <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n850/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0850-0815"/> hand, the Worship of the Lamb, commissioned by
                    Jodocus Vijdts, lord of Bamele, is the noblest creation of the Flemish school, a
                    piece of which we possess all the parts dispersed from St Bavon in Ghent to the
                    galleries of Brussels and Berlin,—one upon which Hubert laboured till he died,
                    leaving it to be completed by his brother. Almost unique as an illustration of
                    contemporary feeling for Christian art, this great composition can only be
                    matched by the Fount of Salvation, in the museum of Madrid. It represents, on
                    numerous panels, Christ on the judgment seat, with the Virgin and St John the
                    Baptist at His sides, hearing the songs of angels, and contemplated by Adam and
                    Eve, and, beneath him, the Lamb shedding His blood in the presence of angels,
                    apostles, prophets, martyrs, knights, and hermits. On the outer sides of the
                    panels are the Virgin and the angel annunciate, the sibyls and prophets who
                    foretold the coming of the Lord, and the donors in prayer at the feet of the
                    Baptist and Evangelist. After this great work was finished it was placed, in
                    1432, on an altar in St Bavon of Ghent, with an inscription on the framework
                    describing Hubert as “<hi rend="italic">maior</hi><hi rend="italic">qτιo nemo
                    reper-tusf</hi> and setting forth, in colours as imperishable as the picture
                    itself, that Hubert began and John afterwards brought it to perfection. John Van
                    Eyck certainly wished to guard against an error which ill-informed posterity
                    showed itself but too prone to foster, the error that he alone had composed and
                    carried out an altarpiece executed jointly by Hubert and himself. His
                    contemporaries may be credited with full knowledge of the truth in this respect,
                    and the facts were equally well known to the duke of Burgundy or the chiefs of
                    the corporation of Bruges, who visited the painter’s house in state in 1432, and
                    the members of the chamber of rhetoric at Ghent, who reproduced the Agnus Dei as
                    a <hi rend="italic">tableau</hi><hi rend="italic">vivant</hi> in 1456. Yet a
                    later generation of Flemings forgot the claims of Hubert, and gave the honours
                    that were his due to his brother John exclusively.</p>
                <p>The solemn grandeur of church art in the 15th century never found, out of Italy,
                    a nobler exponent than Hubert Van Eyck. His representation of Christ as the
                    judge, between the Virgin and St John, affords a fine display of realistic
                    truth, combined with pure drawing and gorgeous colour, and a happy union of
                    earnestness and simplicity with the deepest religious feeling. In contrast with
                    earlier productions of the Flemish school, it shows a singular depth of tone and
                    great richness of detail. Finished with surprising skill, it is executed with
                    the new oil medium, of which Hubert shared the invention with his brother, but
                    of which no rival artists at the time possessed the secret,—a medium which
                    consists of subtle mixtures of oil and varnish applied to the moistening of
                    pigments after a fashion, only kept secret for a time from guildsmen of
                    neighbouring cities, but uurevealed to the Italians till near the close of the
                    15th century. When Hubert died on the 18th September 1426, he was buried in the
                    chapel on the altar of which his masterpiece was placed. According to a
                    tradition as old as the 16th century, his arm was preserved as a relic in a
                    casket above the portal of St Bavon of Ghent. During a life of much apparent
                    activity and surprising successes, he taught the elements of his art to his
                    brother John, who survived him.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="smallcaps">John Van Eyck.</hi> The date of his birth is not more
                    accurately known than that of his elder brother, but he was born much later than
                    Hubert, who took charge of him and made him his “disciple.” Under this tuition
                    John learnt to draw and paint, and mastered the properties of colours from
                    Pliny. Later on, Hubert admitted him into partnership, and both were made court
                    painters to Philip of Charolais. After the breaking up of the prince’s household
                    in 1421, John became his own master, left the workshop of Hubert, and took an
                    engagement as painter to John of Bavaria, at that time resident at the Hague as
                    count of Holland. From the Hague he returned in 1424 to take service with
                    Philip, now duke of Burgundy, at a salary of 100 livres per annum, and from that
                    time till his death John Van Eyck remained the faithful servant of his prince,
                    who never treated him otherwise than graciously. He was frequently employed in
                    missions of trust; and following the fortunes of a chief who was always in the
                    saddle, he appears for a time to have been in ceaseless motion, receiving extra
                    pay for secret services at Leyden, drawing his salary at Bruges, yet settled in
                    a fixed abode at Lille. In 1428 he joined the embassy sent by Philip the Good to
                    Lisbon to beg the hand of Isabella of Portugal. His portrait of the bride fixed
                    the duke’s choice. After his return he settled finally at Bruges, where he
                    married, and his wife bore him a daughter, known in after years as a nun in the
                    convent of Maeseyck. At the christening of this child the duke was sponsor, and
                    this was but one of many distinctions by which Philip the Good rewarded his
                    painter’s merits. Numerous altarpieces and portraits now give proof of Van
                    Eyck’s extensive practice. As finished works of art and models of conscientious
                    labour they are all worthy of the name they bear, though not of equal
                    excellence, none being better than those which were completed about 1432. Of an
                    earlier period, a Consecration of Thomas à Becket has been preserved, and may
                    now be seen at Chatsworth, bearing the date of 1421; no doubt this picture would
                    give a fair representation of Van Eyck’s talents at the moment when he started
                    as an independent master, but that time and accidents of omission and commission
                    have altered its state to such an extent that no conclusive opinion can be
                    formed respecting it. The panels of the Worship of the Lamb were completed nine
                    years later. They show that John Van Eyck was quite able to work in the spirit
                    of his brother. He had not only the lines of Hubert’s compositions to guide him,
                    he had also those parts to look at and to study which Hubert had finished. He
                    continued the work with almost as much vigour as his master. His own experience
                    had been increased by travel, and he had seen the finest varieties of landscape
                    in Portugal and the Spanish provinces. This enabled him to transfer to his
                    pictures the charming scenery of lands more sunny than those of Flanders, and
                    this he did with accuracy and not without poetic feeling. We may ascribe much of
                    the success which attended his efforts to complete the altarpiece of Ghent to
                    the cleverness with which he reproduced the varied aspect of changing scenery,
                    reminiscent here of the orange groves of Cintra, there of the bluffs and crags
                    of his native valley. In all these backgrounds, though we miss the scientific
                    rules of perspective with which the Van Eycks were not familiar, we find such
                    delicate perceptions of gradations in tone, such atmosphere, yet such minuteness
                    and perfection of finish, that our admiration never flags. Nor is the colour
                    less brilliant or the touch less firm than in Hubert’s panels. John only differs
                    from his brother in being less masculine and less sternly religious. He excels
                    in two splendid likenesses of Jodocus Vijdts and his wife Catherine Burluuts.
                    The same vigorous style and coloured key of harmony characterizes the small
                    Virgin and Child of 1432 at Ince, and the Madonna, probably of the same date, at
                    the Louvre, executed for Rollin, chancellor of Burgundy. Contemporary with
                    these, the male portraits in the National Gallery, and the Man with the Pinks,
                    in the Berlin Museum (1432-4), show no relaxation of power; but later creations
                    display no further progress, unless we accept as progress a more searching
                    delicacy of finish, counterbalanced by an excessive softness of rounding in
                    flesh contours. An unfaltering minuteness of hand and great tenderness of
                    treatment may be <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n851/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0851-0816"/> found, combined with angularity of drapery, and
                    some awkwardness of attitude, in a full length portrait couple at the National
                    Gallery (1434), in which a rare insight into the detail of animal nature is
                    revealed in a study of a terrier dog. A Madonna with Saints, at Dresden, equally
                    soft and minute, charms us by the mastery with which an architectural background
                    is put in. The bold and energetic striving of earlier days, the strong bright
                    tone, are not equalled by the soft blending and tender tints of the later ones.
                    Sometimes a crude ruddiness in flesh strikes us as a growing defect, an instance
                    of which is the picture in the museum of Bruges, in w hich Canon Van der Paelen
                    is represented kneeling before the Virgin under the protection of St George
                    (1431). From first to last Van Eyck retains his ability in portrait. Fine
                    specimens are the two male likenesses in the gallery of Vienna (1436), and a
                    female, the master’s wife, in the gallery of Bruges (1439). His death in 1440-41
                    at Bruges is authentically recorded. He was buried in St Donat. Like many great
                    artists he formed but few pupils. Hubert’s disciple, Jodocus of Ghent, hardly
                    does honour to his master’s teaching, and only acquires importance after he has
                    thrown off some of the peculiarities of Flemish teaching. Petrus Cristus, who
                    was taught by John, remains immeasurably behind him in every thing that relates
                    to art. But if the personal influence of the Van Eycks was small, that of their
                    works was immense, and it is not too much to say that their example, taken in
                    conjunction with that of Van der Weyden, determined the current and practice of
                    painting throughout the whole of Europe north of the Alps for nearly a century,
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(j. a. c.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
