<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0848-0813-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">EXTREME UNCTION</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 8, page 813</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1160861">Unction</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1118032">Sick</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1119194">Sin</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1119629">Sins</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198506">Mark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1002186">Lombards</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr70">Sin</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j75q">Sick</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn8c">Mark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n848/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EXTREME UNCTION</label>, one of the seven sacraments of the
                    Romish Church, now to be administered only after those of penance and the
                    Eucharist to persons who are supposed to be at the point of death. Among the
                    Orientals oil has long been employed as a cure for various disorders<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n849/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0849-0814"/>, as well as for the purpose of promoting the
                    general health of the body. According to the narrative of Mark, it was employed
                    by the disciples of Jesus apparently for the purpose of effecting miraculous
                    cures (Mark vi. 13). The apostle James also exhorts Christians to make use of
                    it, accompanied with prayer, in the case of sick persons. “Is any sick among
                    you, let him call for the elders of the church; and let them pray over him,
                    anointing him with oil in the name of the Lord; and the prayer of faith shall
                    save the sick, and the Lord shall raise him up; and if he have committed sins,
                    they shall be forgiven him” (James v. 14, 15). Unction is not referred to by any
                    of the fathers as a sacrament, but Origen, in his second homily on Lev. iv.,
                    implies that in his time it was conjoined with the imposition of hands in the
                    restoration of the lapsed; and Irenaeus (i. 21, 5) states that among some of the
                    Gnostics it was common to anoint the dying with a mixture of oil or opobalsam
                    and water, to render their souls invisible to their spiritual enemies in the
                    other world, and proof against their machinations. There is evidence that among
                    the Christians of the 4th century a superstitious efficacy was ascribed to the
                    use of oil in cases of sickness, and instances are recorded in which the oil
                    used in the ιamps of the churches was stolen in order to be applied in sickness,
                    or to ward off attacks of disease. The first proof of the use of the rite in the
                    Roman Church is contained in a letter of Innocent I. to Decentius, bishop of
                    Eugubium (Gubbiυ), in the year 416, in which he speaks of it as “a kind of
                    sacrament;” but he adds that after the oil has been blessed by the bishop, it
                    may be used, not merely by the bishops and priests, but by Christians generally.
                    From the 8th century the rite is often mentioned in the acts of the councils,
                    and has been the occasion of a considerable amount of discussion and difference
                    of opinion, at least in regard to details. In 850 it was declared by the synod
                    of Regiaticinum (Pavia) to be a sacrament by which sins were forgiven, and
                    consequently bodily health restored, but its chief purpose was represented to be
                    the restoration of the sick person. In the 12th century the question whether the
                    rite could be repeated was raised, and began to be answered in the negative; and
                    an attempt was made by some to obtain a decision that the person to whom it had
                    been administered should not afterwards touch the earth with his bare feet, nor
                    indulge in any of the pleasures of the flesh; and although these proposals were
                    not carried, the general result of the discussions was to deepen the impression
                    that it was a rite of unusual solemnity, to w hich recourse should not be had
                    except in cases of great necessity. About this time the rite came to be known as
                    <hi rend="italic">sacramentum exeuntium</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >extrema</hi><hi rend="italic">unctio.</hi> By Peter the Lombard it was placed
                    fifth in the list of the seven sacraments, and its spiritual significance was
                    further developed by the scholastic theologians, especially by Thomas Aquinas.
                    According.to him, its principal end was the removal of the spiritual weakness
                    resulting from .the sins of the past life, and the healing of the body was only
                    its secondary end; but among other theologians of his time discussions as to the
                    purpose of the rite were the cause of considerable difference of opinion. It
                    was, however, regarded by most as having only a relative necessity, its omission
                    not entailing any positive spiritual evil. According to the decrees of the
                    Council of Trent, it confers the pardon of any faults that may previously have
                    been unexpiated, and it removes the remains of sin; it relieves and strengthens
                    the soul, and enables it better to bear up under pain, and more successfully to
                    withstand the assaults of the devil—bodily ease and health following so far as
                    these are advantageous to the soul’s welfare. As to its repetition the council
                    contented itself with declaring that it might be repeated in cases of similar
                    peril. According to the Romish catechism, two ends are obtained by its
                    observance,—1st, the pardon of venial sins, it not possessing the highest
                    efficacy in regard to mortal sins; 2d, the removal of the spiritual infirmity
                    resulting from sin, and of all the other remains of sin. For the observance of
                    the rite the Romish Church appeals to the authority of Christ, as implied in
                    Mark vi. 13, and to the authority of the apostles, as implied in James v. 14,
                    15. The Council of Trent has decreed extreme unction to be a sacrament, and
                    declares that “whosoever shall affirm that extreme unction is not truly and
                    properly a sacrament, instituted by Christ our Lord, and published by the
                    blessed apostle James, but only a ceremony received from the fathers, or a human
                    invention, is to be accursed.” And it denounces a similar anathema against all
                    who “shall affirm that the sacred unction of the sick does not confer grace, nor
                    forgive sin, nor relieve the sick, but that its power has ceased, as if the gift
                    of healing existed only in past ages.” The ceremony is performed in the
                    following way. When a person’s recovery is despaired of, his eyes, ears,
                    nostrils, mouth, hands, feet, and reins are successively anointed with the
                    sacred oil by the priest. At each anointing the priest says, “By this holy
                    unction, and through His great mercy, Almighty God forgive thee whatever sins
                    thou hast committed by sight” (or smell, hearing, touch, &lt;kc.). The oil used
                    in extreme unction is supposed to represent the grace of God poured down into
                    the soul, and conferring pardon and spiritual strength. It is blessed by the
                    bishop on Maundy Thursday, and delivered to the parochial clergy to be used by
                    them throughout the year. If any oil is left after the expiry of the year it is
                    burned, and if the supply threatens to become exhausted, other oil may be added
                    to that which has been consecrated, but only a small propor. tion of new oil is
                    permitted. In the Greek church the rite is called Ευχ∈λαιov, or "Αγιον ∈λaιov.
                    The oil is not consecrated by the bishop, but is taken out of the sanctuary
                    lamps as required and blessed by seven priests, or, if that number cannot be
                    gathered together, by not less than three. The rite is administered in diseases
                    of all kinds; and such sick persons as are able are expected to visit the
                    church, especially on Maundy Thursday, to experience its bodily and spiritual
                    blessings. Only in extreme cases does the anointing take place in the sick
                    chamber.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
