<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0771-0736-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">EVERETT, Edward</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 8, page 736</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208998">Nebraska</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205585">Panama</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204579">Oregon</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3p063">Lyceums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2md37">Missions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:830184">Bells</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1023771">Missions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n771/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EVERETT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward</hi></label>
                    (1794-1865), brother of the preceding, was born in Dorchester, near Boston, on
                    the 11th November 1794. His father died in his childhood, and his mother removed
                    to Boston with her family after her husband’s death. When he was little more
                    than thirteen he entered Harvard College; and as the full undergraduate course
                    is four years, he became “bachelor of arts” at seventeen. He then took the first
                    college honours of his class. While at college he was the chief editor of <hi
                    rend="italic">The</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n772/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0772-0737"/><hi rend="italic">Lyceum,</hi> the earliest in the
                    series of college journals published at the American Cambridge. His verses and
                    his prose essays then show some of the facility and grace which appear in his
                    later writiugs, and much of the humour which in later times he was always trying
                    to repress. His earlier predilections were for the study of law, but the advice
                    of Joseph Stevens Buckminster, a distinguished preacher in Boston, led him to
                    prepare for the pulpit, and in this calling he at once distinguished himself. He
                    was called to the ministry of one of the largest Boston churches before he was
                    twenty years old. His sermons and his theological writings attracted wide
                    attention in that community. But his tastes were then, as always, those of a
                    scholar; and in 1814, after a service of little more than a year in the pulpit,
                    he resigned his charge to accept a professorship of Greek literature in Harvard
                    College. After nearly five years spent in Europe in preparation, he entered with
                    alacrity on his duties, and, for five years more, gave a vigorous impulse, not
                    simply to the study of Greek, but to all the work of the college. About the same
                    time he assumed the charge of the <hi rend="italic">North American</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Reviere,</hi> which now became a quarterly: and he was
                    indefatigable in contributing on a great variety of subjects, -with a spirit
                    like Sydney Smith’s in the earlier days of the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh
                    Review.</hi> He vigorously defended American institutions against the sneers of
                    English travellers, and had reason to congratulate himself on the success of a
                    series of articles written to bring about a better mutual understanding between
                    Englishmen and Americans, The success of his lectures in Cambridge,, and the
                    enthusiasm aroused by tbe rebellion in Greece, led him to deliver a series of
                    popular lectures on Greek antiquities in Boston. They were the first lectures on
                    purely literary or historical subjects ever delivered in America, and were the
                    first steps toward a system of popular entertainment and education which now has
                    very wide sweep in the United States. He was eagerly engaged in the measures
                    taken in the United States for the relief of Greece in her struggle.</p>
                <p>In 1824 he was chosen a member of Congress, and held a seat for ten years,
                    supporting generally the administration of Adams, and in opposition to that of
                    Jackson, which succeeded it. As a member of the house of representatives he
                    appears to have devoted himself mainly to the discharge of that part of the
                    public business which devolved upon him. He took the floor less frequently than
                    might perhaps have been expected from a person accustomed to public speaking,
                    and able to command the ear of the house. It will be found, however, on looking
                    back to the transactions of the ten years’ sessions during which he was a
                    member, that he bore a part in almost every important debate. He was on the
                    committee of foreign affairs during the whole time of his service in Congress.
                    Of all the most important select committees, such as those on the Indian
                    relations of the State of Georgia, the Apportionment Bill, and the Bank of the
                    United States, Everett was a member, and drew the report either of the majority
                    or the minority. The report on the congress of Panama, the leading measure of
                    the first session of the nineteenth Congress, was drawn by Everett, although the
                    youngest member of the committee, and just entered Congress. He led the
                    opposition to the Indian policy of General Jackson (the removal of the Indians,
                    without their consent, from lands guaranteed to them by treaty). In the winter
                    of 1835 he was nominated as governor of Massachusetts, and was chosen in the
                    autumn of the same year. He brought to the duties of the office the untiring
                    diligence which is the characteristic of his public life. We can only allude to
                    a few of the measures which received his efficient support,— <hi rend="italic"
                    >e.g.,</hi> the establishment of the board of education, the first of such
                    boards in the United States, the scientific surveys of the State, the first of
                    such public surveys, the criminal law commission, and the preservation of a
                    sound currency under the panic of 1837.</p>
                <p>Everett filled the office of governor for four years. The political parties in
                    Massachusetts were at this time very nearly balanced, and divisions of opinion
                    on local questions (the militia and temperance laws) caused his defeat at the
                    election in November 1839. Judge Morton, the opposing candidate, succeeded by a
                    single vote, out of more than a hundred thousand. Everett availed himself of
                    this opportunity, the following spring, to make a visit with his family to
                    Europe. In 1841, while residing in Florence, he was named United States minister
                    to England, and arrived in London to enter upon the duties of his mission at the
                    close of that year. Great questions were at that time open between the two
                    countries,—the north-eastern boundary, the affair of M <hi rend="superscript">
                    i</hi> Leod, the seizure of American vessels on the coast of Africa, in the
                    course of a few months the affair of the “Creole,” to which were soon added
                    Oregon and Texas. His position was more difficult by the frequent changes that
                    took place in the department at home, which, in the course of two years, was
                    occupied successively by Messrs Webster, Legaré, Upshur, Calhoun, and Buchanan.
                    From all these gentlemen Everett received marks of approbation and
                    confidence.</p>
                <p>By the institution of the special mission of Lord Ashburton, the direct
                    negotiations between the two Governments were, about the time of Everett’s
                    arrival in London, transferred to Washington. It appears, however, from
                    documents that have from time to time been communicated to Congress, that
                    various topics connected with all the subjects in dispute were incidentally
                    treated in the correspondence of the American minister at London both with his
                    own and the British Government. Many elaborate notes to Lord Aberdeen and
                    despatches to the American secretary of state have in this way come before the
                    public, forming, however, it is believed, but a small part of the documents of
                    both classes prepared by Everett during his mission. It appears, indeed, that,
                    from the concurrence of a variety of causes, the amount of business transacted
                    at the American legation from 1841 to 1845 was more than double that of any
                    former period of equal duration.</p>
                <p>Immediately after the accession of Polk to the presidency Everett was recalled.
                    Shortly before his return the presidency of Harvard College was vacated by the
                    resignation of Hon. Josiah Quincy, and Everett was strongly urged by the friends
                    and governors of the institution to accept this office, which he did in the
                    month of January 1846. He filled this place of equal distinction and usefulness
                    for about three years. It was a position congenial with his tastes, in harmony
                    with the early associations of his life, and one which seemed to promise large
                    opportunity of applying for the benefit of the rising generation the fruit of
                    his maturer studies and varied experience in life. His health unfortunately soon
                    began to suffer, and before long became seriously impaired under the burdens and
                    cares of the office, and he was compelled at the close of the year 1848 to
                    tender his resignation. Relieved of this charge, he supposed that at last he was
                    to enjoy literary or scholarly leisure, and was already preparing for a treatise
                    on the law of nations. But, on the death of his friend Webster, to whom he had
                    always been closely attached, and of whom he was always a confidential adviser,
                    he was named by President Fillmore secretary of state, and he held that post for
                    the remaining months of Fillmore’s administration, leaving it to go into the
                    senate as the representative of Massachusetts. Under the work of the long
                    session of 1853-54, in which that “Kansas Nebraska” question first appeared in
                    form which ripened into the American civil war, his health gave way.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n773/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0773-0738"/>
                <p>He resigned his seat, on the orders of his physician, and retired to what was
                    called private life.</p>
                <p>But, as it proved, the remaining ten years of his life most widely established
                    his reputation and influence throughout America. As early as 1820 he had
                    established a reputation, such as few men in later days have enjoyed, as an
                    orator. He was frequently invited, as other public men are invited in America,
                    to deliver an “oration” on one or another public topic of historical or other
                    interest. With him these “orations,” instead of being the ephemeral
                    entertainments of an hour, became careful studies of some important theme, so
                    that the collected edition of them is now one of the standard books of reference
                    in an American’s library Eager to avert, if possible, the impending conflict of
                    arms, Everett prepared an “oration” on Washington, which he delivered in every
                    part of America. In a printed note accompanying the published edition of it, he
                    names nearly one hundred and twenty-five occasions, in almost every State in the
                    Union, in every section but the extreme south-west, where it was repeated. This
                    exception was caused only by illness in his family, after he had received
                    invitations to go to that quarter also. He travelled really as an ambassador of
                    peace among irritated States. The eagerness to hear him was so great that, from
                    “the first, his hosts arranged, almost always, that tickets should be sold to
                    all auditors; and as he travelled wholly at his own charges, the audiences thus
                    contributed more than one hundred thousand dollars for the purchase of the old
                    home of Washington at Mount Vernon, and the securing it as a shrine for American
                    patriotism.</p>
                <p>Everett’s name, in direct violation to his wishes, was presented, with Mr Bell’s,
                    as a candidate of North and South jointly for vice-president in the election of
                    1860, when Abraham Lincoln was elected. The civil war followed. Reconciliation
                    was impossible, and he gave all his learning, zeal, and eloquence, to the
                    support of the national government. For four years he was the trusted adviser of
                    every department; he was called upon in every quarter to speak at public
                    meetings. He delivered the last of his great orations at Gettysburg, after the
                    battle, on the consecration of the national cemetery there, In February of 1865
                    the success of the national arms was certain. He had the pleasure of speaking at
                    a public meeting in Boston to raise funds for the Southern poor in Savannah,
                    just taken by General Sherman. At that meeting he caught cold, which was
                    followed by sudden illness, and by his death January 15, 1865.</p>
                <p>In Everett’s life and career was a combination of the results of diligent
                    training, unflinching industry, delicate literary tastes, and unequalled
                    acquaintance with modern politics. This combination made him in America an
                    entirely exceptional person. He was never loved by the political managers; he
                    was always enthusiastically received by assemblies of the people. He would have
                    said himself that the most eager wish of his life had been for the higher
                    education of his countrymen. His orationshave been collected in four volumes. A
                    work on public law, on which he was engaged at his death, was never finished.
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(e. e, h.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
