<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0170-0159-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">QUARTER SESSIONS (9th edition, volume 20, page
                    159)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156290">Trials</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:862898">Civilization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836750">Boroughs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tg7r">Rates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc3p">Appeal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tt4h">Highways</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n170/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">QUARTER SESSIONS</label> (in full, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >General Quarter Sessions of the Peace)</hi> is the name given to a local
                    court with civil and criminal jurisdiction. In England the court consists in
                    counties of two or more justices of the peace, one of whom must be of the quorum
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Justice of the Peace),</hi> in cities and boroughs of
                    the recorder alone. The quarter sessions are a court of record. The records in a
                    county are nominally in the custody of the <hi rend="italic">custos
                        rotulorum,</hi> the highest civil officer in the county, practically in that
                    of the clerk of the peace, who is nominated by the <hi rend="italic">custos</hi>
                    and removable by the quarter sessions. In a city or borough he is appointed by
                    the council and removable by the recorder. The original jurisdiction of quarter
                    sessions seems to have been confined to cognizance of breaches of the peace. By
                    a series of statutes passed in the reign of Edward III. the time of the holding
                    of the sessions was fixed, and their jurisdiction extended to the trial of
                    felonies and trespasses. The jurisdiction now depends upon a mass of legislation
                    reaching from 1344 to the present time. The dates at which the county sessions
                    must meet are fixed, by 2 Geo. IV. and 1 Will. IV. c. 70, to be the first weeks
                    after the 11th of October, the 28th of December, the 31st of March, and the 24th
                    of June. Quarter sessions in a city or borough depend upon the Municipal
                    Corporations Act, 1882, 45 &amp; 46 Vict., c. 50. A grant of quarter sessions to
                    a city or borough is made by the crown in council on petition of the town
                    council. The main points in which borough differ from county quarter sessions
                    are these:—(1) the recorder, a barrister of five years’ standing, is sole judge
                    in place of a body of laymen; (2) the recorder has a discretion to fix his own
                    dates for the holding of a court, as long as he holds it once every quarter of a
                    year; it may be held more frequently if the recorder think fit or a secretary of
                    state so direct; (3) the recorder has no power to levy a borough rate or to
                    grant a licence for the sale of exciseable liquors by retail. In some few
                    boroughs the recorder is judge of the borough civil court. Quarter sessions in
                    the counties of Middlesex, Kent, and Lancaster, as also in London and the Cinque
                    Ports, are governed by special legislation.</p>
                <p>The jurisdiction of quarter sessions is either original or appellate.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Original Jurisdiction.—Civil.—</hi> This includes the levying
                    of a county rate and its application, the appointment of a county licensing
                    committee, and of public officers, such as the county treasurer, the public
                    analyst, and the inspectors of weights and measures, the confirmation of
                    bye-laws made by local authorities, the increase or alteration of polling places
                    and petty sessional divisions, the regulation of police, and powers under
                    various Acts of Parliament, such as the Highway Acts, and the Contagious
                    Diseases (Animals) Act. The quarter sessions of the metropolitan counties have
                    by 25 Geo. II. c. 36 the power of licensing music-halls, &amp;c., within 20
                    miles of London.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Criminal.—</hi> Apart from statute, the commissions of justices
                    of the peace provide that they shall reserve the graver felonies for trial at
                    assizes. They are now forbidden by several Acts of Parliament to try a prisoner
                    for treason or murder, or for any felony punishable without a previous
                    conviction by penal servitude for life (such as burglary and rape), or for any
                    of the offences enumerated in 5 &amp; 6 Vict. c. 38, the most practically
                    important of which are perjury, forgery, bigamy, abduction, concealment of
                    birth, libel, bribery, and conspiracy. The procedure is by indictment, as at
                    assizes, and the trial of offences by jury. In the case of incorrigible rogues
                    and of sureties of the peace the quarter sessions exercise a quasi-criminal
                    jurisdiction without a jury. They may also estreat recognizances entered into
                    for appearance in a court of summary jurisdiction, but this part of their
                    jurisdiction may be considered practically obsolete, as the Summary Jurisdiction
                    Act, 1879, gives the court of summary jurisdiction power to estreat the
                    recognizances itself.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Appellate Jurisdiction.—Civil.—</hi> The principal cases in
                    which this jurisdiction is exercised are in appeals from orders of a court of
                    summary jurisdiction as to the assessment of the poor-rate and the removal and
                    settlement of paupers, and orders made under the Highway, Licensing, and
                    Bastardy Acts.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Criminal.—</hi> An appeal lies to quarter sessions from a court
                    of summary jurisdiction only where such an appeal is expressly given by statute.
                    The appellate jurisdiction has been considerably increased by the Summary
                    Jurisdiction Act, 1879 (42 &amp; 43 Viet, c. 49), which allows an appeal (with
                    certain exceptions) from every conviction or order of a court of summary
                    jurisdiction inflicting imprisonment without the option of a fine. The appeal
                    may be <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n171/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0920-0171-0160"/> brought in accordance with either the Act
                    giving the appeal or the Summary Jurisdiction Act.</p>
                <p>There is no appeal from quarter sessions on the facts, but their decision may be
                    reviewed by the High Court of Justice by means of <hi rend="italic">certiorari,
                        mandamus,</hi> prohibition, or a case stated under 12 &amp; 13 Vict. c. 45,
                    § 11. A case may be stated for the opinion of the court of criminal appeal under
                    1Ï &amp; 12 Vict. c. 78, § 1.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ireland.—</hi> In Ireland the chairman of quarter sessions is a
                    salaried professional lawyer, and has important civil jurisdiction corresponding
                    very much to that of a county court judge in England. His jurisdiction depends
                    chiefly upon 14 &amp; 15 Vict. c. 57. The recorders of Dublin and Cork are
                    judges of the civil bill courts in those cities.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Scotland.—</hi> In Scotland quarter sessions were established
                    by the Act 1661, c. 338, under which justices were to meet on the first Tuesday
                    of March, May, and August, and the last Tuesday of October to “administrate
                    justice to the people in things that are within their jurisdiction and punish
                    the guilty for faults and crimes done and committed in the preceding quarter.”
                    The jurisdiction of quarter sessions in Scotland is more limited than in
                    England, much of what would be quarter-sessions work in England being done by
                    the sheriff or the commissioners of supply. Quarter sessions have appellate
                    jurisdiction in poaching, revenue, and licensing cases, and under the
                    Pawnbrokers and other Acts. All appeals from proceedings under the Summary
                    Jurisdiction Acts are taken to the High Court of Justiciary at Edinburgh or on
                    circuit (44 &amp; 45 Vict. c. 33). The original jurisdiction of quarter sessions
                    is very limited, and almost entirely civil. Thus they have power to divide a
                    county and to make rules for carrying into effect the provisions of the Small
                    Debts Act, 6 Geo. IV. c. 48. The decision of quarter sessions may be reviewed by
                    advocation, suspension, or appeal.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">United States.—</hi> In the United States courts of quarter
                    sessions exist in many of the States; their jurisdiction is determined by State
                    legislation, and extends as a rule only to the less grave crimes. They are in
                    some States constituted of professional judges.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
