<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0157-0146-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">QUAIL (9th edition, volume 20, page 146)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1084890">Quails</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881168">Coturnix</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174597">White</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174816">Whites</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206536">Tasmania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k41c">Quails</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795g1z">Breeding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p8d">Breast</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x62g">Rest</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n157/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">QUAIL</label> (Old French <hi rend="italic">Quaille,</hi>
                    Mod. French <hi rend="italic">Caille,</hi> Italian <hi rend="italic"
                        >Quaglia,</hi> Low Latin <hi rend="italic">Quaquila,</hi> Dutch <hi
                        rend="italic">Kwakkel,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Kwartel,</hi> German <hi
                        rend="italic">Wachtel,</hi> Danish <hi rend="italic">Vagtel),</hi> a very
                    well-known bird throughout almost all countries of Europe, Asia, and Africa,—in
                    modern ornithology the <hi rend="italic">Coturnix</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >communis</hi> or <hi rend="italic">C. dactylisonans.</hi> This last epithet
                    was given from the peculiar three-syllabled call-note of the cock, which has
                    been grotesquely rendered in several European languages, and in some parts of
                    Great Britain the species is popularly known by the nickname of “Wet-my-lips” or
                    “Wet-my-feet.” The Quail varies somewhat in colour, and the variation is rather
                    individual than attributable to local causes; but generally the plumage may be
                    described as reddish-brown above, almost each feather being transversely patched
                    with dark brown interrupted by a longitudinal stripe of light buff; the head is
                    dark brown above, with three longitudinal streaks of ochreous-white; the sides
                    of the breast and flanks are reddish-brown, distinctly striped with
                    ochreous-white; the rest of the lower parts are pale buff, clouded with a darker
                    shade, and passing into white on the belly. The cock, besides being generally
                    brighter in tint, not unfrequently has the chin and a double-throat band of
                    reddish or blackish-brown, which marks are wanting in the hen, whose breast is
                    usually spotted. Quails breed on the ground, as all gallinaceous birds commonly
                    do, and lay from nine to fifteen eggs of a yellowish-white, blotched and spotted
                    with dark brown. Though essentially migratory by nature, not a few Quails pass
                    the winter in the northern hemisphere and even in Britain, and many more in
                    southern Europe. In March and April they cross the Mediterranean from the south
                    on the way to their breed- <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n158/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0920-0158-0147"/></p>
                <p>ing homes in large bands, but these are said to be as nothing compared with the
                    enormous flights that emigrate from Europe towards the end of September. During
                    both migrations immense numbers are netted for the market, since they are almost
                    universally esteemed as delicate meat. On capture they are placed in long narrow
                    and low cages, darkened to prevent the prisoners from fighting, and, though they
                    are often so much crowded as to be hardly able to stir, the loss by death that
                    ensues is but trifling. Food, usually millet or hempseed, and water are supplied
                    in troughs hung in front, and thus these little birds are transported by tens of
                    thousands from the shores of the Mediterranean for consumption in the most
                    opulent and populous cities of Europe. The flesh of Quails caught in spring
                    commonly proves dry and indifferent, but that of those taken in autumn,
                    especially when they have been kept long enough to grow fat, as they quickly do,
                    is excellent. In no part of the British Islands at present do Quails exist in
                    sufficient numbers to be the especial object of sport, though there are many
                    places in which a few, and in some seasons more than a few, yearly fall to the
                    gun. When made to take wing, which is not always easily done, they rise with
                    great speed, but on such occasions they seldom fly far, and no one seeing them
                    only thus would be inclined to credit them with the power of extensive migration
                    that they possess, though this is often overtaxed, and the birds in their
                    transmarine voyages frequently drop exhausted into the sea or on any vessel that
                    may be in their way. In old days they were taken in England in a net, attracted
                    thereto by means of a Quail-call,—a simple instrument,<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>One is figured in Rowley’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Ornithological Miscellany</hi> (ii. p.
                        363).</p></note> the use of which is now wholly neglected,—on which their
                    notes are easily imitated.</p>
                <p>Five or six other species of the restricted genus <hi rend="italic">Coturnix</hi>
                    are now recognized; but the subject of the preceding remarks is generally
                    admitted to be that intended by the author of the book of Exodus (xvi. 13) as
                    having supplied food to the Israelites in the wilderness, though a few
                    ornithological writers have thought that bird to have been a <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Sand-Grouse (&lt;∕.v.).</hi> In South Africa and India
                    allied species, <hi rend="italic">C. delegorguii</hi> and <hi rend="italic">C.
                        coromandelica,</hi> the latter known as the Rain-Quail, respectively occur,
                    as well as the commoner one, which in Australia and Tasmania is wholly replaced
                    by <hi rend="italic">C. pectoralis,</hi> the Stubble-Quail of the colonists. In
                    New Zealand another species, <hi rend="italic">C. novae-zelandiae,</hi> was
                    formerly very abundant in some districts, but is considered to have been nearly
                    if not quite extirpated within the last twenty years by bush-fires. Some fifteen
                    or perhaps more species of Quails, inhabiting the Indian and Australian Regions,
                    have been separated, perhaps unnecessarily, to form the genera <hi rend="italic"
                        >Synoecus,</hi><hi rend="italic">Perdicula, Excalphatoria,</hi> and so
                    forth; but they call for no particular remark.</p>
                <p>America has some fifty or sixty species of birds which are commonly deemed
                    Quails, though by some authors placed in a distinct Family or Sub-family <hi
                        rend="italic">Odontophorinae.</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 1</hi><note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>They form the subject of
                            a monograph in folio by Gould, published between 1844 and
                        1850.</p></note> The best known is the Virginian Quail, or Colin, as it is
                    frequently called—that being, according to Hernandez, its old Mexican name. It
                    is the <hi rend="italic">Ortyx virginianus</hi> of modern ornithology, and has a
                    wide distribution in North America, in some parts of which it is known as the
                    “Partridge,” as well as by the nickname of “Bob-White,” aptly bestowed upon it
                    from the call-note of the cock. Many attempts have been made to introduce this
                    bird to England (as indeed similar trials have been made in the United States
                    with Quails from Europe); but, though it has been turned out by hundreds, and
                    has been frequently known to breed after liberation, its numbers rapidly
                    diminish until it wholly disappears. The beautiful tufted Quail of Cali fornia,
                        <hi rend="italic">Lophortyx</hi><hi rend="italic">californica,</hi> has also
                    been tried in Europe without success. All these American Quails or Colins seem
                    to have the habit of perching on trees, which none of the Old-World forms
                    possess.</p>
                <p>Interesting from many points of view as is the group of Birds last mentioned,
                    there is another which, containing a score of species (or perhaps more) often
                    termed Quails or Button-Quails, is of still greater importance in the eyes of
                    the systematist. This is that comprehended by the genus <hi rend="italic"
                        >Turnix,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Hemipodius</hi> of some authors, the
                    anatomical structure of which removes it far from the genera <hi rend="italic"
                        >Coturnix,</hi><hi rend="italic">Ortyx,</hi> and their allies, and even from
                    any of the normal <hi rend="italic">Gallinae.</hi> Prof. Huxley, as already
                    stated <hi rend="smallcaps">(Ornithology,</hi> vol. xviii. p. 36), would regard
                    it as the representative of a generalized stock from which the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Charadriomorpliae,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Alectoromorphae,</hi> to say
                    nothing of other groups, have sprung. Want of space prevents our here dwelling
                    upon these curious birds. One species, <hi rend="italic">T. sylvatica,</hi>
                    inhabits Barbary and southern Spain, and under the name of Andalucian Hemipode
                    has been included (though on evidence not wholly satisfactory) among British
                    Birds as a reputed straggler. The rest are natives of various parts of the
                    Ethiopian, Indian, and Australian Regions. It is characteristic of the genus <hi
                        rend="italic">Turnix</hi> to want the hind toe; but the African <hi
                        rend="italic">Ortyxelus</hi> and the Australian <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pedionomus</hi> which have been referred to its neighbourhood have four
                    toes on each foot, and, since nothing is known of the anatomy or habits of the
                    first and but little of those of the second,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>Col. Legge’s observations on the habits of <hi
                                rend="italic">Pedionomus</hi> in the Zoological Society’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Proceedings</hi> (1869, pp. 236-238) would seem to
                            shew a Limicoline affinity. Garrod in the same work (1873, p. 34)
                            figured the skull as that of a Turnicine, in which view Forbes
                            acquiesced <hi rend="italic">{Ibis,</hi> 1882, pp. 389, 431); but
                            against it Col. Legge immediately protested <hi rend="italic">{tom.
                                cit.,</hi> p. 610).</p></note> their position must at present be
                    considered doubtful. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
