<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0708-3265-0010-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DICTIONARY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bc9t">Expression</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134302">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:918881">Expression</term>
                    <term ref="fast:938950">Gates</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193323265?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">DICTIONARY</label>, in its original acceptation, is
                    the arranging of all the words of a language according to the order of the
                    alphabet, and annexing a definition or explanation to each word. When arts and
                    sciences began to be improved and extended, the multiplicity of technical terms
                    rendered it necessary to compile dictionaries, either of science in general, or
                    of particular sciences, according to the views of the compiler.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Dictionary</hi><hi rend="italic">of the English
                        Language.</hi> The design of every dictionary of language is to explain, in
                    the most accurate manner, the meaning of every word; and to show the various
                    ways in which it can be combined with others, in as far as this tends to alter
                    or modify its meaning. The dictionary which does this in the most accurate
                    manner is the most complete work of the kind; therefore the principal study of a
                    lexicographer ought to be to discover the method which may seem best adapted for
                    that purpose. Dr Johnson, with great labour, has collected the various meanings
                    of every word, and quoted the authorities; but it would have been an improvement
                    if he had given an accurate definition of the precise meaning of every word;
                    pointed out the way in which it ought to be employed with the greatest
                    propriety; showed the various deviations from the original meaning, which custom
                    had so far established as to render allowable; and fixed the precise limits
                    beyond which it could not be employed without becoming a vicious expression.
                    With this view it would have been necessary to exhibit the nice distinctions
                    which take place between words nearly synonymous, and without which many words
                    can only be defined in such a manner that they must be considered as exactly
                    synonymous. We omit making any quotations from Johnson in order to point out
                    these defects; and shall content ourselves with giving a few examples, to show
                    in what manner, according to our idea, a dictionary of the English language
                    ought to be compiled.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Immediately,</hi><hi rend="italic">adv. of
                        time.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">1. Instantly, without delay. Always employed to denote future time, and
                    never past. Thus we may say, <hi rend="italic">I will come immediately;</hi> but
                    not <hi rend="italic">I am immediately come from such a place.</hi> See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Presently.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">2. Without the intervention of any cause or event; as opposed to <hi
                        rend="italic">mediately.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Presently,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">adv. of time.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">1. Instantly, without delay. Exactly synonymous with <hi rend="italic"
                        >immediately</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> being never with propriety
                    employed to denote any thing but future time.</p>
                <p part="N">2. Formerly it was employed to express present time. Thus, <hi
                        rend="italic">The house presently possessed by such a one,</hi> was often
                    used, but this has now become a vicious expression; and we ought to say, <hi
                        rend="italic">The house possessed at present.</hi> It differs from <hi
                        rend="italic">immediately</hi> in this, that even in the most corrupt
                    phrases it never can denote] past time.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Form,</hi><hi rend="italic">subst.</hi> The
                    external appearance of any object, when considered only with reference to shape
                    or figure. This term, therefore, in the literal sense, can only be applied to
                    the objects of sight and touch, and is therefore nearly synonymous with <hi
                        rend="italic">figure</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but these terms differ in
                    some respects. <hi rend="italic">Form</hi> may be employed to denote more rude
                    and unfinished shapes; <hi rend="italic">figure,</hi> those which are more
                    perfect and regular. <hi rend="italic">Form</hi> can never be employed without
                    denoting matter, whereas <hi rend="italic">figure</hi> may be employed in the
                    abstract: thus we say a square or a triangular^^wre, but not a square or
                    triangular <hi rend="italic">form.</hi> Andin the same manner we say the <hi
                        rend="italic">figure</hi> of a house; but we must denote the substance which
                    forms that figure if we use the word <hi rend="italic">form</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> as, <hi rend="italic">a cloud of the form of a
                        house.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Figure.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">2. In contrast to irregularity or confusion. As beauty cannot exist
                    without order, it is by a figure of speech employed to denote beauty, order, and
                    the like.</p>
                <p part="N">3. As <hi rend="italic">form</hi> respects only the external appearance
                    of bodies, without regard to their internal qualities, it is, by a figure of
                    speech, employed in contrast to these qualities to denote empty show, without
                    essential qualities. In this sense it is often taken when applied to religious
                    ceremonies, pageantry, and so forth.</p>
                <p part="N">4. As <hi rend="italic">form</hi> is employed to denote the external
                    appearance of bodies, so, in a figurative sense, it is applied to reasoning,
                    denoting the particular mode or manner in which this is conducted; as, <hi
                        rend="italic">the form of a syllogism,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p part="N">5. In the same manner it is employed to denote the particular mode of
                    procedure established in courts of law; as, <hi rend="italic">the forms of law,
                        religion,</hi> and the like.</p>
                <p part="N">6. <hi rend="italic">Form</hi> is sometimes, although improperly, used
                    to denote the different circumstances of the same body; as, <hi rend="italic"
                        >water in a fluid or a solid form.</hi> But as this phrase regards the
                    internal qualities rather than the external figure, it is improper, and ought to
                    be, <hi rend="italic">water in a fluid or a solid state.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">7. But when bodies of different kinds are compared with one another,
                    this term may be employed to denote other circumstances than shape or figure;
                    for we may say, <hi rend="italic">a juice exuding from a tree in the form of wax
                        or resin;</hi> although, in this case, the consistence, colour, &amp;c. and
                    not the external arrangement of parts, constitutes the resemblance.</p>
                <p part="N">8. From the regular appearance of a number of persons arranged in one
                    long seat, such persons so arranged are sometimes called a <hi rend="italic"
                        >form;</hi> as, <hi rend="italic">a form of students,</hi> &amp;c. And,</p>
                <p part="N">9. By an easy transition the seat itself has also acquired that
                    name.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Great,</hi> A relative word, denoting largeness of
                    quantity, number, &amp;c., serving to augment the value of those terms with
                    which it is combined, and opposed to <hi rend="italic">small</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">little.</hi> The principal circumstances in which this word
                    can be employed are the following:</p>
                <p part="N">1. When merely inanimate objects are considered with regard to quantity,
                        <hi rend="italic">great</hi> is with propriety employed to denote that the
                    quantity is considerable: as, <hi rend="italic">a great mountain, great
                        house,</hi> and the like; and it is here contrasted with <hi rend="italic"
                        >small.</hi> When <hi rend="italic">great</hi> is thus employed, we have no
                    other word which is exactly synonymous.</p>
                <p part="N">2. When inanimate objects are considered with regard to their extent,
                    this term is sometimes employed, although with less propriety; as, <hi
                        rend="italic">a great plain, a great</hi><pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193323278?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0708-3278-0011"/><hi
                        rend="italic">field,</hi> and the like. In this sense it is nearly
                    synonymous with <hi rend="italic">large</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and these
                    terms were often used indiscriminately, but with some difference of meaning;
                    for, as <hi rend="italic">large</hi> is a term chiefly employed to denote extent
                    of superficies, and as <hi rend="italic">great</hi> more particularly regards
                    the quantity of matter, therefore, when <hi rend="italic">large</hi> is applied
                    to any object which is not merely superficial, it denotes that it is the extent
                    of surface which is there meant to be considered, without regard to the other
                    dimensions; whereas, when the term <hi rend="italic">great</hi> is employed, it
                    has reference to the whole contents. If, therefore, we say <hi rend="italic">a
                        large house,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">a large river,</hi> we express that
                    the house, or the river, has a surface of great extent, without having any
                    necessary connexion with the size in other respects. But if we say <hi
                        rend="italic">a great house,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">a great river,</hi>
                    it at once denotes that these objects have not only a large surface, but are
                    also of great size in every respect.</p>
                <p part="N">3. <hi rend="italic">Great,</hi> when applied to the human species,
                    never denotes the size or largeness of body, but is applied solely to the
                    qualities of the mind. Thus when we say that <hi rend="italic">Socrates was a
                        great mail,</hi> we do not mean that he was a man of great size, but that he
                    was a man who excelled in the endowments of the mind. The terms which denote
                    largeness of size in the human body are <hi rend="italic">big, bulhy,
                    huge.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">4. <hi rend="italic">Great</hi> is sometimes applied to the human
                    species, as denoting high rank. In this case it is oftener used in the plural
                    number than otherwise. Thus we say simply <hi rend="italic">the great,</hi>
                    meaning the whole body of men in high station, as opposed to the <hi
                        rend="italic">mean.</hi> It should seldom be employed in this sense, as it
                    tends to confound dignity of rank with elevation of mind.</p>
                <p part="N">5. As this is a general term of augmentation, it maybe joined with all
                    nouns which denote <hi rend="italic">quantity, quality, number, excellence,</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">defects</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> or such as imply <hi
                        rend="italic">praise, blame, anger, contempt,</hi> or any other affection of
                    the mind.</p>
                <p part="N">6. It is employed to denote every step of ascending or descending
                    consanguinity, as <hi rend="italic">great-grandfather, great-grandson,</hi> and
                    so on.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">High,</hi><hi rend="italic">adj.</hi> Exalted in a
                    perpendicular direction at a distance from the surface of the earth, and opposed
                    to <hi rend="italic">low.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">1. <hi rend="italic">High</hi> is a term altogether indefinite, and is
                    employed to express the degree of elevation of any inanimate body. Thus we say
                        <hi rend="italic">a high mountain, a high house, steeple, tower,
                        pillar,</hi> and the like. Nor is there any other word which can here be
                    considered as synonymous; <hi rend="italic">lofty</hi> being employed only to
                    denote a very eminent degree of elevation.</p>
                <p part="N">2. To express the perpendicular elevation of vegetables either <hi
                        rend="italic">high</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tall</hi> may be employed, as
                    being in this case nearly synonymous. We may therefore say a <hi rend="italic"
                        >high</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tall tree,</hi> a <hi rend="italic"
                        >high</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tall mast,</hi> and so forth, but with this
                    difference between these two expressions, that toZZcan be more properly applied
                    to those which are much elevated and of small dimensions; and <hi rend="italic"
                        >high,</hi> to such as are more bulky and of greater size.</p>
                <p part="N">3. The perpendicular height of man can never be expressed by the word
                        <hi rend="italic">high, tall</hi> being here the proper expression. And
                    although <hi rend="italic">high</hi> is sometimes used to express the height of
                    other animals, yet it seems to be an improper expression. See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Tall.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">4. <hi rend="italic">High,</hi> when applied to the human species,
                    always refers to the mind, and denotes <hi rend="italic">haughtiness,
                        stateliness, pride,</hi> and when combined with expressions indicating
                    energy of mind, it denotes that in a higher degree. In this sense it is opposed
                    to <hi rend="italic">meanness, abjectness,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >humility.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">5. As this is an indefinite term, tending to denote any thing which is
                    elevated above us, it may be combined with almost every noun which admits of
                    this elevation. Hence, as objects high above us are always out of our reach, it
                    is in a metaphorical sense used to denote any thing which seems to be above the
                    ordinary condition of mankind, or those qualities or endowments of mind which
                    are not easily acquired; as, <hi rend="italic">dignity</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >elevation of sentiment, dignity of rank, acuteness in reasoning on
                        difficult subjects, pride, haughtiness,</hi> or any other quality which
                    seems beyond the ordinary level of mankind; <hi rend="italic">dearness of
                        price.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">6. In the same manner we apply this term to time, which having a
                    metaphorical resemblance to a river flowing on with an unceasing current through
                    all successive ages, any thing of remote antiquity is denoted by the term <hi
                        rend="italic">high.</hi><hi rend="italic">7.</hi> Likewise to those degrees
                    of latitude far removed from the line, where the pole becomes more elevated.</p>
                <p part="N">8. And also to some particular crimes, as being attended with peculiar
                    degrees of guilt, as <hi rend="italic">high treason.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Tall,</hi><hi rend="italic">adj.</hi> Something elevated to a considerable
                    degree in a perpendicular direction, and opposed to <hi rend="italic"
                    >low.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">1. This term is chiefly employed to express the height of man and other
                    animals; and is applied to denote the height of the body only, without having
                    any reference to the mind. When applied to man, no other word can be substituted
                    in its stead; when applied to other animals, <hi rend="italic">high</hi> is
                    sometimes considered as nearly synonymous. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >High.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">2. It is likewise employed to denote the perpendicular height of
                    vegetables, and in this case it is nearly synonymous with <hi rend="italic"
                        >high.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">High.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">3. It can in no case be employed to express the height of merely
                    inanimate objects, as we can never say a <hi rend="italic">tall steeple, tower,
                        or pillar,</hi> but a <hi rend="italic">high steeple,</hi> &amp;c. For the
                    distinctions in these cases, see <hi rend="smallcaps">High.</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Long,</hi><hi rend="italic">adj.</hi> A relative term,
                    denoting the distance between the extremes of any body which is extended more in
                    one of its geometrical dimensions than in another. It is opposed to <hi
                        rend="italic">short.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">1. This term maybe applied to all inanimate objects, of whatever kind,
                    whose dimensions in one way exceed their dimensions in the other, and when not
                    in an erect posture, whatever be the other circumstances attending them, whether
                    it relates to superficies alone or to solid bodies, whether these be bounded or
                    open, straight or crooked, flexible or rigid, or in any other circumstances
                    whatever: thus we say <hi rend="italic">a long</hi> or <hi rend="italic">short
                        line, a long</hi> or <hi rend="italic">short ridge, street, ditch, rope,
                        chain, staff,</hi> and the like. But it is to be observed, that although <hi
                        rend="italic">long</hi> is in the strict sense only opposed to <hi
                        rend="italic">short,</hi> yet as it expresses the extension of matter in one
                    of its geometrical proportions, it is often contrasted by those words which
                    express the other proportions when we mean only to describe the several
                    proportions; as, <hi rend="italic">a table long and broad.</hi> And as these
                    several dimensions are expressed by different words, according to the various
                    forms, modifications, and circumstances in which bodies are found, therefore it
                    is in this sense contrasted by a great diversity of terms; as, <hi rend="italic"
                        >a long</hi> i <hi rend="italic">and brood</hi> or <hi rend="italic">wide,
                        narrow</hi> or <hi rend="italic">strait, street</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >lane</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">α long and thick</hi> or
                        <hi rend="italic">small rope, chain, staff.</hi> For the distinctions in
                    these cases see <hi rend="smallcaps">Broad, Wide, &amp;c.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">2. Objects necessarily fixed in an erect position can never have this
                    term applied to them, and therefore we cannot say <hi rend="italic">a long,</hi>
                    but a <hi rend="italic">high tower</hi> or <hi rend="italic">steeple.</hi> And
                    for the same reason, while trees are growing and fixed in an erect position, we
                    cannot apply this term to them; but when they are felled and laid upon the <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193323291?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0708-3291-0012"/>
                    ground, it is quite proper and necessary. Thus we do not say <hi rend="italic">a
                        long,</hi> but <hi rend="italic">a tall</hi> or <hi rend="italic">high
                        tree,</hi> while it is growing; but we say <hi rend="italic">a long,</hi>
                    not <hi rend="italic">a tall log of wood;</hi> and in the same manner we say <hi
                        rend="italic">a tall mast</hi> when it is fixed in the ship, but <hi
                        rend="italic">a long mast</hi> while it lies upon the beach. See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Tall</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">High.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">3. Those vegetables which are of a tender, pliant nature, or so weak as
                    not to be able to retain a fixed position, being considered as of a middle
                    nature between erect and prostrate bodies, admit of either the terms <hi
                        rend="italic">long, tall,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">high</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> as, <hi rend="italic">α long</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >tall rush</hi> or <hi rend="italic">willow wand,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >a long, tall,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">high stalk of corm</hi> See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">High</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Tall.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">4. The parts of vegetables, when considered as distinct from the whole,
                    even when growing and erect, assume the term <hi rend="italic">long</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> for we do not say <hi rend="italic">a tall,</hi> but
                        <hi rend="italic">a long shoot of a tree,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">a tree
                        with a long stem,</hi> in preference to <hi rend="italic">a tree with a high
                        stem.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">5. For the same reason, a staff and pole, even when fixed in a
                    perpendicular direction, assume the word <hi rend="italic">long,</hi> in
                    preference to <hi rend="italic">tall</hi> or <hi rend="italic">high.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">6. With regard to animals, the general rule is applied, without any
                    exceptions; <hi rend="italic">tall,</hi> and not <hi rend="italic">long,</hi>
                    being employed to denote the height of the human body when in an erect posture;
                    and <hi rend="italic">long,</hi> and not <hi rend="italic">tall,</hi> to denote
                    its length when in an incumbent situation. <hi rend="italic">Long</hi> applied
                    to all other animals which do not walk erect, always denotes their greatest
                    length in a horizontal position from head to tail.</p>
                <p part="N">7. In a figurative sense, it denotes, with regard to time, any thing at
                    a great distance from us.</p>
                <p part="N">8. As also, any thing that takes up much time before it is finished, as,
                        <hi rend="italic">a long discourse, a protracted note in music,</hi> and the
                    like.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Broad,</hi><hi rend="italic">adj.</hi> The distance
                    between the two nearest sides of any body whose geometrical dimensions are
                    larger in one direction than in another. It has a reference to superficies only,
                    and never to the solid contents, and is opposed to <hi rend="italic"
                        >narrow.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">1. <hi rend="italic">Broad,</hi> in the strictest acceptation, is
                    applied to denote those bodies only whose sides are altogether open and
                    unconfined; as, <hi rend="italic">a broad table, a broad wheel,</hi> &amp;c. and
                    in these cases it is invariably contrasted with <hi rend="italic">narrow</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> nor is there any other word which in these cases can be
                    considered as synonymous with it, or be used in its stead.</p>
                <p part="N">2. When any object is in some sort bounded on the sides, although not
                    quite closed up, as a road, street, ditch, and the like, either <hi
                        rend="italic">broad</hi> or <hi rend="italic">wide</hi> may be employed, but
                    with some difference of signification; <hi rend="italic">broad</hi> being most
                    properly used for those which are more open, and <hi rend="italic">wide</hi> for
                    those which are more confined: nor can this term be ever applied to such objects
                    as are closely bounded all around, as a house, a church, and the like, <hi
                        rend="italic">wide</hi> being here employed. For the more accurate
                    distinctions in these cases see the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Wide.</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Wide,</hi><hi rend="italic">adj.</hi> A term employed to
                    denote relative extent in certain circumstances, and opposed to <hi
                        rend="italic">narrow</hi> and <hi rend="italic">strait.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">1. This term is in its proper sense applied only to denote the space
                    contained within any body closed all round and on every side; as, a house, gate,
                    or the like; and it differs from <hi rend="italic">broad</hi> in this, that it
                    never relates to the superficies of solid objects, but is employed to express
                    the capaciousness of any body which contains vacant space; nor can capaciousness
                    in this sense be expressed by any other word but <hi rend="italic"
                    >wide.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">2. As many bodies may be considered either with respect to their
                    capaciousness or superficial extent, in all these cases either the term <hi
                        rend="italic">broad</hi> or <hi rend="italic">wide</hi> may be used; as,«
                        <hi rend="italic">broad or wide street orditch,</hi> &amp;c.; but with a
                    greater, or less degree of propriety, according to the circumstances of the
                    object, or the idea which we wish to convey. In a street where the houses are
                    low and the boundaries open, or in a ditch of small depth and large superficies,
                    as this largeness of superficies bears the principal proportion, <hi
                        rend="italic">broad</hi> would be more proper; but if the houses are of
                    gŗeat height, or the ditch of great depth, and capaciousness is the principal
                    property which affects the mind, we would naturally say <hi rend="italic">a wide
                        street</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ditch</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and the
                    same may be said of all similar cases. But there are some cases in which both
                    these terms are applied, with a greater difference of meaning; thus wc say <hi
                        rend="italic">a broad</hi> or <hi rend="italic">a ĩcide gate.</hi> As the
                    gate, however, is employed to denote either the aperture in the wall, or the
                    matter which closes that aperture, these terms are each of them used to denote
                    that particular quality to which they are generally applied; and as the opening
                    itself can never be considered as a superficies, the term <hi rend="italic"
                        >wide,</hi> in this case, denotes the distance between the sides of the
                    aperture; whilst, on the contrary, <hi rend="italic">broad</hi> denotes the
                    extent of matter fitted to close that aperture; nor can these two terms be in
                    any case substituted for one another.</p>
                <p part="N">3. As a figurative expression, it is used as a cant phrase for a
                    mistake; as, <hi rend="italic">you are wide of the mark</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >;</hi> that is, not near the truth.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Narrow,</hi><hi rend="italic">adj.</hi> A relative
                    term, denoting a proportional smallness of distance between the sides of the
                    superficies of plain bodies, and opposed to <hi rend="italic">broad.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">1. As this is only applied to superficies, it is exactly contrasted by
                        <hi rend="italic">broad,</hi> and is applied in all cases where the term <hi
                        rend="italic">broad</hi> can be used (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Broad)</hi>;
                    and in no other case but as a contrast to it, excepting the following.</p>
                <p part="N">2. It sometimes is employed to describe the smallness of space
                    circumscribed between certain boundaries, as opposed to <hi rend="italic"
                        >wide,</hi> and nearly synonymous with <hi rend="italic">straight</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> thus we say <hi rend="italic">a wide</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">a narrow house, church,</hi> and the like. For the necessary
                    distinctions here, see the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Strait.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">3. In a figurative sense it denotes <hi rend="italic">parsimony,
                        poverty, confined sentiments,</hi> and so forth.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Strait,</hi><hi rend="italic">adj.</hi> A relative
                    .term, denoting the extent of space in certain circumstances, and opposed to <hi
                        rend="italic">wide.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Wide.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">1. This term is employed, in its proper sense, to denote only space, as
                    contained between surrounding bodies in such circumstances as to denote some
                    degree of confinement, and is exactly opposed to <hi rend="italic">wide</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> as, <hi rend="italic">a ιoide</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >a strait gate,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Wide.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">2. So necessary is it that the idea of confinement should be connected
                    with this word, that in all those cases where the space contained is large, as
                    in a church or house, we cannot express a smaller proportional width by this
                    term. And as we have no other word to express space in these circumstances, we
                    are obliged to force the word <hi rend="italic">narroτν</hi> from its natural
                    signification, and make it express this. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Narrow.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">3. In some particular cases, <hi rend="italic">narrow</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">strait</hi> may be applied to the same object; as, <hi
                        rend="italic">a narrow</hi> or <hi rend="italic">a strait line</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> but here <hi rend="italic">strait</hi> is never
                    employed except where an idea of confinement is suggested, and where it is
                    exactly contrasted to <hi rend="italic">wide</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> nor
                    can <hi rend="italic">narrow</hi> be employed except in such circumstances where
                        <hi rend="italic">broad</hi> would be a perfect contrast to it. Therefore
                    these two terms may be always used in the same circumstances as those which
                    contrast with them. For an account of these see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Wide.</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193323304?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0708-3304-0013"/>
                <p part="N">4. The term <hi rend="italic">strait</hi> is likewise in a peculiar
                    manner used to denote the smallness of the internal diameter of those bodies
                    which are fitted to receive or contain others, as any kind of bag, tube, body
                    clothes, mortises, and others of the same kind; and in all these cases this term
                    may be employed to denote the smallness of their lesser diameter, and never the
                    term <hi rend="italic">narrow.</hi> But in certain circumstances the word <hi
                        rend="italic">tight</hi> may be substituted for it. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Tight.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">5. <hi rend="italic">Strait,</hi> in a figurative sense, denotes any
                    sort of confinement of sentiment or disposition.</p>
                <p part="N">TIGHT, <hi rend="italic">adj.</hi> A term employed in certain
                    circumstances to denote the internal capacity of particular bodies, and nearly
                    synonymous with <hi rend="italic">strait.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">This term is confined entirely to denote the smallness of the internal
                    dimensions of such objects as are formed to cover, or to receive or contain,
                    other solid bodies, and can be employed in no other case. And although it agrees
                    with <hi rend="italic">strait,</hi> in always denoting confinement, and by being
                    applicable to the same species of objects, yet it differs in the following
                    respects: 1. If there be any difference of the diameter of the objects to which
                    the term <hi rend="italic">strait</hi> can be applied, it has always reference
                    to the smaller; yet <hi rend="italic">tight</hi> may be applied to any sort of
                    confinement, whether it regards the length or breadth. 2. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Strait</hi> can be applied to all bodies of capacity when of small
                    diameter, without any sort of reference to the nature of the substance which it
                    may be capable of containing. . For we can say <hi rend="italic">a strait bag, a
                        strait sleeve, a strait mortise, a strait gate,</hi> and so on, whereas <hi
                        rend="italic">tight</hi> can only be applied to any body when it is
                    considered as having reference to another body which is intended to be contained
                    in it, and is pinched from want of room. Thus we say <hi rend="italic">the
                        sleeve ofa coat is too tight for the arm, the mortise is too tight for the
                        teìwn,</hi> and so forth; but we cannot say <hi rend="italic">the bag</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">the gate is too tight,</hi> because they are fitted to
                    receive any sort of objects. And hence it happens that in many cases the
                    dimensions of the same body may be expressed by <hi rend="italic">tight</hi> or
                        <hi rend="italic">strait,</hi> when considered in different circumstances.’
                    Thus we may say, <hi rend="italic">this sleeve is too strait,</hi> when we look
                    at a coat lying on the table and consider its proportions; but it is not till we
                    have tried it upon the arm which it is intended to cover, that we call it <hi
                        rend="italic">tight.</hi> And we may say, <hi rend="italic">a gate is too
                        strait</hi> or <hi rend="italic">too tight;</hi> but in the first case we
                    consider it as being too confined for admitting objects to pass through it; and
                    in the next, as being too confined with respect to the “leaves” which are to
                    shut the aperture not allowing them space to move with freedom.</p>
                <p part="N">These examples may serve to give some idea of the plan of an English
                    dictionary composed upon philosophical principles. But, besides the
                    circumstances above enumerated, there are many others which would require
                    particular attention in the execution of a work of this kind. In the English
                    language a great variety of terms occur which denote matter under certain
                    general forms or circumstances, without regarding the minute diversities that
                    may take place; as the word <hi rend="italic">cloth,</hi> which denotes matter
                    as manufactured into a particular form, including under it all the variety of
                    stuffs manufactured in that particular way, of whatever materials, colour,
                    texture, or fineness they may be. The same may be said of <hi rend="italic"
                        >wood, iron, yarn,</hi> and a great variety of terms of the same nature,
                    some of which cannot assume any plural; whilst others admit of it in all cases,
                    and others, again, admit or refuse it according to the different circumstances
                    in which they are considered.</p>
                <p part="N">In a dictionary, therefore, all this variety of cases ought to be
                    clearly and distinctly pointed out under each particular article. This is the
                    more necessary, as some of these words have others formed from them which might
                    be readily mistaken for their plurals, although they have a very different
                    signification; as <hi rend="italic">clothes,</hi> which does not denote any
                    number of pieces of different kinds of <hi rend="italic">cloth,</hi> but <hi
                        rend="italic">wearing apparel.</hi> The following example will illustrate
                    this head.</p>
                <p part="N">WOOD, <hi rend="italic">subst.</hi> A solid substance of which the
                    trunks and branches of trees consist.</p>
                <p part="N">1. This term is employed to denote the solid parts of vegetables of all
                    kinds, in whatever form or circumstances they are found. Nor does it admit of a
                    plural with propriety, unless in the circumstances after mentioned; for we say,
                        <hi rend="italic">many different hinds of wood,</hi> in preference to <hi
                        rend="italic">many hinds of woods</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> or we say,
                        <hi rend="italic">oak, ash,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">elm wood,</hi> not <hi
                        rend="italic">woods.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">2. But where we want to contrast wood of one quality or country with
                    that of another, it admits of a plural; for we say, <hi rend="italic">white
                        woods are in general softer than red</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> or, <hi
                        rend="italic">West Indian woods are in general of greater specific gravity
                        than the European woods.</hi> But unless where the colour, or some quality
                    which distinguishes it from growing wood, is mentioned, this plural ought as
                    much as possible to be avoided, as it always suggests an idea of growing
                    wood.</p>
                <p part="N">3. <hi rend="italic">Wood</hi> likewise denotes a number of trees
                    growing near one another, being nearly synonymous with Jò- <hi rend="italic"
                        >rest.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Forest.</hi> In this sense it always
                    admits of a plural; as, <hi rend="italic">Ye woods and wilds whose melancholy
                        gloom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p part="N">A dictionary cannot be reckoned complete without explaining obsolete
                    words; and if the terms of the several provincial dialects were likewise given,
                    it would be of great utility. Nor would this occupy much space, because a number
                    of these words need no other explanation than to mark along with them the words
                    which had come in their place, when there happened to be one perfectly
                    synonymous; and in those cases where the same idea could not be expressed in
                    modern language without a periphrasis, it would be of use to explain them
                    distinctly; so that, when a writer found himself at a loss for a term, and was
                    obliged to search for one beyond the bounds of his own language, he might take
                    one of these, if he found it expressive and energetic, in preference to another
                    drawn from a foreign language. This would at least have one good effect; it
                    would render our language more fixed and stable, not to say more accurate and
                    precise, than by borrowing from foreign languages. The following examples may
                    serve to give some idea of the manner of treating this part of the work.</p>
                <p part="N">MOE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">mo,</hi><hi rend="italic">adj.</hi> An
                    obsolete term still employed in the Scotch dialect, and by them pronounced <hi
                        rend="italic">mae,</hi> denoting a greater number, and nearly synonymous
                    with <hi rend="italic">more</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but it differs in this
                    respect, that in the Scotch dialect, <hi rend="italic">mae</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">mair</hi> (English <hi rend="italic">morej</hi> are each
                    employed in their distinct sphere, without encroaching upon one another, <hi
                        rend="italic">mae</hi> being employed to denote number, but never quantity
                    or quality, and <hi rend="italic">mair</hi> to denote quantity and quality, but
                    never number; thus they say <hi rend="italic">mae,</hi> not <hi rend="italic"
                        >mair, apples, men,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi rend="italic">mair,</hi> not <hi
                        rend="italic">mae, cloth, earth, courage,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Mair.</hi> Both these terms are supplied by the word <hi
                        rend="italic">more,</hi> which in the English language is applied
                    indiscriminately to denote quantity, quality, and number. See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">More.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">As the English language is so exceedingly irregular in the
                    pronunciation, the same letter in the same situation often assuming sounds
                    totally different in different words, it is impossible to establish any general
                    rules on this subject which do not admit of many exceptions; therefore a <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193323317?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0708-3317-0014"
                    />dictionary is the best means of ascertaining and pointing out the proper
                    pronunciations of words. For, if the writer first pointed out all the different
                    sounds which the same letter could ever be made to express, and assigned to
                    every particular sound which each letter could be made to assume, a particular
                    mark, appropriated to denote that particular sound <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the
                    letter whenever it occurred, by placing these particular marks above the letters
                    in the dictionary, the sound <hi rend="italic">of</hi> each letter would be
                    pointed out in all cases with the utmost certainty. It is impossible to
                    illustrate this by examples, without first ascertaining all the sounds of each
                    letter, which would lead into a discussion too long for this place.</p>
                <p part="N">We shall only further observe, that besides having the accented syllable
                    of every word <hi rend="italic">properly</hi> distinguished in a dictionary to
                    assist in the pronunciation, the English language requires another essential
                    improvement, namely, the use of accents to distinguish the meaning <hi
                        rend="italic">of words</hi> and <hi rend="italic">j)hrases,</hi> which,
                    although it is not so properly confined to a lexicographer, yet it is not quite
                    without his sphere. Thus, the word <hi rend="italic">as</hi> admits of two very
                    different sounds, as well as different significations; for example, “Cicero was
                    nearly <hi rend="italic">as</hi> eloquent <hi rend="italic">as</hi> Demosthenes
                    in which the first <hi rend="italic">as</hi> is pronounced <hi rend="italic"
                        >ass,</hi> and the last is pronounced <hi rend="italic">az.</hi> Now it
                    often happens that, in reading, the particular way in which it ought to be
                    understood is not pointed out by the context till after the word itself is
                    pronounced, which has an equal chance at least <hi rend="italic">of</hi> being
                    pronounced wrong; whereas, if it were always accented when employed in the one
                    sense, and not in the other, it would free the reader from this perplexity.
                    There are other cases in which the proper use of accents in writing would be of
                    great consequence; as at the beginning <hi rend="italic">of</hi> a sentence when
                    it is put as a question, or used ironically. But this docs not so properly
                    belong to the lexicographer as the grammarian.</p>
                <p part="N">The above examples, we hope, will be sufficient to give the reader some
                    idea of the plan which we would propose, and will enable him to determine
                    whether or not a dictionary, executed in this way, would convey to his mind a
                    more perfect knowledge of the English language than those dictionaries which
                    have hitherto been published. These examples are given rather with a view to
                    show the manner in which a work of this kind may be conducted, than as perfect
                    and unexceptionable explanations <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the several articles
                    there enumerated; and therefore we have not thought it necessary to produce any
                    authorities, although we are sensible that they would be requisite in such a
                    work.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
