<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0708-4422-0099-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DOMESDAY or Doomsday Book</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:875388">Conquerors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:874681">Confessors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1200824">Liberals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:997183">Liberalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139635">Surveys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139579">Surveying</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vb4q">Liberalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zd00">Surveys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh5s">Columns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193324422?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">DOMESDAY or <hi rend="smallcaps">Doomsday
                        Book</hi></label>, a most ancient record, made in the time of William the
                    Conqueror, and containing a survey of all the lands of England. It consists of
                    two volumes, namely, a greater and a less. The first is a large folio, written
                    on 382 double pages of vellum, in a small but plain character, each page having
                    a double column. Some of the capital letters and principal passages are touched
                    with red ink, and some have strokes of red ink run across them, as if scratched
                    out. This volume contains the description of thirty-one counties. The other
                    volume is in quarto, written upon 450 double pages of vellum, but in a single
                    column, and in a large but very fair character. It contains the counties of
                    Essex, Norfolk, Suffolk, part of the county of Rutland, included in that of
                    Northampton, and part of Lancashire, in the counties of York and Chester.</p>
                <p part="N">This work, according to the red book in the exchequer, was begun by
                    order of William the Conqueror, with the advice of his parliament, in the year
                    1080, and completed in the year 1086. The reason given for taking this survey,
                    as assigned by several ancient records and historians, was, that every man
                    should be satisfied with his own right, and not usurp with impunity what
                    belonged to another. But besides this, it is stated by others, that all those
                    who possessed landed estates now became vassals to the king, and paid him so
                    much money by way of fee or homage, in proportion to the lands they held; a
                    circumstance which appears very probable, as there was at that time extant a
                    general survey of the whole kingdom, made by order of King Alfred.</p>
                <p part="N">For the execution of this survey recorded in Domesday-book,
                    commissioners were sent into every county and shire, and juries summoned in each
                    hundred, out of all orders of freemen, from barons down to the lowest farmers.
                    These commissioners were to» be informed by the inhabitants, upon oath, of the
                    name of each manor and that <hi rend="italic">of</hi> its owner, also by whom it
                    was held in the time of Edward the Confessor; the number of hides; the quantity
                    of wood, of pasture, and of meadow land; how many ploughs tvere in the demesne,
                    and how many in the tenanted part of it; how many mills, and how many fish-ponds
                    or fisheries belonged,to it; the value of the whole in the time of King Edward,
                    as well as when granted by King William, and at the time of this survey; and
                    also whether it was capable of improvement or of being advanced in value. They
                    were likewise directed to return the tenants of every degree, the quantity of
                    lands then and formerly held by each of them, what was the number of villeins or
                    slaves, and also the number and kinds of their cattle and live stock. These
                    inquisitions being first methodized in the county, were afterwards sent up to
                    the king’s exchequer.</p>
                <p part="N">This survey, at the time when it was made, gave great offence to the
                    people, and occasioned a suspicion that it was intended for some new impost. But
                    notwithstanding all the precaution taken by the Conqueror to have the survey
                    faithfully and impartially executed, it appears that a false return was given in
                    by some of the commissioners, probably, as is alleged, from a pious motive. This
                    was particularly the case with the abbey of Croyland in Lincolnshire, the
                    possessions of which were greatly underrated, both with regard to quantity and
                    value. Perhaps more of these pious frauds were discovered, as it is said Ralph
                    Flambard, minister to William Rufus, proposed <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193324435?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0708-4435-0100"/>making a
                    fresh and more rigorous inquisition; but this was never carried into
                    operation.</p>
                <p part="N">Notwithstanding the proof of its falsehood in some instances, which must
                    throw a suspicion on all others, the authority of Domesday-book was never
                    permitted to be called in question; and when it has been necessary to
                    distinguish whether lands were held in ancient demesne or in any other manner,
                    recourse was al ways-had to Domesday-book, and to it only, in order to determine
                    the doubt. From this definitive authority, from which, as from the sentence
                    pronounced at domesday, or the day of judgment, there could be no appeal, the
                    name of the book is said to have been derived. But Stowe assigns another reason
                    for this appellation, namely, that Domesday-book is a corruption of “<hi
                        rend="italic">domus</hi><hi rend="italic">Dei</hi> book ;” a title given it
                    because heretofore it was deposited in the king’s treasury, in a place of the
                    church of Westminster or Winchester called <hi rend="italic">domus</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Dei.</hi> From the great care formerly taken to preserve this
                    survey, we may learn the estimation in which it was held. In the dialogue de
                    Sacrariis it is said, <hi rend="italic">Liber ille</hi> (meaning Domesday-book)
                        <hi rend="italic">sigilli regis</hi><hi rend="italic">comes</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">est individuus</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >thesauro.</hi> Until latterly it has been kept under three different locks
                    and keys; one in custody of the treasurer, and the others in that of the two
                    chamberlains of the exchequer. It is now deposited in the chapter-house at
                    Westminster, where it may be consulted, on paying to the proper officers a fee
                    of six-and-eightpence for a search, and fourpence per line for the matter
                    transcribed from it.</p>
                <p part="N">Besides the two volumes above mentioned, there is also a third made by
                    order of the same king, and which differs from the others in form rather than in
                    matter. There is likewise a fourth, which is kept in the exchequer, and which,
                    though a very large volume, is only an abridgment of the others. In the
                    remembrancer’s office in the exchequer there is kept a fifth book, also called
                    Domesday, which is the same with the fourth book already mentioned. King Alfred
                    had a roll which he called Domesday; and the Domesday-book made by William the
                    Conqueror referred to the time of Edward the Confessor, as that of King Alfred
                    did to the time of Ethelred. As ţhe fourth book of Domesday had many pictures
                    and gilt letters in the beginning, relating to the time of King Edward the
                    Confessor, this led some into an opinion altogether erroneous, namely, that
                    Domesday-book was composed in the reign of King Edward.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
