<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0708-3577-0034-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DIOGENES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 8, page 34</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:802066">Air</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:886086">Cynicism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49z90b98">Epigrams</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193323577" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DIOGENES</label> of Apollonia, in the island of Crete, held a
                    considerable rank among the philosophers who taught in Ionia before Socrates
                    appeared at Athens. He was the scholar and successor of Anaximenes, and in some
                    measure rectified his master’s opinion concerning air being the cause of all
                    things. It is said that he was the first who observed that air was capable of
                    condensation and rarefaction. He passed for an excellent philosopher, and died
                    about the 450th year before the Christian era.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Diogenes</hi><hi rend="italic">the Cynic,</hi> a famous
                    philosopher, was the son of a banker of Sinope, in Pontus. Being banished with
                    his father for coining false money, he retired to Athens, where he studied
                    philosophy under Antisthenes. He added new austerity to the sect of the Cynics,
                    and never did any philosopher carry so far a contempt for the conveniences of
                    life. He was one of those men who push every thing to excess, without excepting
                    even reason itself; and who confirm the saying, that there is no great genius
                    without a tincture of madness. He lodged in a tub; and had no other moveables
                    besides his staff', wallet, and wooden bowl, which last he threw away on seeing
                    a boy*drink out of the hollow of his hand. He used to call himself a vagabond,
                    who had neither house, home, nor country; he was obliged to beg, was ill
                    clothed, and lived from hand to mouth, and yet, says Aelian, he took as much
                    pride in these things as Alexander could in the conquest of the world. He was
                    not indeed a jot more humble than those who are clothed in rich apparel, and
                    fare sumptuously every day. He looked down on all the rest of the world with
                    scorn; he magisterially censured all mankind, and thought himself unquestionably
                    superior to all other philosophers. Alexander one day paid him a visit, and made
                    him an offer of riches, or any thing else; but all that the philosopher
                    requested of him was, to stand from betwixt him and the sun. The conqueror was
                    so affected with the vigour and elevation of his soul, as to declare that, “if
                    he were not Alexander, he would choose to be Diogenes ;” that is, if he were not
                    in possession of all that was pompous and splendid in life, he would, like
                    Diogenes, heroically despise it. Diogenes had great presence of mind, as appears
                    from his sharp sayings and quick repartees; and Plato seems to have hit off his
                    true character when he called him a Socrates run mad. He spent a great part of
                    his life at Corinth. The reason of his living there was curious and
                    characteristic. As he was going over to the island Aegina, he was taken by
                    pirates, who carried him into Crete, and there exposed him to sale. He answered
                    the crier, who asked him what he could do, that “he knew how to command men ;”
                    and perceiving a Corinthian who was passing by, he showed him to the crier, and
                    said, “Sell me to that gentleman, for he wants a master.” Xeniades, for that was
                    the Corinthian’s name, bought Diogenes, and carried him to Corinth, where he
                    appointed him tutor to his children, and intrusted him also with the management
                    of his house. Diogenes’s friends being desirous to redeem him, “You are fools,”
                    said he; “the lions are not the slaves of those who feed them, but they are the
                    servants of the lions.” He therefore plainly told Xeniades that he ought to obey
                    him, as people obey their governors and physicians. Some say that Diogenes spent
                    the remainder of his life in Xeniades’s family; but Dion Chrysostom asserts that
                    he passed the winter at Athens and the summer at Corinth. He died at Corinth
                    when he was about ninety years old; but authors are not agreed either as to the
                    time or the manner of his death. Tĥe following account, Jerome says, is the true
                    one. As he was going to the Olympic games, a fever seized him by the way; upon
                    which he lay down under a tree,· and refused the assistance of those who
                    accompanied him, and who offered him either a horse or a chariot. “Go you to the
                    games,” said he, “and leave me to contend with my illness. If I conquer, I will
                    follow you; if I am conquered, I shall go to the shades below.” He dispatched
                    himself that very night; saying, that “he did not so properly die, as get rid of
                    his fever.” He had for his disciples Onesicritus, Phocion, Stilpo of Megara, and
                    several other great men. His works are lost.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Diogenes</hi><hi rend="italic">Laertius,</hi> so called from
                    Laertia, in Cilicia, where he was born, an ancient Greek author, who wrote ten
                    books of the Lives of the Philosophers, still extant. In what year be flourished
                    it is not easy to determine. The oldest writers who mention him are Sopater
                    Alexandrinus, who lived in the time of Constantine the Great, and Hesychius
                    Milesius, who lived under Justinian. Diogenes often speaks in terms of
                    approbation of Plutarch and Phavorinus; and therefore, as Plutarch lived under
                    Trajan, and Phavorinus under Hadrian, it is certain that he could not flourish
                    before the reigns of those emperors. Ménage has fixed him as contemporary with
                    Severus, that is, about the year of Christ 200. From certain expressions of his,
                    some have fancied him to have been a Christian; but, as Menage observes, the
                    immoderate praises he bestows upon Epicurus will not permit us to believe this,
                    but must incline us rather to suppose that he was an Epicurean. He divided his
                    Lives into books, and inscribed them to a learned lady of the Platonic school,
                    as he himself intimates in his life of Plato. Montaigne was so fond of this
                    author, that, instead of one Laertius, he wishes we had a dozen; and Vossius
                    says that his work is as precious as gold. Without doubt, we are greatly obliged
                    to him for what we know of the ancient philosophers; and if he had been as exact
                    in writing as he was judicious in the choice of his subject, we should have been
                    still more obliged to him. Bishop Burnet, in the preface to his life of Sir
                    Matthew Hale, speaks of him in the following proper manner; “There is no book
                    the ancients have left us, which might have informed us more than Diogenes
                    Laertius’s Lives of the Philosophers, if he had had the art of writing equal to
                    that great subject which he undertook; for if he had given the world such an
                    account of them as <pb break="no" facs="nls:193323590"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0708-3590-0035"/>Gassendus has done of Peiresc, how great a stock
                    of knowledge might we have had, which by his unskilfulness is in a great measure
                    lost, since we must now depend only qn him, because we have no other and better
                    author who has written on that subject.” There have been several editions of his
                    Lives of the Philosophers; but the best is that printed in two volumes 4to, at
                    Amsterdam, 1693. This contains the advantages of all the former, besides some
                    which are peculiar to itself; such as the Greek text and the Latin version
                    corrected and amended by Meibomius; the entire notes of Henry Stephens, of both
                    the Casau-bons, and of Ménage; and twenty-four copperplates of philosophers,
                    elegantly engraved; to which is added, The History of the Female Philosophers,
                    written by Menage, and dedicated to Madame Dacier. Besides this, Laertius wrote
                    a book of Epigrams upon illustrious Men, called Pammetrus, from its various
                    kinds of metre; but this is not now extant.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
