<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0708-6944-0293-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">DUTENS</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 8, page 293</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1155691">Travelers</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1155558">Travel</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4086358z">Medals</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193326944" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">DUTENS</label>, Louis, a late French writer of some
                    celebrity, was born at Tours, of Protestant parents, on the 15th of January
                    1730. In his youth he addicted himself to poetry; and in 1748 he repaired to
                    Paris and composed a tragedy, entitled <hi rend="italic">The Return of Ulysses
                    to Ithaca,</hi> which he showed to the comedian Lanoue, requesting him to bring
                    it on the stage. The latter, how ever, returned the piece, advising the author
                    to retouch it. Irritated at this advice, Dutens went to Orleans, where he got
                    his play represented with great applause; but he soon became sensible of the
                    faults of his work, and abandoned a species of composition in which he found he
                    was not destined to excel. He soon afterwards went to England. Before leaving
                    France, he accidentally became acquainted with Miss Pitt, sister to the Earl of
                    Chatham, who gave him a letter to her brother; but after a short stay in London
                    he returned to France. Not long afterwards, he was recalled to London by one of
                    his uncles, to accompany a young English nobleman on his travels. Soon after his
                    arrival, the young nobleman changed his intention; but, at the same time, he
                    procured for Dutens the situation of a tutor in a private family. The father of
                    the pupil was a man of considerable literary and scientifie attainments, who
                    instructed Dutens in those branches of knowledge in which he was deficient. In
                    this manner he learnt Greek and mathematics; and he at the same time applied
                    himself to the oriental languages, and to Italian and Spanish. At the end of
                    three years his pupil died; but one of his sisters being deaf and dumb, Dutens
                    undertook to educate her. His young pupil, however, having become enamoured of
                    her instructor, he deemed it a matter of delicacy and of duty to leave the
                    house.</p><p>About this time he was appointed ebaplain and secretary to the Honourable Mr
                    Stuart Mackenzie, the English minister at the court of Turin, and left England
                    in the month of October 1758. In 1760, when Mr Mackenzie returned to England,
                    the secretary remained at Turin as charge d’affaires. Dutens came to England in
                    1762, and attached himself to the family of Lord Bute, who, before he retired
                    from office in 1763, procured him a pension. He again went to Turin as chargé
                    d’affaires, and during this second mission he undertook the task of collecting
                    and publishing a complete edition of the works of Leibnitz, and wrote his work
                    on the <hi rend="italic">Discoveries of the Ancients.</hi> He afterwards quitted
                    Turin, returned to Britain, and attached himself to the Duke of Northumberland,
                    who procured him a living in the north of England. He accompanied the duke’s
                    son, Lord Algernon Percy, in his travels through France, Italy, Germany, and
                    Holland; and while at Paris, he was chosen a member of the Aeademy of
                    Inscriptions. In 1776 he returned to England, and soon afterwards accompanied Mr
                    Mackenzie and his lady on a tour to Naples. On his return he was invited by Lord
                    Mountstuart, who had been appointed envoy extraordinary, to accompany him to
                    Turin, and Dutens found himself for the third time chargé d’affaires at that
                    court, during a short absence of the envoy. From Turin, which he left on account
                    of some unpleasant circumstances, he went to Florence, and thence to Rome. He
                    was in Paris in 1783, and returned to London the following year. The revenue lie
                    derived from his living of Elsdon, amounting to L.800 per annum, together with a
                    considerable legacy left him by Mr Mackenzie, and estimated at L. 15,000,
                    enabled him to pass the remainder of his life in affluence, and in the best
                    company. He died at his house, Mount Street, Grosvenor Square, on the 23d of May
                    1812.</p><p>Dutens was the editor of the works of Leibnitz, published at Geneva, 1769, in 6
                    vols. 4to; of the Greek pastoral romance of <hi rend="italic">Daphnis</hi><hi rend="italic">and Chloe,</hi> by Longus, 1776, 12mo, and of Daeier’s translation
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Manual of Epictetus,</hi> 1775, 18mo. He was also the
                    author of the following works: <hi rend="italic">Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Caprice</hi><hi rend="italic">Poétique,</hi> a collection of poems, 1750,
                    16mo. <hi rend="italic">Recherches sur</hi><hi rend="italic">l'</hi><hi rend="italic">origine des Decouvertes attribuées aux Modernes,</hi> 1766, 2
                    vols. 8vo, 4th edition, 1812. <hi rend="italic">Poesies,</hi> 1767, 12mo, and
                    1777, 8vo. <hi rend="italic">Le Tocsin,</hi> Rome, 1769, 12mo, reprinted under
                    the title of <hi rend="italic">Appel</hi><hi rend="italic">au</hi><hi rend="italic">bon Sens,</hi> London, 1777, 8vo. This work was directed against
                    the French philosophers, and was published anonymously. <hi rend="italic">Explication</hi><hi rend="italic">de quelques médailles de Peuples, de Villes,
                    et de Rois, Grecques et Phéniciennes,</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">Ψl⅜,</hi> 4to. <hi rend="italic">Explication de quelques médailles
                    du</hi><hi rend="italic">cabinet</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Duane,</hi> 1774, 4to. <hi rend="italic">Troisième Dissertation
                    sur quelques médailles Grecques et Phéniciennes, ou se trouvent des observations
                    pour servir a l'</hi><hi rend="italic">etude</hi><hi rend="italic">de la
                    Paléographie Numismatique,</hi> 1776, 4to. Dutens, at the same time, published a
                    more complete edition of the two preceding works. <hi rend="italic">Logique, ou
                    l’art de Raisonner,</hi> 1773, 12mo, 1777, 8vo, and reprinted also in his
                    miscellaneous works. <hi rend="italic">Du miroir</hi><hi rend="italic">ardent
                    d'</hi><hi rend="italic">Archimede,</hi> 1755, 1777, 8vo; <hi rend="italic">Des
                    pierres précieuses et des pierres fines, avec les moyens de les connaitre et de
                    les évaluer,</hi> 1776, 12mo, and reprinted at London and Paris. <hi rend="italic">Itinéraire des routes les plus frequentees, ou Journal d’un Voyage
                    aux principales Villes d’Europe,</hi> 1775, 8vo, and frequently republished with
                    additions and improvements. <hi rend="italic">Lettre</hi><hi rend="italic">a Μ.
                    D.E.(De-bure) sιιr la refutation du livre l’Esprit,</hi> par J. J. Rousseau,
                    1779, 12mo, which contains some letters of Helvetius and Rousseau. <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">l'</hi><hi rend="italic">Eglise, du
                    Pape, de quelques</hi><hi rend="italic">points</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    controverse, et moyens de réunion de toutes les Eglises Chrétiennes,</hi> 1781,
                    8vo; several times reprinted, and finally under the title of <hi rend="italic">Considerations</hi><hi rend="italic">Théologiques sur les moyens de réunir
                    toutes les Eglises Chretienncs,</hi> 1798, 8vo. <hi rend="italic">Oeuvres</hi><hi rend="italic">melees,</hi> 1784, 8vo. Under the same title almost the whole
                    works of Dutens were collected and published at London, 1797, 4 vols. 4to. <hi rend="italic">EAmi</hi><hi rend="italic">des etrangers qui voyagent en
                    Angleterre,</hi> 1789, 8vo, frequently reprinted, <hi rend="italic">ilistoire de
                    ce qui s est passe pour le rétablissement d’une régence en Angleterre,</hi>
                    1789, 8vo. <hi rend="italic">Recherches sur le tems le plus recule de l’usage
                    des Voûtes chez les anciens,</hi> 1795. <hi rend="italic">Mémoires d’un Voyageur
                    qui se repose,</hi> Paris, 1806, 3 vols. 8vo. The two first volumes contain the
                    life of the author, written in a romantic style; the third bears the title of
                    <hi rend="italic">Dutensiana,</hi> and is filled with remarks, anecdotes, bon
                    mots, and so forth. Dutens is the author of the <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of
                    Medals</hi> in Swinburne’s <hi rend="italic">Travels,</hi> and of the French
                    text to the second volume of the <hi rend="italic">Marlborough Gems.</hi> There
                    is a <hi rend="italic">Memoir</hi> of his in the Collection of the Academy of
                    Inscriptions, and he also published a small tract on the <hi rend="italic">Iron
                    Mash.</hi> He was a member of the Royal Society of London, and had the title of
                    historiographer to the king. (See Memoirs of Dutens in the <hi rend="italic">Gentlemans Magazine for</hi> 1812; Chalmers’s <hi rend="italic">Biographical
                    Dictionary</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Biographie</hi><hi rend="italic">Universelle.)</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>