<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0708-6866-0287-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DURANGO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 8, page 287</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1744651">Dollarization</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:896433">Dollar</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1064014">Pike</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1097334">Rice</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp1v">Dollar</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86t6p">Mining</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193326866" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DURANGO</label>, a town of Spain, in the province of Biscay.
                    It stands twenty miles south-east of Bilboa, on one of those numerous streams
                    which, when united, form its river. It contains 2800 inhabitants. Manufactories
                    of iron and steel goods are carried on here.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Durango,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">New Biscay,</hi> an
                    intendancy of Mexico in North America. According to Humboldt, it extends from
                    long. 104. 40. to 110. 0. W. and from lat. 23. 55. to 29. 5. N.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>According to Major Pike, a
                    more recent traveller in these parts, it is situated between long. 105. and 111.
                    W. and lat. 24. and</p><p>33. N. lie gives its length from north-west to
                    south-east at G00 miles, its greatest breadth at 400, and its population at
                    200,000.</p></note> It is bounded on the west by Sonora; on the east it touches
                    on San Luis Potosi; and towards the north and east, for upwards of 200 leagues,
                    it borders on an uncultivated country, inhabited by warlike and independent
                    Indians. It comprehends the northern extremity of the great table-land of
                    Anahuac. Its length from north to south, from the celebrated mines of Guarisamey
                    to the mountains of Carcay, is 232 leagues. Its breadth is very unequal, and
                    near Parrel is scarcely fifty-eight leagues. Its extent of surface is greater
                    than that of the united kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland; and yet its total
                    population, according to Humboldt, was in 1803 rather less than 160,000. Of
                    these, Major Pike thinks, three twentieths might be European whites, five
                    twentieths Creoles, five twentieths Mestizoes and half-castes, and seven
                    twentieths Indians. It comprises, besides the city of Durango, six towns
                    (villas), 199 villages (pueblos), seventy-five parishes (paroquias), 152
                    haciencias, thirty-seven missions, and 400 cottages (ranchos).</p>
                <p>The climate of this intendancy is stated by Major Pike to be dry, and the heat,
                    at that period of the year which precedes the rainy season, to be very great.
                    The rains commence in June, and continue by light showers till September. During
                    the remainder of the year there falls neither rain nor snow to moisten the
                    earth, and the atmosphere becomes highly electrified. The agricultural produce
                    consists of wheat, maize, rice, oats, cotton, flax, indigo, and the fruit of the
                    vine. To the north of Chihuahua, about thirty miles to the right of the main
                    road, there is some pine timber. In one place, near a spring, Major Pike noticed
                    a solitary walnut tree; and in all the small streams there are, he says, shrubby
                    cotton trees. “With these few exceptions, the whole province is a naked, barren
                    plain, which presents to the eye an arid unproductive soil; and, more especially
                    in the neighbourhood of mines, even the herbage appears to be poisoned by the
                    qualities of the land.” New Biscay trades with the southern provinces, and also
                    with New Mexicoand Sonora, furnishing to the more populous parts of the kingdom
                    a great number of horses, mules, beeves, sheep, and goats, in return for dry
                    goods, European furniture, ammunition, books, and other articles, which are
                    brought from the capital on mules. “Some individuals make large fortunes by
                    being the carriers from Mexicoto Chihuahua, the freight being eight dollars per
                    cent.; and they generally put 300 lb. on each mule. The merchants make their
                    remittances twice a year, in bullion. Goods sell at Chihuahua about 200 per
                    cent, higher than the prices in the seaport towns of the Atlantic. This was in
                    1807. Horses then averaged six dollars; some, however, fetched a hundred
                    dollars; and trained mules twenty dollars. Rice sold for four dollars the
                    hundredweight. They manufacture some few arms, blankets, stamped leather,
                    embroidery, coarse cotton and woollen cloths, and a species of carpeting.” This
                    traveller concludes his statistical account of <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193326879" xml:id="kp-eb0708-6879-0288"/>the province by stating, that
                    law here is merely a shadow, the only laws that can be said to be in force being
                    the military and the ecclesiastical; that the corruption of morals is general,
                    this being the natural concomitant of a great degree of luxury among the rich,
                    and of misery among the poor; and that the Roman Catholic religion is in full
                    force, but the inferior clergy are much dissatisfied.</p>
                <p>There are no slaves in this province, nor, according to Humboldt, a single
                    tributary individual; and “all the inhabitants, are either white, or consider
                    themselves as such.” Major Pike explains the state of things more specifically.
                    Except the Apadus, who inhabit the Bolson de Mapimi, there are, he says, no
                    uncivilized tribes in this province. “The Christian Indians are so incorporated
                    amongst the lower grades of Mestizoes, that it is scarcely possible to draw the
                    line of distinction, except at the ranchos of some nobleman or large landholder,
                    where they arc in a state of vassalage. This class of people laid a conspiracy,
                    which was so well concerted as to baffle the research of the Spaniards for a
                    length of time, and to occasion them the loss of several hundreds of the
                    inhabitants. The Indians used to go out from their villages in small parties; in
                    a short time a part would return with a report that they had been attacked by
                    the Indians. The Spaniards would, immediately send out a detachment in pursuit,
                    when they were led into an ambuscade, and every soul cut off. They pursued this
                    course so long that the whole province became alarmed at the rapid manner in
                    which their enemies multiplied; but some circumstances leading to a suspicion,
                    they made use of the superstition of these people for their ruin. Some officers
                    disguised themselves like friars, and went round amongst the Indians, pretending
                    to be possessed of the spirit of prophecy. They preached up to them that the day
                    was approaching when a general deliverance from the Spanish tyranny was about to
                    take place, and invited the Indians to join with them in promoting the work of
                    God. The poor creatures came forward, and in their confessions stated the great
                    hand that had already been put to the work. After they had ascertained the
                    nature and extent of the conspiracy, and obtained a body of troops, they
                    commenced the execution, and put to death about four hundred of them. This
                    struck terror and dismay throughout the Indian villages, and they durst not rise
                    to support their freedom and independence.”</p>
                <p>Durango or Guadiana, the principal city, is the residence of the intendant and of
                    a bishop. It is situated in the most southern part of the province, in long.
                    107. W. and lat. 25. N., at 170 leagues distance in a straight line from the
                    city of Mexico and 289 leagues from the town of Santa Fe, in New Mexico The
                    elevation of the town above the sea level is 6800 feet. There are frequent falls
                    of snow, and the thermometer descends to 14° Fahrenheit below the freezing
                    point. The city was founded in 1559. The population in 1803 was 12,000, but
                    Major Pike makes it 40,000. He also states that the city is infested in a very
                    remarkable manner by scorpions. “They come out of the walls and crevices in May,
                    and continue for about a fortnight in such numbers that the inhabitants never
                    walk in their houses after dark without a light, and always shift or examine the
                    bed-clothes and beat the curtains previously to going to rest, after which the
                    curtains are secured under the bed.”</p>
                <p>In the midst of a very level plain, between this city, the plantations Del Ojo
                    and Del Chorro, and the town of Nombre de Dios, which lies in the road to the
                    famous mines of Sombrereto, there arises a singular group of rocks, of a very
                    grotesque form, covered with scoria, called La Breña. They extend twelve leagues
                    from north to south, and rise from east to west, and appear to be a volcanic
                    production, consisting of basaltic amygdaloid. On the summit of one of the
                    neighbouring mountains (the Treayle), is found a crater 300 feet in
                    circumference and 100 feet in perpendicular depth. In the environs of Durango
                    there is also to be found, insulated in the plain, an enormous mass of malleable
                    iron and nickel, said to weigh upwards of 40,000 pounds avoirdupois, and
                    corresponding in its composition to the aëroliths which fell in 1751, near
                    Agram, in Hungary. Major Pike also informs us that there is “a mountain or hill
                    of loadstone” about a hundred miles south of Chihuahua.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
