<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0708-3655-0040-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">DISCORD</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 8, page 40</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1127099">Sounds</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1126935">Sound</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1030814">Musicals</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:900541">Ear</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1050321">Paganism</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77x65">Sound</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f4j">Ear</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40p0wv7t">Paganism</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193323655" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">DISCORD</label>, in general, signifies disagreement or
                    opposition between different persons or things.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Discord,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Music,</hi> is every
                    sound which, joined with another, forms an assemblage disagreeable to the ear;
                    or rather, every interval whose extremes do not coalesce. Now, as there are no
                    other concords or consonances, excepting those which form amongst themselves,
                    and with their fundamental sound, perfect chords, it follows that every interval
                    must be a real dissonance or discord; even the third and sixth were reckoned
                    such among the ancients, who excluded them from the number of consonant
                    chords.</p><p>The term <hi rend="italic">dissonaìice,</hi> which is synonymous with discord, is
                    compounded of two words, namely, the inseparable preposition r‰ and the verb <hi rend="italic">sonare</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> which, both in a literal and
                    metaphorical sense, signifies <hi rend="italic">disagreement</hi> or <hi rend="italic">disunion.</hi> In reality, that which renders dissonances grating,
                    is, that the sounds which form them, so far from uniting in the ear, seem to
                    repel ea^h other, and are heard each by itself as two distinct sounds, though
                    produced at the same time.</p><p>This repulsion or violent oscillation of sounds is heard more or less, as the
                    vibrations which produce it are more or less frequently coincident. When two
                    vocal strings are gradually tuned till they approach a consonant interval, the
                    pulsations become slower as the chord grows more just, till at last they are
                    scarcely heard, if heard at all; and hence it appears certain, that the pleasure
                    produced in us by harmony results from the more or less exact and frequent
                    coincidence or vibration; though the reason why this coincidence should afford
                    pleasure, more than any other modification or combination of sounds, appears to
                    us inscrutable. The agreeable effects of dissonance in harmony are no objection
                    to this theory; since it is allowed that the sensations excited by discord are
                    not in themselves immediately and necessarily pleasing, but only please by
                    auricular deception. The ear is surprised with the shock it receives, without
                    being able to imagine how it should have happened; and in proportion as it is
                    harsh and grating, we feel the pleasure of returning harmony enhanced, and the
                    disappointment of being artfully and insensibly extricated more agreeable.</p><p>The name of <hi rend="italic">dissonance</hi> is given sometimes to the interval,
                    and sometimes also to each of the two sounds which form it. But though two
                    sounds equally form a dissonance between themselves, this term is most
                    frequently applied to that sound in particular which is most extraneous to the
                    chord.</p><p>The number of possible dissonances is indefinite; but as in music we exclude all
                    intervals which are not found in the system received, the number of dissonances
                    is reduced to a very few; besides, in practice we can only select from those few
                    such as are agreeable to the species, and the mode in which we compose; and,from
                    this last number we must exclude such as cannot be used consistently with the
                    rules prescribed. But what, it may be asked, are these rules? Have they any
                    foundation in nature, or are they merely arbitrary? This is what Rousseau, whom
                    in this article we have followed or abandoned as his observations appeared
                    useful or frivolous, purposes to investigate as its principal object.</p><p>But where does his scrutiny terminate? Not in the abolition of the rules
                    prescribed. These have still subsisted, and will continue to subsist, while the
                    frame of man, and the nature of music, remain what they are. If, then, the rules
                    be permanent and universal, the principle upon which they are founded may be
                    latent or ambiguous; but the rules themselves can never be purely arbitrary. How
                    else could it happen that Rameau, D’Alembert, and Rousseau should admit the
                    force and effect of these rules, whilst each of these masters exerted his whole
                    genius to give a different account of their cause and origin? Rousseau himself,
                    as we have seen in a former article, inculcates the necessity of dissonances for
                    the completion of harmony. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chord.) Now,</hi> if this
                    be true, the easiest methods of introducing and dismissing these discords must
                    be the most eligible, and of consequence the rules for using them must be
                    established. It is not then upon the subsistence or demolition of any particular
                    theory that they depend. Were we to attend to the particular objections which
                    may be uιged against any system whatever, where is the theory which will be
                    found proof against the efforts of scepticism? After all, the objections of
                    Rousseau to Rameau’s theory, as applied by D’Alembert to the origin of
                    consonances, appear to be much more frivolous than the analogies from which he
                    pretends that this origin was deduced. It appears from D’Alembert’s exposition
                    of this theory, that, if not for all, it affords a solution for the most
                    material and essential phenomena in harmony, which is sufficient for its
                    establishment, until another can be found which will give a rational and
                    consistent account of the whole; a discovery which has not yet been made. But
                    whilst we acknowledge the futility of Rousseau’s objections against D’Alembert’s
                    explication of dissonances, we must at the same time admire the ingenuity with
                    which he has deduced them from principles purely mechanical, without departing
                    from the system of Rameau. This mechanical explication will be found in his
                    Musical Dictionary, under the article <hi rend="italic">Dissonance.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Discord,</hi> the goddess of, in Pagan theology. She is
                    represented by Aristides with fiery eyes, a pale countenance, livid lips, and
                    wearing a dagger in her bosom. It was she who at the marriage of Peleus and
                    Thetis threw in the golden apple, on which was written “To the fairest,” and
                    which occasioned a contention between the goddesses Juno, Minerva, and Venus,
                    each pretending a title to the apple. She was likewise called <hi rend="italic">Ate</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Eris.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>