<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0708-3239-0008-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">DIARBEKIR</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 8, page 8</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1153279">Towers</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1133812">Stone</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1133955">Stoning</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807572">Amides</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193323239" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">DIARBEKIR</label>, a city of Asiatic .Turkey, and capital of
                    thepashalic of Diarbekir, situated on a mass of basaltic rock, which rises in an
                    eminence on the western bank of the Tigris, the stream of that river flowing by
                    the foot of this hill from north-east to south-west, as it makes a sharp bend in
                    that direction from the northward. The form of the town is very nearly circular.
                    It is about three miles in circuit, and is encompassed by a lofty thick wall of
                    black stone. This wall, which is supposed to be a work of the Romans, is
                    fortified by numerous round and square towers at irregular intervals, which
                    being high, and strongly built of hewn stone, present an appearance of great
                    strength. The most strongly fortified portion of the city is on the north, where
                    the square towers are very thickly placed, and there isalongbattery ofguns
                    mounted, pointing through covered embrasures; but the whole is now in a
                    neglected and ruinous condition. The town is also environed by a ditch. The city
                    hasfour gates, which lead toMardin,to Asia Minor or Rumelia, to the mountains of
                    Armenia and Koordistan, and to the river. The citadel, standing about midway
                    between the two last-mentioned gates, is thus in the north-east angle of the
                    town, and, seated on the eminence of rock in that quarter, overlooks the stream
                    of the Tigris below, and, by its elevation, commands the whole of the town. It
                    is surrounded by a wall, is divided into many courts, and contains the palace of
                    the pasha, which is rather a commodious than a splendid building. Attached to it
                    are extensive stables and an open space, in which the horses and the horsemen
                    are exercised. Onc of the places used as a stable presents the ruins of a
                    handsome and noble edifice, with finely-constructed domes of brickwork, and a
                    beautiful door with columnsand pilasters, the remains, as Mr Buckingham
                    observes, of an old Christian building. The citadel is now almost completely in
                    ruins. There is a fine view of the town from this height. The houses are built
                    of black basalt in the lower stories, and of dark-coloured brick in the upper
                    ones; this, with a succession of flat terraces, gives a sameness and gloominess
                    to the aspect of the town, which, however, is somewhat relieved by the view of
                    the mosques, towers, and little garden-plots seen in different parts of the
                    town. The houses present a handsome appearance, and many of them are elegant. Of
                    the mosques seen from the citadel, there are fifteen with minarets, nine having
                    circular shafts and galleries in the Mahommedan style, and the remaining six
                    having square towers, after the manner of Christian churches. There are five
                    other mosques with domes or cupolas only, and several smaller ones, making
                    altogether twenty-five Mahommedan places of worship. Among the minarets of the
                    mosques, some were observed by Mr Buckingham, to w hose travels in Mesopotamia
                    we are chiefly indebted for this account of Diarbekir, to be highly sculptured;
                    and in several of the square towers were intermixed layers of red burnt brick,
                    mixed with masonry of stone, after the manner of the Roman towers in the walls
                    of Antioch. Amidst the ruins of the castle some fine arches of highly burnt
                    bricks were also observed, which, from their form, as well as material, looked
                    more like Ro man than Saracenic work. The bazars and baths contain brick work of
                    a similar kind, which Mr Buckingham thinks is decidedly Mahommedan. Broken
                    columns of black coral are seen scattered in different quarters of the town; and
                    among these are several Ionic capitals of Greek origin. Of the Christian
                    churches, the Armenians have two, one of them large and richly decorated, and
                    the other smaller, but more tastefully adorned. The Catholics have one church,
                    with a convent attached to it; the Syrians and the Greeks have also each a place
                    of worship; and the Jews have a small synagogue for their service. There are
                    upwards of twenty baths in the town, and about fifteen khans or caravanserais.
                    The Khan Hassan Pasha is particularly fine; and in its lower court the
                    corn-market is usually held. Its magazines within the piazza, which runs round
                    this, are generally filled with goods. In the upper galleries are carried on
                    several trades and manufactures. There are also convenient lodgings here for
                    travellers; and there is an upper story, with apartments for the harems or
                    families of those who may sojourn here, with kitchens, fire-places, and other
                    domestic conveniences. The bažars are well supplied with goods of all
                    descriptions, and during the hours of business are thronged with people. They
                    arc, however, narrow, crooked, and mostly roofed over with wood, being neither
                    so regularly laid out, nor so well covered in, as they generally are in the
                    large towns of Turkey. The manufactures of the town are chiefly silk and. cotton
                    stuffs, printed muslins, shawls, and handkerchiefs, morocco leather in skins of
                    all colours, smiths’ work in hardware, and pipes for smoking, made of the jasmin
                    branch, covered with muslin, and embroidered with gold and silver thread. About
                    1500 looms are supposed to be employed in the weaving of stuffs; and there are
                    about 300 printers of cotton, with as many manufacturers of leather in the skin,
                    besides shoemakers, saddlers, and other workmen. There are 100 smiths, and 150
                    makers of ornamented pipe-stems, besides those who make the clay-bath, amber
                    mouth-pieces, &amp;c. European cloths are introduced here through Aleppo, as
                    well as most of the glass-ware, which is of German manufacture; fine muslins,
                    Cashmere shawls, spices, and drugs, are brought from India through Bagdad. The
                    common manufactures for domestic uses are supplied at home, and provisions and
                    fruit are abundant and cheap.</p><p>The governor of the pashalic and city of Diarbekir has the dignity of three
                    tails, and is immediately dependent on the sultan. He has a force under him of
                    1000 men, of whom more than one half arc Turkish cavalry, and the remainder
                    Turkish and Albanian foot. There are, besides, several petty chiefs among the
                    Turks and the Koords, who are bound, for certain privileges which they enjoy, to
                    furnish each his contingent of troops on the pasha’s requisition. The people,
                    though accustomed to despotic rule, consider the government of the pasha as
                    secure; though, according to Mr Buckingham, there were few Turkish towns in
                    which there seemed to be more of personal liberty, competence, and comfort,
                    among all classes of people.</p><p>From the circumstance of the walls and buildings of this city being constructed
                    almost wholly of black stone, it is called by the Turks Kara Amid, or the Black
                    Amid. Its ancient name was Amida; the name of Diarbekir proceeds chiefly from
                    the Arabs, as the name of Amid is still used by the Turks in all their public
                    writings. Amida was successively taken, retaken, and destroyed, in the ancient
                    wars between the Persians and Romans. It was pillaged by Tamerlane in the year
                    1393; and successive sieges and captures followed by the Persian kings, until it
                    was conquered and taken by Selim, the first sultan of the Osmanlee Turks, in the
                    year 1515. In 1605 it again fell <pb break="no" facs="nls:193323252" xml:id="kp-eb0708-3252-0009"/>under the power
                    of Persia; but it was afterwards retaken by the Turks, under whose dominion it
                    has since continued. General Gardanne computes the population at 80,000,
                    Macdonald Kinneir at 38,000, and Mr Buckingham, the latest traveller, at 50,000.
                    The great majority consist of Osmanlee Turks, who are soldiers, government
                    officers, merchants, and mechanics. The Armenians, who are the next numerous
                    class, amount to 1000 families. The Arab, Turkish, and Armenian followers of the
                    Catholic communion number 500 families, the Syrian sect 400, and the Greeks
                    about 50 families. Almost all the Jews have of late emigrated to Bagdad, Aleppo,
                    or Constantinople. The inhabitants of Diarbekir are thought to be more fanatical
                    in their hatred of Christians than in other parts of the empire. This place is
                    187 miles north-west of Mardin, 220 north-east of Orfah, and 350 north-east of
                    Aleppo. Long. 39. 52. E. Lat. 37. 55. N.</p></div></body></text></TEI>