<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0708-3525-0030-08" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">DILLENIUS, John James</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 8, page 30</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1065823">Plants</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:984609">Judgments</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:936289">Fungi</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fd2x">Fungi</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193323525" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">DILLENIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">John James</hi></label>, a
                    distinguished botanist of the eighteenth century, who may be called the father
                    of cryptogamie botany, was born at Darmstadt in 1687. He was educated as a
                    physician in the university of Giessen; but his attention was very early
                    diverted from ' medical studies to the observation and discrimination of plants;
                    nor does he appear to have ever followed any branch of the practice of physic.
                    In botany he was strictly a practical observer, having addicted himself but
                    little to the principles of classification, and not at all to the physiology of
                    vegetables. Some branches of zoology occasionally engaged him, which an
                    assiduous collector of plants, in their native situations, can hardly escape, so
                    closely are these studies, especially that of insects and the lower tribes of
                    animated beings, connected with botany. Dillenius, whilst at Giessen, wrote
                    several papers for the <hi rend="italic">Ephemerides Natures</hi><hi rend="italic">Curiosorum,</hi> on American plants naturalized in Europe, on
                    coffee, on opium obtained from poppies in Germany, with some minute critical
                    remarks on <hi rend="italic">Spergula pentandra,</hi> as well as on various
                    cryptogamous plants. He published also a paper on leeches, and two species of
                    <hi rend="italic">papilio.</hi> He printed at Giessen in 1719 his <hi rend="italic">Catalogus Plantarum sponte</hi><hi rend="italic">circa
                    Gissam</hi><hi rend="italic">nascentium,</hi> a valuable little octavo volume,
                    with figures drawn and engraved by his own hand, of the parts of fructification,
                    particularly designed to illustrate the generic characters of plants, previously
                    not well arranged or understood. In this work he established many new genera,
                    which have for the most part kept their ground. His great merit as a general
                    botanist consisted in a constant attention to the only sound principle of
                    scientific botany, the discrimination of <hi rend="italic">genera</hi> by the
                    parts of the flower and fruit. This principle, first proposed by the great
                    Conrad Gesncr, Dillenius applied to practice, with a severer judgment and closer
                    attention than perhaps any other person, from Gesner to Linnaeus. The little
                    book in question is arranged most inconveniently according to the times of the
                    plants’ flowering. Its preface, however, enters into the subject of
                    classification, a subject to which young botanists are generally prone, but of
                    which they as generally, after having embroiled it, take their leave, in
                    proportion as they acquire more practical knowledge. Dillenius so far displayed
                    his judgment, that he rather showed the faults of the systems of Tournefort,
                    Knaut, and Rivinus, than offered any thing of his own. This led him into some
                    controversies, from which he soon disengaged himself, and never subsequently
                    took up the question at all.</p><p>The great William Sherard, while returning in 1718 from Smyrna through Germany,
                    met with Dillenius, whose scientific merit could not have escaped so eminent a
                    botanist. He brought him to England in 1721, and excited him to publish, in
                    1724, that valuable enlarged edition of Ray’s <hi rend="italic">Synopsis</hi> of
                    British plants, which has ever since been in general use, and which the editor
                    enriched with engravings of his own. In this publication, compared with the <hi rend="italic">Catalogus</hi> of the plants of Giessen above mentioned, we cannot
                    but perceive the difference between an author working upon his own original
                    materials, and the commentator or illustrator of the labours of another. Though
                    Dillenius made numerous and correct additions to Ray’s work, in the cryptogamie
                    tribes at least, he rather confused than improved the other parts of the book,
                    especially with regard to synonyms, in which department he was never supremely
                    accurate.</p><p>In 1732 Dillenius published his magnificent <hi rend="italic">Hortus</hi><hi rend="italic">El-thamensis,</hi> in two volumes folio, containing 324 plates,
                    engraved on pewter, with his own hand. Their merit consists in their very great
                    precision and fidelity. The descriptions, and historical as well as botanical
                    remarks, render this a classical book in botany. Its style is good, and the
                    whole performance is worthy of the author, and of his eminent patron, whose
                    brother, Dr James Sherard, was the owner of the garden at Eltham, which
                    furnished the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193323538" xml:id="kp-eb0708-3538-0031"/>rich materials of this publication. Before this
                    book appeared, its author was established at Oxford, in the new professorship
                    founded there by the will of William Sherard, who died in August 1728, and who
                    left L.3000 for the purpose, besides his own library, manuscripts, and ample
                    herbarium. Dillenius took the degree of M. D. in this university in 1735, though
                    he had previously obtained the same rank at Giessen; and he now devoted himself
                    to the completion of the <hi rend="italic">Pinax,</hi> or universal collection
                    of synonyms, which was Sherard’s chief object in this foundation. The work was
                    never finished; for indeed neither Dillenius nor any one else could even at that
                    time be competent to it: still less, as botanists and botanical works multiplied
                    excessively, was this undertaking practicable. The publications of Linnaeus soon
                    rendered it unnecessary. That illustrious foreigner in 1736 visited Dillenius,
                    who was desirous of fixing him here as his coadjutor; but to this scheme there
                    were several impediments. Nevertheless these distinguished men continued ever
                    after in correspondence, certainly to the advantage of their common study,
                    except in one but too important instance. We allude to the theory of the
                    fructification of mosses, in which Linnaeus implicitly adopted the faulty
                    opinion of the Oxford professor, contrary to his own better observation and
                    judgment, taking the capsule for the anther. This leads us to mention the
                    immortal work on which the fame of Dillenius rests, and which, in its way, will
                    never be excelled, the <hi rend="italic">Historia Muscorum,</hi> published in
                    1741, in one quarto volume, with eighty-five plates, drawn and engraved by the
                    author. In this performance, laborious investigation, acute discrimination,
                    supreme accuracy, and profound learning, are displayed beyond all example or
                    comparison. Following inquirers, like the celebrated Hedwig, may, with better
                    helps, have examined the same objects more deeply; but none has taken so
                    complete a view of the subject, nor made so very few mistakes. No botanical book
                    perhaps is so perfect in synonyms. Whether the labour of this undertaking was
                    too much for the health of its author, or whether his sedentary mode of life
                    was, on the whole, injurious, we have no particular information; but he began,
                    soon after the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Historia Muscorum,</hi> to
                    complain of ill health and advancing age. He was of a short stature and
                    corpulent habit, and died of an apoplexy on the 2d April 1747, in his sixtieth
                    year. A picture of this distinguished botanist is preserved in the
                    picture-gallery at Oxford, from which a print has been published in Sim’s and
                    Konig’s <hi rend="italic">Annals of Botany,</hi> vol. ii. Dillenius is said to
                    have been amiable and respectable in his private character. He never married.
                    His books, collection of mosses referring to his great work, with many drawings,
                    especially of <hi rend="italic">Fungi,</hi> were bought by his successor Dr
                    Humphrey Sibthorp, and added to the Sherardian Museum, where they still remain.
                    (x. χ.)</p></div></body></text></TEI>