<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0708-3499-0028-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DIGNITY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 8, page 28</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:922595">Felting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:922586">Felt</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984249">Joy</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4nv99f02">Felt</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f4j">Ear</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193323499" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DIGNITY</label>, as applied to the titles of noblemen,
                    signifies honour and authority. Dignity may be divided into superior and
                    inferior; as the titles of duke, earl, baron, &amp;c. which are the highest
                    names of dignity; and those of baronet, knight, serjeant-at-law, &amp;c. which
                    are the lowest. Nobility only can give so high a name of dignity as to supply
                    the want of a surname in legal proceedings; and as the omission of a name of
                    dignity may be pleaded in abatement of a writ, so it may also be where a peer
                    who has more than one name of dignity is not named by the most noble. No
                    temporal dignity of any foreign nation can give a man a higher title here than
                    that of esquire.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dignity,</hi> in the human character, the opposite of
                    meanness.</p>
                <p>Man is endowed with a sense of the worth and excellence of his nature. He deems
                    it more perfect than that of the other beings around him; and he perceives that
                    the perfection of his nature consists in virtue, particularly in virtue of the
                    highest rank. To express that sense, the term <hi rend="italic">dignity</hi> is
                    appropriated. Further, to behave with dignity, and to refrain from all mean
                    actions, is felt to be not only a virtue, but a duty: it is a duty which every
                    man owes to himself. By acting in this manner, he attracts love and esteem; by
                    acting meanly, or below himself, he is discommended and contemned.</p>
                <p>This sense of the dignity of human nature reaches even our pleasures and
                    amusements. If they enlarge the mind by raising grand or elevated emotions, or
                    if they humanize the mind by exercising our sympathy, they are approved as
                    suited to the dignity of our nature; but if they contract the mind by fixing it
                    on trivial objects, they are contemned as not suited to the dignity of our
                    nature. Hence in general every occupation, whether of use or amusement, that
                    corresponds to the dignity of man, is termed manly; and every occupation below
                    his nature is termed childish or puerile.</p>
                <p>To those who make a study of human nature, there is a point which has always
                    appeared intricate. How comes it that generosity and courage are more esteemed,
                    and bestow more dignity, than good nature or even justice, though the latter
                    contribute more than the former to private as well as to public happiness? This
                    question, bluntly proposed, might puzzle even a philosopher; but, by means of
                    the foregoing observations, it will be easily solved. Human virtues, like other
                    objects, obtain a rank in our estimation, not from their utility, which is a
                    subject of reflection, but from the direct impression which they make on us.
                    Justice and good nature are a sort of negative virtues, which scarcely make any
                    impression except when they are transgressed. Courage and generosity, on the
                    contrary, producing elevated emotions, enliven the great sense of a man’s
                    dignity, both in himself and in others; and for this reason courage and
                    generosity are in higher esteem than the other virtues mentioned; we describe
                    them as grand and elevated, as of greater dignity, and more praiseworthy.</p>
                <p>This leads us to examine more directly emotions and passions with respect to the
                    present subject; and it will not be difficult to form a scale of them, beginning
                    with the meanest, and ascending gradually to those of the highest rank and
                    dignity. Pleasure felt as at the organ of sense, in other words, corporeal
                    pleasure, is perceived to be low, and when indulged to excess, is perceived also
                    to be mean; for which reason, persons of any delicacy dissemble the pleasure
                    they take in eating and drinking. The pleasures of the eye and ear having no
                    organic feeling, and being free from any sense of meanness, are indulged without
                    any shame; and they even rise to a certain degree of dignity when their objects
                    are grand or elevated. The case is the same with the sympathetic passions; a
                    virtuous person behaving with fortitude and dignity under cruel misfortunes
                    makes a capital figure, and the sympathizing spectator feels in himself the same
                    dignity. Sympathetic distress, at the same time, is never mean; on the contrary,
                    it is agreeable to the nature of a social being, and excites general
                    approbation. The rank which love possesses in the scale depends in a great
                    measure on its objects. It possesses a low place when founded on external
                    properties merely, and is mean when bestowed on a person of inferior rank,
                    without any extraordinary qualification; but when founded on the more elevated
                    internal properties, it assumes a considerable degree of dignity. The case is
                    the same with friendship. When gratitude is warm it animates the mind; but it
                    scarcely rises to dignity. Joy bestows dignity when it proceeds from an elevated
                    cause.</p>
                <p>If we can depend upon induction, dignity is not a property of any disagreeable
                    passion; one is slight, another severe; one depresses the mind, another animates
                    it. But there is no elevation, far less dignity, in any of them. Revenge, in
                    particular, though it inflames and swells the mind, is not accompanied with
                    dignity, not even with elevation. It is not however felt as mean or grovelling,
                    unless when it takes indirect or cowardly measures for gratification. Shame and
                    remorse, though they sink the spirits, are not mean. Pride, a disagreeable
                    passion, bestows no dignity in the eye of a spectator; but vanity always appears
                    mean, and extremely so where founded, as commonly happens, on trivial
                    qualifications.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193323512" xml:id="kp-eb0708-3512-0029"/>
                <p>The pleasures of the understanding possess a high rank ʹ in point of dignity. Of
                    this every one must be sensible, when he considers the important truths which
                    have been laid open by science; such as general theorems, and the laws which
                    govern the material and moral worlds. The pleasures of the understanding are
                    suited to man as a rational and contemplative being, and they tend not a little
                    to ennoble his nature; even to the Deity he stretches his contemplations, which,
                    in the discovery of infinite power, wisdom, and benevolence, afford delight of
                    the most exalted kind. Hence it appears that the fine arts, studied as a
                    rational pursuit, afford entertainment of great dignity, superior far to what
                    they afford as a subject of taste merely. But contemplation, however in itself
                    valuable, is chiefly respected as subservient to action; for man is intended to
                    be more an active than a contemplative being. He accordingly shows more dignity
                    in action than in contemplation. Generosity, magnanimity, heroism, raise his
                    character to the highest pitch; these best express the dignity of his nature,
                    and advance him nearer to divinity than any other of his attributes.</p>
                <p>Having endeavoured to assign the true cause of dignity and meanness, by unfolding
                    the principle on which they are founded, we proceed to explain the final cause
                    of the dignity or meanness bestowed upon the several particulars above
                    mentioned, beginning with corporeal pleasures. These, as far as useful, are,
                    like justice, fenced with sufficient sanctions to prevent their being neglected.
                    Hunger and thirst are painful sensations; and we are incited to animal love by a
                    vigorous propensity. Were corporeal pleasures over and above dignified with a
                    place in a high class, they would infallibly overturn the balance of the mind,
                    by outweighing the social affections. This is a satisfactory final cause for
                    refusing to these pleasures any degree of dignity; and the final cause is not
                    less evident of their meanness when they are indulged to excess. The more
                    refined pleasures of external sense, conveyed by the eye and the ear from
                    natural objects and from the fine arts, deserve a high place in our esteem,
                    because of their singular and extensive utility. In some cases they rise to a
                    considerable dignity; and the very lowest pleasures of the kind are never
                    esteemed mean nor grovelling. The pleasure arising from wit, humour, ridicule,
                    or from what is simply ludicrous, is useful, by relaxing the mind after the
                    fatigue of more manly occupations; but the mind, when it surrenders itself to
                    pleasure of that kind, loses its vigour, and sinks gradually into sloth. The
                    place which this pleasure occupies in point of dignity is adjusted to these
                    views. To make it useful as a relaxation, it is not branded with meanness; to
                    prevent its usurpation, it is removed from that place but a single degree. No
                    man values himself for that pleasure even during gratification; and if it have
                    engrossed more of his time than is requisite for relaxation, he looks back on
                    the circumstance with some degree of shame.</p>
                <p>In point of dignity, the social emotions rise above the selfish, and much above
                    those of the eye and ear. Man is by his nature a social being; and to qualify
                    him for society, it is wisely contrived that he should value himself more on
                    being social than selfish. The excellency of man is chiefly discernible in the
                    great improvements he is susceptible of in society. These, by perseverance, may
                    be carried on progressively, beyond any assignable limits; and even abstracting
                    from revelation, there is a very great probability that the progress begun here
                    will be completed in some future state. Now, as all valuable improvements
                    proceed from the exercise of our rational faculties, the Author of our nature,
                    in order to excite us to a due use of these faculties, has assigned a high rank
                    to the pleasures of the understanding. Their utility, with respect to this life
                    as well as a future one, entitles them to that rank.</p>
                <p>But as action is the aim of all our improvements, virtuous actions justly possess
                    the highest of all ranks. These, we find, are by nature distributed into
                    different classes, and the first place in point of dignity is assigned to
                    actions which appear not the first in point of use. Generosity, for example, in
                    the sense of mankind, is more respected than justice, though the latter is
                    undoubtedly more essential to society; and magnanimity, heroism, and undaunted
                    courage, rise still higher in our esteem, for the reason which has been already
                    explained.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
