<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0708-6957-0294-04" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">DWARF</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 8, page 294</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1750261">Inch</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:899973">Dwarfs</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:883881">Crofts</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1069177">Polishes</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942628">Gifts</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m147">Dwarfs</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4804xp4n">Polishes</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nx59">Gifts</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193326957" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">DWARF</label>, in general, an appellation given to things
                    greatly inferior in size to that which is usual in their several kinds. Thus
                    there are dwarfs of the human species, dwarf dogs, dwarf trees, and the
                    like.</p><p>The Romans were passionately fond of dwarfs, whom they called <hi rend="italic">nani</hi> or <hi rend="italic">nance,</hi> insomuch that they often used
                    artificial methods to prevent the growth of boys designed for dwarfs, by
                    inclosing them in boxes, or by the use of tight bandages. Augustus’s niece,
                    Julia, was extremely fond of a dwarf called Sonopas, who was only two feet and a
                    handbreadth in height. We have many other accounts of human dwarfs, but most of
                    them deformed in some way or other, besides the smallness of their size. Many
                    relations concerning dwarfs we must necessarily look upon as not less fabulous
                    than those concerning giants. The following history, however, which there is
                    reason to regard as authentic, is too remarkable not to be acceptable to the
                    generality of our readers.</p><p>Jeffery Hudson, the famous English dwarf, was born at Oakham, in Rutlandshire, in
                    1619; and about the age of seven or eight, being then but eighteen inches high,
                    he was retained in the service of the Duke of Buckingham, who resided at
                    Burleigh-on-the-Hill. Soon after the marriage of Charles 1. the king and queen
                    being entertained at Burleigh, little Jeffery was served up at table in a cold
                    pie, and presented by the duchess to the queen, who kept him as her dwarf. From
                    seven years of age till thirty he never grew taller; but after thirty he shot up
                    to three feet nine inches, and there remained fixed. Jeffery became a
                    considerable part of the entertainment of the court. Sir William Davenant wrote
                    a poem called <hi rend="italic">Jeffreidos,</hi> on a battle between him and a
                    turkey-cock; and in 1638 was published a very small book, called the <hi rend="italic">New Years Gift,</hi> presented at court by the Lady Parvula to the
                    Lord Minimus, commonly called <hi rend="italic">Little Jeffery,</hi> her
                    majesty’s servant, written by Microphilus, with a little print of Jeffery
                    prefixed. Before this period Jeffery was employed on a negotiation of great
                    importance; he was sent to France to fetch a midwife for the queen; and on his
                    return with this gentlewoman and her majesty’s dancing-master, and many rich
                    presents to the queen from her mother Mary de’Medicis, he was taken by the
                    Dunkirkers. Jeffery, being thus made of consequence, began to think himself
                    really an important personage. He had borne with little temper the teasing of
                    the courtiers and domestics, and had many squabbles with the king’s gigantic
                    porter. At last, being provoked by Mr Crofts, a young gentleman of family, a
                    challenge ensued; and Mr Crofts coming to the rendezvous armed only with a
                    squirt, the little creature was so enraged that a real duel ensued; and the
                    appointment being on horseback with pistols, to put them more on a level,
                    Jeffery, with the first fire, shot his antagonist dead. This happened in France,
                    whither he had attended his mistress in the troubles. He was again taken
                    prisoner by a Turkish rover, and sold into Barbary. But he probably did not
                    remain long in slavery; for at the beginning of the civil war he was made a
                    captain in the royal army, and in 1644 attended the queen to France, where he
                    remained till the Restoration. At last, upon suspicion of his being concerned in
                    the Popish plot, he was seized in 1682, and confined in the Gatehouse,
                    Westminster, where he ended his life, in the sixty-third year of his age. This
                    little hero cuts a considerable figure in Sir Walter Scott’s novel of <hi rend="italic">Peveril of the Peak.</hi></p><p>In the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Royal Academy of Sciences,</hi> a
                    relation is given by the Count de Tressau, of a dwarf called <hi rend="italic">Hebe,</hi> kept by Stanislaus, king of Poland, and who died in 1764, at the age
                    of twenty-three, when he measured only thirty-two inches. At the time of his
                    birth he measured only between eight and nine inches. Diminutive as were his
                    dimensions, his reasoning faculties were not less scanty, appearing indeed not
                    to have been superior to those of a well-taught pointer. But that the size and
                    strength of the intellectual powers are not affected by the d’minutiveness or
                    tenuity of the corporeal organs, is evident from a still more striking instance
                    of littleness, given us by the same nobleman, in the person of M. Borulawski, a
                    Polish gentleman, whom he saw at Luneville, and who at the age of twenty-two
                    measured only twenty-eight inches. This miniature of a man, considering him only
                    with reference to his bodily dimensions, appeared a giant with regard to his
                    mental powers and attainments. He is described by the count as possessing all
                    the graces of wit, united with a sound judgment and an excellent memory; so that
                    we may with justice say of Μ. Borulawski, in the words of Seneca, and nearly in
                    the order in which he has used them, <hi rend="italic">posse</hi><hi rend="italic">ingenium fortissimum ac beatissimum sub quolibet corpusculo
                    latere.</hi></p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193326970" xml:id="kp-eb0708-6970-0295"/></div></body></text></TEI>