<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-7266-0728-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KINGHORN (7th edition, volume 12, page 728)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sf3s">Charters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100369">Rooms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852538">Charters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827285">Baptists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852215">Chapels</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192947266?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KINGHORN</label>, a small burgh in Fife, which joins with
                    Kirkcaldy, Dysart, and Burntisland in sending a member to parliament. For its
                    constituency, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirkcaldy.</hi> It has charters from King
                    Alexander III. dated 26th June 1284; from King David II. dated 2d July 1364;
                    from King James V. dated 30th August 1541; and from King James VI. dated 12th
                    December 1611. By these charters its privileges as a burgh, and its right to the
                    harbours of Pettycur and Kinghorn, with its lake, lands, and mills, are
                    confirmed. The revenue of these amounted in 1832 to L.670. They were then valued
                    at L.13,114, and the debts upon them amounted to L.5836. 2s. 5d. The various
                    projects for improving the harbours are mentioned in the article <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Forth,</hi> and a negotiation is at present (1836) going on for
                    their execution, by a joint-stock company. The extent of the lake of Kinghorn is
                    about twenty imperial acres, and the length of the stream flowing from it to the
                    sea is nearly 1000 yards. The« height of the mill-sluice upon it above the level
                    of the high-water mark is about 178 feet ten inches. Six mills were, within the
                    last thirty years, driven by the waters flowing from it, and there might have
                    been a seventh. There are at present upon it a meal and barley mill, and three
                    flax spinning-mills, turning, with the aid of powerful steam-engines and their
                    water-wheels, 3660 spindles. The other waterfalls are at present unemployed.
                    Flax spinning is the principal trade of the town. The shipping trade, besides
                    that of the ferry, is of little importance, consisting only of one large brig
                    and two coasting vessels. The government of the town is vested in a provost, two
                    bailies, a treasurer, thirteen councillors, and five police commissioners,
                    chosen by the inhabitants, under the act 5 and 6 William IV. cap. 63. It has
                    also five incorporated trades. The principal buildings are the townhouse,
                    erected on the site of an old Saxon building called St Leonard’s Chapel, and the
                    schools. Both buildings are from plans by Mr Hamilton of Edinburgh. The prison,
                    with its airing ground, annexed to the town-house, is, with the exception of the
                    jails at Kirkcaldy and Cupar, the best in the county. The schools belong to the
                    burgh, but were erected by private subscription; and the gardens were
                    gratuitously laid out chiefly by the working classes. The principal teacher is
                    chosen by the burgage and landward heritors; the burgage heritors pay half of
                    his salary, <pb break="no" facs="nls:192947279?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0712-7279-0729"/> •and the landward heritors the other half. There
                    is an infant school-room, a geological museum and library-room, and a drawing
                    school-room, within the buildings. Upwards of an acre of ground is laid out with
                    shrubbery, and the borders of the walks contain a selection of plants, arranged
                    with tallies bearing their names, and classes, and orders; a portion of the
                    ground forms a bowling-green, and another contains the usual erections for
                    gymnastic exercises. Besides the parish church, there is in the burgh an
                    Associate Secession meeting-house and a Baptist chapel, both of which are well
                    attended. This little town, from its ample revenue and increasing trade and
                    population, bids fair soon to become one of the most prosperous in the county.
                    Much has been done within the last ten years in opening up streetsand removing
                    ancient deformities; .and the operations at present in progress, under the
                    police commissioners, to carry water in pipes through all the streets, and to
                    light them with gas, will add further to the comfort of its inhabitants.
                    Population in 1831, 2579.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Kinghorn</hi><hi rend="italic">Ferry</hi> (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Forth).</hi> This has been a public ferry from the earliest
                    period of Scottish history. By an act of parliament passed in 1474, the freight
                    for the portage of man and horse at Kinghorn was to be six pennies Scotch, and
                    for the man separately two pennies Scotch. In 1551, parliament raised the
                    freight for the portage of the man and horse to twelve pennies Scotch, and for
                    the man separately to six pennies Scotch; and also provided that the ferrymen
                    were never to charge more, under pain of death, and confiscation of all their
                    goods. On the 20th of May 1800, the ferrymen were allowed by the justices at
                    their quarter-sessions to charge passengers, of freight ninepence sterling for
                    the best seats in their boats, and sixpence for the seats before the mast. At
                    present (1836) the freights of passengers are as high as two shillings sterling
                    for the best and eighteenpence for the inferior sittings on board the steamers
                    navigating these ferries.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
