<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-7162-0720-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KINCARDINESHIRE, or the Mearns (7th edition, volume 12,
                    page 720)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07518">Face</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q80j">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919522">Face</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1043442">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192947162?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KINCARDINESHIRE, or the <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Mearns</hi></label>, a county in Scotland, situated between 56. 43. and 57. 5.
                    north latitude, and between 1. 47. and 2. 30. west longitude from Greenw ich. It
                    is bounded on the east by the German Ocean; on the north by Aberdeenshire, from
                    which it is divided along the greater part of the boundary by the river Dee; and
                    on the west and south by Forfarshire, from which it is divided by the river
                    North Esk. The boundary along the shore of the German Ocean extends to
                    thirty-two miles, being the greatest length of the county; and the greatest
                    breadth from east to wmst is twenty-four miles; the superficial contents being
                    360 square miles, or about 243,444 English acres.</p>
                <p>The cultivated parts of the county form three principal divisions; the Howe of
                    the Mearns, the Coast-side, and Dee-side. The Howe of the Mearns, a continuation
                    of the great valley of Strathmore, is divided from the Dee-side district by the
                    Grampian Mountains, which stretch, from west to east, through the whole breadth
                    of the county, gradually declining in elevation, until they disappear in the
                    level ground near the sea, between Stonehaven and Aberdeen. The greater part of
                    this district is in a state of high cultivation, and the face of the country is
                    diversified and ornamented by thriving plantations. The ground in many places is
                    composed of a bright-red clay, which gives the surface, when newly ploughed, a
                    very peculiar appearance. The great road from Perth to Aberdeen through
                    Strathmore traverses this district. The Coast-side district, from the river
                    North Esk to Stonehaven, contains, with some intermixture of inferior ground,
                    the most productive land in the county. The road from Montrose to Aberdeen runs
                    through this division. Notwithstanding the vicinity of the ocean, some thriving
                    plantations are to he seen; and, almost close to the shore, there are trees of
                    considerable magnitude, especially at Brotherton, where a finely-terraced old
                    garden,"although within reach of the sea spray, is remarked as being one of the
                    best and most productive in this part of the country. From Bervie to Stonehaven,
                    a distance of ten miles, the shore is high and bold, presenting to the ocean,
                    along the whole line, a perpendicular face of rock, from 100 to 250 feet in
                    height. The most conspicuous of this range of rocks is Fowlsheugh, well known as
                    the rendezvous, during summer, of innumerable flocks of sea-fowl of various
                    kinds. In the face of the rock are various caverns, and natural arches and
                    galleries, of great extent and magnificence. From Stonehaven northw ard to the
                    river Dee the shore is also bold and rocky; but the face of the country is
                    generally of a very inferior character to that of the same district south of
                    Stonehaven, just described. The appearance of a great part of this tract is as
                    uninviting as can well be imagined. In the neighbourhood of Stonehaven, however,
                    and in some other places, part of the ground is in a state of high
                    productiveness; and, even in the most barren and forbidding parts, great
                    improvements have recently been made, and the progress of cultivation is such as
                    to promise at no distant period a total change on the face of this part of the
                    country. The Dec-side district, forming the third division of the cultivated
                    part of the county, is situated on both sides of the Dee, and extends along the
                    south bank of that river, from the sea westward, for about thirteen miles, and
                    afterwards along both banks for nine or ten miles further, embracing also the
                    valley of the Feugh. Some of the land in this district is fertile, and produces
                    good crops; but a great part of the ground is still in little better than a
                    state of nature, although to a considerable extent capable of, and in many
                    places in progress towards, cultivation. In this district, trees have been
                    planted to a greater extent than in any other part of the county, and the
                    climate is peculiarly favourable to the growth of timber. The plantations
                    greatly embellish the face of the country; and at many points, especially in the
                    neighbourhood of the rising valley of Banchory, the prospect along the Dee is
                    rich and beautiful. Plantations of firs extend in some places to the summits of
                    the adjoining hills.</p>
                <p>These three divisions, comprehending the more level and cultivated parts of the
                    county, extend to about two thirds of the whole surface. The other third
                    consists of the eastern range of the Grampian Mountains, by which the Dee-side
                    district is divided from the Howe of the Mearns. This elevated region is
                    exceedingly sterile and rugged; but in some of the glens through which the
                    mountain-streams flow, there are spots of great natural beauty. On one of these
                    spots, in a romantic situation, stands the shooting lodge of Glendye. The most
                    prominent of the Grampian Mountains in this county are, Mount-Battock, which
                    rises to nearly 3500 feet above t <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:192947175?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0712-7175-0721"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
