<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-2079-0329-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">INTERMENT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 12, page 329</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="20" ref="fasttopic:888385">Dead</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1141359">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192942079" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">INTERMENT</label>, the act of interring, that is, burying or
                    laying a deceased person in the ground.</p>
                <p>Aristotle asserted that it was more just to assist the dead than the living.
                    Plato, in his Republic, does not forget, amongst other acts of justice, that
                    which concerns the dead. Cicero establishes three kinds of justice; the first
                    respects the gods, the second the manes or dead, and the third men. These
                    principles seem to be derived from nature; and they appear at least to be
                    necessary for the support of society, since civilized nations have at all times
                    taken care to bury their dead, and to pay the last respects to their
                    remains.</p>
                <p>We find in history several traces of the respect which the Indians, the
                    Egyptians, and the Syrians entertained for the dead. The Syrians embalmed their
                    bodies with myrrh, aloes, honey, salt, wax, bitumen, and resinous gums; and they
                    also dried them with the smoke of the fir and of the pine tree. The Egyptians
                    preserved theirs with the resin of the cedar, with aromatic spices, and with
                    asphaltum. These people often kept such mummies, or at least their effigies, in
                    their houses; and at grand entertainments they were introduced, that by reciting
                    the great actions of their ancestors they might be the more excited to
                    virtue.</p>
                <p>The Greeks, at first, had probably not the same veneration for the dead as the
                    Egyptians. Empedocles, therefore, in the eighty-fourth Olympiad, restored to
                    life Pontifia, a woman of Agrigentum, who was about to be interred. But this
                    people, in proportion as they became more enlightened, perceived the necessity
                    of establishing laws for the protection of the dead. «</p>
                <p>At Athens the law required that no person should be interred before the third
                    day; and in the greater part of the cities of Greece a funeral did not take
                    place till the sixth or even the seventh day. When a man appeared to have
                    breathed his last, his body was generally washed by ms nearest relations, with
                    warm water mixed with wine. They afterwards anointed it with oil; and covered it
                    with a dress commonly made of fine linen, according to the custom of the
                    Egyptians. This dress was white at Messina, Athens, and in the greater part of
                    the cities of Greece, where the dead body was crowned with flowers. At Sparta it
                    was of a purple colour, and the body was surrounded with olive leaves. The
                    corpse was afterwards laid upon a couch in the entry of the house, where it
                    remained till the time of the funeral. At the magnificent obsequies with which
                    Alexander honoured Hephaestion, the body was not burned until the tenth day.</p>
                <p>The Romans, in the infancy of their empire, paid as little attention to their
                    dead as the Greeks had done. Acilius Aviola having fallen into a lethargic fit,
                    was supposed to be dead; he was therefore carried to the funeral pile; the fire
                    was lighted up; and though he cried out he was still alive, he perished for want
                    of speedy assistance. The praetor Lamia met with the same fate. Tubero, who had
                    been praetor, was saved from the funeral pile. Asclepiades, a physician, who
                    lived in the time of Pompey the Great, about one hundred and twenty years before
                    the Christian era, returning from his country-house, observed near the walls of
                    Rome a grand convoy and a crowd of people, who were in mourning, assisting at a
                    funeral, and showing every exterior sign of the deepest grief. Having asked what
                    was the occasion of this concourse, no one made any reply. He therefore
                    approached the pretended dead body; and imagining that he perceived signs of
                    life in it, he ordered the bystanders to take away the flambeaux, to extinguish
                    the fire, and to pull down the funeral pile. On this a kind of murmur arose
                    throughout the whole company. Some said that they ought to believe the
                    physician, whilst others turned both him and his profession into ridicule. The
                    relations, however, yielded at length to the remonstrances of Asclepiades; they
                    consented to defer the obsequies for a little; and the consequence was that the
                    pretended dead person was restored to life. It appears that these examples, and
                    several others of a similar kind, Induced the Romans to delay funerals longer,
                    and to enact laws to prevent precipitate nterments.</p>
                <p>At Rome, after allowing a sufficient time for mourning, the nearest relation
                    generally closed the eyes of the deceased; and the body was bathed with warm
                    water, either to render it fitter for being anointed with oil, or to re-animate
                    the principle of life, which might remain suspended without*manifesting itself.
                    Proofs were afterwards made to discover whether the person was really dead, and
                    these were often repeated during the time that the body remained exposed; for
                    there were persons appointed to visit the dead, and to prove their situation. On
                    the second day, after the body had been washed a second time, it was anointed
                    with oil and balm. Luxury increased to such a pitch in the choice of foreign
                    perfumes for this purpose, that under the consulship of Licinius Crassus and
                    Julius Caesar, the senate forbade any perfumes to be used except such as were
                    the production of Italy. On the third day the body was clothed according to its
                    dignity and condition. The robe called the <hi rend="italic">praetexta</hi> was
                    put upon magistrates, and a purple robe upon consuls. For conquerors who had
                    merited triumphal honours, this robe was of gold tissue; for other Romans it was
                    white, and for the lower classes of the people black. These dresses were often
                    prepared at a distance, by the mothers and wives of persons still in life. On
                    the fourth day the body was placed on a couch, and exposed in the vestibule of
                    the house, with the visage turned towards the entrance, and the feet near the
                    door; and in this situation it remained till the end of the week. Near the couch
                    were lighted wax-tapers, a small box in which perfumes were burned, and a vessel
                    full of water for purification, with which those who approached the body
                    besprinkled <pb break="no" facs="nls:192942092" xml:id="kp-eb0712-2092-0330"
                    />themselves. An old man belonging to those who furnished every thing necessary
                    for funerals sat near the deceased, with some domestics clothed in black. On the
                    eighth day the funeral rites were performed; but, to prevent the body from
                    corrupting before that time, salt, wax, the resinous gum of the cedar, myrrh,
                    honey, balm, gypsum, lime, asphaltum or bitumen of Judaea, and several other
                    substances, were employed. The body was carried to the pile with the face
                    uncovered, unless wounds, or the nature of the disease, had rendered it
                    loathsome and disgusting. In such a case a mask was used, made of a kind of
                    plaster, which has given rise to the expression of <hi rend="italic">funera
                    larvata,</hi> used in some of the ancient authors. This was the last method of
                    concealment which Nero made use of, after having caused Germanicus to be
                    poisoned; for the effect of the poison had become very sensible, by livid spots,
                    and the blackness of the body; but a shower of rain happening to fall, it washed
                    the plaster entirely away, and thus the horrid crime of fratricide was
                    discovered.</p>
                <p>In the primitive church the dead were washed and then anointed; the body was
                    wrapped up in linen, or clothed in a dress of more or less value according to
                    circumstances, and it was not interred until after being exposed and kept some
                    days in the house. The custom of clothing the dead is in France observed only in
                    the case of princes and ecclesiastics.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the customs above recited, still, in many places, and on numerous
                    occasions in all places, too much precipitation attends this last office; or, if
                    not precipitation, a neglect of due precautions in regard to the body.</p>
                <p>A man may fall into a syncope, and remain in that condition for a very
                    considerable period of time. People in this situation have been known to come to
                    life when deposited amongst the dead. A boy belonging to the hospital at Cassel
                    appeared to have breathed his last; he was carried into the hall where the dead
                    were exposed, and was wrapped up in a piece of canvass. Some time afterwards,
                    recovering from his lethargy, he recollected the place in which he had been
                    deposited, and crawling towards the door, knocked against it with his foot. This
                    noise was luckily heard by the sentinel, who soon perceiving the motion of the
                    canvass, called for assistance. The youth was immediately conveyed to a warm
                    bed, and soon perfectly recovered. Had his body been confined by close bandages
                    or ligatures, he would not have been able, in all probability, to make himself
                    be heard; Kis unavailing efforts would have made him again fall into a syncope,
                    and he would have thus been buried alive.</p>
                <p>We must not be astonished that the servants of an hospital should take a syncope
                    for a real death, since even the most enlightened persons have sometimes fallen
                    into errors of the same kind. Dr John Schmid relates, that a young girl, seven
                    years of age, after being afflicted for some weeks with a violent cough, was all
                    of a sudden freed from this troublesome malady, and appeared to be in perfect
                    health. But some days afterwards, whilst playing with her companions, the child
                    fell down in an instant, as if struck by lightning. A death-like paleness was
                    diffused over her face and arms; she had no apparent pulse, her temples were
                    sunk, and she showed no signs of sensation when shaken or pinched. A physician,
                    who was called, and who believed her to be dead, in compliance with the repeated
                    and pressing request of her parents, attempted, though without any hopes, to
                    recall her to life; and at length, after several vain efforts, he made the soles
                    of her feet be smartly rubbed with a brush dipped in very strong pickle. At the
                    end of three quarters of an hour she was observed to sigh; she was then made to
                    swallow some spirituous liquor; and she was soon afterwards restored to life,
                    much to the joy of her disconsolate parents. A certain man having undertaken a
                    journey in order to see his brother, on his arrival at his house found him dead.
                    This news affected him so much that it brought on syncope, and he himself was
                    supposed to be in the like situation. After the usual means had been employed to
                    recall him to life, it was agreed that his body should be dissected, to discover
                    the cause of so sudden a death; but the supposed dead person overhearing this
                    proposal, opened his eyes, started up, and immediately betook himself to his
                    heels. Cardinal Espinola, prime minister to Philip II. was not so fortunate;
                    for, in the memoirs of Amelot de la Houssai, we are informed that he put bis
                    hand to the knife with which he was opened in order to be embalmed. In short,
                    almost every one knows that Vesalius, the father of anatomy, having been sent
                    for to open the body of a woman subject to hysterics, who was supposed to be
                    dead, he perceived, on making the first incision, that she was still alive; that
                    this circumstance rendered him so odious, that he was obliged to fly; and that
                    he was so much affected by it, that he died soon afterwards. On this occasion we
                    cannot forbear adding an event more recent, but not less melancholy. The Abbé
                    Prevost, so well known by his writings and the singularities of his life, was
                    seized with a fit of apoplexy, in the forest of Chantilly, on the 23d of October
                    1763. His body was carried to the nearest village, and the officers of justice
                    were proceeding to open it, when a "cry which he sent forth terrified all the
                    assistants, and convinced the surgeon that the abbé was not dead; but it was too
                    late to save him, as he had already received a mortal wound.</p>
                <p>We shall conclude this article by subjoining, from Br Hawes’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Address to the Public,</hi> a few of the cases in which this fallacious
                    appearance of death is most likely to happen, together with the respective modes
                    of treatment which he recommends.</p>
                <p>In apoplectic and fainting fits, and in those arising from any violent agitation
                    of mind, and also when opium or spirituous liquors have been taken in too great
                    quantity, there is reason to believe that the appearance of death has been
                    frequently mistaken for the reality. In these cases, the means recommended by
                    the <hi rend="italic">Humane Society for the Recovery of Drowned Persons</hi>
                    should be persevered in for several hours; and bleeding, which in similar
                    circumstances has sometimes proved pernicious, should be used with great
                    caution. In the two latter instances it will be highly expedient, with the view
                    of counteracting the soporific effects of opium and spirits, to convey into the
                    stomach, by a proper tube, a solution of tartar emetic, and by various other
                    means to excite vomiting.</p>
                <p>From the number of children carried off by convulsions, and the certainty arising
                    from undoubted facts that some who have in appearance died from that cause have
                    been recovered, there is the greatest reason for concluding, that many, in
                    consequence of this disease, have been prematurely numbered amongst the dead;
                    and that the fond parent, by neglecting the means of recalling life, has often
                    been the guiltless executioner of her own offspring. To prevent the commission
                    of such dreadful mistakes, no child whose life has been apparently extinguished
                    by convulsions should be consigned to the grave till the means of recovery above
                    recommended have been tried, and, if possible, under the direction of some
                    skilful practitioner of medicine, who may vary them as circumstances seem to
                    require.</p>
                <p>When fevers arise in weak habits, or when the cure of these has been principally
                    attempted by means of depletion, the consequent debility is often very great,
                    and the patient sometimes sinks into a state which bears so close an affinity to
                    that of death, that there is reason to suspect it has too often deceived the
                    bystanders, and induced them to send for the undertaker when they should have
                    had recourse to the succours of medicine. In such cases, volatiles, <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:192942105" xml:id="kp-eb0712-2105-0331"/><hi rend="italic"
                    >eau de</hi><hi rend="italic">^</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> uce</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∙&gt;</hi> f° <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> example, should be
                    applied to the nose, rubbed on the temples, and sprinkled about the bed; hot
                    flannels, moistened with a strong solution of camphorated spirit, may likewise
                    be applied over the breast, and renewed every quarter of an hour; and, as soon
                    as the patient is able to swallow, a teaspoonful of the strongest cordial should
                    be given every five minutes.</p>
                <p>The same methods may also be used with propriety in the small-pox, when the
                    pustules sink, and death apparently ensues; and likewise in any other acute
                    diseases, when the vital functions are suspended from a similar case.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
