<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-0974-0244-10" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">IGNATIUS Loyola</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 12, page 244</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vd72">Scythians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80t3c">Lays</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1163204">Ushers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1109953">Scythians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192940974" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">IGNATIUS <hi rend="smallcaps">Loyola</hi></label>, the
                    founder of the order of Jesuits, was born atthe castle of Loyola, in Biscay, in
                    the year 1491. He became, first, page to Ferdinand V. king of Spain, and then an
                    officer in the army. In the latter capacity he signalized himself by his valour,
                    and was wounded in both legs at the siege of Pampeluna in 1521. To this
                    circumstance the Jesuits owe their origin; for whilst he was under cure of his
                    wound, a <hi rend="italic">Life of the Saints,</hi> which was put into his
                    hands, determined him to exchange the military for the ecclesiastical
                    profession. His first devout exercise was to dedicate himself to the blessed
                    virgin as her knight. He then went on a pilgrimage to the Holy Land; and upon
                    his return to Europe he continued his theological studies in the universities of
                    Spain, though he was then thirty-three years of age. After this he went to
                    Paris, and in France laid the foundation of that new order, the institutes of
                    which he presented to Pope Pau] III. who made many objections to them, but at
                    last, in 1540, confirmed the institution. The founder died in 1555, and left his
                    disciples two famous books; first, Spiritual Exercises; second, Constitutions or
                    Rules of the Order. But it must be remembered, that though these avowed
                    institutes contain many privileges obnoxious to the welfare of society, the most
                    objectionable are contained in the private rules, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Monita Secreta,</hi> which were not discovered till long afterwards; but most
                    writers attribute these, and even the Constitutions, to Lay-nez, the second
                    general of the order.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ignatius,</hi><hi rend="italic">St,</hi> surnamed <hi
                    rend="italic">Theophrastus,</hi> one of the apostolical fathers of the church,
                    was born in Syria, educated under the apostle and evangelist St John, and
                    intimately acquainted with some other of the apostles, especially St Peter and
                    St Paul. Being fully instructed in the doctrines of Christianity, he was
                    ordained by St John, and confirmed, about the year 67, bishop of Antioch, by
                    these two apostles, who first planted Christianity in that city, where the
                    disciples also were first called <hi rend="italic">Christians.</hi> Antioch was
                    then not only the metropolis of Syria, but a city the most renowned of any in
                    the East, and the ancient seat of the Roman emperors, as well as that of the
                    viceroys and governors. In this important see he continued somewhat above forty
                    years, and was both an honour and safeguard to the Christian religion, till the
                    year 107, when Trajan the emperor, flushed with a victory which he had lately
                    obtained over the Scythians and Dacians, about the ninth year of his reign, came
                    to Antioch to make preparations for a war against the Parthians and Armenians.
                    He entered the city with the pomp of a triumph; and as his first care usually
                    was about the affairs of religion, he began presently to inquire into the state
                    of the new faith Christianity had by this time made such progress, that the
                    Romans became jealous and uneasy on account of its advancement. This prince,
                    therefore, had already, in other parts of the empire, commenced a persecution
                    against the Christians, which he now resolved to carry on here. However, as he
                    was naturally of a mild disposition, though he ordered the laws to be put in
                    force against them if convicted, yet he forbade them to be sought after.</p>
                <p>In this state of affairs, Ignatius, thinking it more prudent to go himself than
                    wait to be sent for, presented himself to the emperor; and it is said that there
                    passed a long and particular discourse between them, in the course of which the
                    emperor having expressed surprise how he dared to transgress the laws, the
                    bishop took the opportunity to assert his own innocence, and to explain and
                    vindicate his faith and freedom. The issue was, that he was imprisoned, and
                    sentenced to be carried bound by soldiers to Rome, and there thrown as a prey to
                    the wild beasts of the amphitheatre.</p>
                <p>He was first conducted to Seleucia, a port of Syria, about sixteen miles distant,
                    where Paul and Barnabas set sail for Cyprus. Having arrived at Smyrna, he paid a
                    visit to Polycarp, bishop of that place, and was himself visited by the clergy
                    of the surrounding country. He also wrote letters to several churches, as the
                    Ephesians, Magnesians, Trallians, and even the Romans, for their instruction and
                    establishment in the faith. He then set sail for Troas, a city of Phrygia, not
                    far from the ruins of old Troy, where, upon his arrival, he was much refreshed
                    with the <pb break="no" facs="nls:192940987" xml:id="kp-eb0712-0987-0245"/>news
                    he received of the discontinuance of the persecution in Antioch. From Troas he
                    sailed to Neapolis, a maritime town in Macedonia; thence to Philippi, a Roman
                    colony, where the party were entertained with all imaginable kindness, and
                    conducted forwards on their journey through Macedonia and Epirus, till they came
                    to Epi-damnium, a city of Dalmatia, where, having again taken shipping, they
                    sailed through the Adriatic, arrived at Rhegium, a port-town in Italy, and
                    directed their course thence through the Tyrrhenian Sea to Puteoli, whence
                    Ignatius desired to proceed by land, ambitious to trace the same way by which St
                    Paul had travelled to Rome. But this wish was not complied with; and, after a
                    stay of twenty-four hours, a prosperous wind quickly carried them to the Roman
                    port, the station of the navy, built near Ostia, at the mouth of the Tiber,
                    about sixteen miles from Rome.</p>
                <p>The Christians at Rome, daily expecting his arrival, came out to meet him, and
                    received him with a mixture of joy and sorrow; but when some of them intimated
                    that possibly the populace might be diverted from desiring his death, he
                    expressed a pious indignation, entreating them to cast no obstacles in his way,
                    nor do any thing that might tend to deprive him of that crown of martyrdom to
                    which he ardently aspired. There are many such expressions as this in his
                    epistle to the Romans, yet it does not appear that he rashly sought or provoked
                    danger. Being conducted to Rome, he was presented to the prefect; and the
                    emperor’s letters concerning him were also delivered. The interval before his
                    martyrdom was spent in prayers for the peace and prosperity of the church. That
                    his punishment might be the more public, one of their solemn festivals, the time
                    of the Saturnalia, and that part of it when they celebrated the Sigillaria, was
                    fixed for his execution. Accordingly, on the 20th of December, he was brought
                    out into the amphitheatre, and the lions being let loose, quickly despatched
                    him, leaving nothing but a few of the hardest of his bones. These remains were
                    gathered up by two deacons wlio had been the companions of his journey; and
                    being transported to Antioch, were interred in the cemetery, without the gate
                    which leads to Daphne.</p>
                <p>St Ignatius stands at the head of those Anti-Nicene fathers who occasionally
                    delivered their opinions in defence of the divinity of Christ, whom he calls the
                    <hi rend="italic">Son of God, and his eternal word.</hi> He is also reckoned the
                    great champion of the doctrine <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the episcopal order, as
                    distinct from and superior to that of priest and deacon; and one, the most
                    important, use of his writings respects the authenticity of the Holy Scriptures,
                    which he frequently alludes to in the very same expressions which we find at
                    this day. Archbishop Usher’s edition of his works, printed in 1647. is thought
                    the best; yet there is a more recent edition published at Amsterdam, where,
                    besides the best notes, there arc the dissertations of Usher and Pearson.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">St</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Ignatius’</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">s Bean,</hi> the fruit of a plant. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Ignatia, Botany.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
