<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-4172-0490-09" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">IVORY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 12, page 490</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s70x">Imports</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm4364x">Tusks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07359">Chess</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:848005">Carthaginians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:968197">Imports</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1159722">Tusks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192944172" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">IVORY</label> is the name given to the tusks of the elephant,
                    and of the walrus or sea-horse. Each male elephant arrived at maturity has two
                    tusks. These are extremely diversified in size, which depends principally on the
                    age of the animal; they are hollow at their insertion into the jaw and for a
                    considerable space therefrom, and always taper to an obtuse extremity. The
                    colour externally is yellowish, brownish, and sometimes dark, but internally it
                    is a cream white. The best tusks are large, straight, and light coloured,
                    without flaws; not very hollow in the stump, but, on the contrary, solid and
                    thick. The most esteemed are obtained from Africa, being of a closer texture,
                    and less liable to become yellow, than those imported from the East Indies. The
                    tusks of the sea-horse afford the hardest and whitest of all ivory. They are
                    usually short, and very much curved; the thick end is hollow, as in the tusk of
                    the elephant; a glossy enamel of extreme hardness covers the cortical part; and
                    they vary in weight from three or four pounds to thirty. The horn or tooth of
                    the narwhal, one of the cetaceous tribe, also consists of ivory, which is as
                    hard as that of the elephant, and susceptible of a fine polish. The largest size
                    is ten feet in length, and some inches thick at the lower extremity, forming a
                    slender cone of a twisted or spiral figure. But its texture is in several
                    respects different from that of other ivory; and there is a prejudice against
                    the ordinary use of it amongst those who work in that material.</p>
                <p>From the earliest times, the people of all the Asiatic countries, where the
                    elephant is found, have had the art of taming the animal, and applying it to
                    useful purposes; but no such art has ever been possessed by any African nation.
                    Nor has this apparently been owing to any difference between the Asiatic and
                    African elephant in point of docility; the real cause is probably to be found in
                    the inferior intelligence and sagacity of the African people. Alexander the
                    Great is believed to have been the first European who employed elephants in war.
                    With regard to those made use of by the Carthaginians, it has been supposed,
                    though with little probability, that they were mostly, if not wholly, imported
                    from India, and that they were managed by Indian conductors, some of whom were
                    captured by the Romans in the great victory gained by Metellus over Asdrubal.
                    But, in the first place, the name of Indian, as used by the Romans, was so
                    extremely vague, that no safe conclusion can be drawn from it; nor, even if the
                    conductors were of that people, does it follow that the elephants had been
                    brought from India. And, secondly, it is not reasonable to suppose that an
                    active and enterprising people, like the Carthaginians, would have imported from
                    a distant country, and at an enormous expense, an animal which, they must have
                    known, was to be found in equal vigour and perfection in their own. On this
                    subject. however, we beg to refer the reader to some learned and valuable notes
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Ancient Universal History</hi> (vol. xvii. p. 529,
                    8vo); and also to Buffon’s article on the elephant, one of the most masterly
                    pieces of composition to be found in his admirable work.</p>
                <p>Ivory is applied to a variety of purposes in the arts. In England, the chief
                    consumption of that commodity is in the manufacture of handles for knives; but
                    it is also extensively used in the manufacture of musical and mathematical
                    instruments, chess-pieces, billiard-balls, thin plates for miniatures, toys, and
                    small works of vertù. Articles in ivory, however, are said to be manufactured to
                    agreater extent, and with much more success, at Dieppe, than at any other place
                    in Europe. But the art of working in this <pb break="no" facs="nls:192944185"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0712-4185-0491"/>beautiful material is far better understood by the
                    Chinese than by any other nation. No European artist has hitherto succeeded in
                    cutting concentric balls after the manner of this people; nor have their boxes,
                    chess-pieces, and other articles manufactured in ivory, been approached, far
                    less rivalled, by any similar productions that are to be met with in other
                    countries.</p>
                <p>Ivory, in the rough state, is a very considerable article of commerce. The
                    importation of elephants’ tusks into Great Britain, for twelve years from 1788
                    to 1799 inclusively, amounted to 18,914 cwts. or, on an average, to 1576 cwts.
                    annually. Since that period, however, the trade has much increased. The imports
                    in 1831 and 1832 were, at an average, 4130 cwts., of which 2950 cwts. were
                    retained for home consumption. But as the medium weight of a tusk is about sixty
                    lbs. it follows that the yearly imports of 1831 and 1832 must be taken at 7709
                    tusks, and that, to obtain these, 3854 male elephants must have been destroyed.
                    But, supposing the tusks could only be obtained by killing the animal, the
                    destruction would really be a good deal greater, and must probably have amounted
                    to 4500 or 5000 elephants. Occasionally, however, tusks are accidentally broken,
                    one lost in this way being replaced by a new one; and a good many are also
                    obtained from elephants which have died a natural death. Still it is obvious
                    that the supply from these sources cannot be very large; and if to the quantity
                    of ivory required for Great Britain be added that required for the other
                    countries of Europe, as well as for America and Asia, the slaughter of elephants
                    must, after every deduction, be immense; nor can it fail to excite surprise that
                    the breed of this magnificent animal, and consequently the supply of tusks, has
                    not been more diminished. The western and eastern coasts of Africa, the Cape of
                    Good Hope, Ceylon, India, and the countries to the eastward of the Straits of
                    Malacca, are the great marts whence supplies of ivory are obtained. The imports
                    into Great Britain from Western Africa in 1831 amounted to 2575 cwts. whilst the
                    Cape of Good Hope only furnished 198 cwts. During the same year, the imports
                    from India, Ceylon, and other eastern countries, amounted to 2173 cwts∙ The
                    price per cwt. duty (L.l per cwt.) included, of elephants’ tusks in the London
                    market, in December 1833, was as follows :—</p>
                <table cols="2" rows="7">
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1st sort, weighing from 79 to 90 lbs.
                            per tusk L.29 0 0 to L.31 0 0 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 2d do 56 to 60 25 0 0 to 23 0 0 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 3d do 38 to 55 23 0 0 to 26 0 0 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 4th do 28 to 37 20 0 0 to 24 0 0 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 5th do 18 to 27 18 0 0 to 21 0 0 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Scrivelloes 14 0 0 to 35 0 0 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Sea-horse teeth 5 0 0 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
