<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0070-0059-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RÙMÎ (9th edition, volume 21, page 59)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1023088">Minorities</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1023465">Minors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079211">Prophets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44t5k">Koran</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698j66">Prophets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w66">Cat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688q84">Odes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n70/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RÙMÎ</label>. Mohammed b. Mohammed b. Husaki albalkhi, better
                    known as MaulAnA JalAhuddin Rιιmi, the greatest Suflc poet of Persia, was born
                    on the 30th of September 1207 (601 A.H. 6th of Rabi' I.) at Balkh, in KhorasAn,
                    where his family had resided from time immemorial, rich in property and public
                    renown. He claimed descent from the caliph Abilbekr, and from the KhwArism shah
                    SultAn 'AlA-uddin b. Tukush (1199-1220), whose only daughter, Malika-i-JahAn,
                    had been married to JalAhuddin’s grandfather. Her son, Mohammed, commonly called
                    BahA-uddin Walad, was a famous doctor of Balkh, who, to escape the jealousy with
                    which the sultan viewed his influence, emigrated to Asia Minor in 1212. Young
                    JalAhuddin was only five years old at that time, but the signs of his future
                    greatness in spiritual matters began already to manifest themselves in
                    precocious knowledge and in ecstasies and visions. After residing for some time
                    at Malatiyah and afterwards at ErzinjAn in Armenia, BahA-uddin was called to
                    LArindah in Asia Minor, as principal of the local college, and there young
                    JalAhuddin, who had meanwhile grown under the careful tuition of his father in
                    wisdom and holiness, attained his maturity, and married in 1226 Jauhar KhAtiin,
                    the daughter of LAlA Sharahuddin of Samarkand. Finally, BahA-uddin was invited
                    to Iconium by 'AlA-uddin KaikubAd (1219-1236), the sultAn of Asia Minor, or, as
                    it is commonly called in the East, Rιim,—whence JalAl-uddin’s surname <hi
                    rend="italic">(takhallus)</hi> Rιimi.</p>
                <p>After BahA-uddin’s death in 1231, JalAhuddin went to Aleppo and Damascus for a
                    short time to study, but, as the mere positive sciences in which he had been
                    particularly trained failed to satisfy him, on his return to Iconium, where he
                    became by and by professor of four separate colleges, he took for nine years as
                    his spiritual guide Sayyid BurhAn-uddin Husaini of Tirmidh, one of his father’s
                    disciples, and later on the wandering Süfi Shams-uddin of Tabriz, who arrived in
                    Iconium on the 29th of November 1241, and soon acquired the most powerful
                    influence over JalAhuddin, who even adopted his name as takhallus in his ghazals
                    or mystic odes. Shams-uddin’s rather aggressive character, however, roused the
                    indignation of the people of Iconium against him, and during a riot in which
                    JalAl-uddin’s eldest son, 'AlA-uddin, was killed, he was arrested and probably
                    executed; at least he was no more seen. This fate of his teacher and friend,
                    together with the untimely death of his son, threw JalAhuddin into deep
                    melancholy, and in remembrance of these victims of popular wrath lie founded the
                    order of the Maulawi or (in Turkish pronunciation) Mewlewi dervishes, famous for
                    their piety as well as for their peculiar garb of mourning, their music and
                    their mystic dance (samA), which is the outward representation of the circling
                    movement of the spheres, and the inward symbol of the circling movement of the
                    soul caused by the vibrations of a Siifi’s fervent love to God. The
                    establishment of this order, which still possesses numerous cloisters throughout
                    the Turkish empire, and the leadership of which has been kept in JalAl-uddin’s
                    family in Iconium uninterruptedly for the last six hundred years, gave a new
                    stimulus both to the zeal and energy and the poetical inspiration of the great
                    shaikh. Most of his matchless odes, in which he soars on the wings of a genuine
                    enthusiasm, high over earth and heaven up to the throne of Almighty God, were
                    composed in honour of the Maulawi dervishes, and even his <hi rend="italic">opus
                    magnum,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Mathnawi</hi> or, as it is usually called,
                    <hi rend="italic">The Spiritual Mathnawi</hi> (mathnawi-i-ma'nawi), a production
                    of the highest poetical and religious intuition in six books or daftars, with
                    30,000 to 40,000 double-rhymed verses, can be traced to the same source. The
                    idea of this immense collection of ethical and moral precepts, interwoven with
                    numerous anecdotes and comments on verses of the KorAn and sayings of the
                    Prophet, which the Eastern world reveres as the greatest devotional work, the
                    study of which secures eternal bliss, was first suggested to the poet by his
                    favourite disciple Hasan, better known as HusAm-uddin, who became in 1258
                    JalAl-uddin’s chief assistant. He had frequently observed that the members of
                    the Maulawi fraternity read with great delight the mystic mathnawis of SanA’i
                    and Farid-uddiii 'AttAr, and induced his master to compose a similar poem on a
                    larger scale. JalAhuddin readily fell in with this suggestion and dictated to
                    him, with a short interruption, the whole work during the remaining years of bis
                    life. Soon after the completion of this masterpiece JalAhuddin died on the 17th
                    of December 1273 (672 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.</hi> H. 5th of JumAdA II.),
                    worshipped as a saint by high and low. His first successor in the rectorship of
                    the Maulawi fraternity was HusAm-uddin himself, after whose death in 1284
                    JalAl-uddin’s younger and only surviving son, Shaikh BahAudd-in Ahmed, commonly
                    called SultAn Walad, and favourably known as author of the mystical mathnawi,
                    <hi rend="italic">Rabdbnama,</hi> or the Book of the Guitar (died 1312), was
                    duly installed as grand-master of the order.</p>
                <p>JalAl-uddin’s life is fully described in Shams-uddin Alimed Aflaki’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Mamikib-ul 'arifin</hi> (written between 718 and 754 A. H. ), the
                    most important portions of which have been translated by J. W. Redhouse in the
                    preface to his English metrical version of <hi rend="italic">The Mesnevi, Book
                    the First</hi> (London, 1881; Triibner’s Oriental series). Complete editions
                    have been printed in Bombay, Lucknow, Tabriz, Constantinople, and in Bulak (with
                    a Turkish translation, 1268 A.H. ), at the end of which a Seventhdaftarisadded,
                    the genuineness of which is refuted by a remark of Jalahuddin himself in one of
                    the Bodleian copies of the poem, Ouseley, 294 (f. 328α <hi rend="italic">sq.
                    ).</hi> The revised edition by 'Abd-ullatif (made between 1024 and 1032 A.H.) is
                    still unpublished, but the same author’s commentary on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mathnawi, Latdif-Ulrndnawi,</hi> and his glossary, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Latdif-dlkughdt,</hi> have been lithographed in Cawnpore (1876) and Lucknow
                    (1877) respectively, the latter under the title <hi rend="italic"
                    >Farhang-i-mathnaud.</hi> For the other numerous commentaries and for further
                    biographical and literary particulars of JalAhuddin see Rieu’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cat. of the Persian MSS. of the BrH. Mzιs.,</hi> vol. ii. p. 584 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.;</hi> A. Sprengeris <hi rend="italic">OuFlh Cat.,</hi> p. 489;
                    Sir Gore Ouseley, <hi rend="italic">Notices of Persian Poets,</hi> p. 112 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.</hi>; and H. Ethé, <hi rend="italic"
                    >UiMorgenlaiidiseheSkudien,</hi> Leipsic, 1870, p. 95 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>
                    Select poems from Jalal-uddin’s diwAn (often styled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Diwdn-i-Shams-i-Tabriz)</hi> have been translated in German verse by V. von
                    Rosenzweig, Vienna, 1838. (H. E.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
