<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0046-0035-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ROYAL HOUSEHOLD (9th edition, volume 21, page
                    35)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:962162">Households</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198642">Conquest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133321">Stewards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28g7v">Cloth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f766g40">Sovereigns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n46/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ROYAL HOUSEHOLD</label>. In all the mediaeval monarchies of
                    western Europe the general system of government sprang from, and centred in, the
                    royal household. The sovereign’s domestics were his officers of state, and the
                    leading dignitaries of the palace were the principal administrators of the
                    kingdom. The royal household itself had, in its turn, grown out of an earlier
                    and more primitive institution. It took its rise in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Comitatus</hi> described by Tacitus, the chosen band of <hi rend="italic"
                    >comites</hi> or companions who, when the Roman historian wrote, constituted the
                    personal following, in peace as well as in war, of the Teutonic</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n47/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0047-0036"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Princeps</hi> or chieftain. In England before the Conquest the
                    <hi rend="italic">Comitatus</hi> had developed or degenerated into the
                    thegnhood, and among the most eminent and powerful of the king’s thegns, were
                    his dishthegn, his bowerthegn, and his horsethegn or staller. In Normandy at the
                    time of the Conquest a similar arrangement, imitated from the French court, had
                    long been established, and the Norman dukes, like their overlords the kings of
                    France, had their seneschal or steward, their chamberlain, and their constable.
                    After the Conquest the ducal household of Normandy was reproduced in the royal
                    household of England; and since, in obedience to the spirit of feudalism, the
                    great offices of the first had been made hereditary, the great offices of the
                    second were made hereditary also, and were thenceforth held by the grantees and
                    their descendants as grand-serjeanties of the crown. The consequence was that
                    they passed out of immediate relation to the practical conduct of affairs either
                    in both state and court or in the one or the other of them. The steward and
                    chamberlain of England were superseded in their political functions by the
                    justiciar and treasurer of England, and in their domestic functions by the
                    steward and chamber-lain of the household. The marshal of England took the place
                    of the constable of England in the royal palace, and was associated with him in
                    the command of the royal armies. In due course, however, the marshalship as well
                    as the constableship became hereditary, and, although the constable and marshal
                    of England retained their military authority until a comparatively late period,
                    the duties they had successively performed about the palace had been long before
                    transferred to the master of the horse. Under these circumstances the holders of
                    the original great offices of state and the household ceased to attend the court
                    except on occasions of extraordinary ceremony, and their representatives either
                    by inheritance or by special appointment have ever since continued to appear at
                    coronations and some other public solemnities, such as the opening of the
                    parliament or trials by the House of Lords. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The great officers of state and the household whom we have
                    particularly mentioned do not of course exhaust the catalogue of them. We have
                    named those only whose representatives are still dignitaries of the court and
                    functionaries of the palace. If the reader consults Hallam <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Middle Ages,</hi> vol. i. p. 181 <hi rend="italic">sq.),</hi> Freeman <hi
                    rend="italic">(Norman Conquest,</hi> vol. i. p. 91 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi>
                    and vol. v. p. 426 <hi rend="italic">sq.},</hi> and Stubbs <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Const. Hist.,</hi> vol. i. p. 343, <hi rend="italic">sq.),</hi> he will be
                    able himself to fill in the details of the outline we have given above.
                    </p></note></p>
                <p>The materials available for a history of the royal household are somewhat scanty
                    and obscure. The earliest record relating to it is of the reign of Henry II.,
                    and is contained in the <hi rend="italic">Blaxk Book of the Exchequer.</hi> It
                    enumerates the various inmates of the king’s palace and the daily allowances
                    made to them at the period at which it was compiled. Hence it affords valuable
                    evidence of the antiquity and relative importance of the court offices to which
                    it refers, notwithstanding that it is silent as to the functions and formal
                    subordination of the persons who filled them. <note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The record in question is entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Constitutio Dornus Régis de Procurationibus,</hi> and is printed
                    by Hearne <hi rend="italic">(Liber Niger Scaccarii,</hi> vol. i. p. 341 <hi
                    rend="italic">sqO.</hi> It is analysed by Stubbs <hi rend="italic">(Const.
                    Hist.,</hi> vol. i. note 2. P. 345). </p></note> In addition to this record we
                    have a series of far later, but for the most part equally meagre, documents
                    bearing more or less directly on the constitution of the royal household, and
                    extending, with long intervals, from the reign of Edward III. to the reign of
                    William and Mary. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>.4
                    <hi rend="italic">Collection of Ordinances and Regulations for the Government of
                    the Royal Household, made in Divers Rxigns from King Edward III. to King William
                    and Queen Mary,</hi> printed for the Society of Antiquaries, London, 1790. See
                    also Pegge’s <hi rend="italic">Curialia,</hi> published partly before and partly
                    after this volume; and Carlisle’s <hi rend="italic">Gentlemen of the Privy
                    Chamber,</hi> published in 1829. Pegge and Carlisle, however, deal with small
                    and insignificant portions of the royal establishment. </p></note> Among them,
                    however, are what are known as the <hi rend="italic">Black Book of the
                    Household</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Statutes of Eltham,</hi> compiled the
                    first in the reign of Edward IV. and the second in the reign of Henry VIlI.,
                    from which a good deal of detailed information may be gathered concerning the
                    arrangements of the court in the 15th and lGth centuries. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Statutes of Eltham</hi> were meant for the practical guidance merely of those
                    who were responsible for the good order and the sufficient supply of the
                    sovereign’s household at the time they were issued. But the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Black Book of the Household,</hi> besides being a sort of treatise on princely
                    magnificence generally, professes to be based on the regulations established for
                    the governance of the court by Edward III., who, it affirms, was “the first
                    setter of certeynties among his domesticall meyne, upon a grounded rule” and
                    whose palace it describes as “the house of very policie and flowre of England ;”
                    and it may therefore possibly, and even probably, take us back to a period much
                    more remote than that at which it was actually put together. <note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Liber Niger
                    Domus Regis Edward I V.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ordinances for the Household
                    made at Ellham in the seventeenth year of King Henry VIlI., A.D. 1526,</hi> are
                    the titles of these two documents. The earlier documents printed in the same
                    collection are <hi rend="italic">Household of King Edxoard III. in Peace and War
                    from the eighteenth to the twenty-first year of his reign; Ordinances of the
                    Household of King Henry IV. in the thirty-third year of his reign, A.D.
                    Ui55,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Articles ordained by King Henry VII. for the
                    Regulation of his Household, Λ.D. llβJi.</hi></p></note> Various orders,
                    returns, and accounts of the reigns of Elizabeth, James I., Charles I., Charles
                    IT., and William and Mary throw considerable light on the organization of
                    particular sections of the royal household in times nearer to our own. <note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">The Book of
                    the Household of Queen Elizabeth as it was ordained in the forty-third year of
                    her Reign delivered to our Sovereign Lord King James, &amp;c.,</hi> is simply a
                    list of officers’ names and allowances. It seems to have been drawn up under the
                    curious circumstances referred to in <hi rend="italic">Archaeologia</hi> (vol.
                    xii. pp. 80-85). For the rest of these documents see <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ordinances and Regulations, &amp;c.,</hi> pp. 299, 340, 347, 352, 368, and
                    380.</p></note> Moreover, there were several parliamentary inquiries into the
                    expenses of the royal household in connexion with the settlement or reform of
                    the civil list during the reigns of George III., George IV., and William IV.
                    <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Burke’s celebrated Act
                    “for enabling His Majestytodischargethe debt contracted upon the civil list, and
                    for preventing the same from being in arrear for the future, c.,” 22 Geo. III.
                    c. 82, was passed in 1782. But it was foreshadowed in his great speech on
                    “Economical Reform” delivered two years before. Since the beginning of the
                    current century select committees of the House of Commons have reported on the
                    civil list and royal household in 1SO3, 1804, 1815, and 1831. </p></note> But
                    they add little or nothing to our knowledge of the subject in what was then its
                    historical as distinguished from its contemporary aspects. So much, indeed, is
                    this the case that, on the accession of Queen Victoria, Chamberlayne’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Present State of England,</hi> which contains a catalogue of the
                    officials at the court of Queen Anne, was described by Lord Melbourne the prime
                    minister as the “only authority” which the advisers of the crown could find for
                    their assistance in determining the appropriate constitution and dimensions of
                    the domestic establishment of a queen regnant. <note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Torrens’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of
                    William, second Viscount Melbourne,</hi> vol. ii. p. 303. </p></note></p>
                <p>In its main outlines the existing organization of the royal household is
                    essentially the same as it was under the Tudors or the Plantagenets. It is now,
                    as it was then, divided into three principal departments, at the head of which
                    are severally the lord steward, the lord chamber-lain, and the master of the
                    horse, and the respective provinces of which may be generally described as
                    “below stairs,” “above stairs,” and “out of doors.” But at present, the
                    sovereign being a queen, the royal household is in some other respects rather
                    differently arranged from what it would be if there were a king and a queen
                    consort. λVhen there is a king and a queen consort there is a <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n48/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0048-0037"/>separate establishment “above stairs” and “out of
                    doors” for the queen consort. She has a lord chamberlain’s department and a
                    department of the master of the horse of her own, and all the ladies of the
                    court from the mistress of the robes to the maids of honour are in her service.
                    At the commencement of the reign of Queen Victoria the two establishments were
                    combined, and on the whole considerably reduced. Hence the royal household,
                    although it is of course much larger than that of a queen consort would be, is
                    also appreciably smaller than that of a king and queen consort together has been
                    since the reigning family acceded to the throne. <note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Hansard, <hi rend="italic">Part.
                    Debates,</hi> vol. xxxix. pp. 146 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> 1342 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="italic">Department of the Lord Steward of the Household—</hi> The
                    hall; the kitchen, ewry, and pantry; the wine, beer, and coal cellars; and the
                    almonry are in the lord steward’s department. The lord steward is the first
                    dignitary of the court, and presides at the Board of Green Cloth, where all the
                    accounts of the household are examined and passed. <note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In the <hi rend="italic">Statutes of
                    Elthatn</hi> he is called “the lord great master,” but in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Household Book</hi> of Queen Elizabeth “the lord steward," as before and since.
                    In 31 Hen. VIII. c. 10, “for placing of the lords,” he is described as “the
                    grand master or lord steward of the king’s most honourable household." The whole
                    business of purveyance and pre-emption was anciently managed by the Board of
                    Green Cloth. See under heading “The counting house of the king’s household, <hi
                    rend="italic">Dornus Cotnpotus Hospitii RegisJ</hi> in Coke, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Institutes,</hi> iv. cap. 19. Tt is designated “the court of the virge or green
                    cloth “in 22 Geo. III. c. 82, § 5. </p></note> He is always a member of the
                    Government of the day, a peer, and a privy councillor. He receives his
                    appointment from the sovereign in person, and bears a white staff as the emblem
                    and warrant of his authority. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>In the old time the lord steward had three courts besides
                    the board of green cloth under him, namely, the lord steward’s court, the court
                    of the Marshalteyand the palace court (Coke, <hi rend="italic">Inst.,</hi> iv.
                    caps. 20 and 21; Reeves, <hi rend="italic">Hist, of the Late of England,</hi>
                    vol. ii. pp. 138 and 297; Stephen, <hi rend="italic">Commentaries on the Law of
                    England,</hi> vol. iv. p. 222). The lord steward or his deputies formerly
                    administer; d the oaths to the members of the House of Commons, and frequent
                    inconveniences were the consequence (see Hatsell, <hi rend="italic">Precedents
                    of Proceedings in the House of Commons,</hi> London, 1818, vol. ii. pp. 84-91).
                    In certain cases now “the lords with white staves” are the proper persons to
                    bear communications between the sovereign and the Houses of Parliament.
                    </p></note> In his department the treasurer and comptroller of the household are
                    the officers next in rank to him. They also sit at the Board of Green Cloth,
                    carry white staves, and belong to the ministry. They are always peers or the
                    sons of peers, and privy councillors. But the duties which in theory belong to
                    the lord steward, treasurer, and comptroller of the household are in practice
                    performed by the master of the household, who is a permanent officer and resides
                    in the palace. It is he who really investigates the accounts and maintains
                    discipline among the ordinary servants of the royal establishment. He is a
                    white-staff officer and a member of the Board of Green Cloth but not of the
                    ministry, and among other things he presides at the daily dinners of the suite
                    in waiting on the sovereign. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>In the case of the master of the household we see history
                    repeating itself. He is not named in the <hi rend="italic">Black Book</hi> of
                    Edward IV. or in the <hi rend="italic">Statutes</hi> of Henry VIII., and is
                    entered as “master of the household and clerk of the green cloth " in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Household Book</hi> of Queen Elizabeth. But practically he has
                    superseded the lord steward of the household, as the lord steward of the
                    household at one time superseded the lord high steward of England. </p></note>
                    Irt the lord steward’s department are the secretary and three clerks of the
                    Board of Green Cloth; the coroner and paymaster of the household; and the
                    officers of the almonry, namely, the hereditary grand almoner, <note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The marquess of Exeter.
                    </p></note> the lord high almoner, the sub-almoner, the groom of the almonry,
                    and the secretary to the lord high almoner. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>In the lord steward's department the OflBces of cofferer of
                    the household, treasurer of the chamber, paymaster of pensions, and six clerks
                    of the Board of Green Cloth were abolished by 22 Geo. III. c. 82.
                    </p></note></p>
                <p>II. <hi rend="italic">Department of the Lord (Chamberlain of the Household.—</hi>
                    The bedchamber, privy chamber, and presence chamber, the wardrobe, the
                    housekeeper’s room, and the guardroom, the metropolitan theatres, and the
                    chapels royal are in the lord chamberlain’s department. The lord chamberlain is
                    the second dignitary of the court, and is always a member of the Government of
                    the day, a peer, and a privy councillor. He carnes a white staff, and wears a
                    golden or jewelled key, typical of the key of the palace, which is supposed to
                    be in his charge, as the ensigns of his office. He is responsible for the
                    necessary arrangements connected with state ceremonies, such as coronations and
                    royal marriages, christenings, and funerals. All invitations to court are sent
                    out in his name by command of the sovereign, and at drawing rooms and levees he
                    stands next to the sovereign and announces the persons who are approaching the
                    throne. It is also part of his duty to conduct the sovereign to and from his or
                    her carriage. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The lord
                    chamberlain of the household at one time discharged some important political
                    functions, which are described by Sir Harns Nicolas <hi rend="italic"
                    >!Proceedings of the Privy Council,</hi> vol. vi., Preface, p. xxiii).
                    </p></note> The vice-chamberlain of the household is the lord chamberlain’s
                    assistant and deputy. He also is one of the ministry, a white-staff officer, and
                    the bearer of a key; and he is always a peer or the son of a peer as well as a
                    privy councillor.</p>
                <p>When there is a king the groom of the stole comes next to the vice-chamberlain in
                    rank and authority. At present, however, the mistress of the robes in some
                    measure occupies the position of the groom of the stole. <note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In the reign of Queen Anne, Sarah duchess of
                    Marlborough from 1704, and Elizabeth duchess of Somerset from 1710, held the
                    combined offices of mistress of the robes and groom of the stole. </p></note>
                    She is the only lady of the court who comes into office and goes out with the
                    administration, and the duties she performs are merely occasional and formal.
                    She is always a duchess, and attends the queen at all state ceremonies and
                    entertainments, but is never in permanent residence at the palace. <note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Since the great “bedchamber
                    question” of 1839 the settled practice has been for all the ladies of the court
                    except the mistress of the robes to receive and continue in their appointments
                    independently of the political connexions of their husbands, fathers, and
                    brothers (see Mr Gladstone's <hi rend="italic">Gleanings of Past Years,</hi>
                    vol. i. p. 40; and Torrens's <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Lord Melbourne,</hi>
                    vol. ii. p. 304). </p></note> On the contrary the ladies of the bedchamber share
                    the function of personal attendance on the sovereign throughout the year. Of
                    these there are eight, always peeresses, and each is in waiting for about a
                    fortnight or three λveeks at a time. But the women of the bedchamber, of whom
                    there are also eight, appear only at court ceremonies and entertainments
                    according to a roster annually issued under the authority of the lord
                    chamberlain. They are usually the daughters of peers or the wives of the sons of
                    peers, and in the old time, like the mistress of the robes and the ladies of the
                    bedchamber, habitually assisted the queen at her daily toilette. But this has
                    long ceased to be done by any of them. The maids of honour, whose situations are
                    by no means sinecures, are likewise eight in number and have the same terms of
                    waiting as the ladies of the bedchamber. They are commonly if not always the
                    daughters Orgranddaughtersof peers, and when they have no superior title and
                    precedence by birth are called “honourable” and placed next after the daughters
                    of barons. The queen as a special mark of Iierfavour nominates “extra” ladies
                    and women of the bed-chamber and maids of honour. But their position is
                    altogether honorary and involves no charge on the civil list. There are eight
                    lords and eight grooms, who are properly described as “of the bedchamber” or “in
                    waiting,” according as the reigning sovereign is a king or a queen, and whose
                    terms of attendance are of similar duration to those of the ladies of the
                    bedchamber and the maids of honour. Occasionally “extra” lords and grooms in
                    waiting are nominated by the queen, who, however, are unpaid and have no regular
                    duties. The master, assistant master, and marshal of the ceremonies are the
                    officers whose special function it is to enforce the observance of the <hi
                    rend="italic">etiquette</hi> of the court. The reception of foreign potentates
                    and ambassadors is under their particular care, and they assist in the ordering
                    of all entertainments and festivities at the palace. <note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The office of master of the ceremonies was
                    created by James I. The master of the ceremonies wears a medal attached to a
                    gold chain round his neck, on one side being an emblem of peace with the motto
                    “Beati pacifici,” and on the other an emblem of war with the motto “Dieu et mon
                    droit” (see <hi rend="italic">Finetti PhHoxensis,</hi> by Sir John Finett,
                    master of the ceremonies tβ James I. and Charles I., 1656; and D’Israeli's <hi
                    rend="italic">Curiosities of Literature,</hi> 10:h ed., p. 242 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sqi).</hi></p></note> The gentleman usher of the black rod—the black rod which
                    he carries being the ensign of his office—is the principal usher of the court
                    and kingdom. He is one of the original functionaries of the order of the Garter,
                    and is in constant attendance on the House of Lords, from whom, either
                    personally or by his deputy the yeoman usher of the black rod, it is part of his
                    duty to carry messages and summonses to the House of Commons. The gentlemen
                    ushers of the privy chamber and the gentlemen ushers daily waiters, of whom
                    there are four each, and the gentlemen ushers quarterly waiters and the
                    sergeants-at-arms, of whom there are eight each, are in waiting only at drawing
                    rooms and levees and state balls and concerts. But of the sovereign’s
                    sergeants-at-arms there are two others to whom special duties are assigned, the
                    one attending the speaker in the House of Commons, and the other attending the
                    lord chancellor in the House of Lords, carrying their maces and executing their
                    orders. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See May, <hi
                    rend="italic">Parliamentary Practice,</hi> pp. 236, 244. </p></note> The yeomen
                    of the guard date from the reign of Henry VII., and the gentlemen-at-arms from
                    the reign of Henry VIII. The captain of each corps is always a member of the
                    ministry and a peer. Besides the captains, the former, now called the queen’s
                    bodyguard, consists of a lieutenant, ensign, clerk of the cheque and adjutant,
                    four exons, and a hundred yeomen; and the latter, once called the gentlemen
                    pensioners, consists of a lieutenant, standard-bearer, clerk of the cheque and
                    adjutant, a sub-officer, and forty gentlemen. The comptroller and examiner of
                    accounts, the licenser of plays, the dean and subdean of the chapel royal, the
                    clerk of the closet, the groom of the robes, the pages of the backstairs, of the
                    chamber, and of the presence, the poet laureate, the royal physicians and
                    surgeons, chaplains, painters and sculptors, librarians and musicians, amp;c.,
                    are all under the superintendence of the lord chamberlain of the household.
                    <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The offices of master
                    of the great wardrobe and master of the jewel house id the lord chamberlain’s
                    department were abolished by 22 Geo. III. c. 82. </p></note></p>
                <p>III. <hi rend="italic">Department of the Master of the Horse.—</hi> The stables
                    and coachhouses, the stud, mews, and kennels, are in the master of the horse’s
                    department. The master of the horse is the third <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n49/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0049-0038"/>dignitary of the court, and is always a member of
                    the Government of the day, a peer, and a privy councillor. All matters connected
                    with the horses and hounds of the sovereign are within his jurisdiction. The
                    master of the buckhounds, who is also one of the ministry, ranks next to him,
                    and it is his duty.to attend the royalhunt and to head the procession of royal
                    equipages on the racecourse at Ascot, where he presents himself on horseback in
                    a green and gold uniform wearing the couples of a hound as the badge of his
                    office. The hereditary grand falconer <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The duke of St Albans. </p></note> is also subordinated to
                    the master of the horse. But the practical management of the royal stables and
                    stud in fact devolves on the chief or crown equerry, formerly called the
                    gentleman of the horse, who is never in personal attendance on the sovereign,
                    and whose appointment is permanent. The clerk marshal has the supervision of the
                    accounts of the department before they are submitted to the Board of Green
                    Cloth, and is in waiting on the sovereign on state occasions only. Exclusive of
                    the crown equerry there are seven regular equerries, besides extra and honorary
                    equerries, one of whom is always in attendance on the sovereign and rides at the
                    side of the royal carriage. They are always officers of the army, and each of
                    them is “on duty” for about the same time as the lords and grooms in waiting.
                    There are also three pages of honour in the master of the horse’s department,
                    who must not be confounded with tho pages of various κinds who are in the
                    department of the lord chamberlain. They are youths aged from twelve to sixteen,
                    selected by the sovereign in person, to attend on her at state ceremonies, when
                    two of them arrayed in an antique costume assist the groom of the robes in
                    carrying the royal train.</p>
                <p>It remains to be said that to the three ancient departments of the royal
                    household which we have already noticed two others have been added in
                    comparatively recent times. The departments of the private secretary and the
                    keeper of the privy purse to the sovereign, which are for the present combined,
                    originated no longer ago than the earlier part of the current century. Very
                    great doubts were at one time entertained as to whether such an office as that
                    of private secretary to the sovereign could constitutionally exist, and the
                    privy purse itself was unknown until after the passing of Burke’s Act of 1782.
                    As at present organized these branches of the royal household consist of the
                    private secretary and keeper of the privy purse, two assistant private
                    secretaries and keepers of the privy purse, aud a secretary and two clerks of
                    the privy purse. By the statute which settled the civil list at the beginning of
                    the current reign (1 &amp; 2 Vict. c. 2) the privy purse was fixed at £60,000 a
                    year, am I the salaries, allowances, and other expenses of the royal household
                    were fixed at £303,760 a year. (F. DR.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
