<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0074-0063-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RUSHWORTH (9th edition, volume 21, page 63)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dz7j">Clerks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bt4s">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43r0pw1h">Protectorates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864129">Clerks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1008230">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156290">Trials</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079666">Protectorates</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095999">Restorationism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n74/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RUSHWORTH</label><hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">(c.</hi> 1607—1690), the compiler of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historical Collections</hi> Commonlydescribed by his name, was born in
                    Northumberland about the year 1607. After a period of study at Oxford, but not,
                    it appears, as a member of the university, he came to London, was entered at
                    Lincoln’s Inn, and was in due course called to the bar. As early as 1630 he
                    seems to have commenced attendance at the courts, especially the Star Chamber
                    and the Exchequer Chamber, not for the purpose of practising his profession, but
                    in order that he might observe and record the more remarkable of their
                    proceedings. On the meeting of the Long Parliament in 1640
                    Lewasappointedassistant clerk to the House of Commons, and was in the habit of I
                    making short-hand notes of the speeches he heard delivered in debate. He himself
                    states that it was from his report that the words used by Charles I. during his
                    memorable attempt to seize the “five members” were printed for public
                    distribution under the king’s orders. Being an expert horseman, it seems that
                    Rushworth was frequently employed by the House as their messenger as well as in
                    the capacity of clerk. When the king left London, and while the earl of Essex
                    was general, he was often the bearer of communications from the parliament to
                    one or the other of them. In 1645 Sir Thomas Fairfax, to whom he was distantly
                    related, and who was then in command of the Parliamentary forces, made him his
                    secretary, and he remained with the army almost continuously until 1650. In 1649
                    he was at Oxford, and the degree of master of arts was conferred on him by the
                    university. In 1652 he was nominated one of the commissioners for the reform of
                    the common law, and in 1658 he was elected member for Berwick in the parliament
                    of the commonwealth. Almost immediately before the Restoration he published the
                    first volume of his <hi rend="italic">Historical Collections,</hi> which had
                    been submitted in manuscript to Oliver Cromwell, with a very laudatory
                    dedication to Richard Cromwell, then Lord Protector. But the turn of events
                    induced him to withdraw this dedication, and he subsequently endeavoured without
                    success to conciliate Charles II. by presenting him with some of the registers
                    of the privy council which had come into his possession. In the convention of
                    1660, which recalled the king, he sat again as member for Berwick. In 1677 he
                    was made secretary to Sir Orlando Bridgeman, then lord keeper, and he was
                    returned for Berwick a third and a fourth time to the parliaments of 1679 and
                    1681. Soon after this he appears to have fallen into straitened circumstances.
                    In 1684 he was arrested for debt, and cast into the King’s Bench prison, where
                    he died, after lingering for some time in a condition of mental infirmity, the
                    result of excessive drinking, in 1690.</p>
                <p>Rushworth’s <hi rend="italic">Historical Collections of Private Passages of
                    Stats, IVeighty Matters in Law, and Remarkable Proceedings in Parliament</hi>
                    was reprinted in eight folio volumes in 1721. The eighth volume of this edition
                    is an account of the trial of the earl of Strafford, the other seven volumes
                    being concerned with the miscellaneous transactions of the period from 1618 to
                    1648. Only the first three volumes and the trial of Strafford were originally
                    published in Rushworth’s lifetime; but the manuscript of the other volumes was
                    left by him ready for the press. The extreme value of the work is well known to
                    all inquirers into the history of the Civil War, and much of the information it
                    contains is to be found nowhere else. Its impartiality, however, can hardly be
                    seriously maintained, and hence it is necessary to consult it with some
                    caution.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
