<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0921-0071-0060-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RUNNING (9th edition, volume 21, page 60)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hn54">Sports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fs4j">Toes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w237">Running</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk0743s">Winds</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1129434">Speed</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1152071">Toes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1101348">Running</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130432">Sports</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n71/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RUNNING</label>. In this mode of progression the step is
                    lighter and gait more rapid than in walking, from which it differs in consisting
                    of a succession of springs from toe to toe, instead of a series of steps from
                    toe to heel. As an athletic exercise, it has been in vogue from the earliest
                    times, and the simple foot race, δpd∕χoς, run straight from starting point to
                    goal, was a game of the Greek pentathlon. It was diversified with the
                    διαυλοδρό/zoç, in which a distance mark was rounded and the starting and winning
                    points were the same, and also by the δρό/zoç οπλιτών, which might be compared
                    to the modern heavy marching order race. In ancient Italy running was practised
                    in circus exhibitions, as described by Virgil (√Λ7ι. v. 286 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sqj.</hi> In modern times it has been developed almost into a science by the
                    Anglo-Saxon race in Great Britain and North America, till the distances recently
                    covered appear almost <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit21newyrich/page/n72/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0921-0072-0061"/>fabulous compared with the performances up to the
                    end of the first half of the century. In all kinds of running the entire weight
                    of the body is thrown on the toes, from which light strides are taken with all
                    possible freedom of action from the hips. At starting the feet are placed about
                    a foot apart, the body being inclined slightly forward, with the weight of it on
                    the right or Iiindermost foot. A bent double position with the feet wide apart
                    is on no account advisable. The start cannot be made too quickly on the signal
                    being given. Two or three short steps are taken to get fairly into stride, after
                    which the runner should look straight before him, set his eyes steadfastly on
                    the goal, and run towards it at his longest and quickest stride, care being
                    taken not to swerve or get out of stride.</p>
                <p>Running is usually thus classified :—(1) sprinting includes all distances up to
                    400 yards; (2) medium distances range from one quarter to three quarters of a
                    mile; (3) long distances are those of one mile and upwards. The first-named is
                    the most popular, and is much practised in the north of England, especially at
                    Sheffield, which may be termed the home of sprint running. It is less fatiguing
                    than long distances and requires less arduous training, while strength to a
                    certain extent replaces wind. A great point in sprinting is to obtain a good
                    start, for which purpose incessant practice is required. A first-class sprinter
                    when at full sp.eed will clear from 8 to 9 feet in each stride, and his toes
                    leave the ground with inconceivable rapidity. When in good condition he will run
                    100 yards at top speed in one breath, and probably 150 yards without drawing a
                    second one. The quickest authenticated times in which short distances have been
                    run on perfectly level ground are as follows :—120 yards, 11⅜ sec.; 150 yards,
                    15 sec.; 200 yards, 19⅜ sec.; 300 yards, 30 sec.; and 400 yards, 43 j sec.</p>
                <p>Of medium distances the quarter mile race is by far the most difficult to run, as
                    a combination of speed and endurance is requisite. In fact a runner should be
                    able to sprint the whole way. Six hundred yards and half a mile are the other
                    chief distances in this class of running. The stride is slower than in
                    sprinting, and a man cannot maintain the same speed throughout as is possible up
                    to 300 yards. The best authenticated times are—quarter mile, 48J <hi
                    rend="superscript">sec</hi> ∙ &gt; 600 yards, 1 min. 11⅜ sec.; half mile, 1 min.
                    53⅛ sec.; 1000 yards, 2 min. 13 sec.; three quarter mile, 3 min. 7 sec.</p>
                <p>Light wiry men are best fitted for long-distance running, where stamina and wind
                    are more useful than speed. The strides must be long and light. After some miles
                    a runner is unable to keep the weight of the body on his toes any longer owing
                    to fatigue, puts his heels down, and runs flat-footed. The times accomplished of
                    late years by long-distance runners are most remarkable. Those for the chief
                    distances are as follows :—1 mile, 4 min. 16⅜ sec.; 2 miles, 9 min. 11⅜ sec.; 3
                    miles, 14 min. 36 sec.; 4 miles, 19 min. 36 sec.; 5 miles, 24 min. 40 sec.; 10
                    miles, 51 min. 6⅛ sec.; 20 miles, 1 h. 56 min. 38 sec.; 30 miles, 3 h. 15 min. 9
                    sec.; 40 miles, 4 h. 34 min. 27 sec.; 50 miles, 6 h. 8 min.; 100 miles, 13 h. 26
                    min. 30 sec.; 200 miles, 35 h. 9 min. 28 sec.; 300 miles, 58 h. 17 min. 6 sec.;
                    400 miles, 85 h. 52 min.; 500 miles, 109 h. 18 min. 20 sec.; 600 miles, 137 h.
                    25 min. 10 sec.; 610 miles, 140 h. 34 min. 10 sec.</p>
                <p>Nearly all running contests now take place on prepared cinder paths, which from
                    their springiness assist speed considerably. A runner’s dress should be as light
                    as possible, and consist merely of a thin jersey, a pair of drawers covering the
                    waist and loins and extending downwards to the top of the knee caps, and
                    heelless running shoes with a few short spikes in the soles just under the tread
                    of the foot. The spikes are longer for sprinting. Chamois leather socks for the
                    toes and ball of the foot may be added, since they diminish concussion as each
                    foot reaches the ground. Since the introduction of Athletic Sports (see vol.
                    iii. p. 12) into England and America commenced in 1860 the popularity of amateur
                    running races has vastly increased. These contests are governed by the rules of
                    the Amateur Athletic Association. At Sheffield a code of rules has been drawn up
                    for the regulation of the more important professional handicaps.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
