<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0010-0001-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DEAD SEA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 1</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="29" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1004334">Lynching</term>
                    <term n="29" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:827285">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:1163841">Valleys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="14" ref="fastgeo:1205669">Jordan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n10/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DEAD SEA</label>, the largest lake in Palestine, and
                    physically, as well as historically, among the most remarkable in the world. It
                    is called in Scripture <hi rend="italic">The Salt Sea</hi> (Gen. xiv. 3), <hi
                    rend="italic">The Sea of the Plain,</hi> or more correctly of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Arabah</hi> (Deut. iii. 17), and <hi rend="italic">The East
                    Sea</hi> (Ezek. xlvii. 18). Josephus calls it the <hi rend="italic">Asphaltic
                    Lake (B. J.</hi> iii. 10, 17), a name adopted by classic writers in allusion to
                    the bitumen, or asphaltum, which abounds in its basin. Jerome gave it the name
                    <hi rend="italic">Dead Sea</hi> because its waters are fatal to animal life, and
                    in the Talmud it is called the <hi rend="italic">Sea of Sodom.</hi> Its common
                    name among the inhabitants of Palestine is <hi rend="italic">Baheiret</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Lût,</hi><hi rend="italic">“</hi> The Sea of Lot.”</p>
                <p>The sea is 46 miles long, and varies from 5 to 9 in breadth. Its bed is the
                    lowest part of the great valley of the Jordan; and its surface has a depression
                    of no less than 1308 feet beneath the level of the ocean. The Jordan valley
                    itself, for a distance of about 80 miles to the northward and 30 to the
                    southward, is also below the level of the ocean. The general contour of the sea
                    is an elongated oval, with a number of bold promontories and deep bays along the
                    western shore, and a large, low peninsula on the south-east. It is shut in on
                    the east and west by parallel ranges of mountains which rise steeply, and in
                    some places in precipices of naked rock, from the water. The western range is
                    the mountain chain of Judah, and is composed of white limestone intermixed with
                    yellow and reddish strata. Its whole eastern slopes are bare, rugged, and
                    desolate, forming that wilderness in which David found an asylum, in which the
                    Baptist preached, and in which our Lord was tempted. The average height of the
                    cliffs along the shore is about 2000 feet; but they are deeply fissured by
                    torrent beds, which are all dry in summer. There are, however, a few fountains
                    in the glens and near the shore, the most celebrated of which is the Biblical
                    Engedi. At the north-west curve of the sea are extensive salt marshes, and at
                    the south-west is a range of hills of rock salt, 7 miles long and 300 feet high,
                    called <hi rend="italic">Khashm Usdom,</hi> “The ridge of Sodom.” On the south
                    of the sea lies a low marshy plain, partially covered with jungles of reeds,
                    tamarisk, and broom.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n11/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0011-0002"/>
                <p>The mountain range along the eastern side of the Dead Sea is the sustaining wall
                    of the tableland of Moab, which has an elevation of about 2800 feet, and is
                    therefore 4000 feet above the lake. At the southern end the range is composed of
                    red sandstone, a continuation of the “red mountains of Edom. At the valley of
                    Kerek the sandstone gives place to limestone; but further north it again appears
                    in thick strata below the limestone. The range is intersected by the deep and
                    wild ravines of Kerak (the <hi rend="italic">Kir-Moab</hi> of the Bible), Mojeb
                    (the ancient <hi rend="italic">Amon),</hi> and Zerka Main (J∕αon). A few miles
                    from the mouth of the latter are the warm springs of Callirrhoe, famous in
                    Jewish and Roman times. A copious stream of warm sulphureous water flows into
                    the lake between stupendous cliffs of sandstone. North of Zerka Main the cliffs
                    along the shore are sandstone, but higher up the limestone overlies the
                    sandstone, while dykes and seams of old trap-rock also occur.</p>
                <p>At the mouth of the ravine of Kerak, on the south-east of the sea, is the
                    peninsula of <hi rend="italic">Lisân,</hi> “The Tongue.” Its neck is a strip of
                    bare sand about 3 miles broad. In form the peninsula bears some resemblance to
                    the human foot, the toe projecting northward up the centre of the sea. Its
                    length is about 9 miles. It is a post-tertiary deposit of layers of marl,
                    gypsum, and sandy conglomerate; the surface is white and almost destitute of
                    vegetation.</p>
                <p>The Jordan enters the lake at the centre of its northern end, and has on each
                    bank a low alluvial plain, now a desert, and mostly coated with a white nitrous
                    crust. In fact the whole circuit of the lake is wild, dreary, and desolate.
                    Ridges of drift mark the water-line, which rises a few feet in spring, when the
                    Jordan, fed by the melting snows of Hermon, flows in full stream. The drift is
                    composed of broken canes and willow branches, with trunks of palms, poplars, and
                    other trees, half-imbedded in slimy mud, and covered with incrustations of salt.
                    Lying in a deep cavity, shut in by naked white hills, exposed during the long
                    summer to the burning rays of an unclouded sun, nothing could be expected on the
                    shores of the Dead Sea but sterility. Yet here and there on the low plains to
                    the north and south, and on the eastern and western sides, wherever a little
                    fountain springs up, or a mountain streamlet flows, there are thickets of
                    willow, tamarisk, and acacia, among which the birds ,’sing as sweetly as in more
                    genial climes. The Arab also pitches his tent beside them, and sometimes
                    cultivates a few patches of grain and tobacco. The heat causes such excessive
                    evaporation that though the Jordan and other smaller streams fall into the lake
                    the water seems to be gradually decreasing. The marshes along the shore,
                    especially to the north and south, emit pestilential exhalations during summer
                    and autumn which are fatal to strangers, and which make the inhabitants of
                    Jericho, and the few poor tribes who pitch their tents in the surrounding
                    territory, weak and sickly. They are degraded and immoral also, as were their
                    progenitors in the “cities of the plain.”</p>
                <p>The only ruin of note close to the Dead Sea is the fortress of Masada, on a cliff
                    on the western shore, opposite the peninsula of Lisân. It was the scene of the
                    final struggle between the Jews and the Romans after the destruction of
                    Jerusalem by Titus. At Engedi there are a few ruins; and also at Ain-el-Feshkhah
                    on the north-west, and on a little peninsula near the mouth of the Jordan. The
                    ruins of Sodom and Gomorrah have entirely disappeared. Their site is disputed,
                    for some hold that they stood near the northern end of the lake, while others
                    affirm that they must have been situated at the southern end.</p>
                <p>The bed of the Dead Sea is divided into two sections; the northern, extending
                    from the mouth of the Jordan to the peninsula of Lisân, is 33 miles long, and is
                    a regular basin shaped cavity, its sides descending steeply and uniformly to a
                    depth of 1308 feet. The southern section is shallow, the greatest depth of the
                    channel between the peninsula and the western shore being only 13 feet, while no
                    part of the lake south of the peninsula is more than 12 feet, and most of it
                    only 3 or 4 feet deep.</p>
                <p>The water is intensely salt and bitter, and its density is so great that the
                    human body will not sink in it. The following is an analysis of water lifted by
                    Captain Lynch from a depth of 1110 feet, the specific gravity of which was 1 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 227 :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Chloride of calcium</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3'107</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Chloride of magnesium ...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14-889</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Chloride of sodium</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7∙855</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Chloride of potassium</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0-658</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sulphate of lime</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0∙070</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Bromide of potassium</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0.137</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>26-416</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The presence of so much saline matter is accounted for by the washings of the
                    salt range of Sodom, the numerous brackish springs along the shore, and the
                    great evaporation. The reports of early travellers, however, regarding the Dead
                    Sea were to a great extent fabulous. They represented it as an infernal region,
                    its black and fetid waters always emitting a noisome vapour, which being driven
                    over the adjoining land destroyed all vegetation; they also stated that no birds
                    could fly over it. All this is untrue; the water is as transparent as that of
                    the Mediterranean, and a bath in it is both pleasant and refreshing.</p>
                <p>The historical notices of the Dead Sea extend back nearly 40Q0 years. When Lot
                    looked down from the heights of Bethel, he “beheld all the plain of the Jordan
                    that it was well watered, before the Lord destroyed Sodom, even·as the garden of
                    the Lord” (Gen. xiii. 10). The region is further described as a “deep valley”
                    <hi rend="italic">(ſEmek,</hi> Gen. xiv. 3, 8), distinguished by “fertile
                    fields” <hi rend="italic">{Siddim).</hi> The aspect now is entirely different.
                    There must have been a lake then as now; but it was smaller, and had a margin of
                    fertile plain, especially on the southern end, “as thou comest unto Zoar.” In
                    the narration of the capture of the cities of the plain by the Eastern kings, it
                    is said that they were situated in the “vale of Siddim,” which was full of
                    “bitumen (slime) pits.” When the cities were destroyed, “the Lord rained upon
                    Sodom and upon Gomorrah brimstone and fire from the Lord out of heaven;” and
                    Abraham from the mountain ridges “looked toward Sodom, and toward all the land
                    of the plain, and, lo, the smoke of the country went up as the smoke of a
                    furnace” (Gen. xix. 24, 28). The sacred writer further asserts regarding the
                    vale of Siddim that it became the Salt Sea, or was submerged; and consequently
                    it now forms part of the bed of the lake.</p>
                <p>These events entirely changed, as it would seem, both the political and physical
                    condition of the whole region. Upon the plains originally existing round the sea
                    Gentile and Jewish records combine in placing the earliest seat of Phoenician
                    civilization. “The Tyrians,” says Justin, “first dwelt by the Syrian lake before
                    they removed to Sidon.” Sodom and Gomorrah are mentioned as the first cities of
                    the Canaanites; and when Lot went down from Bethel “the cities of the plain”
                    formed a nucleus of civilized life before any city, except Hebron and perhaps
                    Jerusalem, had sprung up in central Palestine. The great catastrophe in the days
                    of Abraham changed the aspect of the country, and gave a death-blow to its
                    prosperity. With the exception of the village of Engedi, and the small town of
                    Jericho, the circuit of the Dead Sea appears to have remained ever afterwards
                    almost without settled inhabitants.</p>
                <p>Recent researches, especially those of Μ. Lartet, the Due de Luynes, and Canon
                    Tristram, have contributed greatly to our knowledge of the physical geography of
                    the Dead Sea basin. It is now shown from the geological <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n12/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0012-0003"/> structure of the watershed in the valley of the
                    Arabah to the south, and from the direction of the lateral ravines which fall
                    into the great Jordan valley, that the river Jordan could never have run into
                    the Red Sea. The <hi rend="italic">depression</hi> of the Dead Sea is 1308 feet,
                    while the <hi rend="italic">elevation</hi> of the watershed is 787 feet; and the
                    action which upheaved the watershed occurred at the same geological period which
                    gave to the whole of Palestine its present form. The formation of the Jordan
                    valley Μ. Lartet accounts for in this way. At some remote period a fracture took
                    place in the upper strata in this region, extending north and south. In
                    consequence of the unequal strength of the strata the western side of the
                    fracture sank, occasioning the abrupt dip observable in the strata on the
                    western side of the valley, and the great depression of the valley itself; while
                    the eastern side of the fracture remained <hi rend="italic">in situ,</hi>
                    showing at various places along the eastern shore of the Dead Sea a vertical
                    section through the limestone and sandstone. The basin of the Dead Sea has thus
                    been since its foundation a reservoir for the rainfall: while its saltness
                    originally proceeded from the saltspring and hills, and gradually increased by
                    evaporation.</p>
                <p>Deposits of great depth have accumulated in the whole valley since «its
                    formation, composed of beds of gypsum, marl, flint, and alluvium, similar to
                    those now in process of formation at the bottom of the Dead Sea. They show that
                    at one period the whole Jordan valley was under water; while the sides of the
                    valley indicate successive stages in the fall of the water from the time when
                    its surface was on the level of the ocean down to the present age. The
                    hill-sides and strips of plain on both the eastern and western banks of the Dead
                    Sea are marked by a series of terraces or shore-lines. The highest has an
                    elevation corresponding to the level of the Mediterranean. About 230 feet above
                    the present level of the lake there is another shore-line, marked by a strip of
                    alluvial marl adhering to the rocks and cliffs, particularly at the north-west
                    angle. The deposit is mixed with shells of existing species, layers of gypsum
                    and gravel. This line would correspond with the general level of the great
                    valley northward, through which the river Jordan has cut a deep channel. There
                    are, besides, in the ravines which descend to the lake, comparatively recent
                    deposits, reaching up their sides in places to a height of 400 feet, and then
                    sloping down in a series of terraces to the present level of the Jake, showing
                    the gradual depression of the water. Tristram also remarked on the western shore
                    “no less than eight low gravel terraces, the ledges of comparatively recent
                    beaches, distinctly marked. The highest of them was 44 feet above the present
                    sea-level.”</p>
                <p>Many traces of volcanic action, both remote and recent, have been observed in the
                    basin of the Dead Sea, such as trap dykes, and hot sulphur and brackish springs.
                    Tristram describes a valley at the northern end of the salt range of Sodom, in
                    which there are</p>
                <p>“large masses of bitumen mingled with gravel. These overlie a thick stratum of
                    sulphur, which again overlies a thicker stratum of sand so strongly impregnated
                    with sulphur that it yields powerful fumes on being sprinkled over a hot coal.
                    The bitumen, unlike that which we pick up on the shore, is strongly impregnated
                    with sulphur. Above all, it is calcined, and bears the marks of having been
                    subjected to extreme heat. So far as I can understand this deposit, if there be
                    any physical evidence left of the catastrophe which destroyed Sodom and.
                    Gomorrah, or. of similar occurrences, we have it here. The whole appearance
                    points to a shower of hot sulphur, and an irruption of bitumen upon it, which
                    would naturally be calcined and impregnated with its fumes; and this at a
                    geological period quite subsequent to all the diluvial and alluvial action of
                    which we have such abundant evidence. The catastrophe must have been since the
                    formation of the valley, and while the water was at its present
                    level,—therefore, probably during the historic period.” <hi rend="italic">{Land
                    of Israel,</hi> pp. 355, <hi rend="italic">sq.)</hi></p>
                <p>Tristram applies the above-observed facts to the solution of the great historical
                    question about the destruction of the cities of the plain in the following
                    manner :—</p>
                <p>“Setting aside all preconceived notions, and taking the simple record of Genesis
                    xix. as we find it, let us see whether the existing condition of the country
                    throws any light on the Biblical narrative. Certainly we do observe by the lake
                    sulphur and bitumen in abundance. Sulphur springs stud the shores, sulphur is
                    strewn, whether in layers or in fragments, over the desolate plains; and bitumen
                    is ejected in great floating masses from the bottom of the sea, oozes through
                    the fissures of the rocks, is deposited with gravel on the beach, or appears
                    with sulphur to have been precipitated during some convulsion. We know that at
                    the time of earthquakes bitumen seems to be detached from the bottom of the
                    lake. Everything leads to the conclusion that the agency of fire was at work.
                    The kindling of such a mass of combustible material, either by lightning from
                    heaven, or by other electrical agency, combined with an earthquake ejecting
                    other bitumen or sulphur from the lake, would soon spread devastation over the
                    plain, so that the smoke of the country would go up as the smoke of a furnace.”
                    <hi rend="italic">{Land of Israel,</hi> p. 359).</p>
                <p>Here we have to do only with physical facts and appearances. A mass of burning
                    sulphurous matter might be ejected from some open crater, as is often the case
                    with Vesuvius; and this, falling upon the cities and the bituminous plain around
                    them, would produce just such a form of conflagration as Abraham is stated to
                    have seen. The valley may then have sunk a few feet, and become submerged. This,
                    it is true, is mere theory; it is a theory, however, suggested, and to a large
                    extent confirmed, by the physical aspect of the country, and the careful
                    observations of travellers around the lake. The subject is not one for vague
                    speculation, and much less for dogmatic assertion. The problems which the Dead
                    Sea present must be-·solved, if they are ever to be solved, by scientific
                    research.</p>
                <p>It is not strange that the Dead Sea has never been navigated to any extent. It
                    seems probable from the statement of Josephus <hi rend="italic">{Ant.</hi> ix.
                    1, 2) that the Moabites crossed it to invade Judah; and he tells us the Romans
                    used boats, against the fugitive Jews (7?. <hi rend="italic">J.</hi> iv. 7, 6).
                    Costigan was the first in modern times to navigate it, going from the mouth of
                    the Jordan to the peninsula of Lisân in the boat by which he had came from
                    Tiberias. He afterwards died of fatigue and exhaustion. In 1837 Moore and Beck
                    conveyed a little boat from Joppa, and visited some points. Ten years later
                    Lieutenant Molyneux took a boat to the peninsula, and his life was also
                    sacrificed. The expedition of Lynch was far more successful, and he was the
                    first thoroughly to examine the shores, and to determine the depths by
                    soundings. Several of his party took the fever which is so fatal, and one died.
                    Winter is the proper season for such researches. Rain seldom falls; - and the
                    air during the depth of winter is fresh, and cold almost unknown.</p>
                <p>The following are the leading works which treat of the Dead Sea :—Robinson, <hi
                    rend="italic">Physical Geography of Palestine;</hi> De Saulcy, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Voyage</hi><hi rend="italic">autour de la Mer Morte</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> Lynch, <hi rend="italic">Official Report to United States
                    Government;</hi> Ritter, <hi rend="italic">Comparative Geography of
                    Palestine,</hi> vol. iii. appendix i. (J. L. P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
