<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0031-0022-05" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DEE, John (9th edition, volume 7, page 22)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xp4n">Polishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bt4s">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892p9k">Spiritism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1069177">Polishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130040">Spirit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n31/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DEE, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1527-1608), a
                    mathematician and astrologer, was born in July 1527, in London, where his father
                    was a wealthy vintner. In 1542 he was sent to St John’s College, Cambridge.
                    After five years’ close application to mathematical studies, particularly
                    astronomy, he went to Holland, in order to visit several eminent Continental
                    mathematicians. Having remained abroad nearly a year, he returned to Cambridge,
                    and was elected a fellow of Trinity College, then first erected by King Henry
                    VIII. In 1548 he took the degree of master of arts; but in the same year he
                    found it necessary to leave England on account of the suspicions entertained of
                    his being a conjuror, which were first excited by a piece of machinery, in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Irene</hi> of Aristophanes, he exhibited to the
                    university, representing the scarabaeus flying up to Jupiter, with a man and a
                    basket of victuals on its back. On leaving England he went first to the
                    university of Louvain, where he resided about two years, and then to the college
                    of Rheims, where he read lectures on Euclid’s <hi rend="italic">Elements</hi>
                    with great applause. On his return to England in 1551 King Edward assigned him a
                    pension of 100 crowns, which he afterwards exchanged for the rectory of
                    Upton-upon-Severn. Soon after the accession of Mary, he was accused of using
                    enchantments against the queen’s life; but after a tedious confinement, he
                    obtained his liberty in 1555, by an order of council.</p>
                <p>When Elizabeth ascended the throne, Dee was asked by Lord Dudley to name a
                    propitious day for the coronation. On this occasion he was introduced to the
                    queen, who took lessons in the mystical interpretation of his writings, and made
                    him great promises, which, however, were never fulfilled. In 1564 he again
                    visited the Continent, in order to present a book which he had dedicated to the
                    Emperor Maximilian. He returned to England in the same year; but in 1571 we find
                    him in Lorraine, whither two physicians were sent by the queen to his relief in
                    a dangerous illness. Having once more returned to his native country, he settled
                    at Mortlake, in Surrey, where he continued his studies with unremitting ardour,
                    and made a collection of curious books and manuscripts, and a variety of
                    instruments, most of which were destroyed by the mob during his absence, on
                    account of his supposed familiarity with the devil. In 1578 Dee was sent abroad
                    to consult with German physicians and astrologers in regard to the illness of
                    the queen. On his return to England, he was employed in investigating the title
                    of the Crown to the countries recently discovered by British subjects, and in
                    furnishing geographical descriptions. Two large rolls containing the desired
                    information, which he presented to the queen, are still preserved in the
                    Cottonian Library. A learned treatise on the reformation of the calendar,
                    written by him about the same time, is still preserved in the Ashmolean Library
                    at Oxford.</p>
                <p>From this period the philosophical researches of Dee were concerned entirely with
                    the pseudo-science of necromancy. In 1581 he became acquainted with Edward
                    Kelly, an apothecary who professed to have discovered the philosopher’s stone,
                    and by whose assistance he performed various incantations, and maintained a
                    frequent imaginary intercourse with spirits. Shortly after, Kelly and Dee were
                    introduced to a Polish nobleman, Albert Laski, palatine of Siradia (Sieradz),
                    devoted to the same pursuits, who persuaded the two friends to accompany him to
                    his native country. They embarked for Holland in September 1583, and arrived at
                    Laski’s place of residence in February following. They lived for some years in
                    Poland and Bohemia in alternate wealth and poverty, according to the credulity
                    or scepticism of those before whom they exhibited. They professed to raise
                    spirits by incantation. Kelly dictated their utterances to Dee, who wrote them
                    down and interpreted them,</p>
                <p>Dee, having at length quarrelled with his companion, quitted Bohemia and returned
                    to England, where he was made chancellor of St Paul’s Cathedral in 1594, and
                    warden of Manchester College in 1595. He afterwards returned to his house at
                    Mortlake, where he died in 1608, at the age of eighty-one.</p>
                <p>His principal works are— <hi rend="italic">Propaedeumata Aphoristica,</hi> Lond.
                    1558; <hi rend="italic">Monas Hieroglyphica,</hi> Antwerp, 1564; <hi
                        rend="italic">Epistola</hi><hi rend="italic">ad Fredericum Commandinum,</hi>
                    Pesaro, 1570; <hi rend="italic">Preface Mathematical to the English Euclid,</hi>
                    1570; <hi rend="italic">Divers Annotations and Inventions added after the tenth
                        book of English Euclid,</hi> 1570; <hi rend="italic">Epistola</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">preefixa</hi><hi rend="italic">Ephemeridibus</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Joannis Feldi, a</hi> 1557; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Parallaticae</hi><hi rend="italic">Commentationis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Praxeos∙</hi><pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n32/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0032-0023"/><hi rend="italic">que Nucleus</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">quidam,</hi> London, 1573. The catalogue of his printed and
                    published works is to be found in his <hi rend="italic">Compendious
                        Rehearsal,</hi> as well as in his letter to Archbishop Whitgift, to which
                    the reader is referred. A manuscript of Dee’s, relating what passed for many
                    years between him and some spirits, was edited by Meric Casaubon and published
                    in 1659. <hi rend="italic">The Private Diary of Dr John Dee, and the Catalogue
                        of his Library of Manuscripts,</hi> edited by J. 0. Halliwell, was published
                    by the Camden Society in 1842.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
