<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0107-0094-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DENNIS, John (9th edition, volume 7, page 94)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xf77">Criticism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:991153">Lampoon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883769">Critics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883735">Criticism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n107/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DENNIS, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1657-173t), a
                    critic and poet of some celebrity in his own day, was the son of a saddler in
                    London, where he was born in the year 1657. He received the first branches of
                    education at Harrow aud at Caius College, Cambridge, from which after four
                    years’ residence he removed to Trinity Hall. In 1683 he graduated M.A. When he
                    quitted the university he made the tour of Europe, in the course of which he
                    acquired a strong prejudice against foreign manners and customs, and became
                    confirmed, as was natural in one born and brought up a Whig, in his dislike of
                    foreign Governments. On his return to England he became acquainted with Dryden,
                    Wycherly, Congreve, and Southerne, whose conversation, inspiring him with a
                    passion for poetry, and a contempt for every attainment that had not in it
                    something of the <hi rend="italic">belles</hi><hi rend="italic">lettres,</hi>
                    diverted him from entering any profession. He lived for a time on a small
                    fortune he had inherited from an uncle, but this was soon squandered. Through
                    the patronage of the duke of Marlborough, to whom he had recommended himself by
                    his zeal for the Protestant succession, he obtained a place in the customs worth
                    £120 per annum. After some years, however, his extravagance reduced him to the
                    necessity of disposing of it; but, in selling it, he reserved to himself an
                    annuity for a term of years. Outliving this term, he was in the closing years of
                    his life reduced to extreme necessity.</p>
                <p>Dennis was the author of several small poems of little merit, and one or two
                    plays which possess none, though one at least of the latter was received with
                    considerable favour at the time of its production, on account of its hitting the
                    strongest popular prejudice then existing. His tragedy of <hi rend="italic">Love
                        Asserted,</hi> produced at Lincoln’s Inn Fields theatre in 1704, was
                    fiercely anti-French, and as such met with warm sympathy and approval. Dennis
                    conceived the insane idea that by writing it he had roused the implacable
                    resentment of the French Government, and amusing stories are told of the
                    precautions he thought it necessary to take in consequence. He is said to have
                    visited the duke of Marlborough, previous to the negotiations for the peace of
                    Utrecht, and asked him to secure the insertion of a special clause in the treaty
                    protecting his person* from vengeance. On another occasion the appearance of an
                    approaching vessel is said to have caused him to flee to London from a friend’s
                    house on the coast of Sussex. His tragedy of <hi rend="italic">Aprpius and
                        Virginia,</hi> produced at Drury Lane in 1709, was unsuccessful. It is
                    memorable only on account of a peculiar kind of thunder used in the performance,
                    which was both novel and effective. A few nights after the failure of his play
                    Dennis, sitting in the pit, heard the thunder introduced into the tragedy of
                    Macbeth, whereupon he rose and cried to the audience, “They won’t act my
                    tragedy, but they steal my thunder.”</p>
                <p>But for his inordinate vanity, and an infirmity of tempeι that fell little short
                    of insanity, Dennis might have made some mark in literature as a critic. His
                    reviews of Pope’s <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi> and Addison’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Cato</hi> showed considerable discernment and not a little
                    wit; but they were disfigured by bitter personal feeling. As his attacks were
                    almost always on persons of abilities greatly superior to his own, like Addison,
                    Steele, and Pope, their replies usually turned opinion strongly against him,
                    irritating his testy temper, and rendering him a perpetual torment to himself.
                    Pope pilloriedhim in the <hi rend="italic">Dunciad,</hi> and in the following
                    epigram—</p>
                <p>Should Dennis publish you had stabb’d your brother, Lampoon’d your monarch, or
                    debauch’d your mother,— Say, what revenge on Dennis can be had?</p>
                <p>Too dull for laughter, for reply too mad; On one so poor you cannot take the law;
                    On one so old your sword you scorn to draw. Uncag’d then let the harmless
                    monster rage, Secure in dulness, madness, want, and age.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n108/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0108-0095"/>
                <p>At length, after a long life of vicissitudes, he was compelled to receive
                    obligations from those whom he had been continually reviling. In the very close
                    of his days a play was acted for his benefit at the little theatre in the
                    Haymarket, through the united interests of Thomson, Mallet, and Pope. It is much
                    to the credit of Pope especially that, notwithstanding the gross manner in which
                    Dennis had calumniated him on many occasions, he took part in the arrangements,
                    and even wrote an occasional prologue to the play, which was spoken by Cibber.
                    Not long after this Dennis died, on the 6th of January 1734.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
