<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0376-0359-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DONATISTS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 359</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mv15">Sects</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc3p">Appeal</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z186">Gallicisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:896825">Donatists</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:843825">Caecilians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:937258">Gallicisms</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1110714">Sects</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1106691">Schism</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n376/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DONATISTS</label>, a powerful sect which formed itself in the
                    Christian church of northern Africa in the beginning of the 4th century.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>There were two Donatuses
                    connected with the Donatist sect, Donatus of Casae Nigrae, and Donatus surnamed
                    Magnus, who succeeded Majorinus as the Donatist bishop of Carthage. The name of
                    the sect was probably derived from the latter, who was the more influential of
                    the two. It is to be observed that the Donatists themselves repudiated that
                    designation, which was applied to them by their opponents as a reproach. They
                    called themselves “Pars Majorini’ or “Pars Donati.”</p></note> In its doctrine
                    it sprang from the same roots, and in its history it had in many things the same
                    character, as the earlier Novatians. The predisposing causes of the Donatist
                    schism were the belief, early introduced into the African church, that the
                    validity of all sacerdotal acts depended upon the personal character of the
                    agent, and the question, arising out of that belief, as to the eligibility for
                    sacerdotal office of the <hi rend="italic">traditores,</hi> or those who had
                    delivered up their copies of the Scriptures under the compulsion of the
                    Diocletian persecution; the exciting cause was the election of a successor to
                    Mensurius, bishop of Carthage, who died in 311. Mensurius had held moderate
                    views as to the <hi rend="italic">quaestio</hi><hi rend="italic">υexata</hi> of
                    the treatment of the <hi rend="italic">traditores,</hi> and accordingly a strong
                    fanatical party had formed itself in Carthage in opposition to him, headed by a
                    wealthy and therefore influential widow named Lucilla, and countenanced by
                    Secundus of Tigisis, primate of Numidia. There were thus two parties each
                    anxious to secure the succession to the vacant see. The friends of the late
                    bishop fixed their choice on Caecilian, the archdeacon, and secured his election
                    and his consecration by Felix, the bishop of Aptungis, before the other party
                    were ready for action. It had been customary, though probably it was not
                    essential, that the Numidian bishops should be present at the election and
                    consecration of the bishop of Carthage; Caecilian’s party had not waited for
                    them, knowing them to be in sympathy with their opponents. Soon after
                    Caecilian’s consecration, however, Secundus and seventy of the Numidian bishops
                    arrived at Carthage, and steps were at once taken to displace the new bishop. A
                    synod was formed before which Caecilian was summoned; his consecration was
                    declared invalid, on the ground that Felix had been a traditor; and finally,
                    having refused to obey the summons to appear, he was excommunicated, and
                    Majorinus, a dependent of Lucilla’s, consecrated in his stead. Thus the schism
                    became overt, and in a very short time there were rival bishops and rival
                    churches in most of the cities of North Africa, as well as in Carthage.</p>
                <p>The inevitable appeal to the civil power to settle the dispute was first made by
                    the Donatists, who were incited to do so by receiving proof, in their exclusion
                    from certain privileges conferred on the African church, that the sympathies of
                    Constantine were with the other party.</p>
                <p>They accordingly petitioned the emperor to appoint a commission to try the case,
                    indicating a preference for Gallic bishops, among whom there were no traditors,
                    the Diocletian persecution not having extended to Gaul. The result was that a
                    commission was issued to five Gallic bishops, under the presidency of Miltiades,
                    bishop of Rome. The number of referees was afterwards increased to twenty, and
                    the case was tried at Rome in 313. Ten bishops appeared on each side, the
                    leading representative of the Donatists being Donatus of Casae Nigrae. The
                    decision was entirely in favour of Caecilian, and Donatus was found guilty of
                    various ecclesiastical offences. An appeal was taken and allowed; but the
                    decision of the synod of Arles (314) not only confirmed the position of
                    Caecilian, but greatly strengthened it by passing a canon that ordination was
                    not invalid because performed by a traditor, if otherwise regular. Felix had
                    previously been declared innocent after an examination of records and witnesses
                    at Carthage. A further appeal to the emperor in person was heard at Milan in
                    316, when all points were finally decided in favour of Caecilian. As a necessary
                    consequence of this the power of the state was directed to the suppression of
                    the defeated party. Persistent Donatists were no longer merely heretics; they
                    were rebels, and incurred the confiscation of their church property and the
                    forfeiture of their civil rights.</p>
                <p>The attempt to destroy by force a fanatical sect had its usual result in only
                    intensifying its fanaticism and consolidating its sectarianism. Majorinus, the
                    Donatist bishop of Carthage, dying in 315, was succeeded by Donatus, surnamed
                    Magnus, a man of great force of character, under whose influence the schism
                    gained fresh strength from the opposition it encountered. Force was met with
                    force; the Circumcelliones, bands of fugitive slaves and vagrant <hi
                    rend="italic">(circum cellas)</hi> peasants, were enlisted as the champions of
                    Donatism, and their violence reached such a height as to threaten civil war. In
                    321 Constantine, seeing probably that he had been wrong in abandoning his usual
                    policy of toleration in this case, sought to retrace his steps by granting the
                    Donatists liberty to act according to their consciences, and declaring that the
                    points in dispute between them and the orthodox should be left to the judgment
                    of God. This wise policy, to which he consistently adhered to the close of his
                    reign, was not followed by his son and successor in the Western Empire,
                    Constans, who, after repeated attempts to win over the sect by bribes, resorted
                    to persecution. The renewed excesses of the Circumcelliones, among whom were
                    ranged fugitive slaves, debtors, and political malcontents of all kinds, had
                    given to the Donatist schism a socialist aspect; and its forcible suppression
                    may therefore have seemed to Constans even more necessary for the preservation
                    of the empire than for the vindication of orthodoxy. The power which they had
                    been the first to invoke having thus declared so emphatically and persistently
                    against them, the Donatists were led to adopt the theory known in more recent
                    times as that of spiritual independence, which Donatus Magnus formulated in the
                    question, “What has the emperor to do with the church!” <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Quid</hi><hi rend="italic">est imperatori</hi><hi rend="italic">cum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ecclesia?)</hi> Such a theory naturally aggravated the lawlessness
                    of the Circum-cellion adherents of the sect, and their outrages were in turn
                    made the justification for the most rigorous measures against the whole Donatist
                    party indiscriminately. Many of their bishops fell victims to the persecution,
                    and. Donatus and several others were banished from their sees.</p>
                <p>With the accession of Julian (361) an entire change took place in the treatment
                    of the Donatists. Their churches were restored and their bishops reinstated,
                    with the natural result of greatly increasing both the numbers and the
                    fanaticism of the sect. A return to the earlier policy of repression was made
                    under Valentinian I. and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n377/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0377-0360"/> Gratiau, by whom the Donatist churches were again
                    closed, and all assemblies of adherents of the sect forbidden. It was not,
                    however, until the commencement of the 5th century that the sect began to
                    decline, owing partly to the occurrence of a division within it, but still more
                    to the arguments used against it by the greatest theologian of the early church.
                    The division arose out of a quarrel between Maximian, a deacon in Carthage, and
                    Primian, the successor, of Parmenian in the (Donatist) bishopric. Maximian,
                    being excommunicated, formed a party which, as Neander puts it, “stood in
                    precisely the same relation to the body of the Donatists as the Donatists
                    themselves did to the Catholic church.” The dispute was a source of weakness in
                    itself, and still more by the unanswerable arguments it furnished to the
                    Catholic party, who during the reign of the emperor Honorius made repeated and
                    determined efforts to secure the extinction of the schism. In 405 an imperial
                    edict was issued commanding the Donatists, under the severest penalties, to
                    return to the Catholic church. Meanwhile the more appropriate weapon of argument
                    was being effectively wielded by the Catholic party, under the leadership of one
                    of the ablest controversialists the Christian church has ever known. Augustine,
                    bishop of Hippo, after several years’ negotiation, found it possible to arrange
                    a great conference between the Donatists and the orthodox, which took place
                    under the orders of the emperor at Carthage in 411. There were present two
                    hundred and eighty-six Catholic and two hundred and seventy-nine Donatist
                    bishops. Before entering on the proceedings the Catholics pledged themselves, if
                    defeated, to give up their sees, while in the other event they promised to
                    recognize the Donatists as bishops on their simply declaring their adherence to
                    the Catholic church. The latter proposal, though it was received with scorn at
                    the time, had perhaps ultimately as much influence as the resistless logic of
                    Augustine in breaking the strength of the schism. The discussion, which lasted
                    for three days, Augustine and Aurelius being the chief speakers on the one side,
                    and Primian and Petiliau on the other, turned exclusively upon the two questions
                    that had given rise to the schism,—first, the question of fact, whether Felix
                    had been a traditor, and secondly, the question of doctrine, whether a church by
                    tolerance of unworthy members within its pale lost the essential attributes of
                    purity and catholicity. On the second point, to which alone abiding interest
                    attaches itself, the Catholic view was stated and defended by Augustine with a
                    force of argument, an aptness of quotation from Scripture (often, however,
                    founded on misinterpretation), and a beauty of language that all but compel
                    assent. Nowhere else in polemical theology are there to be found more valuable
                    statements as to the connection between the divine and the human elements in the
                    communication of grace, and as to the relative importance of the two attributes
                    of catholicity and purity respectively as tests of the true church. It is to be
                    observed, however, that on the side of Augustine as well as on that of his
                    opponents there is the inevitable confusion of thought that arises from failure
                    to apprehend the distinction between the visible and the invisible church.</p>
                <p>The decision of Marcellinus, the imperial commissioner, was in favour of 'the
                    Catholic party on both questions, and it was at once confirmed on an appeal to
                    the emperor. As in the case of the similar decision almost exactly a century
                    earlier, there followed the severest penal measures against the schismatics, the
                    clergy being banished and the laity subjected to heavy fines. The extinction of
                    the schism, which all the arguments of Augustine had failed to effect, was still
                    less to be brought about by persecution. The Donatists continued to maintain an
                    independent existence until the 7th century, when they disappear from history,
                    along with the whole Christian church of North Africa, before the invading
                    Saracens.</p>
                <p>Sources.—1. Contemporary. - <hi rend="italic">-Optatus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >MilevitanUs</hi><hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Schismate</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Donatistarum Lib. VII.,</hi> (Dupuis’s ed., Paris, 1700), and
                    several of the works of Augustine. 2. Modem.—Walsh’s <hi rend="italic">Entwurf
                    einer vollständigen Historie der Ketzereien,</hi> Neander’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kirchcngeschichte,</hi> Hagenbach’s <hi rend="italic">Kirchengeschichte,</hi>
                    Herzog’s <hi rend="italic">Encyclopädie,</hi> art. “Don-atisten,” Robertson’s
                    <hi rend="italic">History of the Christian Church.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
