<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0395-0376-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DOUGLAS, Gawain (9th edition, volume 7, page
                    376)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833880">Blacks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833576">Black</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204270">Maine</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37m39g">Sage</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p0j">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w66">Cat</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n395/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DOUGLAS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Gawain</hi></label> or <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Gavin (c.</hi> 1474-1522), bishop of Dunkeld, and the
                    ancient classical poet of Scotland, was the third son of Archibald, earl of
                    Angus, known in Scottish history as “Bell-the-Cat.” His mother was Elizabeth,
                    daughter of Robert Lord Boyd, high chamberlain of Scotland. The year when he was
                    born has not been recorded, but it is almost certain that it was 1474, or the
                    beginning of 1475; and of his father’s seats the one most likely to have been
                    his birthplace was Douglas Castle, Lanarkshire.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Brechin has been stated as the
                            birth-place of Douglas by Mr D. Black in his history of that town (2d
                            ed. p. 287), but no authority for this is quoted.</p></note> Being
                    intended for the church, Douglas studied at the university of St Andrews, where
                    his name appears in the lists of alumni between 1489 and 1494. Having entered
                    into holy orders, he was shortly afterwards appointed rector of Hauch, or
                    Prestonkirk, and parson of Linton in East Lothian.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The authority for the former designation
                            is Myln’s MS. <hi rend="italic">Vita Episcop. Dunkeld.</hi>, by
                            misreading which Douglas is by Bishop Sage called rector of Herriot, and
                            by Dr Irving and others, rector of Hawick. His latter designation is
                            found in the MS. of his <hi rend="italic">Translation of Virgil</hi>
                            preserved in Trinity College, Cambridge.— <hi rend="italic">IVorks,</hi>
                            i. p. 173.</p></note> In 1501 he was elected dean or provost of the
                    collegiate church of St Giles’s, Edinburgh, an office of dignity and
                    emolument.</p>
                <p>In the battle of Flodden (1513), when James IV. and many of the Scottish nobility
                    and ecclesiastics were killed, the earl of Angus lost his two eldest sons, which
                    so affected him that he retired to St Mains, a religious house in Galloway,
                    where he soon after died. He was succeeded by his grandson, Archibald, a
                    handsome young nobleman, who attracted the attention of the widowed Queen
                    Margaret, sister of Henry VIII. of England, and they were married within eleven
                    months after the death of the king. While this precipitate connection incensed
                    the nobility and caused much jealousy of the Douglas family, it seemed to open
                    up a way for the preferment of Gavin Douglas. By the influence of the queen,
                    Douglas was “postulated” by the Pope to the abbacy of Aberbrothock, or Arbroath.
                    He met with such opposition, however, from a rival claimant, that his
                    appointment was never completed, and he was unable to obtain his abbacy. Douglas
                    was next recommended by the queen to the Pope for the archbishopric of St
                    Andrews, then vacant; and, relying upon the validity of this appointment, he
                    attempted by force to obtain possession of the castle of St Andrews. He was,
                    however, unsuccessful, and ultimately w as passed over in favour of Andrew
                    Forman. At length, by the united influence of the queen and the Pope, he was
                    nominated for the bishopric of Dunkeld, which shortly afterwards became vacant.
                    The people were so indignant at the marriage of the queen with Angus that the
                    Parliament deprived her of the regency of the kingdom and the charge of the
                    young King James V., and appointed the duke of Albany to be regent in her rooìn.
                    One of the first acts of the duke, who came from France to assume the reins of
                    government, was to bring Douglas to trial for intriguing for ecclesiastical
                    benefices with the queen and the pope without the sanction<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n396/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0396-0377"/> of Parliament. He was found guilty, and put
                    in prison in what he calls the “wyndy and richt vnplesant castell and royk of
                    Edinburgh,” where he continued for about a year. This harsh step of the duke of
                    Albany seems to have brought about a feeling of sympathy for Douglas. He was at
                    length set at liberty, and, to make some amends, the duke permitted him to be
                    consecrated bishop of Dunkeld.</p>
                <p>The marriage of the queen with the earl of Angus proved an unhappy one; and, in
                    consequence of his ill-treatment of her, the queen separated from her husband
                    and joined with the regent against the Douglases. Angus fled to the borders for
                    a time; and in 1521 his uncle Gavin was deprived of his bishopric. The bishop
                    then took shelter at the court of Henry VIII., but in 1522 he died of the plague
                    at London, in the forty-eighth year of his age. His remains were interred in the
                    Hospital Church of the Savoy.</p>
                <p>The works of Bishop Douglas, though not numerous, are important. They consist
                    of—(1) <hi rend="italic">The Police of Honour,</hi> a poem written in 1501,—an
                    allegorical description of many gorgeous cavalcades of famous persons trooping
                    to a magnificent palace somewhat like Chaucer’s Temple of Fame, in the execution
                    of which Douglas has displayed much originality of treatment; (2) Another
                    allegorical poem called <hi rend="italic">King Hart,</hi> or the heart of man,
                    descriptive of the progress of life from youth to age; (3) A short poem called
                        <hi rend="italic">Conscience;</hi> and (4) A <hi rend="italic">Translation
                        of the Aeneid of Virgü,</hi> with the supplemental book of Maphaeus Vegius.
                    To each book a short prologue is prefixed, of which the one before the 12
                    th,</p>
                <p>“Where splendid Douglas paints the blooming May,” is perhaps the finest effort of
                    his muse.</p>
                <p>This <hi rend="italic">Translation of Virgil,</hi> by which Douglas is best
                    known, is a work of which Scotland will always be proud, as it was the first
                    metrical translation of a classical author made in Britain, and the precursor of
                    many others. Although it is very diffuse, from the difficulty its author had in
                    adapting the Doric language of his country to the purposes of translation, by
                    the same reason it is a work of considerable philological value in tracing the
                    history of the literary language of Scotland. Although Douglas was the first
                    native writer who applied the name “Scottis” to the language he employed, he has
                    Scotticized many Latin words, and imported many expressions from the French;
                    while his admiration of Chaucer has induced him to avail himself of some of the
                    grammatical forms used by that poet. Still, his translation, written in the
                    broad and widely spread dialect common at an early period to the north of
                    England and Scotland, will always form one of the most important landmarks in
                    Scottish philology. In concluding it Douglas unfortunately took farewell of
                    poetical composition, and entered the arena of political strife, as the
                    following extract shows :—</p>
                <p>“Thus yp my pen and instrumentis full yore On Virgillis post I fix for
                    evirmore.</p>
                <p>Neuir from tnens syk matteris to discryue, My muse sail now be clene
                    contemplatiue And r&gt;olitar as doith the byrd in cage.</p>
                <p>Sen fer by worn is all my chyldis age, And of my dayis nere passit the half date
                    That nature suld me grantyn, wele I wate; Thus, sen I feill doun sweyand the
                    ballance, Here I resigne vp younkeris obseruance, And wyil direk my labouris
                    euermoir</p>
                <p>Vnto the commoun welth and Goddis gloir.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>Works, vol. iv. ρ. 233. The last two lines occur in the
                            Bl. L. cd. of 1553.</p></note></p>
                <p>Several early MSS. of Douglas’s <hi rend="italic">Translation of Virgil</hi>
                    exist. One is preserved in the library of Trinity College, Cambridge, copied by
                    his amanuensis, Matthew Geddes, from the bishop’s own papers. Two are in the
                    library of the university of Edinburgh, and one in that of the marquis of Bath
                    at Longleat. Of the printed editions one was issued by William Copland at London
                    in 1553, one was printed by Ruddiman at Edinburgh in 1711, and one was presented
                    to the members of the Bannatyne Club in 1839. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Palice</hi><hi rend="italic">of Honour</hi> was first printed at London by
                    William Copland, without date, but probably in 1553; and an edition, printed by
                    “Johne Ros for Henrie Charteris,” appeared at Edinburgh in 1579, of which only
                    two copies are known to exist. This rare edition was reprinted for the Bannatyne
                    Club. The poems called <hi rend="italic">King Hart</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Conscience</hi> exist in the Maitland MS. in the Pepysian Library,
                    Cambridge. The works of the bishop were first collected and published at
                    Edinburgh in 1874, under the editorship of Mr John Small, with a life prefixed,
                    and a glossary appended. (J. SM.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
