<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0161-0144-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DE WETTE, Wilhelm Martin Leberecht</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 144</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:851811">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:949578">Gymnasiums</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:955402">Herders</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1104803">Sand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p527">Basel</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n161/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DE WETTE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilhelm Martin
                    Leberecht</hi></label> (1780- 1849), a distinguished German theologian, was born
                    on the 12th January 1780, at Ulla, near Weimar, where his father was clergyman.
                    After receiving his preliminary education at a local school he was sent to the
                    gymnasium at Weimar, a town which was then at the height of its literary glory.
                    Here, as he himself testified in glowing terms many years later, he was much
                    influenced by intercourse with Herder, who as “ephorus” frequently visited the
                    gymnasium and examined the pupils. In 1799 he entered on his theological studies
                    at the university of Jena, his principal teachers being Griesbach and Paulus,
                    from the latter of whom more than any other he derived the tendency to free
                    critical inquiry which characterized him as an expositor. Herder and Paulus were
                    thus in some sense his spiritual fathers, but the relationship was entirely one
                    of spirit and aim; in method and results he occupied an independent and almost
                    solitary position among German theologians. Having taken his doctor’s degree, De
                    Wette at once commenced, according to German custom, the career of a
                    “privat-docent” at Jena, which, however, he was not permitted to continue long.
                    In 1807 he became professor of theology at Heidelberg, and in 1810 he was
                    transferred to a similar chair in the newly-founded university of Berlin, from
                    which he was dismissed in 1819 on account of his having written a letter of
                    consolation to the mother of Sand, the murderer of Kotzebue. The letter was
                    defensible, though it drew a distinction between the morality of the deed and of
                    the doer which many were not prepared to admit, and a petition in its author’s
                    favour was presented by the senate of the university. The king, however, proved
                    inexorable, and a decree was issued not only depriving De Wette of the chair,
                    but banishing him from the Prussian kingdom. He retired for a time to Weimar,
                    where he occupied his enforced leisure in the preparation of his edition of
                    Luther, and in writing the romance <hi rend="italic">Theodor</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">oder</hi><hi rend="italic">die</hi><hi rend="italic">Weihe des
                    Zweiflers</hi> (Berlin, 1822), in which he∙describes the education of an
                    evangelical pastor. During this period he made his first essay in preaching, and
                    proved himself to be possessed of very popular gifts. An invitation to a
                    pastoral charge in Brunswick was under his consideration, when the offer in 1822
                    of the chair of theology in the university of Basel, which had been reorganized
                    four years before, opened up to him a still more congenial sphere. Though his
                    appointment had been strongly opposed by the orthodox party, De Wette soon won
                    for himself a position of great influence both in the university and in the
                    community of Basel. He was early admitted a citizen, and received many proofs of
                    the esteem of his fellow-townsmen; and the university owed much of its recovered
                    strength, particularly in the theological faculty, to his individual efforts. He
                    died on the 16th June 1849, being rector of the university at the time.</p>
                <p>De Wette’s chief work as a theologian was ’ in the department of biblical
                    criticism and exegesis, though he made valuable contributions to other branches
                    of theology. In fact his range was unusually extensive, and he did much by
                    precept as well as by example to widen the limits of theological culture. He had
                    considerable poetic faculty, and wrote a drama in three acts, entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Entsagung</hi> (Berlin, 1823). He had an
                    intelligent interest in art, and devoted much attention to ecclesiastical music
                    and architecture. As a biblical critic he is sometimes classed with the
                    destructive school, but his position was unique, and cannot be accurately
                    defined by merely referring him to a leader or a school. In the work of
                    interpretation he strove to keep himself entirely free from dogmatic
                    prepossessions, and he was fearless in recognizing and grappling with
                    difficulties; but he was prevented by his deeper spirituality from identifying
                    himself with the hard and uncompromising rationalism of Paulus, and on the other
                    hand his unfettered critical method separated him distinctly from the
                    supernaturalist or strictly orthodox school of interpreters. Thus it has
                    happened that each school has classed him with the followers of the other, as he
                    himself predicted would be the case in the preface to his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Christliche Sittenlehre.</hi> His works are generally admitted to be marked by
                    great exegetical skill, unusual power of condensation, and. uniform fairness.
                    Accordingly they possess an element of permanent value which is little affected
                    by the progress of criticism. The following is a list of the most important of
                    them :—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Beiträge zur Einleitung</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">das Alte Testament</hi> (2 vols. 1806-7); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Commentar</hi><hi rend="italic">über die Psalmen</hi> (1811), which has passed
                    through several editions, and is still regarded as of high authority; <hi
                    rend="italic">Lehrbuch der Hebräisch-jüdischen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Archaeologie</hi> (1814); <hi rend="italic">Ueber Religion</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">und Theologie</hi> (1815), a work of great importance as showing
                    its author’s general theological position; <hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der
                    Christlichen Dogmatik</hi> (1813-16); <hi rend="italic">Christliche
                    Sittenlehre</hi> (1819-21); <hi rend="italic">Einleitung in das Neue
                    Testament</hi> (1836); <hi rend="italic">Religion, ihr Wesen, ihre
                    Erscheinungsform, und ihre Einfluss auf das Leben</hi> (1827); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Das Wesen des Christlichen Glaubens</hi> (1846); and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kurzgefasstes exegetisches Handbuch zum Neuen Testament</hi> (1848). De Wette
                    also edited Luther’s works.</p>
                <p>See Hagenhach in Herzog’s <hi rend="italic">Real-Encyclopaedie,</hi> Liicke’s <hi
                    rend="italic">W. Μ. L. De Wette,</hi><hi rend="italic">zur freundschaftlicher
                    Erinnerung</hi> (1850), and Schenkel’s <hi rend="italic">W. Μ. L. De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Wette und die Bedeutung seiner Theologie für unsere Zeit</hi>
                    (1849).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
