<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0560-0541-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DUNEDIN (9th edition, volume 7, page 541)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179993">Wool</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9v878">Wool</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240888">Australasia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208479">Fiji</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n560/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DUNEDIN</label>, a city in New Zealand, in 45° 52' 12" S.
                    lat. and 170° 32' 37" E. long., at the head of Otago harbour, an arm of the sea
                    on the east coast of the South Island. It is the capital of the late province
                    and present provincial district of Otago, and was founded as the chief town of
                    the Otago settlement by settlers sent out under the auspices of the Lay
                    Association of the Free Church of Scotland in 1848. The discovery of large
                    quantities of gold in Otago in 1861 and the following years, and the great
                    increase in the production of wool, have made Dunedin a very flourishing place.
                    The city is beautifully situated in an amphitheatre of hills. The streets,
                    nearly all paved and kerbed, have been made at considerable expense and
                    trouble,—some being carried through swamps and others through cuttings and along
                    embankments. The cost of permanent improvements during the last fifteen years
                    has been about £300,000. The town is supplied with pure water, and (since 1862)
                    with gas from works belonging to the corporation. Dunedin is the seat of a judge
                    of the supreme court, and of a resident minister, who is a member of the
                    Colonial Executive; and it also has a Waste Lands Board, a body constituted for
                    the purpose of administering the public estate of the provincial district. The
                    city contains some fine buildings, especially two handsome Presbyterian
                    churches, constructed of white stone from Oamaru. The so-called university of
                    Otago, now affiliated with the university of New Zealand, which alone has the
                    power to grant degrees, possesses chairs of classics, mathematics, mental and
                    moral philosophy, as well as lectureships on botany, mineralogy, law, and modern
                    languages. A museum (well built of concrete) contains an excellent collection of
                    New Zealand flora and fauna, including some fine skeletons of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Dinornis.</hi> There is also a scientific body called the
                    Otago Institute, affiliated with the New Zealand Institute. There are three good
                    libraries—one at the supreme court, a second at the university, and a larger one
                    at the Athenaeum—six banks, and several large mercantile houses. The people are
                    mostly of Scotch origin, with a considerable intermixture of immigrants from
                    England, Ireland, the British colonies, and Germany. All classes are prosperous:
                    except among the extremely limited criminal class, poverty rarely occurs, and
                    absolute pauperism is quite unknown.</p>
                <p>Otago harbour, by which the city is approached from the sea, is an inlet about 18
                    miles long. There is about 22 feet of water on the bar at low tide. Half way up
                    to Dunedin is Port Chalmers, a fine anchorage for the largest vessels, where,
                    owing to the presence of precipitous hills, the land was found too limited in
                    area for a large city. From this point the water grows shallower as it
                    approaches Dunedin. Until lately no vessels drawing more than 10 feet could pass
                    up; but by two years dredging the channel has been made available for steamers
                    drawing 13 or 14 feet, and this depth is gradually being increased. The Harbour
                    Board has authority to raise £250,000 by bonds, of which £129,400 has been
                    raised, but £66,000 is still unexpended. The revenue of the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n561/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0561-0542"/> board is £14,500, which is rapidly
                    increasing, as it arises from a munificent landed endowment. A large part of
                    this money is available for works. The harbour was until lately the terminus of
                    a line of large mail steamers running monthly to San Francisco <hi rend="italic"
                        >via</hi> Auckland and Honolulu, but it is now found more convenient to use
                    smaller steamers for the coastal section. It is, however, still the terminus of
                    a line of fine vessels running at intervals of about ten days to Melbourne, and
                    carrying the monthly mail for Suez and England. There is also direct steam
                    communication with Sydney and Hobart Town, and communication <hi rend="italic"
                        >via</hi> Auckland with Fiji. All the coasting steamers and many sailing
                    vessels are owned in Dunedin. In 187S, besides the San Francisco boats, 69
                    vessels, varying from 250 to 1800 tons, entered the port from places beyond the
                    seas other than Australasia. The greater number of these arrive in the early
                    part of the summer, and load with wool for London. The customs revenue collected
                    in 1876 amounted to £362,335. The municipal debt amounts to £328,000, and the
                    revenue (raised by rates, rents, water and gas works, &lt;fcc.) to £47,500. The
                    population of the city in the beginning of 1877 was about 22,500, and that of
                    the suburbs about 9000, while other towns within a circuit of a few miles bring
                    it up to 35,000.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
