<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0210-0193-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DIDEROT, Denis</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 193</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20f33">Blind</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jm23g7d">Blindness</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41n7xn4q">Blinds</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:834457">Blinds</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:834438">Blindness</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n210/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DIDEROT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Denis</hi></label> (1713-1784),
                    one of the most active and original of the famous group of men of letters in
                    France in the middle of the 18th century. He was born at Langres in 1713; he was
                    educated by the Jesuits, like most of those who afterwards became the bitterest
                    enemies of Catholicism; and, when his education was at an en 1, he vexed his
                    brave and worthy father’s heart by turning away from respectable callings, like
                    law or medicine, and throwing himself into the vagabond life of a bookseller’s
                    hack in Paris. An imprudent marriage (1743) did not better his position. His
                    wife was a devout Catholic, but her piety did not restrain a narrow and fretful
                    temper, and Diderot’s domestic life was irregular and unhappy. He sought
                    consolation for chagrins at home in attachments abroad, first with a Madame
                    Puisieux, a fifth-rate female scribbler, and then with Mdlle. Voland, to whom he
                    was constant for the rest of her life. His letters to her are among the most
                    graphic of all the pictures that we have of the daily life of the philosophic
                    circle in Paris. An interesting contrast may be made between the Bohemianism of
                    the famous literary set who supped at the Turk’s Head with the Tory Johnson and
                    the Conservative Burke for their oracles, and the Bohemianism o the set who
                    about the same time dined once a week at the Baron D’Holbach’s, to listen to the
                    wild sallies and the inspiring declamations of Diderot. For Diderot was not a
                    great writer; he stands out as a fertile, suggestive, and daring thinker, and a
                    prodigious and most eloquent talker.</p>
                <p>Diderot’s earliest writings were of as little importance as Goldsmith’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Enquiry into the State of Polite Learning</hi> or Burke’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Abridgement of English History.</hi> He earned 100 crowns by
                    translating Stanyan’s <hi rend="italic">History of Greece;</hi> with two
                    colleagues he produced a translatio» of James’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of
                    Medicine;</hi> and about thesame date(1745) he published a free rendering of
                    Shaftesbury’s <hi rend="italic">Inquiry Concerning Virtue and Merit,</hi> with
                    some original notes of his own. With strange and characteristic versatility, he
                    turned from ethical speculation to the composition of a volume of stories, which
                    are gross without liveliness, and impure without wit. In later years he repented
                    of this shameless work, just as Boccaccio is said in the day of his gray hairs
                    to have thought of the sprightliness of the <hi rend="italic">Decameron</hi>
                    with strong remorse. From tales Diderot went back to the more congenial region
                    of philosophy. Between the morning of Good Friday and the evening of Easter
                    Monday he wrote the <hi rend="italic">Philosophic Thoughts</hi> (1746), and he
                    presently added to this a short complementary essay <hi rend="italic">On the
                    Sufficiency of Natural</hi><hi rend="italic">Religiσn.</hi> The gist of these
                    performances is to press the ordinary rationalistic objections to a supernatural
                    revelation; but though Diderot did not at this time pass out into the wilderness
                    beyond natural religion, yet there are signs that he accepted that less as a
                    positive doctrine, resting on grounds of its own, than as a convenient point of
                    attack against Christianity. In 1747 he wrote the <hi rend="italic">Sceptic's
                    Walk,</hi> a rather poor allegory—pointing first to the extravagances of
                    Catholicism; second, to the vanity of the pleasures of that world which is the
                    rival of the church; and third, to the desperate and unfathomable uncertainty of
                    the philosophy which professes to be so high above both church and world.</p>
                <p>Diderot’s next piece was what first introduced him to the world as an original
                    thinker, his famous <hi rend="italic">Letter on the Blind</hi> (1749). The
                    immediate object of this short but pithy writing was to show the dependence of
                    men’s ideas on their five senses. It considers the case of the intellect
                    deprived of the aid of one of the senses; and in a second piece, published
                    afterwards, Diderot considered the case of a similar deprivation in the deaf and
                    dumb. The <hi rend="italic">Letter on Deaf-Mutes,</hi> however, is substantially
                    a digressive examination of some points in aesthetics. The ρhiloso-phie<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n211/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0211-0194"/> significance of the two essays is in the advance
                    they make towards the principle of Relativity. But what interested the militant
                    philosophers of that day was an episodic application of the principle of
                    relativity to the master-conception of God. What makes the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Letter on the Blind</hi> interesting at the present moment is its presentation,
                    in a distinct though undigested form, of the modern theory of variability, and
                    of survival by superior adaptation. It is worth noticing, too, as an
                    illustration of the comprehensive freedom with which Diderot felt his way round
                    any subject that he approached, that in this theoretic essay he suggests the
                    possibility of teaching the blind to read through the sense of touch. If the <hi
                    rend="italic">Letter on the Blind</hi> introduced Diderot into the worshipful
                    company of the philosophers, it also introduced him to the penalties of
                    philosophy. His speculation was too hardy for the authorities, and he was thrown
                    into the prison of Vincennes. Here he remained for three months; then he was
                    released, to enter upon the gigantic undertaking of his life.</p>
                <p>A certain bookseller had applied to him with a project for the translation into
                    French of Ephraim Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia,.</hi> Diderot
                    accepted the proposal, but in his busy and pregnant intelligence the scheme
                    became transformed. Instead of a mere reproduction of Chambers, he persuaded the
                    bookseller to enter upon a new work, which should collect under one roof all the
                    active writers, all the new ideas, all the new knowledge, that were then moving
                    the cultivated class to its depths, but still were comparatively ineffectual by
                    reason of their dispersion. His enthusiasm infected the publishers; they
                    collected a sufficient capital for a vaster enterprise than they had at first
                    planned; D’Alembert was persuaded to become Diderot’s colleague; the requisite
                    permission was procured from the Government; in 1750 an elaborate prospectus
                    announced the project to a delighted public; and in 1751 the first volume was
                    given to the world. The last of the letter-press was issued in 1765, but it was
                    1772 before the subscribers received the final volumes of the plates. These
                    twenty years were to Diderot years not merely of incessant drudgery, but of
                    harassing persecution, of sufferings from the cabals of enemies,and of
                    injuryfrom the desertion of friends. The ecclesiastical party detested the <hi
                    rend="italic">Encyclopaedia,</hi> in which they saw a rising stronghold for
                    their philosophic enemies. By 1757 they could endure the sight no longer. The
                    subscribers had grown from 2000 to 4000, and this was a right measure of the
                    growth of the work in popular influence and power. To any one who turns over the
                    pages of these redoubtable volumes now, it seems surprising that their doctrines
                    should have stirred such portentous alarm. There is no atheism, no overt attack
                    on any of the cardinal mysteries of the faith, no direct denunciation even of
                    the notorious abuses of the church. Yet we feel that the atmosphere of the book
                    may well have been displeasing to authorities who had not yet learnt to
                    encounter the modern spirit on equal terms. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Encyclopaedia</hi> takes for granted the justice of religious tolerance and
                    speculative freedom. It asserts in distinct tones the democratic doctrine that
                    it is the common people in a nation whose lot ought to be the main concern of
                    the nation’s government. From beginning to end it is one unbroken process of
                    exaltation of scientific knowledge on the one hand, and pacific industry on the
                    other. All these things were odious to the old governing classes of France;
                    theirspirit was absolutist, ecclesiastical, and military. Perhaps the most
                    alarming thought of all was the current belief that the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Encyclopaedia</hi> was the work of an organized band of conspirators against
                    society, and that a pestilent doctrine was now made truly formidable by the
                    confederation of its preachers into an open league. When the seventh volume
                    appeared, it contained an article on <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> Geneva,”
                    written by D’Alembert. The writer contrived a panegyric on the pastors of
                    Geneva, of which every word was a stinging reproach to the abbés and prelates of
                    Versailles. At the same moment Helvétius’s book, <hi rend="italic"
                    >L’Esprit,</hi> appeared, and gave a still more profound, and, let us add, a
                    more reasonable shock to the ecclesiastical party. Authority could brook no
                    more, and in 1759 the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia</hi> was formally
                    suppressed.</p>
                <p>The decree, however, did not arrest the continuance of the work. The connivance
                    of the authorities at the breach of their own official orders was common in
                    those times of distracted government. The work went on, but with its
                    difficulties increased by the necessity of being clandestine. And a worse thing
                    than troublesome interference by the police now befell Diderot. D’Alembert,
                    wearied of shifts and indigpities, withdrew from the enterprise. Other powerful
                    colleagues, Turgot among them, declined to contribute further to a book which
                    had acquired an evil fame. Diderot was left to bring the task to an end as he
                    best could. For seven years he laboured like a slave at the oar. He wrote
                    several hundred articles, some of them very slight, but many of them most
                    laborious, comprehensive, and ample. He wore out his eyesight in correcting
                    proofs, and he wearied his soul in bringing the manuscript of less com petent
                    contributors into decent shape. He spent his days in the workshops, mastering
                    the processes of manufactures, and his nights in reproducing on paper what he
                    had learnt during the day. And he was incessantly harassed all the time by
                    alarms of a descent from the police. At the last moment, when his immenso work
                    was just drawing to an end, he encountered one last and crowning mortification:
                    he discovered that the bookseller, fearing the displeasure of the Government,
                    had struck out from the proof sheets, after they had left Diderot’s hands, all
                    passages that he chose to think too hardy. The monument to which Diderot had
                    given the labour of twenty long and oppressive years was irreparably mutilated
                    and defaced. It is calculated that the average annual salary received by Diderot
                    for his share in the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia</hi> was about £120
                    sterling. “And then to think,” said Voltaire, “that, an army contractor makes
                    £800 in a day !”</p>
                <p>Although the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia</hi> was Diderot’s monumental work,
                    he is the author of a shower of dispersed pieces that sowed nearly every field
                    of intellectual interest with new and fruitful ideas. We find no masterpiece,
                    but only thoughts for masterpieces; no creation, but a criticism wi th the
                    quality to inspire and direct creation. He wrote plays <hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi><hi rend="italic">le Fils Naturel</hi> and <hi rend="italic">le Père de
                    Famille·-—</hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi> they are very insipid performances in
                    the sentimental vein. But he accompanied them by essays on dramatic poetry,
                    including especially the <hi rend="italic">Paradoxe sur le Comédien,</hi> in
                    which he announced the principles of a new drama,—the serious, domestic,
                    bourgeois drama of real life, in opposition to the stilted conventions of the
                    classic French stage. It was Diderot’s lessons and example that gave a decisive
                    bias to the dramatic taste of Lessing, whose plays, and his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hamburgische Dramaturgie</hi> (1768), mark so important an epoch in the history
                    of the modern theatre. In the pictorial art, Diderot’s criticisms are no less
                    rich, fertile, and wide in their ideas. His article on “Beauty” in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Encyclopaedia</hi> shows that he had mastered and passed beyond
                    the metaphysical theories on the subject, and the <hi rend="italic">Essay on
                    Painting</hi> was justly described by Goethe, who thought it worth translating,
                    as “a magnificent work, which speaks even more helpfully to the poet than to the
                    painter, though to the painter too it is as a blazing torch.” Diderot’s most
                    intimate friend was Grimm, one of the conspicuous figures of the philosophic
                    body. Grimm wrote news-letters to various high personages in Germany, reporting
                    what was going on in the world of art and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n212/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0212-0195"/> literature in Paris, then without a rival as the
                    capital of the intellectual activity of Europe. Diderot helped his friend at
                    onetime and another between 1759 and 1779, by writing for him an account of the
                    annual exhibitions of paintings. These <hi rend="italic">Salons</hi> are among
                    the most readable of all pieces of art criticism. They have a freshness, a
                    reality, a life, which took their readers into a different world from the dry
                    and conceited pedantries of the ordinary virtuoso. As has been said by
                    Ste-Beuve, they initiated the French into a new sentiment, and introduced people
                    to the mystery and purport of colour by ideas. “Before Diderot,” Madame Necker
                    said, “I had never seen anything in pictures except dull and lifeless colours;
                    it was his imagination that gave them relief and life, and it is almost a new
                    sense for which I am indebted to his genius.”</p>
                <p>Greuze was Diderot’s favourite among contemporary artists, and it is easy to see
                    why. Greuze’s most characteristic pictures were the rendering in colour of the
                    same sentiment of domestic virtue and the pathos of common life, which Diderot
                    attempted with inferior success to represent upon the stage. For Diderot was
                    above all things interested in the life of men,—not the abstract life of the
                    race, but the incidents of individual character, the fortunes of a particular
                    family, the relations of real and concrete motives in this or that special case.
                    He delighted with the enthusiasm of a born casuist in curious puzzles of right
                    and wrong, and in devising a conflict between the generalities of ethics and the
                    conditions of an ingeniously contrived practical dilemma. Mostly his interest
                    expressed itself in didactic and sympathetic form; in two, however, of the most
                    remarkable of all his pieces, it is not sympathetic but ironical. <hi
                    rend="italic">Jacques</hi><hi rend="italic">le Fataliste</hi> (written in 1773,
                    but not published until 1796) is in manner an imitation of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tristram Shandy</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Sentimental Journey.</hi> Few
                    modern readers will find in it any true diversion. In spite of some excellent
                    criticisms dispersed here and there, and in spite of one or two stories that are
                    not without a certain effective realism, it must as a whole be pronounced
                    savourless, forced, and as leaving unmoved those springs of laughter and of
                    tears which are the common fountain of humour. <hi rend="italic">Rameau's
                    Nephew</hi> is a far superior performance. If there were any inevitable
                    compulsion to name a masterpiece for Diderot, one must select this singular
                    “farce-tragedy.” Its intention has been matter of dispute; whether it was
                    designed to be merely a satire on contemporary manners, or a reduction of the
                    theory of self-interest to an absurdity, or the application of an ironical
                    clencher to the ethics of ordinary convention, or a mere setting for a
                    discussion about music, or a vigorous dramatic sketch of a parasite and a human
                    original. There is no dispute as to its curious literary flavour, its mixed
                    qualities of pungency, bitterness, pity, and, in places, unflinching
                    shamelessness. Goethe’s translation (1805) was the first introduction of <hi
                    rend="italic">Rameau's Nephew</hi> to the European public. After executing it,
                    he gave back the original French manuscript'. ,to Schiller, from whom he had it.
                    No authentic French copy of it appeared until the writer had been nearly forty
                    years in his grave (1823).</p>
                <p>It would take several pages of this encyclopaedia merely to contain the list of
                    Diderot’s miscellaneous pieces, from an infinitely graceful trifle like the <hi
                    rend="italic">Regrets on My Old Dressing Gown</hi> up to <hi rend="italic"
                    >D’Alembert's Dream,</hi> where he plunges into the depths of the controversy as
                    to the ultimate constitution of matter and the meaning of life. It is a mistake
                    to set down Diderot for a coherent and systematic materialist. We ought to look
                    upon him “as a philosopher in whom all the contradictions of the time struggle
                    with one another” (Rosenkranz). That is to say, he is critical and not dogmatic.
                    There is no unity in Diderot, as there was in Voltaire or in Rousseau. Just as
                    in cases of conduct he loves to make new ethical assumptions and argue them out
                    as a professional sophist might have done, so in the speculative problems as to
                    the organization of matter, the origin of life, the compatibility between
                    physiological machinery and free will, he takes a certain stand-point, and
                    follows it out more or less digressively to its consequences. He seizes an
                    hypothesis and works it to its end, and this made him the inspirer in others of
                    materialist doctrines which they held more definitely than he did. Just as
                    Diderot could not attain to the concentration, the positiveness, the finality of
                    aim needed for a master-piece of literature, so he could not attain to those
                    qualities in the way of dogma and system. Yet he drew at last to the conclusions
                    of materialism, and contributed many of its most declamatory pages to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Système</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Nature</hi> of his friend
                    D’Holbach,—the very Bible of atheism, as some one styled it. All that he saw, if
                    we reduce his opinions to formulas, was motion in space: “attraction and
                    repulsion, the only truth.” If matter produces life by spontaneous generation,
                    and if man has no alternative but to obey the compulsion of nature, what remains
                    for God to do î</p>
                <p>In proportion as these conclusions deepened in him, the more did Diderot turn for
                    the hope of the race to virtue; in other words, to such a regulation of conduct
                    and motive as shall make us tender, pitiful, simple, contented. Hence his one
                    great literary passion, his enthusiasm for Richardson, our English novelist.
                    Hence, also, his deepening aversion for the political system of France, which
                    made the realization of a natural and contented domestic life so hard. Diderot
                    had almost as much to say against society as even Rousseau himself. The
                    difference between them was that Rousseau was a fervent theist. The atheism of
                    the Holbachians, as he called Diderot’s group, was intolerable to him.; and this
                    feeling, aided by certain private perversities of humour, led to a breach of
                    what had once been an intimate friendship between Rousseau and Diderot (1757).
                    Diderot was still alive when the <hi rend="italic">Confessions</hi> appeared,
                    and he was so exasperated by Rousseau’s stories about Grimm, then and always
                    Diderot’s intimate, that in 1782 he transformed a life of Seneca, that he had
                    written four years earlier, into an <hi rend="italic">Essay on the Reigns of
                    Claudius and Nero,</hi> which is much less an account of Seneca than a
                    vindication of Diderot and Grimm, and is one of the most rambling and inept
                    productions in literature. As for the merits of the old quarrel between Rousseau
                    and Diderot, we may agree with the latter, that too many sensible people would
                    be in the wrong if Jean Jacques was in the right.</p>
                <p>Varied and incessant as was Diderot’s mental activity, it was not of a kind to
                    bring him riches. He secured none of the posts that were occasionally given to
                    needy men of letters; he could not even obtain that bare official recognition of
                    merit which was implied by being chosen a member of the Academy. The time came
                    for him to provide a dower for his daughter, and he saw no other alternative
                    than to sell his library. When the empress Catherine of Russia heard of his
                    straits, she commissioned an agent in Paris to buy the library at a price equal
                    to about £1000 of our money, and then she handsomely requested the philosopher
                    to retain the books in Paris until she required them, and to constitute himself
                    her librarian, with a yearly salary. In 1773 Diderot started on an expedition to
                    thank his imperial benefactress in person, and he passed some months at St
                    Petersburg. The empress received him cordially. The strange pair passed their
                    afternoons in disputes on a thousand points of high philosophy, and they debated
                    with a vivacity and freedom not usual in courts. <hi rend="italic">“Fi,
                    done,"</hi> said Catherine one day, when Diderot hinted that he argued with her
                    at a disadvantage, “<hi rend="italic">is there any difference among men?"</hi>
                    Diderot returned home in 1774. Ten years remained to him, and he spent them in
                    the industrious acquisition of new knowledge, in the composition <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n213/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0213-0196"/> cf a host of fragmentary pieces, some of them
                    mentioned above, and in luminous declamations with his friends. All accounts
                    agree that Diderot was seen at his best in conversation. “He who only knows
                    Diderot in his writings,” says Marmontel, “doesnot know him at all. When he grew
                    animated in talk, and allowed his thoughts to flow in all their abundance, then
                    he became truly ravishing. In his writings he had not the art of ensemble; the
                    first operation which orders and places everything was too slow and too painful
                    to him.” Diderot himself was conscious of the want of literary merit in his
                    pieces. In truth he set no high value on what he had done. It is doubtful
                    whether he was ever alive to the waste that circumstance and temperament
                    together made of an intelligence from which, if it had been free to work
                    systematically, the world of thought had so much to hope. He was one of those
                    simple, disinterested, and intellectually sterling workers to whom their own
                    personality is as nothing in presence of the vast subjects that engage the
                    thoughts of their lives. He wrote what he found to write, and left the piece, as
                    Carlyle has said, “on the waste of accident, with an ostrich-like indifference.”
                    When he heard one day that a collected edition of his works was in the press at
                    Amsterdam, he greeted the news with “peals of laughter,” so well did he know
                    the.haste and the little heed with which those works had been dashed off.</p>
                <p>Diderot died in the month of July 17'84, six years after Voltaire and Rousseau,
                    one year after his old colleague D’Alembert, and five years before D’Holbach,
                    his host and intimate for a lifetime. Notwithstanding Diderot’s peals of
                    laughter at the thought, there is now just completed— nearly a hundred years
                    since his death—an elaborate and exhaustive collection of his -writings in
                    twenty stout volumes, edited by MM. Assézat and Tourueux. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(j.</hi> MO.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
