<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0063-0052-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DE LOUTHERBOURG, Philip James (9th edition, volume 7,
                    page 52)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xp4n">Polishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k59v">Mesmerism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cz3256r">Storms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1069177">Polishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1017315">Mesmerism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134142">Storms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:918096">Exhibitionism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n63/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DE LOUTHERBOURG, <hi rend="smallcaps">Philip
                        James</hi></label> (1740-1812), an artist of remarkably versatile ability
                    and interesting personality. He was born at Strasburg, 31st October 1740, where
                    his father, the representative of a noble Polish family, practised miniature
                    painting in a semi-amateur manner; but he spent the greater part of his life in
                    London, where he was naturalized, and exerted a considerable influence on the
                    scenery of the English stage, as well as on the artists of the following
                    generation, Turner, Martin, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>Young De Loutherbourg was intended for the Lutheran ministry, and was educated at
                    the university of Strasburg. As the calling, however, was foreign to his nature,
                    he insisted on being a painter, and placed himself under Vanloo in Paris. The
                    result was the inåmediate and precocious development of extraordinary powers.
                    Besides this triumph, and independently of it, he became a figure in the
                    fashionable society of that day, and the friend of such men as Diderot, who had
                    just then mainly contributed to make Gesner celebrated. He was elected into the
                    French Academy below the age required by the law of the institution, and painted
                    landscapes, sea-storms, battles, all of which had a celebrity above those of the
                    specialists then working in Paris. By temperament whatever was extraordinary and
                    sensational was attractive to him, and the <hi rend="italic">bizarre</hi>
                    appeared in all he did. His <hi rend="italic">début</hi> was made by the
                    exhibition of twelve pictures, including Storm at Sunset, Night, Morning after
                    Rain; and when he painted common things, as a group of asses, he gave the
                    picture such a fantastic title as—Father and Mother, Ijittle Fanfan, Aunt and
                    Uncle à la Bretagne, Cousin Germain, and the Perruquier of all the Family. In
                    the next stage of his life we find him travelling in Switzerland, Germany, and
                    Italy, distinguishing himself as much by mechanic inventions as by painting. One
                    of these, constructed at his native city, was the wonder of the day, showing
                    quite new effects produced in a model theatre. The exhibition of lights behind
                    canvas representing the moon and stars, the illusory appearance of running water
                    produced by clear blue sheets of metal and gauze, with loose threads of silver,
                    and so on, were his devices. Charles Blanc says one of these curious models,
                    called “Le Séraphin,” still existed in the Palais Royal at the date of
                    publication of his work, <hi rend="italic">École Française.</hi> Having repaired
                    to London, De Loutherbourg was employed by Garrick, who offered him £500 a year
                    to apply his mechanisms to Drury Lane, and to superintend the scene-painting,
                    which he did with complete success, making a new era in the adjuncts of the
                    stage. Garrick’s own piece, the <hi rend="italic">Christmas Tale,</hi> and the
                    pantomime, 1781-2, introduced the novelties to the public, and the delight not
                    only of the masses, but of Reynolds and the artists, was unbounded. The green
                    trees gradually became russet, the moon rose and lit the edges of passing
                    clouds, and all the world was captivated by effects we now take little notice
                    of. A still greater triumph awaited him on his opening an entertainment he
                    called the “Eidophusicon,” which showed the rise, progress, and result of a
                    storm at sea—that which destroyed the great Indiaman, the “Halsewell,”—and the
                    Fallen Angels raising the Palace of Pandemonium. De Loutherbourg has been called
                    the inventor of the panorama, but this honour does not belong to him, although
                    it first appeared about the same time as the eidophusicon. The first panorama
                    was painted and exhibited by Barker the elder.</p>
                <p>All this mechanism did not in the least prevent De Loutherbourg from painting.
                    Lord Howe’s Victory off Ushant, 1794, and other large naval pictures, were
                    commissioned for Greenwich Hospital Gallery, where they still remain. His
                    grandest work, the Destruction of the Armada, is one of the finest sea-fights
                    ever realized on canvas. He painted also the Great Fire of London, anj severaI
                    historical works, one of these being the Attack of the Combined Armies on
                    Valenciennes, 1793. He was made R.A., in addition to other distinctions, in
                    1781, shortly after which date we find an entirely new mental impulse taking
                    possession of him. He joined Balsamo, Comte de Cagliostro, and travelled about
                    with this extraordinary person,—happily leaving him, however, before the priests
                    in Rome condemned him to death. We do not hear that Mesmer had attracted De
                    Loutherbourg, or that the Revolution carried him away, nor do we find an exact
                    record of his connection with Cagliostro; but there exists a pamphlet published
                    in 1789, <hi rend="italic">A List of a few Cures performed by Mr and Mrs De
                        Loutherbourg without Medicine,</hi> which relates some very remarkable
                    examples of such cures. Cagliostro had led him to seek the philosopher’s stone,
                    but his success was frustrated by a female relative breaking in on his nocturnal
                    experiments and destroying the crucible at the very moment of projection. He
                    died 11th March 1812. His publications are few,—some sets of etchings, and <hi
                        rend="italic">English Scenery,</hi> 1805. His colour is hot and brown, which
                    has injured his fame as a painter.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
