<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0584-0563-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DURHAM, John George Lambton, First Earl of</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 563</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1068347">Poles</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1129153">Speech</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:952743">Health</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1138503">Summer</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947883">Grief</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bv7b36b">Reformers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6rb7d">Voting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n584/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DURHAM, <hi rend="smallcaps">John George Lambton, First Earl
                    of</hi></label> (1792-1840), born at Lambton Castle, Durham, on the 12th April
                    1792, was the eldest son of William Henry Lambton, M.P. for the city of Durham.
                    It is noteworthy that the family to which he belonged had held the Lambton
                    estate in uninterrupted male succession from the 12th century. Educated at Eton,
                    he held for a short time a commission in a regiment of hussars. In 1813, soon
                    after attaining his majority, he was returned to Parliament as representative of
                    his native county. He was an advanced Liberal from the beginning to the end of
                    his political career, and distinguished himself by his uncompromising opposition
                    to the reactionary measures of the Tory Government His political position was
                    strengthened by his marriage in 1816 to the eldest daughter of Earl Grey. In
                    1819 he championed the rights of the people by his denunciation, in the House of
                    Commons and at numerous public meetings, of the coercive measures proposed by
                    the Government against the Chartists. In April 1821 he proposed in the House a
                    scheme of parliamentary reform which was in some points, notably in regard to
                    the redistribution of seats, more thoroughgoing than that which was carried
                    eleven years later. The delicate state of his health compelled him in 1826 to
                    proceed to Naples, where he resided for about a year. He was a prominent
                    supporter of the Canning administration of 1827, and of that of Lord Goderich by
                    which it was succeeded. When the latter fell to pieces owing to its inherent
                    weakness in January 1828, Lambton’s services were acknowledged by his elevation
                    to the peerage as Baron Durham. On the accession of Lord Grey to power in 1830
                    Lord Durham obtained the office of lord privy seal. He was one of a Cabinet
                    committee of four who were intrusted with the preparation of the Reform Bill,
                    the others being Sir James Graham, Lord John Russell, and Lord Duncannon. It was
                    understood at the time that his influence was exerted to make the measure as
                    liberal as possible, and in particular that he wished to introduce the ballot as
                    one of its provisions. In the debates on the bill in the Lords he did not take
                    the leading part that might naturally have been expected from the only peer who
                    had been on the Cabinet committee for its preparation. This was owing partly to
                    his own indifferent health and partly to grief at the death of his eldest son,
                    the Master Lambton of one of Lawrence’s most admired portraits. Continued
                    ill-health led him to resign office in March 1833, when he was raised to the
                    dignity of Viscount Lambton and earl of Durham. In the summer of the same year,
                    however, he was able to undertake a special embassy to the court of St
                    Petersburg, the chief object of which was to secure lenient treatment for the
                    insurgent Poles. In this he was unsuccessful. When the party that had carried
                    reform began to be divided, Lord Durham was generally regarded as a likely
                    leader of the more advanced section, and a strongly radical speech which he
                    delivered at the celebrated Grey banquet at Edinburgh in 1834 helped to
                    strengthen his claims to the position. It took the form of a reply to a previous
                    speech of Lord Brougham, whose enmity Lord Durham thus provoked. In 1837 he
                    accepted the post of ambassador at St Petersburg, which he occupied for about a
                    year. Meanwhile a very serious insurrection had broken out in Canada, and early
                    in 1838 the Government found it necessary to suspend the colonial constitution
                    and send out a new governor with special powers. Lord Durham was selected to
                    undertake the difficult task, for which his extensive experience and his
                    well-known advanced liberalism were supposed specially to qualify him. Somewhat
                    hasty and irascible in his temperament, he unfortunately adopted measures which
                    were beyond the powers conferred upon him by the special Act of Parliament under
                    which he had been appointed. These measures were disapproved of by a vote of the
                    House of Lords on the motion of Lord Brougham, who imported the bitterness of
                    his earlier quarrel with Lord Durham into the debate, and the Government were
                    compelled to disallow the ordinances in which they were embodied. Lord Durham
                    was so deeply incensed at this that he took the extraordinary step of returning
                    home without waiting for his recall, and the Government marked its disapproval
                    of his conduct by directing that he should not receive the customary salute on
                    landing in England. He defended his plan of administration in an able and
                    elaborate report addressed to the queen, and his policy was practically
                    justified by being adopted by his successor. He had returned to England in
                    shattered health, and he died at Cowes, in the Isle of Wight, on the 28th July
                    1840.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
