<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0061-0050-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DELIRIUM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 50</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:804631">Alcohols</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:804414">Alcoholics</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:804361">Alcoholates</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:804461">Alcoholism</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:804264">Alcohol</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04032">Alcohol</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b41z41s37">Alcoholates</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70w4g">Alcohols</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b43t9d59r">Alcoholism</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tg59">Delirium</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n61/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DELIRIUM</label>, a temporary disorder of the mind, generally
                    occurring in connection with some form of bodily disease. It may vary in
                    intensity from slight and occasional wandering of the mind and incoherence of
                    expression, to fixed delusions and violent maniacal excitement, and again it may
                    be associated with more or less of coma or insensibility (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Mental Diseases).</hi> Delirium is apt to occur in most
                    diseases of an acute nature, such as fevers or inflammatory affections, in
                    injuries affecting the brain, in blood diseases, in conditions of exhaustion,
                    and as the result of the action of certain specific poisons, such as opium,
                    Indian hemp, belladonna, chloroform, and alcohol. The form of delirium which is
                    due to the action of the last-named substance is one of great importance from
                    its comparative frequency, and is well known by the name of Delirium
                    Tremens.</p>
                <p>Delirium Tremens is one of a train of symptoms of what is termed in medical
                    nomenclature acute alcoholism, or recent excessive indulgence in alcohol. It
                    must, however, be observed that this disorder, although arising in this manner,
                    rarely comes on as the result of a single debauch in a person unaccustomed to
                    the abuse of stimulants, but generally occurs in cases where the nervous system
                    has been already subjected for a length of time to the poisonous action of
                    alcohol, so that the complaint might be more properly regarded as acute
                    supervening on chronic alcoholism. It is equally to be borne in mind that many
                    habitual drunkards never suffer from delirium tremens.</p>
                <p>It was long supposed, and is indeed still believed by some, that delirium tremens
                    only comes on. when the supply of alcohol has been suddenly cut off; but this
                    view is now generally rejected, and there is abundant evidence to show that the
                    attack comes on while the patient is still continuing to drink. Even in those
                    cases where several days have elapsed between the cessation from drinking and
                    the seizure, it will be found that in the interval the premonitory symptoms of
                    delirium tremens have shown themselves, one of which is aversion to drink as
                    well as food—the attack being in most instances preceded by marked derangement
                    of the digestive functions. Occasionally the attack is precipitated in persons
                    predisposed to it by the occurrence of some acute disease, such as pneumonia, by
                    accidents, such as burns, also by severe mental strain, and by the deprivation
                    of food, even where the supply of alcohol is less than would have been likely to
                    produce it otherwise. Where, on the other hand, the quantity of alcohol taken
                    has been very large, the attack is sometimes ushered in by fits of an
                    epileptiform character. Males are much more frequently the subjects of delirium
                    tremens than females.</p>
                <p>One of the earliest indications of the approaching attack of delirium tremens is
                    sleeplessness, any rest the patient may obtain being troubled by unpleasant or
                    terrifying dreams. During the day there is observed a certain restlessness and
                    irritability of manner, with trembling of the hands and a thick or tremulous
                    articulation. The skin is perspiring, the countenance oppressed-looking and
                    flushed, the pulse rapid and feeble, and there is evidence of considerable
                    bodily prostration. These symptoms increase each day and night for a few days,
                    and then the characteristic delirium is superadded. The patient is in a state of
                    mental confusion, talks incessantly and incoherently, has a distressed and
                    agitated or perplexed appearance, and a vague notion that he is pursued by some
                    one seeking to injure him. His delusions are usually of transient character, but
                    he is constantly troubled with visual hallucinations in the form of disagreeable
                    animals or insects which he imagines he sees all about him. He looks
                    suspiciously around him, turns over his pillows, and ransacks his bedclothes for
                    some fancied object he supposes to be concealed there. There is constant
                    restlessness, a common form of delusion being that he is not in his own house,
                    but imprisoned in some apartment from which he is anxious to escape to return
                    home. In these circumstances he is ever wishing to get out of bed and out of
                    doors, and, although in general he may be persuaded to return to bed, he is soon
                    desiring to get up again. The trembling of the muscles from which the name of
                    the disease is derived is a prominent but not invariable symptom. It is most
                    marked in the muscles of the hands and arms and in the tongue. The character of
                    the delirium is seldom wild or noisy, but is much more commonly a combination of
                    busy restlessness and indefinite fear. When spoken to the patient can answer
                    correctly enough, but immediately thereafter relapses into his former condition
                    of incoherence. Occasionally maniacal symptoms develop themselves, the patient
                    becoming dangerously violent, and the case thus assuming a much graver aspect
                    than one of simple delirium tremens.</p>
                <p>In most cases the symptoms undergo abatement in from three to six days, the
                    cessation of the attack being marked by the occurrence of sound sleep, from
                    which the patient awakes in his right mind, although in a state of great
                    physical prostration, and in great measure if not entirely oblivious of his
                    condition during his illness.</p>
                <p>Although generally the termination of an attack of delirium tremens is in
                    recovery, it occasionally proves fatal by the supervention of coma and
                    convulsions, or acute mania, or by exhaustion, more especially when any acute
                    bodily disease is associated with the attack. In certain instances delirium
                    tremens is but the beginning of serious and permanent impairment of intellect,
                    as is not unfrequently observed in confirmed drunkards who have suffered from
                    frequent attacks of this disease.</p>
                <p>The treatment of delirium tremens has given rise to much discussion among medical
                    men, and the result has been that more rational views now prevail on the subject
                    than formerly. This change is doubtless in great measure to be ascribed to the
                    clearer ideas respecting the real nature and true cause of the malady which
                    extensive and accurate observation has afforded. The theory once so widely
                    accepted, that delirium tremens was the result of the too sudden breaking off
                    from indulgence in alcohol, led to its treatment by regular and often large
                    doses of stimulants, a practice fraught with mischievous results, since however
                    much the delirium appeared to be thus calmed for the time, the continuous supply
                    of the poison which was the original source of the disease inflicted serious
                    damage upon the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n62/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0062-0051"/> •brain, and led in many instances to the
                    subsequent development of insanity. The former system of prescribing large doses
                    of opium, with the view of procuring sleep at all hazards, was no less
                    pernicious; and there is Reason to fear that not a few cases of delirium tremens
                    have ended in fatal coma from what was in reality opium poisoning. In addition
                    to these methods of treatment, mechanical restraint of the patient was the
                    common practice.</p>
                <p>The views of the disease which now prevail, recognizing the delirium as the
                    effect at once of the poisonous action of alcohol upon the brain and of the want
                    of food, encourage reliance to be placed for its cure upon the entire
                    withdrawal, in most instances, of stimulants, and the liberal administration of
                    light nutriment, in addition to quietness and gentle but firm control, without
                    mechanical restraint. In mild attacks this is frequently all that is required.
                    In more severe cases, where there is great restlessness, sedatives have to be
                    resorted to, and many substances have been recommended for the purpose. Opiates
                    administered in small quantity, and preferably by hypodermic injection, are
                    undoubtedly of value; and chloral, either alone or in conjunction with bromide
                    of potassium, often answers even better. Such remedies, however, should be
                    administered with great caution, and only under medical supervision.</p>
                <p>Stimulants may be called for where the delirium assumes the low or adynamic form,
                    and the patient tends to sink from exhaustion, or when the attack is complicated
                    with some other disease. Such cases are, however, in the highest degree
                    exceptional, and do not affect the general principle of treatment already
                    referred to, which inculcates the entire withdrawal of stimulants in the
                    treatment of ordinary attacks of delirium tremens. (j. o. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
