<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0030-0021-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DECLARATION OF PARIS (9th edition, volume 7, page
                    21)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1748515">Exceptionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116439">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kn9d">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n30/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DECLARATION OF PARIS</label>, a diplomatic instrument or
                    protocol signed by the representatives of all the powers present at the Congress
                    of Paris in 1856, and subsequently accepted as a binding engagement of public
                    law by all the other powers (except the United States of America, Spain, and
                    Mexico), for the purpose of settling and defining certain rules of maritime law,
                    in time of war, on points of great moment to belligerent and neutral
                    states—points, it must be added, upon which the ancient law of nations had
                    gradually undergone some change, and on which great differences of opinion and
                    practice prevailed. The four propositions agreed to by the plenipotentiaries
                    were embodied in the following terms :—</p>
                <p>1. Privateering is and remains abolished.</p>
                <p>2. The neutral flag covers enemy’s goods, with the exception of contraband of
                    war.</p>
                <p>3. Neutral goods, with the exception of contraband of war, are not liable to
                    capture under an enemy’s flag.</p>
                <p>4. Blockades, in order to be binding, must be effective,—that is to say,
                    maintained by a force sufficient readily to prevent access to the coast of the
                    enemy.</p>
                <p>By most of the modern writers on international law these principles are regarded
                    as a distinct gain to the cause of civilization, international justice,
                    commerce, and peace. But a feeble and ineffectual attempt has been made to
                    repudiate these new rules of maritime law, though they received the tacit assent
                    of Parliament, and have been acted upon by all nations in the six wars which
                    have occurred since 1856, including the American civil war, although the United
                    States had not concurred in the Declaration. The American Government withheld
                    its assent, not because it objected to these principles, but because it held
                    that they did not go far enough, and that they ought to be extended to secure
                    from capture all private property at sea. It is argued by the opponents of the
                    Declaration that the British envoy at Paris exceeded his powers; that the form
                    of the instrument itself is declaratory, but not binding either as a contract or
                    a legislative act; that it is not competent to a congress to change the rights
                    of belligerents founded on ancient law and usage; and that Great Britain
                    committed a fatal error in renouncing the right to seize enemy’s goods in
                    neutral ships and to equip privateers.</p>
                <p>To these arguments it is said in reply that the British envoy at Paris had full
                    powers to pledge the faith of the Crown, with the concurrence of the Cabinet,
                    and that if Parliament disapproved his conduct, it ought to have been pressed to
                    a division at the time, and not when Great Britain has enjoyed the benefit of
                    the Declaration, as a neutral, for twenty years. It is a part of the prerogative
                    of the Crown to fix our international relations, and to determine the conditions
                    of maritime warfare. The most fitting and binding expression of international
                    law (which cannot assume the form of positive law by sovereign enactment) is to
                    be found in instruments recording in solemn form the consent of all civilized
                    nations. On the ground of expediency, it is contended by the supporters of the
                    Declaration of Paris, that Great Britain is, of all countries in the world, that
                    which has most to gain by it, because shq is not only the greatest naval power,
                    but the power which has the largest number of merchant vessels and the largest
                    amount of property afloat on the seas, and liable to attack.</p>
                <p>The primary advantage of the Declaration no doubt accrues to neutrals, as it
                    secures to them a larger carrying trade in time of war, and exempts them from
                    the seizure of enemy’s goods in neutral ships. Hence, if a belligerent were now
                    to violate the rules of the Declaration, he would have to encounter the
                    opposition of all neutral states, and would speedily find them arrayed on the
                    side of the enemy. But in the event of war, Great Britain is the state most
                    exposed, by reason of the magnitude of her maritime trade, to the depredations
                    of hostile cruisers; the injury done is to be measured by the amount of the
                    shipping and property exposed to it; and a single cruiser of a small state may
                    cause enormous losses to the commerce of a great power, as was seen in the
                    American civil war. Since the establishment of a general system of railroads,
                    the greater part of the trade of all the states of continental Europe can be
                    carried on by land, either by direct communication or through neutral ports. The
                    power of a naval state to inflict serious injury on an enemy by the interruption
                    of her trade is therefore by the nature of things greatly diminished, and the
                    same remark applies to commercial blockades. To England all foreign commodities
                    must be brought by sea, and England is more dependent than any other country on
                    foreign trade for the raw material of her manufactures, and even for the food of
                    her inhabitants. It is therefore the paramount interest of England to keep open
                    all the channels of trade, as much as possible, both in peace and war; and
                    injuries done to the trade of an enemy are often equally prejudicial to the
                    state which <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n31/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0031-0022"/> inflicts them. These are some of the leading
                    arguments which have been advanced in defence of the Declaration of Paris, and
                    which no doubt actuated the authors of it.</p>
                <p>A full account of the controversy will be found in the third volume of Sir Robert
                    Phillimore’s <hi rend="italic">Commentaries on International Law,</hi> where the
                    learned author supports and advocates the old traditions of the Court of
                    Admiralty, and also in Hall’s <hi rend="italic">Rights and Duties of
                        Neutrals</hi> (1874). The principles on which the Declaration of Paris is
                    based are explained and defended in an article in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Edinburgh Review,</hi> No. 296. (H. R.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
