<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0089-0078-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DENHAM, Sir John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 78</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:878236">Cooperativeness</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:878116">Cooperation</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:883881">Crofts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4959c77k">Cooperation</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz36">Inns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n89/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DENHAM, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir John</hi></label>
                    (1615-1668), a royalist poet, who has won a place among the foremost British
                    authors more by a happy accident than by any decided genius, was the only son of
                    Sir John Denham, lord chief baron of the Exchequer in Ireland, and was born in
                    Dublin in 1615. In 1617 his father was promoted to the rank of baron of the
                    Exchequer in England, and removed to London with his family. The future poet
                    attended a grammar school in London, and in Michaelmas term 1631 was removed to
                    Oxford, where be was entered a gentleman commoner of Trinity College. Having
                    taken his degree of B.A., be began the study of the law at Lincoln’s Inn in
                    1634; but the character he had <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n90/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0090-0079"/> maintained at Oxford, of being “a slow, dreaming
                    young man,” gave way to a scandalous reputation for gambling, by which he
                    beggared himself and seriously embarrassed his father. We learn that, by way of
                    penance, he wrote at this time an <hi rend="italic">Essay against Gaming,</hi>
                    whether in prose or verse is not recorded. After his father’s death the habit
                    became still more dominant, and he squandered a fortune. It was a surprise to
                    every one, therefore, when in 1642 he suddenly, as Waller said, “broke out like
                    the Irish rebellion, threescore thousand strong, when no one was aware, nor in
                    the least expected it,” by publishing in that year two most successful volumes
                    of verse. The first of these was <hi rend="italic">The Sophy,</hi> a tragedy in
                    five acts, a thin folio, the theme of which was a Turkish tale of blood and
                    intrigue, drawn from Sir Thomas Herbert’s travels. This, Denham’s only dramatic
                    performance, is tame and correct, without passion, but free from the faults of
                    some of the minor authors of the time. It was successful, but it enjoyed nothing
                    of the unparalleled popularity of his simultaneous venture, the descriptive poem
                    of <hi rend="italic">Cooper's Hill,</hi> the first edition of which in quarto
                    was anonymous. In this famous piece no entirely new style was attempted, for Ben
                    Jonson had led the way in theme and Cowley in manner; but it had a smooth grace
                    and a polished antithesis that were doubtful merits in poetry, but extremely
                    dear to the rising generation. One quatrain, out of the three or four hundred
                    lines of reflection and description, has been universally praised, and forms one
                    of our most familiar quotations. Addressing the Thames, the poet says—</p>
                <p>“0 could I flow like thee, and make thy stream My great example, as it is my
                    theme!</p>
                <p>Though deep, yet clear; though gentle, yet not dull;</p>
                <p>Strong without rage, without o’erflowing full.”</p>
                <p>Brought into royal notice by his poems, Denham was appointed high sheriff for
                    Surrey and governor of Farnham Castle; but he showed no military talent, and
                    soon followed the king to Oxford. During the civil war he served the queen
                    mother, and was intrusted with the letters in cipher that Cowley wrote to the
                    king, which he managed to deliver into Charles’s hands. Being detected, however,
                    he was obliged to escape into France. In April 1648 he is said to have conveyed
                    the young duke of York from St James’s to Paris; it is certain that, later in
                    that year, he was sent in company with Lord Crofts, as ambassador to Poland, to
                    obtain money for the king, and he succeeded in bringing back £10,000. In 1652 he
                    returned, a ruined man, to England, and resided as the guest of the earl of
                    Pembroke at Wilton for a year. He now disappears until the Restoration. When
                    Charles II. returned, Denham was made surveyor-general and Knight of the Bath,
                    and seems to have been well provided for; but his subsequent life was far from
                    happy, for his second wife, a young woman of great beauty, was seduced by the
                    duke of York, and became his mistress. This catastrophe, which is abundantly
                    noticed in the current literature of that day, shattered the old poet’s reason;
                    and he recovered from his insanity only to die, at his house near Whitehall, on
                    the 10th of March 1668. He was buried in Westminster Abbey. In the same year,
                    1668, his works were collected in a single volume, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Poems and Translations.</hi> This included, besides <hi rend="italic">Cooper's
                    Hill</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Sophy,</hi> a fragment of an epic on the
                    destruction of Troy, some beautiful lines on the death of Cowley, written a few
                    months before his own decease, a didactic poem on the progness of learning, and
                    some translations. Notwithstanding the fame of <hi rend="italic">Cooper's
                    Hill,</hi> which Pope imitated in his <hi rend="italic">Windsor Forest,</hi>
                    Denham’s poems have not been edited in modern times. He was one of the very
                    first to note the tendency towards rhetorical and gallicized forms in public
                    taste, and to gratify the new fashion. But to speak of him, as was once
                    customary, as a great reformer of metre and fashioner of language, is to fail to
                    realize the limitations of his talent.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
