<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0265-0248-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DIONYSUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 248</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vb4q">Liberalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29n23">Soma</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z984">Thracians</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3kb0r">Vines</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kn07">Priests</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10s39">Infants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1125698">Soma</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1200824">Liberals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1151519">Titanates</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1062222">Phrygians</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1739388">Womanism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1895887">Womanizers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:841533">Bulls</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n265/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DIONYSUS</label>, in Greek Mythology, is principally the god
                    of the vine; and in the myths concerning him it is clear that the effects of
                    wine and the spread of vine growing have both been kept in view. No sooner had
                    the god grown up than he started on distant expeditions to teach men to
                    cultivate the vine, and on these occasions his followers were known for their
                    ecstatic ceremonies. It would seem also as if the story of his birth was only a
                    mythical representation of the growth and ripening of the grape. Thebes in
                    Baeotia was originally the local centre of his worship in Greece; and he was a
                    son of Semele, a daughter of Cadmus, the king of Thebes, his father being Zeus,
                    who among other divine functions exercised also that of god of the fertilizing
                    spring showers. Before the child was mature, Zeus appeared to Semele at her
                    request in his majesty as god of lightning, by which she was killed, but the
                    infant was saved from the same fate by cool ivy which grew up suddenly around
                    him. Zeus took him up, inclosed him within his own thigh till he came to
                    maturity, and then brought him to the light, so that he was twice born; and it
                    was to celebrate this double birth that the <hi rend="italic">dithyrambus</hi>
                    was sung. He was now conveyed by Hermes to be brought up by the nymphs of Nysa,
                    from which place it is probable his name Dio-nysus, or “god of Nysa,” is
                    derived; but among the many places of this name claiming to have been the true
                    one it is impossible to decide. In his journeys to teach the cultivation of the
                    vine he met with opposition in some cases, as in that of Lycurgus, a Thracian
                    king, from whose attack Dionysus saved himself by leaping into the sea, where he
                    was kindly received by Thetis. Lycurgus was blinded by Zeus and soon died, or,
                    according to another story, became frank'c and hewed down his own son, mistaking
                    him for a vine; while in a third story Ambrosia, who was changed <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n266/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0266-0249"/> into a vine, clung so closely round him that,
                    failing to escape, he died. A similar incident is that of Pentheus, king of
                    Thebes, who opposed the orgiastic ceremonies introduced by Dionysus among the
                    women of Thebes, and, having been present watching one of these ceremonies, was
                    mistaken for some animal of the chase, pursued, and slain by his own mother. At
                    Orchomenus, the three daughters of Minyas refused to join the other women in
                    their nocturnal orgies, and for this were transformed into birds. It was in
                    accordance with this tradition that in after times, at the festival of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Agrionia,</hi> the priests of Dionysus pursued the women of the
                    race of Minyas with drawn swords, and if they captured them, killed them, which
                    incident, it will be seen, also justifies the title of w/£yo-nýç applied to
                    Dionysus. On the other hand, when the god was received hospitably he repaid the
                    kindness by the gift of the vine, and of this the chief instance is that of
                    Icarius of Attica, who lived in the time of King Pandion. But Icarius, instead
                    of keeping secret the use of the vine, spread it among the herdsman and
                    labourers, who, becoming intoxicated with the wine, slew him and threw him into
                    a well or buried him under a tree, where his daughter Erigone found his grave,
                    and in her despair hanged herself on the tree. In recollection of this it was
                    the custom to hang small figures and masks on trees at the ceremony in her
                    honour. The district of Icaria, though in Attica, was on the borders of Baeotia,
                    which latter was the earliest and chief seat of the worship of Dionysus in
                    Greece, with its famous festival on Mount Cithaeron. Festivals of the same
                    ecstatic kind spread to Attica, to Mount Parnassus, and north to Thrace. But in
                    Baeotia Dionysus was personally associated with so many festivals and incidents
                    that he has more the appearance of a hero or demigod than of a god, and it may
                    have been from a sense of this that Herodotus (ii. 52) calls him the most recent
                    of the gods. In Homer also he has a secondary character. To what extent the idea
                    of his functions may have been derived from the Vedic god Soma cannot be
                    determined, but the similarity between the two deities becomes the more striking
                    when we remember how actively the worship of Dionysus was conducted in Asia
                    Minor, particularly in Phrygia and Lydia, where he was styled Sabazius, with the
                    epithet also of /Sayaîoç, from which it is supposed his Greek name of Bacchos
                    was derived. As Sabazius he was associated with the Phrygian goddess Cybele, and
                    was followed in his expeditions by a <hi rend="italic">thiasos</hi> of Centaurs,
                    Pan, Satyrs, and Silenus. In Lydia his triumphant return from India was
                    celebrated by an annual festival on Mount Tmolus, and it was in Lydia that he
                    assumed the long beard and long robe which were afterwards given him in his
                    character as the “Indian Bacchus.” The other incidents in which he appears in a
                    purely triumphal character are his transforming the Tyrrhene pirates who
                    attacked him into dolphins, as told in the Homeric hymn to Dionysus, and as
                    represented on the monument of Lysicrates at Athens, and his part in the war of
                    the gods against the giants. The adventure with the pirates occurred on his
                    voyage to Naxos, where he found Ariadne when she had been abandoned by Theseus.
                    At Naxos Ariadne was associated with Dionysus as his wife, and their marriage
                    was annually celebrated by a festival. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ariadne.)</hi>
                    Another phase in the myth of Dionysus originated in observing the decay of
                    vegetation in winter, to suit which he was supposed to be slain and to join the
                    deities of the lower world, in which connection he figured in the mysteries of
                    Eleusis. This phase of his character was developed by the Orphic poets, he
                    having here the name of Zagreus, and being no longer the Theban god, but a son
                    of Zeus and Persephone. The child was brought up secretly, watched over by
                    Kuretes; but the jealous Hera discovered where he was, and sent Titans to the
                    spot, who, finding him at play, tore him to pieces, and cooked and ate his
                    limbs, while Hera gave his heart to Zeus. To connect this with the myth of tſie
                    Theban birth of Dionysus, it is said that Zeus gave the child’s heart to Semele,
                    or himself swallowed it and gave birth to the Theban god. Altogether there were,
                    it was said, five different gods “Dionysus,” each having different parentage.
                    The conception of Zagreus, or the winter Dionysus, appears to have originated in
                    Crete, but it was accepted also in Delphi, where his grave was shown, at which
                    sacrifice was secretly offered annually on the shortest day. This feature of
                    going away in the winter and returning at spring, which was common to Dionysus
                    and Apollo, would commend the former god to the priests of Apollo at Delphi.
                    Dionysus had further, in common with Apollo, the prophetic gift. Like Hermes, he
                    was a god of the productiveness of nature, and hence Priapus was one of his
                    regular companions, while not only in the mysteries but in the rural festivals
                    his symbol, the phallus, was carried about ostentatiously. His symbols from the
                    animal kingdom were the bull, panther, ass, and goat. His personal attributes
                    are an ivy wreath, the thyrsus (a staff with pine cone at the end), a drinking
                    cup <hi rend="italic">{cantharus),</hi> and sometimes the horn of a bull on his
                    forehead. Artistically he was represented mostly either as a youth of soft
                    nearly feminine form, or as a bearded and draped man, but frequently also as an
                    infant, with reference to his birth or to his bringing up in Nysa. The earliest
                    images were of wood with the branches still attached in parts, whence he was
                    called Dionysus Dendrites. He was figured also, like Hermes, in the form of a
                    pillar or term surmounted by his head.</p>
                <p>The Greek colonists of Southern Italy (Magna Graecia) had taken w ith them the
                    worship of Dionysus, and so successfully had it spread there that Sophocles <hi
                    rend="italic">{Antig.</hi> 1106) speaks of him as the god who rules in Italy.
                    From Campania the joint worship of Dionysus (Liber), Demeter (Ceres), and Kore
                    (Libera) was introduced into Rome, and a temple was erected to them 495 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> in obedience to the Sibylline books. But the
                    mysteries which were held in connection with this worship were suppressed by the
                    senate, 186 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> In Campania Dionysus was styled
                    Hebon, and conceived in the form of a bull with a human head. Libera, usually
                    identified with Kore, corresponds rather to the goddess Hebe as worshipped at
                    Phlius. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. s. μ.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
