<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0524-0505-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DUCIS, Jean François</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 505</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:897549">Dramatists</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1181638">Writing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vs7f">Dramatists</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n524/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DUCIS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jean François</hi></label>
                    (August 22, 1733-March 31, 1816), a French dramatic poet, famous more especially
                    for his adaptations of Shakespeare to the Parisian stage of the 18th century. He
                    was born and brought up at Versailles, where his father, originally from Savoy,
                    held the position of a respectable linen-draper; and all through life he
                    retained the simple tastes and straightforward independence fostered by his
                    bourgeois education. The friendship of Marshal Belleisle procured him an
                    appointment as clerk, and even after he ceased to discharge the duties of his
                    post secured the continuance of his salary. In 1768 the passion for the theatre
                    which had been growing within him during the previous years found vent in the
                    tragedy of <hi rend="italic">Amelise;</hi> and the failure of this first attempt
                    was fully compensated by the success of his <hi rend="italic">Hamlet</hi> in
                    1767, and of <hi rend="italic">Romeo and Juliette</hi> in 1772. <hi
                    rend="italic">Oedipe chez Admète,</hi> imitated partly from Euripides and partly
                    from Sophocles, appeared in 1778, and secured him in the following year the
                    chair in the Academy left vacant by the death of Voltaire. Equally successful
                    was <hi rend="italic">Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Roi Lear</hi> in 1783, at the
                    representation of which the author received what was then the rare honour of
                    being called before the curtain. <hi rend="italic">Macbeth</hi> in 1783 did not
                    take so well, and <hi rend="italic">Jean sans Peur</hi> in 1791 was almost a
                    failure; but <hi rend="italic">Othello</hi> in 1792, supported by the acting of
                    Talma, obtained immense applause. The next appearance of the author was no
                    longer as an adapter or imitator of foreign models, but as a dramatist with a
                    plot and characters of his own contrivance.and invention; and though his
                    contrivance produced nothing more original than the old story of unlawful love
                    between brother and sister ultimately obtaining sanction by their supposed
                    kinship being disproved, the poetic charm of the verse and its vivid picturing
                    of desert life secured for <hi rend="italic">Abufar,</hi><hi rend="italic">ou la
                    famille arabe,</hi> a flattering reception. On the failure of a similar piece,
                    <hi rend="italic">Phédor</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Waldemar,</hi><hi rend="italic">ou la famille de Sibérie,</hi> Ducis ceased to
                    write for the stage; and the rest of his life was spent in quiet retirement at
                    Versailles. He had been named a member of the Council of the Ancients in 1798,
                    but he never discharged the functions of the office; and, when at a later date
                    Napoleon wished him to accept some post of honour under the empire, he escaped
                    from his solicitations by a happy <hi rend="italic">brusquerie,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> “General, do you like wild duck shooting Ί I am something
                    of a wild duck myself.” Amiable, religious, and bucolic, he had little sympathy
                    with the fierce, sceptical, and tragic times in which his lot was cast. “Alas !”
                    he said in the midst of the Revolution, “tragedy is abroad in the streets; if I
                    step outside of my door, I have blood to my very ankles. I have too often seen
                    Atreus in clogs, to venture to bring an Atreus on the stage.” Though actuated by
                    what seems to have been an honest and ardent admiration of the great English
                    dramatist, Ducis is not in any deep sense of the word Shakespearian. His
                    ignorance of the English language left him at the mercy of such translators as
                    Letourneur and La Place; and even this modified Shakespeare had still to undergo
                    a process of purification and correction before he could be presented to the
                    fastidious criticism of French taste. That such was the case was not, however,
                    the fault of Ducis; and his works, defective as they were, did good service in
                    modifying the judgment of his fellow countrymen. He did not pretend to
                    reproduce, but to excerpt and refashion; and consequently the French play
                    sometimes differs from its English namesake in everything almost but the name.
                    The plot is different, the characters are different, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >motif</hi> different, and the scenic arrangement different. The result is
                    really a new play, and a new play, be it said, with undoubted merits of its own.
                    <hi rend="italic">Le banquet</hi><hi rend="italic">de l'amitié,</hi> a poem in
                    four cantos, 1771, <hi rend="italic">Au</hi><hi rend="italic">Roi de
                    Sardaigne,</hi> 1775, <hi rend="italic">Discours de réception a l'académie
                    française, 1779,Épître à l'amitié,</hi> 1786, and a <hi rend="italic">Recueil de
                    Poésies,</hi> 1809, complete the list of Ducis’s publications. An edition of his
                    works in three volumes appeared in 1813; <hi rend="italic">Oeuvres
                    posthumes</hi> were edited by Campenon in 1826; and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hamlet,</hi><hi rend="italic">Oedipe chez Admète,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Macbeth,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Abufar</hi> are reprinted in vol. ii. of
                    Didot’s <hi rend="italic">Chefs</hi><hi rend="italic">d'oeuvre
                    tragiques.</hi></p>
                <p>See Campenon, <hi rend="italic">Essai</hi><hi rend="italic">de mémoires</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">sur Dueis,</hi> 1824; Onêsime Leroy, <hi rend="italic">Étude sur
                    la personne et les écrits</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Ducis,</hi> 1832, based on L'ucis’s own memoirs preserved in the library at
                    Versailles; Sainte-Beuve, <hi rend="italic">Causeries</hi><hi rend="italic">du
                    lundi,</hi> t. vi., and <hi rend="italic">Nouveaux</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >lundis,</hi> t. iv.; Villemain, <hi rend="italic">Tableau de la</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">litt,</hi><hi rend="italic">au</hi><hi rend="italic">X</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Ville, siècle.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
