<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0491-0472-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DROPSY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 472</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:928067">Fluids</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:953493">Heart</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1047771">Organisms</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1165047">Veins</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48w38662">Fluids</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v41r">Heart</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4br8mh3x">Organ</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qz22h3h">Veins</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n491/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DROPSY</label> (contracted from the old word <hi
                    rend="italic">hydropisy,</hi> from the Greek <hi rend="italic">v8pωψ—υ8ωp,</hi>
                    water, and <hi rend="italic">ωψ,</hi> the appearance) signifies a collection of
                    simple serous fluid in all or any of the cavities of the body, or in the meshes
                    of its tissues. Dropsy of the subcutaneous connective tissue is termed <hi
                    rend="italic">oedema</hi> when it is localized and limited in extent; when more
                    diffuse it is termed <hi rend="italic">anasarca;</hi> the term <hi rend="italic"
                    >oedema</hi> is also applied to dropsies of some of the internal organs, notably
                    to that of the lungs. <hi rend="italic">Hydrocephalus</hi> signifies an
                    accumulation of fluid within the ventricles of the brain or in the arachnoid
                    cavity; <hi rend="italic">hydrothorax,</hi> a collection of fluid in one or both
                    pleural cavities; <hi rend="italic">hydropericardium,</hi> in the pericardium;
                    <hi rend="italic">ascites,</hi> in the peritoneum; and, when <hi rend="italic"
                    >anasarca</hi> is conjoined with the accumulation of fluid in one or more of the
                    serous cavities, the dropsy is said to be general·</p>
                <p>Dropsy is essentially a symptom and not a specific disease, and ought not to be
                    confounded with inflammatory exudations of a serous character. The transudation
                    is a mere filtrate from the blood produced by increased intravascular pressure,
                    of local or general origin, and occurring through the walls of the capillaries
                    or smaller venules. Its specific gravity varies from 1Ό08 to 1’014; it is
                    alkaline, occasionally neutral, very rarely feebly acid; it is not the liquor
                    sanguinis, but merely water holding in solution a varying proportion of the
                    constituents of the blood serum, chiefly the saline constituents, and of these
                    notably the chloride of sodium, occasionally urea, sometimes cholestrine, always
                    more or less albumen, and a proportionate amount of fibrogenous matter. It may
                    be colourless, greenish or reddish from the presence of blood pigment, or
                    yellowish from the presence of bile pigment; transparent, or opalescent, or
                    milky from the presence of fatty matter derived from the chyle. The membrane
                    from which the dropsical fluid escapes is healthy, or at least not inflamed, and
                    only somewhat sodden by long contact with the fluid— the morbid condition on
                    which the transudation depends lying elsewhere. The occurrence of dropsy is
                    favoured by a watery condition of the blood due to imperfect nutrition, the
                    pre-occurrence of acute disease, or the long continuance of exhausting
                    discharges, as of albumen in Bright’s disease, &amp;c. This watery condition of
                    the blood not only predisposes to dropsy, but also lends active aid in producing
                    it by enfeebling the heart and thus disturbing the relations of the
                    intravascular pressure. The active agents in the production of dropsy are
                    whatever increases the intravenous blood pressure locally or generally.
                    Obstruction to the centripetal venous current by thrombosis of the veins, by the
                    pressure of hyperplasie connective tissue, as in hepatic cirrhosis, by the
                    pressure of tumours either pathological, as aneurisms, cancerous or tubercular
                    masses, or physiological, as a gravid uterus or a mass of faeces, or by the mere
                    weight of the body in certain positions, as the sedentary, are efficient causes
                    in the production of local dropsies. These are also more rarely brought about by
                    thrombosis, or compression of the lymphatics, or of the thoracic duct, and this
                    partly directly and partly indirectly by acting on the venous blood stream. The
                    active agents in the production of general dropsy aie diseases of the heart, the
                    lungs, and the kidneys. The natural tendency of all diseases of the heart is to
                    transfer the blood pressure from the arteries to the veins, and, so soon as this
                    has reached a sufficient degree, dropsy in the form of local <hi rend="italic"
                    >oedema</hi> commences to appear at whatever may be the most depending part of
                    the body—the instep and ankle in the upright position, the lower part of the
                    back or the lungs if the patient be in bed—and this tends gradually to increase
                    till all the cavities of the body are invaded by the serous accumulation. The
                    diseases of the lungs which produce dropsy are those which obstruct the passage
                    of the blood through them, such as emphysema and bronchitis, and thus act
                    precisely like disease of the heart in transferring the blood pressure from the
                    arteries to the veins, inducing dropsy in exactly a similar manner. The diseases
                    of the kidney which give rise to dropsy are those in which there is more or less
                    obstruction to the secretion of the watery and saline constituents of the urine,
                    accompanied by a more or less free escape of albumen; these are the acute
                    congestive form of nephritis following scarlet fever, the inflammatory or
                    intratubular form of chronic Bright’s disease, and the final stage of amyloid
                    degeneration. In the two former the dropsy is often very considerable, and in
                    the absence of cardiac disease will be found to appear first about the loose
                    cellular tissue surrounding the eyes, where the vessels, turgid with watery
                    blood, have less efficient support. Dropsy, though often a terminal and always a
                    serious symptom, is yet one which much can be done to ameliorate and in many
                    cases to remove, and this is particularly the case in many local dropsies and in
                    those of cardiac origin. Lung, kidney, and hepatic dropsies are less amenable to
                    treatment; yet one case of ascites is on record in which a perfect recovery took
                    place after the woman had been tapped 133 timee, and nearly 400 gallons of fluid
                    removed. Diuretics and purgatives are the remedies chiefly employed; but in
                    certain cases diaphoretics and especially the use of a hot air bath are very
                    effectual, and in a large number paracentesis or tapping is either
                    indispensable, or at all events much expedites the cure.</p>
                <p>It may be well to mention that there are certain affections which may be termed
                    <hi rend="italic">spumous dropsies,</hi> such as <hi rend="italic">ovarian
                    dropsy,</hi> which is only a cystic disease of the ovary; <hi rend="italic"
                    >hydrometma,</hi> dropsy of the uterus, due to inflammatory occlusion of the os
                    uteri; <hi rend="italic">hydronephrosis,</hi> dropsy of the kidney, due to
                    obstruction of the ureter, and subsequent distention of these organs by serous
                    accumulations; other hollow organs may also be similarly affected. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(g. w. b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
