<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0549-0530-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DUMOURIEZ, Charles François</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 530</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2md37">Missions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z5k">Pensions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1057086">Pensions</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1023771">Missions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:899352">Dues</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1053705">Parks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n549/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DUMOURIEZ, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles François</hi></label>
                    (1739-1823), general of the French republican army, was bora at Cambray in 1739
                    of a respectable family of Provençe. His father was a commissary of the royal
                    army, and had acquired some celebrity as a poet; and from him young Dumouriez
                    received his earliest instructions. His studies were con-tιnued<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n550/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0550-0531"/> at the college of Louis-le-Grande for three
                    years. In 1757, his father having been attached to the army under D’Estrées
                    about to invade Hanover, he accompanied him to Mauberge, and served with
                    distinction during the Seven Years’ War. In 1763 he attained the rank of
                    captain; but, in consequence of a reform reducing the numbers of the army, he
                    retired with a small pension and the cross of St Louis. He afterwards received a
                    subordinate situation in the secret service.</p>
                <p>On his return from a pedestrian tour in Italy, he addressed a memorial to the Due
                    de Choiseul, urging him to embrace the cause of the Corsicans against the
                    Genoese; and a public audience which he had with the minister on the subject led
                    to a violent altercation, the result of which was a <hi rend="italic"
                    >lettre</hi><hi rend="italic">de cachet</hi> which forced Dumouriez to leave
                    France. But the expedition which he had advised being afterwards resolved on,
                    Choiseul made him an honourable public reparation, and appointed him
                    quartermaster-general of the troops. The political conjunctures of the times
                    offered an unlimited scope for his fertility in diplomatic expedient, and he
                    mingled in all the intrigues of the age. In 1770 he was sent on a secret mission
                    to Poland with the view of neutralizing the efforts of Catherine II., and
                    succeeded in seeming fifty senators for the cause of independence, effected a
                    unity of action among the confederates, and disciplined a militia; but, when
                    there was some appearance of the resurrection of Poland being effected, Choiseul
                    lost his place, owing to the machinations of the Due d’Aiguillon and Madame Du
                    Barry, and Dumouriez was recalled to Paris. He was soon, however, sent back on a
                    similar mission by D’Aiguillon. He endeavoured to assist the revolutionists in
                    Sweden, and to raise troops in the Hanse towns to menace Stockholm, but this was
                    contrary to the views of the French cabinet; and the Due d’Aiguillon. having
                    discovered his project, had him arrested and imprisoned in the Bastille for six
                    months. He was afterwards sent to the castle of Caen, from which he was not
                    released until the accession of Louis XVI.</p>
                <p>Dumouriez had naturally little inclination to resume the connection with foreign
                    politics which had proved so dangerous, and he accordingly devoted his attention
                    to the iuternal economy of his own country. He wrote a memoir on the great
                    importance that might be given to the harbour of Cherbourg, one result of which
                    was that he was appointed governor of the place in 1778.</p>
                <p>In 1788 Dumouriez w as promoted to the rank of majorgeneral. When the
                    revolutionary movement began he pronounced in favour of political reform without
                    breaking with the court. The connections which he held with the leading men of
                    the Girondist party greatly advanced his political career. At the opening of the
                    second legislative assembly he was appointed minister for foreign affairs in
                    place of Delessart, but he held the position for only three months. During his
                    short tenure of office he exerted himself to the utmost in reforming abuses, and
                    in introducing the greatest economy into every department.</p>
                <p>He held for one month the office of minister of war after the dismissal of his
                    colleagues Roland, Servan, and Clavière. At length his own resignation followed,
                    which increased his popularity. When the troops of the coalition advanced
                    against France, he was appointed to the command of the army of the north as
                    lieutenant-general under Marshal Luckner. He made a determined stand against the
                    advance of die allies, which was decisively checked by the defeat inflicted on
                    them at Valmy on the 20th September 1792. This was followed by a campaign in the
                    Austrian Netherlands, in which Dumouriez was uniformly successful, until he was
                    signally defeated by Coburg in the battle of Neerwinden in January 1793. The
                    execution of Louis had estranged him from the republican party; and, when in
                    consequence of his defeat he was recalled by the Convention and threatened with
                    a charge of treason, he sought refuge in the camp of the Austrians, accompanied
                    by the Due de Chartres (afterwards Louis Philippe) and his brother.</p>
                <p>Lost without hope of return to his native country, Dumouriez wandered a long time
                    an exile in Brussels, England, Switzerland, Germany, Denmark, and St Petersburg.
                    At last in 1804 he took up his permanent residence in England, where the
                    Government conferred on him a pension of £1200 a year. In 1814 and 1815 he
                    endeavoured to procure from Louis XVIII. the baton of a marshal of France, but
                    was refused. He died at Turville Park, near Henley-on-Thames, on the 14th March
                    1823. His memoirs, written by himself, were published at Hamburg in 1794. An
                    enlarged edition, under the title <hi rend="italic">La</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Vie</hi><hi rend="italic">et les Mémoires</hi><hi rend="italic">du General
                    Dumouriez,</hi> appeared at Paris in 1822. Dumouriez was also the author of a
                    large number of political pamphlets.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
