<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0381-0364-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DONNE, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 364</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw1m">Martyrs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz36">Inns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1010918">Martyrs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1432098">Soul</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n381/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DONNE, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1573-1631),
                    poet and divine of the reign of James I., was born in London in 1573 of Catholic
                    parents. His father was a wealthy and influential merchant, a Welshman by
                    descent; his mother claimed relationship with Sir Thomas More and Heywood the
                    epigrammatist. Brought up under a tutor at home until his tenth year, he
                    proceeded to Oxford, and was entered at Hart Hall about 1583. At the university
                    his learning was extraordinary, and he was compared, for juvenile erudition,
                    with Pico della Mirandola. In 1587 he was removed to Trinity College, Cambridge,
                    but he took no degree there or at Oxford, his scruples as a Catholic standing in
                    the way. In 1590 he went up to London and was admitted into Lincoln’s Inn. His
                    father presently died, and left his son £3000. Until he came of age, he was
                    under his mother’s care, and it is supposed that this was the period to which he
                    refers in <hi rend="italic">Pseudo-Martyr,</hi> in which an increasing
                    conviction of the truth of Protestantism struggled with the old faith and the
                    familiar surroundings. Walton has given an interesting account of Donne’s change
                    of faith, which probably took place about 1592. Before this he must have been
                    writing, for many of the <hi rend="italic">Divine Poems,</hi> and of these not
                    the worst, are obviously written by a sincere Catholic. The rebound from
                    Catholic asceticism was a severe trial to an ardent nature; it seems that he
                    plunged into various excesses, and that his father’s legacy was rapidly
                    squandered. In 1593, however, he had already laid the foundation of his poetic
                    reputation. The first three of his famous <hi rend="italic">Satires</hi> exist
                    in a MS. dated 1593, and the rest appear to have been composed at various times
                    before 1601. In 1594 he commenced his travels, wandering over Europe, and
                    accompanying the earl of Essex at the taking of Cadiz in 1596, and again in the
                    expedition of 1597. It has been thought that he was engaged in military service
                    in Holland in 1596. He did not return to England until he had seen Italy, and
                    was planning an excursion into Palestine, when the difficulty of travelling in
                    the East diverted his thoughts to Spain, In both Italy and Spain he took
                    considerable pains to master the language and existing literature of each
                    country, as the notes to his works testify. It is possible that the fantastic
                    Spanish school of conceits, which takes its name from Gongora, may have affected
                    the style of Donne. Returning to England, he secured the patronage of Sir Thomas
                    Egerton, afterwards Lord Chancellor Ellesmere, who appointed him his chief
                    private secretary, aud took so much delight in his company and conversation that
                    he made him lodge under his roof. The young poet was five years in Egerton’s
                    house, with every prospect of a successful career. He had the misfortune,
                    however, to fall in love with the daughter of Sir George More of Loxly, lord
                    lieutenant of the Tower, who was visiting in the house. Donne’s love was
                    returned, but her father violently objected. Recalling her to Loxly, he was
                    enraged to find that the young couple had already been privately married. In his
                    anger, Sir George More not only persuaded Lord Ellesmere to dismiss his
                    secretary, but threw Donne, with his friend Christopher Brooke, the poet, who
                    had given the bride away, into prison. They were soon released, but the father
                    was inexorable, and the young couple would have suffered from penury if it had
                    not been for the generosity of Sir Francis Wooley, who invited them to reside at
                    his house. During these later years Donne had written much in prose and verse.
                    He had completed his <hi rend="italic">Satires,</hi> and in 1601 he had written
                    his extraordinary poem of <hi rend="italic">The Progress of the Soul,</hi> which
                    De Quincey has so warmly praised. In 1602 ten sonnets, addressed to Philomel,
                    were printed in Davison’s <hi rend="italic">Poetical Rhapsody.</hi> It is
                    probable that many of his miscellaneous elegies and lyrics date from the same
                    period of early manhood. Among his early works, too, we know was the singular
                    treatise called Btα0αvατoς, in praise of suicide, of which he was afterwards
                    ashamed, and which was not printed until long after his death, in 1648. The
                    early follies of his career were now, however, played out, and his temperament
                    was become so grave and earnest that it attracted the attention of Morton,
                    afterwards bishop of Durham, who was staying in the house of Sir Francis Wooley
                    in 1607, and who offered the poet certain preferment in the church, if he would
                    only consent to take holy orders. Donne, however, had conscientious scruples
                    against taking such a step. His generous patron soon after died, and the Donnes
                    took a house at Mitcham, where they resided for two years. It was here that in
                    1610 he published his prose work against the Catholics, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pseudo-Martyr,</hi> and in 1611 a still more bitter polemical treatise,’ <hi
                    rend="italic">Ignatius his Conclave.</hi> In 1611, moreover, appeared Donne’s
                    first poetical work, <hi rend="italic">The Anatomy of the World,</hi> of which
                    revised and enlarged editions appeared in 1612, 1621, and 1625. This was but a
                    pamphlet, however. He was urged by Sir Robert Drury to come with his wife and
                    their eleven children to reside in his mansion in Drury Lane; after some demur
                    this offer was accepted, but when, almost immediately after their arrival, Sir
                    Robert desired Donne to travel on the Continent with him, Mrs Donne, who was in
                    feeble health, strongly objected. It seems almost certain that this objection
                    caused him to compose one of his loveliest poems—</p>
                <p>Sweetest Love, I do not go For weariness of thee.</p>
                <p>He permitted himself to be persuaded, however, and accompanied his patron to
                    Paris, where he is said to have had a vision of his wife, with her hair over her
                    shoulders, bearing a dead child in her arms, on the very night that Mrs Donne,
                    in London, was delivered of a still-born infant. This was in 1612. In 1613 he
                    published <hi rend="italic">An Elegy on the Death of Prince Henry.</hi> Efforts
                    were made to gain him preferment at court, but James I., who had conceived a
                    high opinion of Donne’s theological gifts, refused to give him a single post out
                    of the church. The poet’s scruples were at last removed, and in 1614 he preached
                    in orders before the king at Whitehall. Within a single year fourteen good
                    livings were offered to him; but he refused them all, simply accepting the post
                    of lecturer at Lincoln’s Inn. In 1617 the death of his wife was a blow under
                    which his health <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n382/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0382-0365"/> so far suffered that he was persuaded by his
                    friends to go abroad, and to spend more than a year in Germany. In 1619 he
                    returned, with the expectation of the deanery of Can - terbury. This he did not
                    gain, but in 1620 he was appointed dean of St Paul’s. To the kindness of the
                    earl of Dorset he owed the vicarage of St Dunstan in the West. In 1624 he was
                    elected prolocutor to Convocation, and the same year was attacked by an illness
                    that threatened to prove immediately fatal, but from which he rallied. He
                    continued in feeble health for some years, and preached for the last time before
                    Lent 1630, an oration which the king called “the Dean’s own funeral sermon,” and
                    which was printed, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Death's Duel,</hi> in
                    1632. On the 31st of March 1631, he died, having previously wrapped himself in
                    his winding sheet to have his portrait taken. He was buried in St Paul’s
                    cathedral. Very few of Dr Donne’s writings were published during his life-time.
                    It is supposed that an edition of the <hi rend="italic">Satires</hi> may have
                    been printed before the close of the 16th century, but if so, it has entirely
                    disappeared. His poems were first collected in 1633, and afterwards in
                    1635,1639, 1649, 1650,1654, and 1669, of which editions the second and last
                    appear to be tolerably trustworthy. Of his prose works the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Juvenilia</hi> appeared in 1633; the <hi rend="italic">LXXX. Sermons,</hi> with
                    an admirable life of the author by Izaak Walton, in 1640; the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Essays in Divinity</hi> in 1650; and the <hi rend="italic">Letters to Several
                    Persons of Honour</hi> in 1651. No very excellent modern biography of the poet
                    or edition of his works has been issued. Dr A. B. Grosart’s privately printed
                    edition of the poetical works is very complete.</p>
                <p>It is singularly difficult to pronounce a judicious opinion on the writings of
                    Donne. They were excessively admired by his own and the next generation, praised
                    by Dryden, paraphrased by Pope, and then entirely neglected for a whole century.
                    The first impression of an unbiassed reader who dips into the poems of Donne is
                    unfavourable. He is repulsed by the intolerably harsh and crabbed versification,
                    by the recondite choice of theme and expression, and by the oddity of the
                    thought. In time, however, he perceives that behind the fantastic garb of
                    language there is an earnest and vigorous mind, an imagination that harbours
                    fire within its cloudy folds, and an insight into the mysteries of spiritual
                    life which is often startling. Donne excels in brief flashes of wit and beauty,
                    and in sudden daring phrases that have the full perfume of poetry in them. Some
                    of his lyrics and one or two of his elegies excepted, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Satires</hi> are his most important contribution to literature. They are
                    probably the first poems of their kind in the language, and they are full of
                    force and picturesqueness. Their obscure and knotty language only serves to give
                    peculiar brilliancy to the not uncommmon passages of noble perspicacity. To the
                    odd terminology of Donne’s poetic philosophy Dryden gave the name of
                    metaphysics, and Johnson, borrowing the suggestion, invented the title of the
                    metaphysical school to describe, not Donne only, but all the amorous and
                    philosophical poets who succeeded him, and who employed a similarly fantastic
                    language, and who affected odd figurative inversions. <hi rend="smallcaps">(e.
                    w. g.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
