<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0214-0197-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DIEPENBECK, Abraham van</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 197</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1103083">Sacraments</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1164079">Vans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:825039">Bachelors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:943029">Glass</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:949055">Guilds</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg1r">Bachelors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kn24">Glass</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04774">Representation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n214/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DIEPENBECK, <hi rend="smallcaps">Abraham van</hi></label>
                    (1599-1675), was born at Herzogenbusch, and studied painting at Antwerp, where
                    he became one of Rubens’s “hundred pupils.” Rubens complains in his letters
                    that, being overwhelmed with applications for apprentices’ indentures, he
                    refused to accept as disciples even the children of some of his best friends.
                    Diepenbeck was one of those who was fortunate enough to obtain admission to
                    Rubens’s workshop. But he was not one of the cleverest of Rubens’s followers,
                    and he succeeded, at the best, in imitating the style and aping the
                    peculiarities of his master. We see this in his earliest pictures—a portrait
                    dated 1629 in the Munich Pinakothek, and a Distribution of Alms of the same
                    period in the same <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n215/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0215-0198"/> collection. Yet even at this time there were
                    moments when Diepenbeck probably fancied that he might take another path. A
                    solitary copperplate executed with his own hand in 1630 represents a peasant
                    sitting under a tree holding the bridle of an ass, aud this is a minute and
                    finished specimen of the engraver’s art which shows that the master might at one
                    time have hoped to rival the animal draughtsmen who flourished in the schools of
                    Holland. However, large commissions now poured in upon him; he was asked for
                    altar-pieces, subject-pieces, aud pagan allegories. He was tempted to try the
                    profession of a glass-painter, and at last he gave up every other occupation for
                    the lucrative business of a draughtsman and designer for engravings. Most of
                    Diepenbeck’s important canvases are in Continental galleries. The best are the
                    Marriage of St Catherine at Berlin, and Mary with Angels Wailing over the Dead
                    Body of Christ in the Belvedere at Vienna, the first a very fair specimen of the
                    artist’s skill, the second a picture of more energy and feeling than might be
                    expected from one who knew more of the outer form than of the spirit of Rubens.
                    Then we have a fine Entombment at Brunswick, and St Francis Adoring the
                    Sacrament at the museum of Brussels, Clelia aud her Nymphs Flying from the
                    Presence and Pursuit of Porsenna in two examples at Berlin and Paris, and
                    Neptune and Amphitrite at Dresden. In all these compositions the drawing and
                    execution are after the fashion of Rubens, though inferior to Rubens in harmony
                    of tone and force of contrasted light and shade. Occasionally a tendency may be
                    observed to imitate the style of Vandyck, for whom, in respect of pictures,
                    Diepenbeck in his lifetime was frequently taken. But Diepenbeck spent much less
                    of his leisure on canvases than on glass-painting. Though he failed to master
                    the secrets of gorgeous tinting, which were lost, apparently for ever in the
                    16th century, he was constantly employed during the best years of his life in
                    that branch of his profession. In 1635 he finished forty scenes from the life of
                    St Francis of Paula in the church of the Minimes at Antwerp. In 1644 he received
                    payment for four windows in St Jacques of Antwerp, two of which are still
                    preserved, and represent the Virgins to whom Christ appears after the
                    Resurrection. The windows ascribed to him at St Gudule of Brussels are now
                    proved to have been executed from the cartoons of Theodore van Thulden. On the
                    occasion of his matriculation at Antwerp in 1638-9, Diepenbeck was registered in
                    the guild of St Luke as a glass-painter. He resigned his membership in the
                    Artist Club of the Violette in 1542, apparently because he felt hurt by a
                    valuation then made of drawings furnished for copper-plates to the engraver
                    Pieter de Jode. The earliest record of his residence at Antwerp is that of his
                    election to the brotherhood (Soda-lität) “of the Bachelors” in 1634. It is
                    probable that before this time he had visited Rome and London, as noted in the
                    work of Houbraken. In 1636 he was made a burgess of Antwerp. He married twice,
                    in 1637 and 1652. His death took place in December 1675, and his funeral was
                    celebrated at St Jacques of Antwerp on the 31st day of that month.</p>
                <p>Consult, besides earlier authorities, the Antwerp <hi rend="italic"
                    >Liggeτen.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
