<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0380-0363-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DONIZETTI, Gaetano</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 363</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw1m">Martyrs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1046191">Operas</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1110522">Sebastianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1010918">Martyrs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n380/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DONIZETTI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Gaetano</hi></label>
                    (1798-1848). There is a strange parallelism observable in the lives of the three
                    most celebrated Italian composers of the present century. Rossini, Bellini, and
                    Donizetti had no sooner established their reputations on the Italian stage than
                    they left their own country for Paris, at that time the centre of the musical
                    world. All three settled in France, and all three were anxious to adapt the
                    style of their music to the taste and artistic traditions of their adopted
                    country. The difference which exists between Rossini’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tell</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Semiramide</hi> may, although in a less
                    striking degree, be noticed between Donizetti’s <hi rend="italic">Fille du
                    Régiment</hi> and one of his earlier Italian operas. But here the parallel ends.
                    As regards artistic genius Donizetti can by no means be compared with his
                    illustrious countrymen. He has little of Bellini’s melancholy sweetness, less of
                    Rossini’s sparkle, and is all but devoid of spontaneous dramatic impulse. For
                    these shortcomings he atones by a considerable though by no means extraordinary
                    store of fluent melody, and by Lis rare skill in writing for the voice. The duet
                    in the last act of the <hi rend="italic">Favorita</hi> and the celebrated <hi
                    rend="italic">ensemble</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Lucia</hi> following upon the
                    signing of the contract, are masterpieces of concerted music in the Italian
                    style. These advantages, together with considerable power of humorous
                    delineation, as evinced in <hi rend="italic">Don Pasquale</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">L</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Elisir d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic"
                    >Amore,</hi> must account for the unimpaired vitality of many of his works on
                    the stage.</p>
                <p>The life of Donizetti may be told in few words. He was born at Bergamo in 1798,
                    the son of a Government official of limited means. Originally destined for the
                    bar, he showed at an early age a strong taste for art. At first, strangely
                    enough, he mistook architecture for his vocation, and only after an unsuccessful
                    trial in that direction did he discover his real talent. He entered the
                    conservatoire of his native city, where he studied under Simon Mayr, the fertile
                    operatic composer. His second master was Mattei, the headmaster of the
                    celebrated music school of Bologna, where Donizetti resided for three years.
                    After his return to Bergamo the young composer determined to devote himself to
                    dramatic music, but his father insisted upon his giving lessons with a view to
                    immediate gain. The disputes arising from this cause ultimately led to
                    Donizetti’s enlisting in the army. But this desperate step proved beneficial
                    against all expectation. The regiment wäs quartered at Venice, and here the
                    young composer’s first dramatic attempt, an opera called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Enrico Comte di Borgogna,</hi> saw the light in 1818. The success of this work,
                    and of a second opera brought out in the following year, established Donizetti’s
                    reputation. He obtained his discharge from the army, and henceforth his operas
                    followed each other in rapid and uninterrupted succession at the rate of three
                    or four a year. Although he had to contend successively with two such dangerous
                    rivals as Rossini and Bellini, he succeeded in taking firm hold of the public,
                    and the brilliant reception accorded to his <hi rend="italic">Anna Bolena</hi>
                    at Milan carried his name beyond the limits of his own country. In 1835
                    Donizetti went for the first time to Paris, where, however, his <hi
                    rend="italic">Marino Faliero</hi> failed to hold its own against Bellini’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Puritani,</hi> then recently produced at the Théâtre Italien. The
                    disappointed composer went to Naples, where the enormous success of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Lucia di Lammermoor</hi> consoled him for his failure in Paris.
                    For Naples he wrote a number of works, none of which is worth notice. In 1840
                    the censorship refused to pass his <hi rend="italic">Poliuto,</hi> an Italian
                    version of Corneille’s <hi rend="italic">Polyeucte,</hi> in consequence of which
                    the disgusted composer once more left his country for Paris. Here he produced at
                    the Opéra Comique his most popular opera, <hi rend="italic">La Fille</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">du Regiment,</hi> but again with little success. It was not till
                    after the work had made the round of the theatres of Germany and Italy that the
                    Parisians reconsidered their unfavourable verdict. A serious opera, <hi
                    rend="italic">Les Martyrs,</hi> produced about the same time with the <hi
                    rend="italic">Daughter of the Regiment,</hi> was equally unsuccessful<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n381/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0381-0364"/>, and it was reserved to <hi rend="italic"
                    >La</hi><hi rend="italic">Favorita,</hi> generally-considered as Donizetti’s
                    masterpiece, to break the evil spell. His next important work, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Linda di Chamounix,</hi> was written for Vienna, where it was received most
                    favourably in 1842, and the same success accompanied the production of <hi
                    rend="italic">Don Pasquale</hi> after Donizetti’s return to Paris in 1843. Soon
                    after this event the first signs of a fatal disease, caused to a great extent by
                    overwork, began to show themselves. The utter failure of <hi rend="italic">Don
                    Sebastian,</hi> a large opera produced soon after <hi rend="italic">Don
                    Pasquale,</hi> is said to have hastened the catastrophe. A paralytic stroke in
                    1844 deprived Donizetti of his reason; for four years he lingered on in <hi
                    rend="subscript"> ι</hi> a state of mental and physical prostration. A visit to
                    his country was proposed as a last resource, but he reached his native place
                    only to die there on April 1st, 1848. The sum total of his operas amounts to 64,
                    the more important of which have been mentioned in the course of this notice,
                    The large number of Donizetti’s works at the same time accounts for many of
                    their chief defects. His rapidity of working made all revision impossible. It is
                    said that he once wrote the instrumentation of a whole opera within thirty
                    hours, a time hardly sufficient, one would think, to put the notes on paper. And
                    yet it may be doubted whether more elaboration would have essentially improved
                    his work; for the last act of the <hi rend="italic">Favorita,</hi> infinitely
                    superior to the preceding ones, is also said to have been the product of a
                    single night.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
