<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0075-0064-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DE MORGAN, Augustus</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 64</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1002014">Logic</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:804885">Algebra</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1161461">Unitarians</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b40r9m368">Algebra</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b49z90c0c">Logic</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n75/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DE MORGAN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Augustus</hi></label>
                    (1806-1871), one of the most eminent mathematicians and logicians of his time,
                    was born June 1806, at Madura, in the Madras presidency. His father was Colonel
                    John De Morgan, employed in the East India Company’s service, and his
                    grandfather and great-grandfather had served under Warren Hastings. On the
                    mother’s side he was descended from James Dodson, F.R.S., author of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Anti-logarithmic Canon</hi> and other mathematical works of merit,
                    and a friend of Demoivre.</p>
                <p>Very shortly after the birth of Augustus, Colonel De. Morgan brought his wife,
                    daughter, and infant son to England, where he left them during a subsequent
                    period of service in India, dying in 1816 on his way home. Augustus, then ten
                    years of age, received his early education in several private schools, and
                    before the age of four <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n76/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0076-0065"/> teen years had learned Latin, Greek, and some
                    Hebrew, in addition to acquiring much general knowledge. At the age of sixteen
                    years aud a half he entered Trinity College, Cambridge, and studied mathematics,
                    partly under the tuition of Airy, subsequently the astronomer royal. In 1825 he
                    gained a Trinity scholarship. De Morgan’s attention was by no means confined to
                    mathematics, and his love of wide reading somewhat interfered with his success
                    in the mathematical tripos, in which he took the fourth place in 1827, before he
                    had completed his twenty-first year. He was prevented from taking his Μ. A.
                    degree, or from obtaining a fellowship, to which he would doubtless have been
                    elected, by his conscientious objection to signing the theological tests then
                    required from masters of arts and fellows at Cambridge. A strong repugnance to
                    any sectarian restraints upon the freedom of opinion was one of De Morgan’s most
                    marked characteristics throughout life.</p>
                <p>A career in his own university being closed against him, he entered Lincoln’s
                    Inn; but had hardly done so when the establishment, in 1828, of the university
                    of London, in Gower Street, afterwards known as University College, gave -him an
                    opportunity of continuing his mathematical pursuits. At the early age of
                    twenty-two years he gave his⅞ifirst lecture as professor of mathematics in a
                    college which he served with the utmost zeal and success for a third of a
                    century. His connection with the college, indeed, was interrupted in 1831, when
                    a disagreement with the governing body caused De Morgan and some other
                    professors to resign their chairs simultaneously. When, in 1836, his successor
                    Mr White was accidentally drowned, De Morgan was requested to resume the
                    professorship. It may be added that his choice of a literary and scientific
                    career was made against the advice of his relatives and friends, who, on his
                    entering Lincoln’s Inn, confidently anticipated for him a distinguished and
                    lucrative career at the bar.</p>
                <p>In 1837 De Morgan married Sophia Elizabeth, daughter of William Frend, a
                    Unitarian in faith, a mathematician and actuary in occupation, a notice of whose
                    life, written by his son-in-law, will be found in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                    Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</hi> (vol. v). Henceforward De
                    Morgan’s life is scarcely more than a record of his constant labours, and his
                    innumerable publications. As in the case of many scholars, the even tenor of his
                    life was unbroken by remarkable incidents. Surrounded by a growing family,
                    ultimately seven in number, he sought happiness in his home, in his library, and
                    in the energetic and vigorous discharge of his college duties. He seldom
                    travelled or enjoyed relaxation, and could with difficulty be induced to remain
                    many days from home.</p>
                <p>As a teacher of mathematics De Morgan was unrivalled. He gave instruction in the
                    form of continuous lectures delivered <hi rend="italic">extempore</hi> from
                    brief notes. The most prolonged mathematical reasoning, and the most intricate
                    formulae, were given with almost infallible accuracy from the resources of his
                    extraordinary memory. De Morgan’s writings, however excellent, give little idea
                    of the perspicuity and elegance of his <hi rend="italic">viva voce</hi>
                    expositions, which never failed to fix the attention of all who were worthy of
                    hearing him. Many of his pupils have distinguished themselves, and, through Mr
                    Todhunter and Mr Routh, he has had an important influence on the modern
                    Cambridge school. In addition to occasional extra courses, it was his habit to
                    give two lectures on each of the six week days throughout the working session of
                    thirty weeks or more. Each lecture was exactly one hour and a quarter in length,
                    and at the close a number of questions and problems were always given, to which
                    the pupils returned written answers. These were all corrected by the professor’s
                    own hand, and personal explanations given before or after the lecture.</p>
                <p>Although the best hours of the day were thus given to arduous college work, his
                    public labours in other directions were extensive. For thirty years he took an
                    active part in the business of the Royal Astronomical Society, editing its
                    publications, supplying obituary notices of members, and for 18 years acting as
                    one of the honorary secretaries. His work for this society alone, it is said,
                    would have been occupation enough for an ordinary man. He was also frequently
                    employed as consulting actuary, a business in which his mathematical powers,
                    combined with sound judgment and business-like habits, fitted him to take the
                    highest place.</p>
                <p>De Morgan’s mathematical writings contributed powerfully towards the progress of
                    the science. His memoirs on the “Foundation of Algebra,” in the 7th and 8th
                    volumes of the <hi rend="italic">Cambridge Philosophical Transactions,</hi>
                    contain some of the most important contributions which have been made to the
                    philosophy of mathematical method; and Sir W. Rowan Hamilton, in the preface to
                    his <hi rend="italic">Lectures on Quaternions,</hi> refers more than once to
                    those papers as having led and encouraged him in the working out of the new
                    system of quaternions. The work on <hi rend="italic">Trigonometry and Double
                    Algebra,</hi> published by De Morgan in 1849, contains in the latter part a most
                    luminous and philosophical view of existing and possible systems of symbolic
                    calculus. But De Morgan’s influence on mathematical science in England can only
                    be estimated by a review of his long series of publications, which commence, in
                    1828, with a translation of part of Bourdon’s <hi rend="italic">Elements of
                    Algebra,</hi> prepared for his students. In 1830 appeared the first edition of
                    his well-known <hi rend="italic">Elements of Arithmetic,</hi> which has been
                    widely used in schools, and has done much to raise the character of elementary
                    training. It is distinguished by a simple yet thoroughly philosophical treatment
                    of the ideas of number and magnitude, as well as by the introduction of new
                    abbreviated processes of computation, to which De Morgan always attributed much
                    practical importance. Second and third editions were called for in 1832 and
                    1835, and more than 20,000 copies have been sold; the book is still in use, a
                    sixth edition having been issued in 1876.</p>
                <p>De Morgan’s other principal mathematical works were <hi rend="italic">The
                    Elements of Algebra,</hi> 1835, a valuable but somewhat dry elementary treatise;
                    the <hi rend="italic">Essay on Probabilities,</hi> 1838, forming the 107th
                    volume of <hi rend="italic">LardnePs Cyclopaedia,</hi> still much used, being
                    probably the best simple introduction to the theory in the English language; and
                    <hi rend="italic">The Elements of Trigonometry and Trigonometrical Analysis,
                    preliminary to the Differential Calculus,</hi> 1837.</p>
                <p>Several of his mathematical works were published by the Society for the Diffusion
                    of Useful Knowledge, of which De Morgan was at one time an active member. Among
                    these may be mentioned the great <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Differential
                    and Integral Calculus,</hi> 1842, which still remains the most extensive and
                    complete English treatise on the subject; the <hi rend="italic">Elementary
                    Illustrations of the Differential and Integral Calculus,</hi> first published in
                    1832, but often bound up with the larger treatise; the valuable essay, <hi
                    rend="italic">On the Study and Difficulties of Mathematics,</hi> 1831; and a
                    brief treatise on <hi rend="italic">Spherical Trigonometry,</hi> 1834. By some
                    accident the work on probability in the same series, written by Lubbock and
                    Drinkwater-Bethune was attributed to De Morgan, an error which seriously annoyed
                    his nice sense of bibliographical accuracy. For fifteen years he did all in his
                    power to correct the mistake, and finally wrote to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Times</hi> to disclaim the authorship. (See <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                    Notices</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> qì</hi> the Royal Astronomical Society,
                    vol. xxvi. p. 118.)</p>
                <p>Two of his most elaborate treatises are to be found in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Encydopaedia</hi><hi rend="italic">Metropolitana,</hi> namely the articles on
                    the <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n77/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0077-0066"/> Calculus of Functions, and the Theory of
                    Probabilities. The former article contains a profound investigation into the
                    principles of symbolic reasoning; the latter is still the most complete
                    mathematical treatise on the subject in the English language, giving as it does
                    a resumé of Laplace’s <hi rend="italic">Théorie Analytique des
                    Probabilités.</hi> De Morgan’s minor mathematical writings are scattered over
                    various periodicals; five papers will be found in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cambridge Mathematical Journal,</hi> ten in the <hi rend="italic">Cambridge and
                    Dublin Mathematical Journal,</hi> several in the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical
                    Magazine,</hi> while others of more importance are printed in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Cambridge Philosophical Transactions.</hi> A list of these and
                    other papers will be found in the <hi rend="italic">Royal Society's
                    Catalogue,</hi> which contains 42 entries under the name of De Morgan.</p>
                <p>In spite of the excellence and extent of his mathematical writings, it is
                    probably as a logical reformer that De Morgan will be best known to future
                    times. In this respect he stands alongside of his great contemporaries Hamilton
                    and Boole, as one of several independent discoverers of the all-important
                    principle of the quantification of the predicate. Unlike most mathematicians, De
                    Morgan always laid much stress upon the importance of logical training. In his
                    admirable papers upon the modes of teaching arithmetic and geometry, originally
                    published in the <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Journal of Education</hi>
                    (reprinted in <hi rend="italic">The Schoolmaster,</hi> vol ii.), he remonstrated
                    against the neglect of logical doctrine. In 1839 he produced a small work called
                    <hi rend="italic">First Notions of Logic,</hi> giving what he had found by
                    experience to be much wanted by students commencing with <hi rend="italic"
                    >Euclid.</hi></p>
                <p>In October 1846 he completed the first of his original investigations, in the
                    form of a paper printed in the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Cambridge
                    Philosophical Society</hi> (vol. viii. No. 29). In this paper the principle of
                    the quantified predicate was referred to, and there immediately ensued a
                    memorable controversy with Sir W. Hamilton regarding the independence of De
                    Morgan’s discovery, some communications having passed between them in the autumn
                    of 1846. The details of this dispute will be found by those interested in the
                    original pamphlets, in the <hi rend="italic">A tkenaeum</hi> newspaper, or in
                    the appendix to De Morgan’s <hi rend="italic">Formal Logic.</hi> Suffice it to
                    say that the independence of De Morgan’s discovery was subsequently recognized
                    by Hamilton, and that those acquainted with De Morgan’s character could never
                    suppose that it was otherwise. Moreover, the eight forms of proposition adopted
                    by De Morgan as the basis of his system partially differ from those which
                    Hamilton derived from the quantified predicate. The general character of De
                    Morgan’s development of logical forms was wholly peculiar and original on his
                    part.</p>
                <p>Not a year passed before De Morgan, late in 1847, published his principal logical
                    treatise, called <hi rend="italic">Formal Logic, or the Calculus of Inference,
                    Necessary and Probable.</hi> This contains a reprint of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >First Notions,</hi> an elaborate development of his doctrine of the syllogism,
                    and of the numerically definite syllogism, together with chapters of great
                    interest on probability, induction, old logical terms, and fallacies. The
                    severity of the treatise is relieved by characteristic touches of humour, and by
                    quaint anecdotes and allusions furnished from his wide reading and perfect
                    memory.</p>
                <p>There followed at intervals, in the years 1850, 1858, 1860, and 1863, a series of
                    four elaborate memoirs on the “Syllogism,” printed in volumes ix. and x. of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Cambridge Philosophical Transactions.</hi> These papers taken
                    together constitute a great treatise on logic, in which he substituted improved
                    systems of notation, and developed a new logic of relations, and anew onymatic
                    system of logical expression. Apart, however, from their principal purpose,
                    these memoirs are replete with acute remarks, happy illustrations, and abundant
                    proofs of De Morgan’s varied learning. Unfortunately these memoirs are
                    accessible to few readers, otherwise they would form invaluable reading for the
                    logical student. In 1860 De Morgan endeavoured to render their contents better
                    known by publishing a <hi rend="italic">Syllables of a Proposed System of
                    Logic,</hi> from which may be obtained a good idea of his symbolic system, but
                    the more readable and interesting discussions contained in the memoirs are of
                    necessity omitted. The article “Logic” in the <hi rend="italic">English
                    Cyclopaedia</hi> (1860) completes the list of his logical publications.</p>
                <p>Throughout his logical writings De Morgan was led by the idea that the followers
                    of the two great branches of exact science, logic and mathematics, had made
                    blunders,— the logicians in neglecting mathematics, and the mathematicians in
                    neglecting logic. He endeavoured to reconcile them, and in the attempt showed
                    how many errors an acute mathematician could detect in logical writings,· and
                    how large a field there was for discovery. But it may be doubted whether De
                    Morgan’s own system, “horrent with mysterious spiculae,” as Hamilton aptly
                    described it, is fitted to exhibit the real analogy between quantitative and
                    qualitative reasoning, which is rather to be sought in the logical works of
                    Boole. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Boole,</hi> vol. iv. p. 47.)</p>
                <p>Perhaps the largest part, in volume, of De Morgan’s writings remains still to be
                    briefly mentioned.; it consists of detached articles contributed to various
                    periodical or composite works. During the years 1833-43, he contributed very
                    largely to the first edition of the <hi rend="italic">Penny Cyclopaedia,</hi>
                    writing chiefly on mathematics, astronomy, physics, and biography. His articles
                    of various length cannot be less in number than 850, as may be ascertained from
                    a signed copy in the British Museum, and they have been estimated to constitute
                    a sixth part of the whole <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia, of</hi> which they
                    formed perhaps the most valuable portion. He also wrote biographies of Newton
                    and Halley for Knight’s <hi rend="italic">British Worthies,</hi> various notices
                    of scientific men for the <hi rend="italic">Gallery of Portraits,</hi> and for
                    the uncompleted <hi rend="italic">Biographical Dictionary</hi> of the Useful
                    Knowledge Society, and at least seven articles in Smith’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography.</hi></p>
                <p>Some of De Morgan’s most interesting and useful minor writings are to be found in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Companions to the British A</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >lmanack,</hi> to which he contributed without fail one article each year from
                    1831 up to 1857 inclusive. In these carefully written papers he treats a great
                    variety of topics relating to astronomy, chronology, decimal coinage,
                    life-assurance, bibliography, and the history of science. Most of them are as
                    valuable now as when written.</p>
                <p>Among De Morgan’s miscellaneous writings may be mentioned his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Explanation of the Gnomonic Projection of the Sphere,</hi> 1836, including a
                    description of the maps of the stars, published by the Useful Knowledge Society;
                    his <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Globes, Celestial and Terrestrial,</hi>
                    1845; and his remarkable <hi rend="italic">Book of Almanacks,</hi> (second
                    edition 1871), which contains a series of 35 almanacks, so arranged with indices
                    of reference, that the almanack for any year, whether in old style or new, from
                    any epoch, ancient or modern, up to 2000 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> may be
                    found without difficulty, means being added for verifying the almanack and also
                    for discovering the days of new and full moon from 2000 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi> up to 2000 A.D. De Morgan expressly draws attention to the fact that
                    the plan of this book was that of Francaeur and Ferguson, but the plan was
                    developed by one who was an unrivalled master of all the intricacies of
                    chronology. The two best tables of logarithms, the small five-figure tables of
                    the Useful Knowledge Society (1839 and 1857), and Shroen’s Seven Figure-Table
                    (5th ed. 1865), were printed under De Morgan’s superintendence. Several works
                    edited by him will be found mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">British Museum
                    Catalogue.</hi> His numerous anonymous contributions through a long series of
                    years to the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum,</hi> and to <hi rend="italic">Notes
                    and Queries,</hi> and his occasional articles in the <hi rend="italic">North
                    British Review, Macmillan's Magazine, Ac.,</hi> must be passed over with this
                    bare mention.</p>
                <p>Considerable labour was spent by De Morgan upon the subject of decimal money. He
                    was a great advocate of the pound and mil scheme. His evidence on this subject
                    was sought by the Royal Commission, and, besides constantly supporting the
                    Decimal Association in periodical publications, he published several separate
                    pamphlets on the subject</p>
                <p>One marked character of De Morgan was his intense and yet reasonable love of
                    books. He was a true bibliophil, and loved to surround himself’, as far as his
                    means allowed, with curious and rarebooks. He revelled in all the mysteries of
                    watermarks, title pages, colophons, catch-words, and the like; yet he treated
                    biblio∙</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n78/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0078-0067"/>
                <p>graphy as an important science. As he himself wrote, “the most worthless book of
                    a bygone day is a record worthy of preservation; like a telescopic star, its
                    obscurity may render it unavailable for most-purposes; but it serves, in hands
                    which know how to use it, to determine the places of more important bodies.” His
                    evidence before the Royal Commission on the British Museum in 1850, (Questions
                    5704*-5815,* 6481-6513, and 8966-8967), should be studied by all who would
                    comprehend the principles of bibliography or the art of constructing a
                    catalogue, his views on the latter subject corresponding with those carried out
                    by Panizzi in the <hi rend="italic">British Museum Catalogue.</hi> A sample of
                    De Morgan’s bibliographical learning is to be found in his account of <hi
                    rend="italic">Arithmetical Books, from the Invention of Printing</hi> (1847),
                    and finally in his <hi rend="italic">Budget of Paradoxes.</hi> This latter work
                    consists of articles most of which were originally published in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Athenaeum,</hi> describing the various attempts which have been
                    made to invent a perpetual motion, to square the circle, or to trisect the
                    angle; but De Morgan took the opportunity to include many curious bits gathered
                    from his extensive reading, so that the <hi rend="italic">Budget</hi> as
                    reprinted by his widow (1872), with much additional matter prepared by himself,
                    forms a remarkable collection of scientific <hi rend="italic">ana.</hi> De
                    Morgan’s correspondence with contemporary scientific men was very extensive and
                    full of interest. It remains unpublished, as does also a large mass of
                    mathematical tracts which he prepared for the use of his students, treating all
                    parts of mathematical science, and embodying some of the matter of his lectures.
                    De Morgan s library was purchased by Lord Overstone, and presented to the
                    university of London.</p>
                <p>From the above enumeration it will be apparent that the extent of De Morgan’s
                    literary and scientific labours was altogether extraordinary; nor was quality
                    sacrificed to quantity. On the contrary every publication was finished with
                    extreme care and accuracy, and no writer can be more safely trusted in every
                    thing which he wrote. It is possible that his continual efforts to attain
                    completeness and absolute correctness injured his literary style, which is
                    wanting in grace; but the estimation in which his books are held is shown by the
                    fact that they are steadily rising in market price. Apart from his conspicuous
                    position as a logical and mathematical discoverer, we may conclude that hardly
                    any man of science in recent times has had a more extensive, though it may often
                    be an unfelt influence, upon the progress of exact and sound knowledge.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p> In a notice of De Morgan’s
                    character it is impossible to omit a reference to his witty sayings, some
                    specimens of which are preserved in Dr Sadler’s most interesting <hi
                    rend="italic">Diary of Henry Crabb Robinson</hi> (1869), which also contains a
                    humorous account of H. C. R. by De Morgan. It may be added that De Morgan was a
                    great reader and admirer of Dickens; he was also fond of music, and a fair
                    performer on the flute</p></note></p>
                <p>De Morgan has left no published indications of his opinions on religious
                    questions, in regard to which he was extremely reticent. He seldom or never
                    entered a place of worship, and declared that he could not listen to a sermon, a
                    circumstance perhaps due to the extremely strict religion? discipline under
                    which he was brought up. Nevertheless there is reason to believe that, he was of
                    a deeply religious dispositiou. Like Faraday and Newton he entertained a
                    confident belief in Providence, founded not on any tenuous method of inference,
                    but on personal feeling. His hope of a future life also was vivid to the
                    last.</p>
                <p>In the year 1866 a life as yet comparatively free from trouble became clouded by
                    the circumstances which led him to abandon the institution so long the scene of
                    his labours. The refusal of the council to accept the recommendation of the
                    senate, that they should appoint an eminent Unitarian minister to the
                    professorship of logic and mental philosophy, revived all De Morgan’s
                    sensitiveness on the subject of sectarian freedom; and, though his feelings were
                    doubtless excessive, there is no doubt that gloom was thrown over his life,
                    intensified in 1867 by the loss of his son George Campbell De Morgan, a young
                    man of the highest scientific promise, whose name, as De Morgan expressly
                    wished, will long be connected with the London Mathematical Society, of which he
                    was one of the founders. From this time De Morgan rapidly fell into ill-health,
                    previously almost unknown to him, dying on the 18th March 1871. An interesting
                    and truthful sketch of his life will be found in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                    Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society,</hi> for the 9th February 1872, vol.
                    xxii. p. 112, written by Mr Ranyard, who says, “He was the kindliest, as well as
                    the most learned of men—benignant to every one who approached him, never
                    forgetting the claims which weakness has on strength.’’ (w. s. J.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
