<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0482-0463-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DREDGING (9th edition, volume 7, page 463)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tw1v">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q67d">Costs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j960b1w">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880656">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:890865">Depositions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:863821">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1052348">Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n482/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DREDGING</label>. Dredging is the name given by engineers to
                    the process of excavating materials under water, raising them to the surface,
                    and depositing them in barges. It is a process which has been useful from very
                    early times in works of marine and hydraulic engineering, and it has of late
                    years, by improved appliances, been brought to high perfection.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bag and Spoon Dredge.—</hi> The first employment of machinery
                    to effect this object is, like the discovery of the canal lock, claimed alike
                    for Holland and Italy, in both of which countries dredging is believed to have
                    been practised before it was introduced into Britain. The Dutch at a very early
                    period used what is termed the “bag and spoon” dredge for cleaning their canals.
                    It was <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n483/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0483-0464"/> simply a ring of iron, about 2 feet in
                    diameter, flattened and steeled for about one-third of its circumference, having
                    a bag of strong leather attached to it by leathern thongs. The ring and bag were
                    fixed to a pole, which, on being used, was lowered to the bottom from the side
                    of a barge moored in the canal or river. A rope made fast to the iron ring was
                    then wound up by a windlass placed at the other end of the barge, and the spoon
                    was thus dragged along the bottom, and was guided in its progress by a man who
                    held the pole. When the spoon reached the end of the barge where the windlass
                    was placed, the winding was still continued, and the suspending rope being
                    nearly perpendicular, the bag was raised to the surface, bringing with it the
                    stuff excavated while it was being drawn along the bottom. The windlass being
                    still wrought, the whole was raised to the gunwale of the barge, and the bag,
                    being emptied, was again hauled back to the opposite end of the barge, and
                    lowered for another supply. This system is slow, and only adapted to a limited
                    depth of water and a soft bottom. But it has been generally employed in canals,
                    aud is much used in the Thames. The writer had occasion to use it at the
                    Fossdyke Canal, in Lincolnshire, where 135,000 tons were raised in the manner
                    described.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Dredging by Bucket between two Lighters.—</hi> Another plan,
                    practised at an early period in rivers of considerable breadth, was to moor two
                    large barges, one on each side; between them was slung an iron dredging bucket,
                    which was attached to both barges by chains wound round the barrels of a crab
                    wincn worked by six men in one barge, and round a simple windlass, worked by two
                    men in the other. The bucket, being lowered at the side of the barge carrying
                    the windlass, was drawn across the bottom of the river by the crab winch on the
                    other barge; and, having been raised and emptied, it was hauled across by the
                    opposite windlass for a repetition of the process. This plan was in use in the
                    Tay till 1833.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Steam Dredges.—</hi> In all large operations these and other
                    primitive appliances have now, as is well known, been superseded by the steam
                    dredge, which was first employed, it is believed, in deepening the Wear at
                    Sunderland about the year 1796. The Sunderland machine was made for Mr Grimshaw
                    by Boulton and Watt. Receiving improvements from Mr Hughes, Mr Rennie, Mr
                    Jessop, and others, the steam dredge, as now generally constructed, is a most
                    powerful machine in skilful hands, excavating and raising materials from depths
                    of 15 to upwards of 30 feet of water according to the size of the machinery, at
                    a cost not very different from, and in some cases even less than, that at which
                    the same work could be performed on dryland.</p>
                <p>As to the kind of work that may be accomplished by dredging, it may be stated
                    that almost all materials, excepting solid rock or very large boulders, may now
                    be dredged with ease. Loose gravel is probably the most favourable material to
                    work in; but a powerful dredge will readily break up and raise indurated beds of
                    gravel, clay, and boulders, and even find its way through the surface of soft
                    rock, though it will not penetrate very far into it. In such cases it is usual
                    to alternate on the bucket-frame a bucket for raising the stuff, with a rake or
                    pronged instrument for disturbing the bottom. The writer in his own' experience
                    has raised boulders weighing upwards of a ton with a powerful dredge of the
                    ordinary construction, and removed disintegrated or rotten rock at least to a
                    limited depth, and he believes that in many cases the surfaces of submerged
                    rocks may, by means of such appliances, be to some extent broken up and removed,
                    so as to obtain in certain situations a considerable increase of depth, without
                    recourse to cofferdams, which involve great expense.</p>
                <p>The construction of large river steam dredges is now carried on by many
                    engineering firms. The main feature of the machineis the buck et-lad der,
                    whichis lowered through an ark formed in the vessel till it reaches the bottom.
                    Along this ladder a series of buckets traverse which cut into the bottom at the
                    lower extremity of the ladder and return loaded with the excavated material,
                    which is discharged at the top of the bucket-ladder into a lighter or barge
                    prepared for its reception. The machines are sometimes made with single and
                    sometimes with double ladders, sometimes discharging at the stem of the vessel
                    and sometimes at both sides, but it is obviously impossible to give illustrative
                    drawings of the different forms of dredgers in sufficient detail to be
                    practically useful. It maybe stated that a first-class dredging machine to work
                    in 30 feet water, and discharge over either side, of 60 horse-power complete,
                    costs at present prices about £16,000 to £18,000. The steam hoppers employed to
                    receive and remove the dredgings carry about 500 tons of excavations; they are
                    70 horsepower, and steam at about 9 miles per hour. The hopper barges are made
                    with opening hinged bottoms, which can be opened when the place of deposit is
                    reached, and the dredgings easily and quickly discharged. These steam barges
                    cost about £8000. Large dredges, such as those constructed by Messrs Wingate of
                    Glasgow for the Tyne and other places, will excavate at the rate of 460 tons per
                    hour when working on favourable ground.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hopper Dredge.—</hi> Some improvements that have been suggested
                    on the dredging plant hitherto used deserve notice. Among these may be mentioned
                    that of Messrs Simons &amp; Company, Renfrew, who have patented and constructed
                    what they have called a hopper-dredge, combining in itself the advantages of a
                    dredge for raising the material and a screw hopper vessel for conveying it to
                    the place of discharge, both which services are performed by the same engines
                    and the same crew. Messrs Simons have constructed seven hopper dredges on this
                    plan, varying from 200 to 1000 tons of “hopper capacity."</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Silt Dredge.</hi> —Another of the recently suggested
                    improvements is that by Mr C. Randolph, who, in 1870, proposed that, instead of
                    the ordinary dredging buckets, pipes should be lowered until they come into
                    contact with the sand or mud at the bottom. The tops of these pipes were to be
                    in communication with powerful centrifugal pumps, so that the velocity of the
                    in-flowing water through the pipes could be made so great as to carry with it a
                    large percentage of the sand or mud from the bottom; and when the solid matter,
                    and the water in which it is suspended, were raised to the desired height, they
                    would flow freely to any required place for deposit of the suspended material.
                    It is not known that this plan has been carried into practical operation.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Dredging at Amsterdam and Suez Canals.—</hi> Another
                    arrangement is that of raising the material by buckets in the ordinary way, and
                    thereafter receiving it in a vessel and floating'it off by pipes to the place of
                    deposit. This, of course, can only be done where the place of deposit is close
                    to the spot whence the material is dredged. Two plans have been proposed for
                    effecting this. One of these has been used in the Amsterdam Canal, where the
                    stuff is discharged from the buckets into a vertical cylinder, and is there
                    mingled with water by a revolving Woodford-pump and sent off under pressure to
                    the place of deposit in a semi-fluid state. At the Amsterdam Canal this was done
                    by pipes made of timber, and hooped with iron like barrels. These wooden
                    cylinders were made in lengths of about 15 feet, connected with leather joints,
                    and floated on the surface of the water, conveying the stuff to the requisite
                    distance, like the hose of a fire engine, under a head of pressure, it is
                    believed, of 4 or 5 feet, and depositing it over the banks of the canal. A
                    somewhat similar process was employed <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n484/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0484-0465"/> on the Suez Canal,—not, however, by using
                    pumps, but simply by running the stuff to the banks on steeply inclined shoots,
                    which were supplied with water when the material raised did not contain
                    sufficient water to cause it to run freely. It is obvious, however, that these
                    arrangements can only be applied in situations where the material to be
                    excavated is of a very soft nature, and where the place of deposit is close at
                    hand. In keeping clear the Suez Canal such appliances may be very useful, as the
                    soft deposit of the canal has only to be raised and projected over the banks on
                    either side.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">American Dredges.—</hi> Dredging in Canada and the United
                    States is done by what are called <hi rend="italic">Dipper</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Clam-shell</hi> dredges, the bucket dredge being seldom
                    used.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">dipper dredge</hi> consists of a barge, with a derrickcrane
                    reaching over the stern, suspending a large wroughtiron bucket which brings up
                    the dredged material. To the bucket is attached a pole 6 inches by 4 inches in
                    cross section, by which means it is guided while being drawn along the bottom;
                    it is then raised, and its bottom being made to drop open, the contents fall
                    into the barge moored alongside of the dredge. The bottom of the bucket is kept
                    closed by a catch, which, by means of a rope, can be withdrawn at the proper
                    moment. The <hi rend="italic">clamshell</hi> is a box made of two similar pieces
                    of wrought iron hinged together at one end; by a simple arrangement of the
                    gearing the clam, mouth open, drops down and sinks into the bottom, and the
                    first effect of heaving up is to close it, thus imprisoning a quantity of
                    material which is raised and deposited as in the case of the dipper. Both kinds
                    of dredges are worked by a steam-engine, and rough as they appear to be, they
                    are extensively employed in deepening and widening river channels, making or
                    deepening canals, and other such works.</p>
                <p>This is not the place to discuss the merits of different apparatus, which perhaps
                    can only be settled by the actual performance of different arrangements when
                    fully tested by practice. Having thus briefly noticed them, a few practical
                    observations on dredging, as more immediately applicable to British rivers, have
                    still to be mentioned.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Longitudinal and Cross Dredging.—</hi> In river dredging two
                    systems are pursued. One plan consists in excavating a series of longitudinal
                    furrows parallel to the axis of the stream, the other in dredging cross furrows
                    from side to side of the river. It is found that inequalities are left between
                    the longitudinal furrows when that system is practised, which do not occur, to
                    the same extent, in side or <hi rend="italic">cross dredging;</hi> and the
                    writer invariably finds cross dredging to leave the most uniform bottom. To
                    explain the difference between the two systems of dredging it may be stated that
                    in either case the dredge is moored from the head and stern by chains about 250
                    fathoms in length. These chains in improved dredges are wound round windlasses
                    worked by the engine, so that the vessel can be moved ahead or astern by simply
                    throwing them into or out of gear. In longitudinal dredging the vessel is worked
                    forward by the head chain, while the buckets are at the same time performing the
                    excavation, so that a longitudinal trench is made in the bottom of the river.
                    When the dredge has proceeded a certain length, it is stopped and permitted to
                    drop down and commence a new longitudinal furrow, parallel to the first one. In
                    cross-dredging, on the other hand, the vessel is supplied with two additional
                    moorings, one on each side; and these chains are, like the head and stem chains,
                    wound round barrels wrought by the engine. In commencing to work by cross
                    dredging we may suppose the vessel to be at one side of the channel to be
                    excavated. The bucket frame is set in motion, but, instead of the dredge being
                    drawn forward by the head chain, she is drawn to the opposite side of the river
                    by the side chain, and, having reached the extent of her work in that direction,
                    she is then drawn a few feet forward by the head chain, and, the bucket frame
                    being still in motion, the vessel is hauled across by the opposite chains to the
                    side whence she started. By means of this transverse motion of the dredge a
                    series of cross furrows is made; she takes out the whole excavation from side to
                    side as she goes on, and leaves no protuberances such as are found to exist
                    between the furrows of longitudinal dredging, even where it is executed with
                    great care. The two systems will be best explained by reference to fig. 1, where
                    A and B are the head and stern moorings, and C and D the side moorings; the arc
                    c∕ represents the course of the vessel in cross dredging; while in longitudinal
                    dredging, as already explained, she is drawn forward towards A, and again
                    dropped down to commence a new longitudinal furrow.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Blasting combined with Dredging.—</hi> In some cases, however,
                    the bottom is found to be too hard to be dredged until it has been to some
                    extent loosened and broken up. Thus at Newry, Mr Rennie, after blasting the
                    bottom in a depth of from 6 to 8 feet at low water, removed the material by
                    dredging at an expense of from 4s. to 5s. per cubic yard. The same process was
                    adopted by Messrs Stevenson at the bar of the Erne at Ballyshannon, where, in a
                    situation exposed to a heavy sea, large quantities of boulder stones were
                    blasted, and afterwards raised by a dredger worked by hand at a cost of 10s. 6d
                    per cubic yard.</p>
                <p>Sir William Cubitt also largely employed blasting in connection with dredging on
                    the Severn, of which an instructive account is given in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Minutes of Proceedings of the Institution of Civil Engineers,</hi> from
                    which the following particulars are taken :—</p>
                <p>“It appears that a succession of marl beds, varying from 100 yards to half a mile
                    in length, were found in the channel of the Severn, which proved too hard for
                    being dredged, the whole quantity that could be raised being only 50 or 60 tons
                    per day, while the machinery of the dredgers employed was constantly giving way.
                    Attempts were first made to drive iron rods into the marl bed, and to break it
                    up; a second attempt was made to loosen it by dragging across its surface an
                    instrument like a strong plough. But these plans proving unsuccessful, it was
                    determined to blast the whole surface to be operated on. The marl was very
                    dense, its weight being 146 lb per cubic foot;<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Clay weighs about 109 lb, and sandstone
                            about 155 lb per cubiα foot.</p></note> and it was determined to drill
                    perpendicular bores, 6 feet apart, to the depth of 2 feet below the level of the
                    bottom to be dredged out. The bores were made in the following manner, from
                    floating rafts moored in the river. Pipes of <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ⅛th
                    inch wrought iron, 3⅜ inches diameter, were driven a few inches into the marl.
                    Through these pipes holes were bored, first with a 1⅜ inch jumper, and then with
                    an auger. The holes were bored 2 feet below the proposed bottom of the dredging,
                    as it was expected that each shot would dislocate or break in pieces a mass of
                    marl of a conical form, of which the bore-hole would be the centre and its
                    bottom the apex; so that the adjoining shots would leave between them a
                    pyramidal piece of marl where the powder would have produced little or no
                    effect. By carrying the shot holes lower than the intended dredging, the apex
                    only of this pyramid was left to be removed; and in practice this was found <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n485/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0485-0466"/> to form but a small impediment. Fig. 2 is a
                    section of the boreholes, and fig. 3 a plan in which the inner dotted circles
                    represent the diameters of the broken spaoes at the level of the bottom of
                    dredging. The cartridges were formed, in the ordinary way, with canvas, and
                    fired with Bickford’s fuse. The weights of powder used for bore-holes of 4 feet,
                    4 feet 6 inches, ana 5 feet were respectively 2 lb, 3 lb, and 4 lb. The effect
                    of the shot was generally to lift the pipes—which were secured by ropes to
                    the</p>
                <p>τafts—a few inches. Mr Edwards says that not one in a hundred shots missed fire,
                    and these shots were generally saved by the following singular expedient :—The
                    pointed end of an iron bar, ⅞ inch diameter, was made red hot, and, being put
                    quickly through the water, and driven through the tamping as rapidly as
                    possible, was, in nine cases out of ten, sufficiently hot to ignite the
                    gunpowder and fire the shot.</p>
                <p>The cost of each shot is calculated as follows :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Use of material</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>...£0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Labour</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Pitched bag for charge</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>3 lb of powder at 5⅜d</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4⅛</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>15 ft. of patent fuse at ⅛ of a penny</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Pitch, tallow, twine, coals, &amp;c</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4⅛</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Cost per shot...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>...£0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Each shot loosened and prepared for dredging about four cubic yards, so that the
                    cost of blasting was Is. 9d. per yard. The cost of dredging the material, after
                    it had been thus prepared, was 2s. 3d., making the whole charge for removing the
                    marl 4s. per cubic yard.”</p>
                <p>One of the most recent successful combinations of blasting and dredging was that
                    completed in 1875 by Mr John Fowler of Stockton at the river Tees, to whom the
                    writer is indebted for the following particulars. The chief novelty was in the
                    barge upon which the machinery was fixed. It was 58 feet by 28 feet by 4 feet,
                    and had eight legs which were let down when the barge was in position. The legs
                    were then fixed to the barge, so that on the tide falling it became a fixed
                    platform from which the drilling was done. The holes were bored and charged, and
                    when the tide rose the legs were heaved up and the barge removed, after which
                    the shots were discharged. There were 24 boring tubes on the barge, and that was
                    the limit which could at any time be done in one tide. The surface over which
                    the blasting was done measured 500 yards in length by 200 yards in breadth, a
                    small part of that surface being uncovered at low water. The depth obtained in
                    midchannel was 14 feet at low-water, the average depth of rock blasted being
                    about 4 feet 6 inches. The holes, which were bored with the diamond drill,
                    varied in depth from 7 to 9 feet, the distance between them being 10 feet.
                    Dynamite in tin canisters fired by patent fuse was used as the explosive, the
                    charges being 2 Bö and under. The rock is Oolite shale of variable hardness, and
                    the average time occupied in drilling 5-feet holes was twelve minutes.</p>
                <p>The dredger raised the blasted rock,—the cost for blasting, lifting, and
                    discharging at sea being about 4s. per cubic yard, including interest on
                    dredging and other plant employed. The dredger sometimes worked a face of
                    blasted material of from 7 to 8 feet. The quantity blasted was 110,000 cubic
                    yards, and the contract for blasting so as to be lifted by the dredger was 3s. 1
                    d. per cubic yard.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Dredging in Exposed Situations.—</hi> In some cases dredging
                    has to be conducted in exposed situations such as the deepening of the “flats”
                    at Londonderry and the bar at Carlingford. Messrs Stevenson found that dredging
                    at the Foyle could not be conducted when the height of the waves exceeded 2∣
                    feet; and Mr Barton at Dundalk so far confirms this, as he estimates a swell of
                    2 feet as the highest to work in.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Dredging on the River Clyde.—</hi> An important point connected
                    with this subject is the cost at which dredging may be done when conducted on a
                    large scale. This, of course, must depend on the character of the stuff to be
                    raised and other circumstances; but the following information, kindly
                    communicated by Mr James Deas, the engineer to the Trustees of the Clyde
                    Navigation, cannot fail to be both interesting and useful.</p>
                <p>Mr Deas says truly that the Clyde Trustees employ probably the largest dredging
                    fleet of any trust in the kingdom, in maintaining and still deepening and
                    widening the river to meet the ever-increasing demands of the shipping
                    trade.</p>
                <p>In the year 1871, for example, 904,104 cubic yards, or about 1,130,000 tons, were
                    dredged from the river, of which 689,560 cubic yards were carried to sea by
                    steam hopper barges, and 214,544 cubic yards deposited on land by means of
                    punts. Of this 904,104 cubic yards, 345,209 cubic yards were deposit from the
                    higher reaches of the river and its tributaries, and from the city sewers, and
                    558,895 cubic yards new material. The total cost for dredging and depositing was
                    &lt;£35,448, or about 9"41 pence per cubic yard.</p>
                <p>Owing to the difference in power of the dredging machines employed, and the
                    character of the material lifted, the cost of dredging varies much. In 1871 the
                    most powerful machine, working 2420 hours, lifted 430,240 cubic yards of silt
                    and sand at a cost of 2 ’ 60 pence per yard; and this was deposited in Loch
                    Long, 27 miles from Glasgow, by steam hopper barges, at 5 ’ 46 pence per yard.
                    On the other hand, another dredger, working 2605 hours, lifted only 26,720 cubic
                    yards of hard gravel and boulder clay, at the cost of 20 ’ 8 pence per cubic
                    yard, which was deposited on the alveus of the river at the cost of 17’46 pence
                    per cubic yard; another, working 1831∣ hours, lifted 122,664 cubic yards of
                    silt, sand, and sewage deposit, at the cost of 5 ’ 67 pence per cubic yard,
                    which was deposited on land at the cost of 16 ’ 40 pence per cubic yard; and
                    another, working 2233 hours, lifted 65,160 cubic yards of till, gravel, and
                    sand, at the cost of 5 89 pence per cubic yard, which was deposited on the
                    alveus of the river at the cost of 9 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 83 pence per
                    cubic yard.</p>
                <p>The total quantity dredged from the river during the twenty-seven years prior to
                    1872 amounts to 13,617,000 <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n486/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0486-0467"/> cubic yards, or upwards of 17,000,000 tons.
                    The dredging plant of the Clyde Trust comprises—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>6 steam dredges,</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>14 steam hopper barges,</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1 steam-tug,</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>3 diving-bells,</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>270 punts, and numerous small boats.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The expenditure for wages of crews, coal, and stores amounted in the year 1871 to
                    fully £14,000, and for repairs £10,775. The value of the dredging plant employed
                    is about £140,000.</p>
                <p>Mr Deas has also kindly furnished the following tables, from which the reader
                    will see the gradual increase that has been made on the size of the dredging
                    machines to meet the increased depth of water and growing necessity of increased
                    accommodation for the larger class of vessels which now frequent the river
                    :—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">General Dimensions of Dredgers employed on the Clyde in</hi>
                    1872.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>ό <hi rend="italic">⅛</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Year built.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Length.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Breadth.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Depth.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>M</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Greatest depth can dredge in.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Single or double bucket ladder.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Remarks.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1851</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ft. in.</p><p>99 9</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ft. in.</p><p>32 4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ft. in.</p><p>10 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ft.</p><p>22⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Double</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Punt-loading Machine.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1841</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>95 6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>22 6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10 4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>18</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Single</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Do. Do.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1855</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>121 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>33 6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>25</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Double</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Hopper Barge Do.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1860</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>108 6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>23 6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>25</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>25</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Single</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Punt Do.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1865</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>161 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>29 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>75</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>28</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Do.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Hopper Barge Do.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1871</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>161 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>29 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>75</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>30</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Do.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Do. Do.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The following are the details as regards the dredgers and barges employed on the
                    Clyde :—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ho.</hi> 8 <hi rend="italic">Dredger.</hi></p>
                <p>Length, 161 ft.</p>
                <p>Breadth moulded, 29 ft.</p>
                <p>Depth, 10 feet.</p>
                <p>Engine, 75 horse power. Cylinder, 48 in. diameter. Stroke, 3 ft.</p>
                <p>One bucket ladder, 90 ft. 9 in. between centres.</p>
                <p>Size of buckets, 3 ft. 3 in. × 2 ft. 5 in. × 1 ft. 11 in.</p>
                <p>When working in sand, can lift 190 cubic yards per hour.</p>
                <p>Greatest depth can dredge in, 28 feet.</p>
                <p>Working draught, 6 to 7 feet.</p>
                <p>Wages per day of 10 hours as under :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Master</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7 <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi>.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0d.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Mate</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Engineer</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Fireman</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>a</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Assistant do. and cook</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Bow crabman</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Stern crabman</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Deck hands (3), each</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>„ „ one at</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>o</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Watchman</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ä</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>∩</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Coals</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Tallow</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>ΟΪ1 (Lard)</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>waste</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Steam Hopper Barge.</hi></p>
                <p>Length, 145 ft.</p>
                <p>Breadth moulded, 25 ft.</p>
                <p>Depth, <hi rend="italic">Ί</hi> 1 ft. 9 in.</p>
                <p>Engines, 40 horse power.</p>
                <p>Draught light (average), 5 ft. 6 in.</p>
                <p>Draught loaded, 11 ft.</p>
                <p>Speed, 8 to 9 miles per hour.</p>
                <p>Capacity of hopper, 320 cubic yards, or say 400 tons Average distance run,
                    loaded, 20 miles.</p>
                <p>Wages per day as under :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Master <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi>- <hi rend="subscript">
                                    oλ</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Engineer &gt;; <hi rend="subscript"> ln</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Fireman o <hi rend="subscript"> c</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Deck hands (3) <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> each</p><p>Coals per
                                day of 10 hours</p><p>Tallow</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3 4 -.70 cwts. κ τ¾</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>„ » 9β p∙∏1a</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>waste „: i::::::::::::::::::::::::::;:::::::::::
                            2»</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Quantity and cost of dredging done by No. 8 Dredger during year ending 30th June
                    1871 . <hi rend="superscript"> 6 e</hi></p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>wages</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>...£678</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Coals</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 371</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>18</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Stores .. „</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 182</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>£1232</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Repairs</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>....1669</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>11</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>£2901</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Interest and depreciation—cost of dredger, £17,653,
                            at</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>10 per cent</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>.. 1765</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>£4,666</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>18</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Time worked during year, 2419f engine hours.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Sand, silt, till, and gravel lifted, 430,240 cubic
                            yards.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>2419≡ hours <hi rend="superscript"> -177 80 cubic</hi>
                                yards lifted per hour.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>£4666, 18s. 3d.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="3"><p>430,240 cubic yards <hi rend="superscript"> -i oυ</hi> P
                                    <hi rend="superscript"> eute cost</hi> P <hi rend="superscript">
                                    el cudic</hi> yarα nttea.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Quantity and cost of conveying and discharging the total dredgings lifted by Nos.
                    6 and 8 Dredgers during the year ending 30th June 1871 :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>wages, coals, and stores</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>£6,917 0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Repairs -,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>— - 3,255 7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>£10,172 8 2</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Interest and depreciation—cost of 10 hopper
                            barges,</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>£51,510, at 10 per cent</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>.... 5,151 0 0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>£15,323 8 2</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>£15,323, 8s. 2d.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>—K∙4Λ <hi rend="smallcaps">πatiaa</hi> roκιt <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">daγ</hi> rιιhin <hi rend="smallcaps">va</hi>
                                rd</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>673,240 cubic yards, )</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>total dredgings conveyed, i</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Note.—</hi> Four hopper barges are required to keep one dredger
                    in constant work.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Abstract of the Quantity and Cost per Cubic yard of Dredging
                        and Depositing during the year ending</hi> 30ZA <hi rend="italic">June</hi>
                    1871.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Dredger, etc.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Nature of stuff, and where dredged generally.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Total cubic yards lifted.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Cubic yards lifted per engine-hour.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="6"><p>Pence per cubic yard.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Dredging.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Conveying and depositing by barges.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Towing punts to discharging ground.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Discharging dredgings from punts.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>jΓ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> o ⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> l</hi>
                                fi</p><p>Λ ’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Total Cost.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>No. 1</p><p>Dredger</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Sand, silt, and sewage from Glasgow harbour.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>122,664</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>66∙96</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5∙67</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2∙88</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10'00<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                                        ><p>Contractor’s price for discharging at Blythswood Park,
                                        including slip docks, and waggoning a distance of about f
                                        mile.</p></note> I</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3'52</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>22'07</p><p>L∙72</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>No. 5</p><p>Dredger</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Hard till, gravel, and sand, from Erskine Ferry,
                            &lt;fcc.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>65,160</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>29∙18</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5'89</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>1'76</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5'42<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                                        ><p>Discharging by Trustees’ men on river banks near Erskine
                                        Ferry, <hi rend="italic">by beaching punts and
                                            wheeling.</hi></p></note></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2'65</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>No. 6</p><p>Dredger</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Sand, clay, and mud,from Pt. Glasgow, &amp;c.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>243,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>83∙19</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3∙36</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5'46</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>...</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>8'82</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>No. 7</p><p>Dredger</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Hard till and clay from Erskine Ferry, Elderslie,
                            &amp;c.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>26,720</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10'26</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>20∙81</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>2'34</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5'42<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                                        ><p>Discharging by Trustees’ men on river banks near Erskine
                                        Ferry, <hi rend="italic">by beaching punts and
                                            wheeling.</hi></p></note></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9'70</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>38'27</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>No. 8</p><p>Dredger</p><p>10 Hopper barges .</p><p>Tug
                            steamer</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Sand, silt, till, and gravel, from Glasgow and Bowling harbours,
                                &lt;fcc.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>430,240</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>177'80</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2∙60</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5'46</p><p>average 5'46</p><p>Ί</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>[average</p><p>2'83</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>8'06</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Nos. 1, 5, and 7 are punt-loading machines. Nos. 6 and 8 are hopper barge
                    machines.</p>
                <p>Reference is made to the following works :— <hi rend="italic">Ency. of Civil
                        Engineering,</hi> by Edward Cressy, London, 1847; “The Dredging Machine,”
                    Weale’s <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Papers,</hi> i., London 1843; <hi
                        rend="italic">The Improvement of the Port of London,</hi> by R. Dodd,
                    Engineer, 1798; “Account of Blasting on the Severn,” by George Edwards, C.E.,
                        <hi rend="italic">Minutes of Proceedings of the Institution of Civil
                        Engineers,</hi> vol. iv. p. 361; “the River Clyde,” by James Deas, C.E., <hi
                        rend="italic">Minutes of Proceedings of the Institution of Civil
                        Engineers,</hi> vol. xxxvi. p. 124; <hi rend="italic">Principles and
                        Practice of Canal and River Engineering,</hi> by David Stevenson, 2d ed., A.
                    &amp; C. Black, Edinb. 1872, p. 126. (D. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
