<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0047-0038-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DE LA BECHE, Henry Thomas</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 38</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65f63">Soldiers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zd00">Surveys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:874582">Conducting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1139635">Surveys</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1139579">Surveying</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n47/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DE LA BECHE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry Thomas</hi></label>
                    (1796-1855), one of the band of enthusiastic workers by whom the science of
                    geology was developed so rapidly in England during the early part of this
                    century, was born in the year 1796. His father, an officer in the army,
                    possessed landed property in Jamaica, but died while his son was still young.
                    The boy accordingly spent his youth with his mother among the interesting and
                    picturesque coast cliffs of the south-west of England, where probably he early
                    imbibed that Jove for geological pursuits, and cultivated that marked artistic
                    faculty, to which in large measure be owed the high position he ultimately
                    reached. When fourteen years of age, being destined, like his friend Murchison,
                    for the military profession, he entered the college at Great Marlowe, where ho
                    specially distinguished himself by the rapidity and skill with which he executed
                    sketches showing the salient <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n48/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0048-0039"/> features of a district. But this aptitude, which
                    would have been of great service in a soldier’s life, was not called forth for
                    warlike purposes. The peace of 1815 changed the career of many young aspirants
                    for military distinction, and among them De la Beche. Instead of pursuing the
                    calling he had chosen, he began to devote himself with ever-increasing assiduity
                    to the pursuit of geology. When only twenty-one years of age he joined the
                    Geological Society of London, continuing throughout life to be one of its most
                    active, useful, and honoured members. Possessing a fortune sufficient for the
                    gratification of his tastes, he visited many localities of geological interest
                    in Britain, and spent some time on the Continent studying features in the
                    geology and physical geography of France and Switzerland. His journeys seldom
                    failed to bear fruit in suggestive notes, papers, or sketches. Early attachment
                    to the south-west of England led him back to that region, where, with augmented
                    power from enlarged experience and reflection, he began the detailed
                    investigation of the rocks of Cornwall and Devon. Thrown much into contact with
                    the mining community of that part of the country, he conceived the idea that the
                    nation ought to compile a geological map of the United Kingdom, and collect and
                    preserve specimens to illustrate, and perhaps even to aid in further developing,
                    its mineral industries. He showed his skilful management of affairs by inducing
                    the Government of the day to recognize his work and give him an appointment in
                    connection with the Ordnance Survey. This formed the starting-point of the
                    present Geological Survey of Great Britain and Ireland. Year by year increasing
                    stores of valuable specimens were transmitted to London <hi rend="italic">;
                    for</hi> De la Beche enlisted the sympathy and co-operation of the mining
                    authorities of Cornwall and Devon. At last the building where the young Museum
                    of Economic Geology was placed became too small. But De la Beche, having seen
                    how fruitful his first idea had become, determined to use all his persuasion to
                    prevail on the authorities not merely to provide a large structure, but to widen
                    the whole scope of the scientific establishment of which he was the head, so as
                    to impart to it the character of a great educational institution where practical
                    as well as theoretical instruction should be given in every branch of science
                    necessary for the conduct of mining work. In this endeavour he was again
                    successful. Parliament sanctioned the erection of a museum in Jermyn Street,
                    London, and the organization of a staff of professors with laboratories and
                    other appliances. The establishment was opened in 1851. The Geological Survey
                    also, which had grown up under his care, no longer under the Ordnance
                    Department, received a new organization and an increase to its staff. To De la
                    Beche belongs the high praise of having entirely originated and developed this
                    important branch of the public service. Many foreign countries have since formed
                    geological surveys avowedly based upon the organization and experience of that
                    of the United Kingdom. The British colonies, also,have in many instances
                    established similar surveys for the development of their mineral rèsources, and
                    have had recourse to the parent survey for advice and for officers to conduct
                    the operations.</p>
                <p>De la Beche was an able mineralogist as well as an admirable field-geologist. He
                    published numerous memoirs on English geology in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Transactions of the Geological Society of London,</hi> as well as in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoirs of the Geological Survey of the United Kingdom.</hi> He
                    likewise wrote a valuable text-book of geology, and a work of singular breadth
                    and clearness— <hi rend="italic">Researches in Theoretical Geology—</hi> in
                    which he enunciated a philosophical treatment of geological questions much in
                    advance of his time. An early volume, <hi rend="italic">Howto Observe in
                    Geology,</hi> was rewritten and enlarged by him late in life, and published
                    under the title of <hi rend="italic">The Geological Observer.</hi> It was marked
                    by wide practical experience, multifarious knowledge, philosophical insight, and
                    a genius for artistic delineation of geological phenomena. He received from many
                    foreign societies recognition of his services to science, and at the close of
                    his life was awarded the Wollaston medal—the highest honour in the gift of the
                    Geological Society of London. After a life of constant activity he began to
                    suffer from partial paralysis, but, though becoming gradually worse, continued
                    able to transact his official business until a few days before his death, which
                    took place on !3th April 1855.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
