<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0588-0567-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DWARF (9th edition, volume 7, page 567)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:899973">Dwarfs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150468">Thumb</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942497">Giants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wq36">Thumb</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m62">Aztecs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qz22m9r">Giants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m147">Dwarfs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205049">Victoria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n588/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DWARF</label> (Saxon <hi rend="italic">dwerg, dweorg∙,</hi>
                    German, <hi rend="italic">Zwerg},</hi> a term applied to men, animals, and
                    plants that fail to reach even the mediocrity of growth natural to their
                    respective classes. It is also otherwise applied. In France, for instance, a
                    yolkless egg is termed “un oeuf nain,” or dwarf <hi rend="italic">egg;</hi> and
                    an imitation of fine English cloth is called “nain Londrin,” technically “London
                    dwarf.”</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">nanus</hi> or <hi rend="italic">pumilο</hi> of the Romans
                    might be a dwarf by nature or a person dwarfed by cruel art. In the former case,
                    his lack of height found compensation in increased strength, as exemplified in
                    the line by Propertius, “Nanus et ipse suos breviter concretus in artus,”
                    &amp;c.; in the latter, where growth had been early suppressed by the dealers
                    who manufactured monstrosities for fashionable people in Rome, weakness bred
                    contempt. The <hi rend="italic">nanus,</hi> or, if he were more than usually
                    diminutive, the <hi rend="italic">nanium,</hi> was exposed to application of the
                    proverb, “nanus cum sis, cede,” equivalent to “little people must not be in our
                    way !”</p>
                <p>Various have been the recipes for dwarfing children from birth. The most
                    effective, according to report, was anointing the back bone with the grease of
                    moles, bats, and dormice. It is also said that pups were dwarfed by frequently
                    washing their feet and backbone; the consequent drying and hardening of those
                    parts hindered, it was alleged, their extension. In England, the growth of boys
                    intended for riders in horse-races is kept down to some extent by the weakening
                    process of “sweating.”</p>
                <p>There is a familiar story of a partnership entered into between a dwarf and a
                    giant. The dwarf had the intellect, the giant had the strength; the result of
                    this limited liability was that the giant received all the blows, and the dwarf
                    all the profits. The partnership was consequently broken up. A fact, of which we
                    are reminded by this fiction, occurred in Austria in the 17th century. To please
                    the caprice of an empress, all the giants and dwarfs in the empire were brought
                    together to Vienna, and were lodged in one building. The dwarfs were told they
                    had nothing to fear from the giants; but the latter were soon put in bodily fear
                    of the dwarfs, who made the life of their stupendous companions unbearable by
                    teazing them, molesting them, tripping them up, and unscrupulously robbing them.
                    The giants, with tears as big as pearls in their eyes, prayed the authorities to
                    relieve them from the persecution of their tiny enemies, and the prayer was
                    granted. At a later period, another German princess promoted marriages among
                    dwarfs, but without succeeding in the object she had in view. When Lady Mary
                    Wortley Montague was in Germany, in the last century, she found that a dwarf was
                    a necessary appendage to every noble family. At that time English ladies kept
                    monkeys. The imperial dwarfs at the Viennese court were described by Lady Mary
                    as “as ugly as devils” and “bedaubed with diamonds.” They had succeeded the
                    court fools, and exercised some part of the more ancient office. Absolute
                    princes could not stoop to familiar discourse with mankind of less degree.
                    Therefore did they hold dwarfs to be outside humanity, made intimate associates
                    of them, and allowed them an unrestrained freedom of speech, by the exercise of
                    which the dwarfs imparted to their masters wholesome truths which on the lips of
                    ordinary men would have been treason. One of the kings of Denmark is said to
                    have made a prime-minister of his dwarf, in order to get at rough truths which a
                    minister of ordinary stature would have been afraid to utter.</p>
                <p>It could not have been for this reason that Stanislas, exking of Poland and duke
                    of Lorraine, was so attached to his dwarf, Nicholas Ferry, otherwise known as
                    “Bébé,” for this dwarf was weak in mind and body. Bébé was one of three dwarf
                    children of peasant parents in the Vosges. He was 3 feet in height, and his fame
                    has not died out at Nancy and the department of the Meurthe. At his death in
                    1764 he was in his twenty-third year; and, among the fine phrases of which his
                    epitaph is composed, the world is still assured that Bébé was “chéri du nouvel
                    Antonin.”</p>
                <p>But Bébé was not so remarkable a dwarf as Richebourg, who died in Paris in 1858,
                    at the age of ninety. He was only 23 inches in height. In his childhood he was a
                    servant (without especial duty) in the Orleans family. In later years,
                    Richebourg was their pensioner. He is said to have been put to strange use in
                    the Revolutionary period,— passing in and out of Paris as an infant in a nurse’s
                    arms, but with despatches, dangerous to carry, in the little man’s baby
                    wrappings! At present, on the Continent, Russia and Turkey alone have a common
                    sympathy for dwarfs. At the court of the sultan, should the dwarf, besides being
                    of elfish height, be deaf, dumb, and qualified to hold a place <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n589/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0589-0568"/> among the official eunuchs, the poor creature
                    is accounted as a priceless treasure.</p>
                <p>The early history of British dwarfs is less studded with wonders than the record
                    of dwarfs of the classical times. Britain has nothing to compare with Philetas
                    of Cos, the little tutor of Ptolemy Philadelphus. Aelian would have us believe
                    that Philetas was so light as well as diminutive that he wore leaden weights in
                    his pockets to prevent his being blown away. Nor does any British chronicle
                    register such minute marvels as the couple of dwarfs possessed by Julia, the
                    niece of Augustus, namely, Coropas and Julia’s little handmaid Andromeda. The
                    height of both was 2 feet 4 inches. This, however, was little less than the
                    stature of the Aztec dwarfs who were exhibited (and were publicly married) in
                    London some twenty years ago. It is not that British annals or tradition can be
                    said to be entirely silent on dwarfs as wonderful as Aelian’s. The earliest,
                    known by the now generic name of “Tom Thumb,” presents himself to us in the
                    ancient ballad which begins with the record that “In Arthur’s court Tom Thumb
                    did live.” Antiquaries, on probably no better foundation, are content with
                    placing the proto-Thumb at the court of King Edgar. It is certain that such
                    shrunken samples of humanity figured in great festivals, as we see their foreign
                    brethren in some of the pictures of the Italian and Spanish masters. The first
                    English dwarf of whom there is authentic history was presented to Queen
                    Henrietta by the duchess of Buckingham, as he stept out of a pie at a banquet.
                    This was Jeffery Hudson of Rutlandshire. He was born in 1619, and was only 1⅛
                    feet high from his eighth year to his thirtieth, after which he grew to the
                    stature of 3 feet 9 inches, and never went beyond it. His life was not made up
                    of court pleasures. He fought two duels,—one with a turkey-cock, a battle
                    recorded by Davenant, and a second with Mr Crofts, who came to the meeting with
                    a squirt, but who in the more serious encounter which ensued was shot dead by
                    little Hudson, who fired from horseback, the saddle putting him on a level with
                    his lofty but unlucky antagonist. Twice was Jeffery made prisoner,—once by the
                    Dunkirkers as he was returning from France, whither he had been on homely
                    business for the queen; the second time was when he fell into the hands of
                    Barbary corsairs. In each case his liberty was soon purchased. But Jeffery died
                    in prison, nevertheless. He was accused of participation in the “Popish Plot,”
                    and in 1682 this dwarf died in the Gate House, in the sixty-third year of his
                    age.</p>
                <p>Contemporary with Hudson were the two dwarfs of Henrietta Maria, Gibson and his
                    wife Anne. They were married by the queen’s wish; and the two together measured
                    only a couple of inches over 7 feet. They had nine children, five of whom, who
                    lived, were of ordinary stature. Edmund Waller celebrated the nuptials, Evelyn
                    designated the husband as the “compendium of a man,” and Lely painted them hand
                    in hand. Gibson was miniature painter to Charles I., and drawing-master to the
                    daughters of James IL, the Princesses Mary and Anne, w hen they were children.
                    This Cumberland pigmy, who began his career as a page, first in a “gentle,” next
                    in the royal family, died in 1690, in his seventy-fifth year, and is buried in
                    St Paul’s, Covent Garden. The last court dwarf in England was Coppernin, a
                    lively little imp in the service of the Princess (Augusta) of Wales, the mother
                    of George III. The last dwarf retainer in a gentleman’s family was the one kept
                    by Mr Beckford, the author of <hi rend="italic">Valhek</hi> and builder of
                    Fonthill. He was rather too big to be flung from one guest to another, as used
                    to be done at after-dinner tables, when the wine had got the better of common
                    sense.</p>
                <p>Of exhibited dwarfs in England, the most celebrated was the Pole, Bυrulwaski,
                    whom fashion patronized in the last century and forgot in the present one. He
                    was then a yard and 3 inches in height, and he had a sister shorter than himself
                    by the head and shoulders. Borulwaski was a handsome man, a wit, and something
                    of a scholar. He travelled over all Europe; and he—born in the reign of George
                    II., 1739—died in his well-earned retirement near Durham, in the reign of
                    Victoria, 1837. Borulwaski, buried in the above-named city, lies by the side of
                    the Falstaffian Stephen Kemble. The companionship reminds one of that of the
                    dwarf skeleton of Jonathan Wild by the side of that of the Irish Giant, at the
                    Royal College of Surgeons, London.</p>
                <p>In the year in which Borulwaski died, 1837, the line of publicly exhibited dwarfs
                    was continued by the birth of the existing American pigmy, Charles Stratton,
                    better known as “General Tom Thumb.” In 1844 he appeared in England, where his
                    grace, vivacity, and good humour made him popular, from the royal family to the
                    general public, before whom he acted at the Lyceum Theatre. He also made his
                    appearance on the stage in Paris. After extensive travel in both hemispheres, he
                    again visited England in 1857, but the dwarf man, despite many personal and
                    intellectual qualities, was less attractive than the dwarf boy. In the year 1863
                    the “General” married the very minute American lady, Lavinia Warren (bom in
                    1842), with whom he has seen many lands, and they are now enjoying honourable
                    retirement in their own. (j. <hi rend="smallcaps">do.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
