<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0397-0378-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DOUVILLE, Jean Baptiste (9th edition, volume 7, page
                    378)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838162">Brazilians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155691">Travelers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155558">Travel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355164">Travels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093204">Regionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49p2wf9z">Travel</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm13z3g">Heirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n397/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DOUVILLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jean Baptiste</hi></label>
                    (1794-C. 1837), a French traveller born at Hambye, in the department of Manche,
                    whose asserted discoveries in Africa have in large measure been relegated to the
                    region of romance. At an early period his imagination seems to have been fired
                    by narratives of travel and adventure; and accordingly, when he fell heir to a
                    wealthy relation, he at once proceeded to gratify his desire for personal
                    acquaintance with foreign lands. He certainly wandered far and wide; and,
                    according to his own profession, he visited India, Kashmir, Khorassan, Persia,
                    Asia Minor, and many parts of Europe. After spending some time in Paris, and
                    being admitted a member of the Société de Géographie, he proceeded in 1826 to
                    Brazil, with the intention apparently of carrying on scientific explorations:
                    from this purpose, however, he was diverted by the political circumstances of
                    the country; and to replenish his funds he started business at Montevideo in
                    partnership with a Μ. Laboissière. Towards the close of the following year,
                    probably in October, after a short residence at Rio Janeiro, he left Brazil for
                    the Portuguese possessions on the west coast of Africa, where his presence in
                    March 1828 is proved by the mention made of him in certain letters of Castillo
                    Branco, the governor-general of Loanda. In May 1831 he reappeared in France,
                    claiming to have pushed his explorations into the very heart of Africa, as far
                    as the 27th degree of longitude E. of Greenwich, or, in other words, into what
                    is now known as the great equatorial lake region. His story was readily accepted
                    by the Société de Géographie at Paris, which hastened to recognize his services
                    by assigning him the great gold medal, and appointing him their secretary for
                    the year 1832. On the publication of his narrative <hi rend="italic">—
                        Voyage</hi><hi rend="italic">au</hi><hi rend="italic">Congo</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">et dans l'intérieur de</hi><hi rend="italic">V</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Afrique équinoxiale</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> which
                    occupied four large volumes, and was accompanied by an elaborate atlas, the
                    public enthusiasm might well run high. In company with his wife (a sister of his
                    old Montevidean partner), and attended by about 400 native porters, the happy
                    traveller had advanced from kingdom to kingdom rather like a monarch making a
                    progress through his tributary states, distributing largesses and receiving
                    homage, than like a humble adventurer defraying his expenses from his private
                    purse. Everything went smooth for a time; the interior of Africa was described
                    in text books and depicted in maps according to the discoveries of Douville; but
                    in the August number of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Quarterly Review</hi> for
                    1832 the most sweeping charges of ignorance and fraud were launched against the
                    author, and this attack wað followed up in the <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux
                        Mondes</hi> for November, by Thomas Lacordaire, who asserted that, during
                    part of the time which he claimed to have spent in Africa, Douville had been a
                    familiar object in the streets of Rio Janeiro. The tide of popular favour
                    turned; and, in spite of the explanations furnished by Douville in <hi
                        rend="italic">Ma defence,</hi> 1832, and <hi rend="italic">Trente mois de ma
                        vie, ou quinze mois avant et quinze mois après mon voyage au Congo,</hi>
                    1833, the general decision was openly against him. Mlle. Audrun, a lady to whom
                    he was about to be married, committed suicide from grief at the disgrace; and,
                    after vainly attempting to obtain satisfaction from Lacordaire by duel, the poor
                    adventurer himself withdrew in 1833 to Brazil, and proceeded to make
                    explorations in the valley of the Amazon. According to Dr Gardner, in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Travels in the Interior of Brazil,</hi> he was murdered in
                    1837 on the banks of the São Francisco for charging too high for his medical
                    assistance. His Brazilian manuscripts fell into the hands of Μ. S. Rang, by whom
                    they were transmitted to Μ. Ferdinand Denis. While modern exploration has done
                    nothing to support the wider pretensions of Douville, no less an authority than
                    Captain Burton asserts that his descriptions of the country of the Congo are
                    life-like aud <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n398/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0398-0379"/> picturesque; that his observations on the
                    anthropology, ceremonies, customs, and maladies of the people are remarkably
                    accurate; and that even the native words inserted into the text of his narrative
                    “are for the most part given with unusual correctness.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
