<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0372-0355-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DOMITIAN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 355</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:846504">Capitols</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:922595">Felting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4nv99f02">Felt</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz5d">Youth</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ht2gd1x">Chatti</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fc9v">Cola</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n372/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DOMITIAN</label> (52-96). Titus Flavius Domitianus, the
                    second son of Titus Flavius Vespasianus and Flavia Domitilla, twelfth of the
                    Caesars, and third of the Flavian dynasty, was born at Rome, 24th October 52 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> He enjoys an evil prominence as the only tyrant among
                    the succession of good and just princes from Vespasian down to Commodus.
                    According to Suetonius, he was brought up in squalor and ignorance, and led a
                    degraded and miserable youth; but it is hardly credible that so good a prince
                    and so indulgent a father in all his other acts should thus have neglected his
                    son’s education, and the story of his scandalous youth was more probably
                    invented to suit his after life. When Vespasian was proclaimed emperor, Domitian
                    escaped with difficulty from the burning temple of the Capitol, and lay in
                    hiding from the Vitellians till his father’s party proved victorious. After the
                    fall of Vitellius he was saluted as Caesar, or prince imperial, by the troops,
                    obtained the city praetorship, and was intrusted with the administration of
                    Italy till his father’s return from the East. Intoxicated by this sudden rise
                    from obscurity, he grossly abused the power committed to him, and conducted
                    himself more like a Turkish pasha than the son of a sturdy Sabine soldier. Such
                    were the airs of authority he assumed that Vespasian, as the story goes, wrote
                    in irony to thank him for not having dismissed his own father. Certain it is
                    that though in his father’s lifetime he several times filled the office of
                    consul, and after his death was nominally the partner in the empire with his
                    brother, yet he never took any part in public business, but lived in great
                    retirement, devoting himself to a life of pleasure and of literary pursuits till
                    he succeeded to the purple. The death of Titus, if not hastened by foul means,
                    was at least eagerly welcomed by his brother. His succession (13th Sept. 81) was
                    unquestioned, and it would seem as if, when his ambition was sated, and before
                    his fears were aroused, he intended, as far as his weak volitions and mean
                    abilities would allow, to govern well. Like Augustus, he attempted a reformation
                    of morals and religion. As chief pontiff he inquired into the character of the
                    vestal virgins, three of whom were found guilty, while in the case of one the
                    awful penalty of a living entombment was revived. He enforced the laws against
                    adultery, mutilation, and the grosser forms of immorality. He forbade the public
                    acting of mimes. He erected many temples and public buildings and restored the
                    temple of the Capitol, on the gilding of which, if Plutarch is to be believed,
                    he expended 12,000 talents, or nearly two and a half millions of our money. He
                    passed many sumptuary laws, one of which is noticeable as showing the increasing
                    dearth of com, which was now grown mainly by the wasteful and inefficient
                    process of slave labour. An edict was issued forbidding the withdrawal of arable
                    land from the plough, and reducing existing vineyards by one half. Finally, he
                    took a personal share in the administration of justice at Rome, and exercised a
                    jealous supervision over the governors of provinces.</p>
                <p>Such public virtues counterbalanced in the eyes of the people all his private
                    vices, gross and glaring as they were from the first. Former emperors had been
                    deified after their death, but Domitian was the first to arrogate divine honours
                    in his lifetime, and cause himself in public documents to be styled <hi
                    rend="italic">Our Lord and God.</hi> Doubtless in the poets (such as Martial,
                    who calls the emperor’s minion the Ganymede of our second Jove) this deification
                    was nothing but fulsome flattery, but in the case of the provincials it was a
                    sincere tribute to the impersonation of the Roman Empire, as the administrator
                    of good government, and the peacemaker of the world. Even when Rome and Italy
                    felt his heavy hand, and smarted beneath his proscriptions and extortions, the
                    provinces were undisturbed. Though he took the title of imperator more than
                    twenty times, and enjoyed at least one triumph, his achievements as a general
                    were insignificant. His campaign in 83 against the Chatti was “a mere summer
                    promenade <hi rend="italic">;” in</hi> Dacia (87) he received a severe check,
                    and the peace concluded with this nation in 90 was due to the victories of his
                    lieutenant Julianus. Juvenal hints that the flaxen-haired Germans who figured in
                    his triumph were purchased slaves. His jealousy was provoked by the successes of
                    Agri cola in Britain, and the conqueror of Galgacus and the hero of the battle
                    of the Grampians was recalled to Rome (84) in the midst of his conquests,
                    condemned to retirement, and, as Tacitus is inclined to believe, removed by
                    poison.</p>
                <p>The revolt of Antonius Saturninus, the commander of the Roman forces in Upper
                    Germany (93), marks the turning point in his reign. By a fortunate rising of the
                    Rhine, which prevented his barbarian allies from coming to his assistance, and
                    by the vigour of Norbanus, it was speedily crushed; but the fears of the emperor
                    once aroused seem never again to have slept. A proscription as bloody as that of
                    Sulla followed, and no man of eminence could feel his life safe. Before this he
                    had sought out victims to gratify his cupidity and replenish his exhausted
                    treasury. Now he struck at all that was conspicuous for talent or virtue,
                    glutted himself with the blood of the Lamiae, and sentenced to death his own
                    cousin and nephew by marriage, Flavius Clemens. A conspiracy among his own
                    freedmen— set on foot, it is said, by his wife, who knew her own life to be
                    threatened—cut short his career of tyranny and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n373/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0373-0356"/> bloodshed. He was stabbed in his bedroom by a
                    freedman of Clemens named Stephanus, 18th Sept. 96. Had Domitian died after as
                    short a reign as his brother he might have left behind him as fair a name, and
                    the interesting problem for the historian is to connect the two portions of his
                    reign, and account for the double part he played. Like Hamlet he was born to a
                    position which he felt himself unequal to fill. So long as the popularity which
                    he inherited from his brother lasted, and he felt himself secure on his throne,
                    he carried on the traditions of his father’s government, denounced delators, and
                    administered even justice. After his unsuccessful campaign and the conspiracy of
                    his general, he was seized with the common disease of absolute monarchs, the
                    fear of assassination and distrust of all around him. The last three years of
                    his reign witnessed the awful spectacle of the acts of a madman endowed with
                    unlimited power.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
