<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0552-0533-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DUNCAN, Adam, First Viscount (9th edition, volume 7,
                    page 533)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sn01992">Monarchs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25p07">Winter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m6290g">Vice</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p30">Flags</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tg7r">Rates</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176048">Winter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116439">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926942">Flags</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095872">Rest</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n552/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DUNCAN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Adam, First
                        Viscount</hi></label> (1731-1804), an illustrious naval commander, was born
                    July 1, 1731, at Lundie, in Forfarshire, Scotland. After receiving the rudiments
                    of his education at Dundee, he was in 1746 placed under Captain Haldane, of the
                    “Shoreham” frigate, and in 1749 he became a midshipman in the “Centurion.” In
                    1755 he was appointed second lieutenant of the “Norwich,” a fourth-rate; but on
                    the arrival of that ship in America, whither, with the rest of Keppel’s
                    squadron, it had convoyed General Braddock’s forces, he was transferred to the
                    “Centurion.” Once again in England, he was promoted to be second lieutenant of
                    the “Torbay,” 7 4, and after three years on the home station he assisted in the
                    attack on the French settlement of Goree, on the African coast, in which he was
                    slightly wounded. He returned to England as first lieutenant of the “Torbay ;”
                    and in 1759 was made a commander, and in 1761 a post-captain. His vessel,
                    the</p>
                <p>“Valiant,” was Commodore Keppel’s flag-ship in the expedition against Belleisle
                    in that year, and also in 1762, when it took an important part in the capture of
                    Havana. In 1778, on the recommencement of war with France, Captain Duncan was
                    appointed to the “Suffolk,” whence before the close of the year he removed to
                    the “Monarch,” one of the Channel Fleet. On January 16,1780, in an action off
                    Cape St Vincent, between a Spanish squadron under Don Juan de Langara and the
                    British fleet under Sir George Rodney, Captain Duncan in the “Monarch” was the
                    first to engage the enemy; and in 1782, as captain of the “Blenheim,”he took
                    part in Lord Howe’s relief of Gibralta;·. From the rank of rear-admiral of the
                    blue, received in 1789, he was gradually promoted until, in 1799, he became
                    admiral of the white. In February 1795 he hoisted his flag as commander-in-chief
                    of the North-Sea fleet, appointed to harass the Batavian navy. Towards the end
                    of May 1797, though, in consequence of the wide-spread mutiny in the British
                    fleet, he had been left with only the “Adamant,” 50, besides his own ship the
                    “Venerable,” 74, Admiral Duncan proceeded to his usual station off the Texel,
                    where lay at anchor the Dutch squadron of fifteen sail of the line, under the
                    command of Vice-Admiral De Winter. From time to time he caused signals to be
                    made, as if to the main body of a fleet in the offing, a stratagem which
                    probably was the cause of his freedom from molestation until, in the middle of
                    June, reinforcements arrived from England. On October 3 the admiral put into
                    Yarmouth Roads to refit and victual his ships, but, receiving information early
                    on the 9th that the enemy was at sea, he immediately hoisted the signal for
                    giving him chase. On the morning of the 11th De Winter’s fleet, consisting of
                    four seventy-fours, seven sixty-fours, four fifty-gun ships, two forty-four-gun
                    frigates, and two of thirty-two guns, besides smaller vessels, was sighted lying
                    about nine miles from shore, between the villages of Egmont and Camperdown. The
                    British fleet numbered seven seventy-fours, seven sixty-fours, two fifties, two
                    frigates, with a sloop and several cutters, and was slightly superior in force
                    to that of the Dutch. Shortly after mid-day the British ships, without waiting
                    to form in order, broke through the Dutch line, and an engagement commenced
                    which, after heavy loss on both sides, resulted in the taking by the British of
                    eleven of the enemy’s vessels. When the action ceased the ships were in nine
                    fathoms water, within five miles of a lee shore, and there was every sign of an
                    approaching gale. So battered were the prizes that it was found impossible to
                    fit them for future service, and one of them, the “Delft,” sank on her way to
                    England. In recognition of this victory, Admiral Duncan was, on October 21,
                    created Lord Viscount Duncan of Camperdown, and baron of Lundie, with an annual
                    pension of £3000 to himself and the two next heirs to his title. In 1800 Lord
                    Duncan withdrew from naval service. He died August 4, 1804.</p>
                <p>See Charnock, Biographia Navalis, 1794-6; Collins, Peerage of England, p. 378,
                    1812; W. James, Naval History of Great Britain, 1822; Yonge, History of the
                    British Navy, vol. i. 1863.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
