<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0215-0198-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DIEPPE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 198</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40z7110r">Lime</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:998853">Limes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:998827">Lime</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1028427">Mouth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206005">Guinea</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206830">Brazil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n215/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DIEPPE</label>, a seaport town of France, at the head of an
                    arrondissement in the department of Seine-Inférieure, 38 miles north of Rouen
                    and 125 north-west of Paris by rail, in 49° 55' 35" N. lat. and 1° 5' 9" E.
                    long. It lies at the mouth of the River Arques, in a hollow of the coast,—the
                    main part of the town being on the west side of the river, aud the suburb of
                    Pollet on the east. Its principal street stretches for about a mile along the
                    shore, and terminates in the west at the foot of the chalk cliff, which is
                    surmounted by a castle of the 15 th century, now employed as barracks.</p>
                <p>The whole town has a modern aspect; its streets are wide aud regular, and its
                    houses mostly built of brick. The principal building is the church of St
                    Jacques, which was founded in the 13th century, but consists in good measure of
                    considerably later workmanship, and has in some portions been restored in the
                    present century; the main entrance (of the 14th century) and the Ango chapel are
                    worthy of special remark. It is sufficient to mention the church of St Remi
                    (1522-1640), the town-house, the hospital, the theatre, and the communal college
                    which preserves some fragments of Ango’s mansion. As the chief town of an
                    arrondissement, aud an important seaport, Dieppe is the seat of a large number
                    of public offices. Its harbour, which has been greatly improved during the
                    present century, is protected by two piers, admits vessels of 500 tons burden,
                    and has a large floating dock. There is regular steamboat communication with
                    England, the passage to Newhaven being accomplished in about six hours. The
                    general trade of the town, both export and import, is extensive; and it carries
                    on ship-building, rope-spinning, cooperage, watchmaking, and a remarkable
                    manufacture of articles in ivory and bone, which dates from the 15th century.
                    The tobacco factories alone employ upwards of 1000 work people. Oysters in large
                    numbers are fattened in the <hi rend="italic">retenue des chasses</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> and the fishermen of Pollet are among the main providers of
                    the Parisian markets. Ever since the time of the duchess of Berry (whose
                    favourite residence, the <hi rend="italic">maison Quenouille,</hi> is still
                    pointed out) the town has been a fashionable watering-place; and in 1857 a large
                    bathing establishment was erected after the model of the Crystal Palace. The
                    so-called Jardin Anglais, the Cours Bourbon, and the cliffs are the principal
                    promenades; and the castle of Arques, the Manoir d’Ango, the abbey of St Victor,
                    and the ancient camp, locally known as <hi rend="italic">la cité</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Limes,</hi> are the most interesting objects of interest in
                    the neighbourhood. Population in 1851, 16,216; and in 1872, 19,757.</p>
                <p>It may be safely asserted, on the authority of its name, that Dieppe owed its
                    origin to a band of Norman adventurers, who found its “diep” or inlet suitable
                    for their ships. Its first castle was probably built in 1188 by Henry II. of
                    England, and it was counted a place of some importance when Philip Augustus
                    attacked it in 1195. By Richard I. of England it was bestowed, in 1197, on the
                    archbishop of Rouen in return for certain territory in the neighbourhood of the
                    episcopal city. In 1339 it was plundered by the English, but it soon recovered
                    from the blow, and in spite of the opposition of the Lords of Hantot, managed to
                    surround itself with fortifications. Its commercial activity was already great,
                    and it is believed its seamen visited the coast of Guinea in 1339, and founded
                    there a Petit Dieppe in 1365. A siege undertaken in 1442 by Talbot in person was
                    raised by the Dauphin, afterwards Louis XL, and the day of the deliverance
                    continued for centuries to be celebrated by a great procession and miracle
                    plays. In the beginning of the 16th century we find Parmentier, a native of the
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n216/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0216-0199"/> town, taking vessels to Brazil and Sumatra; and a
                    little later, its merchant pnπce, Ango, was able to blockade the Portuguese
                    fleet in the Tagus. Its inhabitants in great numbers embraced the Reformed
                    religion; and they were among the first to acknowledge Henry 1V., who fought one
                    of his great bkttles at the neighbouring village of Arques. Few of the cities of
                    France suffered more from the revocation of the Edict of Nantes in 1685; and
                    this blow was followed in 1694 by a terrible bombardment on the part of the
                    English and Dutch. The town was rebuilt after the peace of Ryswick, but the
                    decrease of its population and the deterioration of its port prevented the
                    restoration of its commercial prosperity. Within the present century, however,
                    especially since communication by rail was effected with Paris, it has made
                    rapid advances. During the Franco-German war the town was occupied by the
                    Germans from December 1870 till July 1871.</p>
                <p>See Pierre Pillon, <hi rend="italic">Recueil général des édits, &amp;c., donnez
                    en faveur des habitants de Dieppe,</hi> Dieppe, 1700; Vitet, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histoire de Dieppe,</hi> 1844; Cochet, <hi rend="italic">Les églises de
                    farrondissement de Dieppe,</hi> 1846-1850, and <hi rend="italic">Galerie
                    Dieppoise,</hi> 1862; Jules Hardy, <hi rend="italic">Les Dieppois en Guinée
                    en</hi> 1364, 1864; Asseline, <hi rend="italic">Les Antiquitez et Chroniques de
                    la ville de</hi><hi rend="italic">Dieppe,</hi> a 17th century account, which
                    comes down only to 1694, and was first published in 1874 by Hardy, Guerillon,
                    and Sauvage.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
