<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0523-0504-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DUCANGE, Charles Dufresne, Seigneur</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 504</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1091324">Rebuses</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1008230">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bt4s">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40k26k28">Rebuses</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n523/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DUCANGE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Dufresne,
                    Seigneur</hi></label> (16ΙΟΙ 6 88), a most learned historical and philological
                    writer, was born at Amiens, December 18,1610. His father, who was royal provost
                    of Beauquesne, sent him at an early age to the Jesuits’ College in Amiens, where
                    he soon distinguished himself. Having completed the usual course at this
                    seminary, he applied himself to the study of law at Orleans, and afterwards went
                    to Paris, where he was received as advocate before the parliament in August
                    1631. Meeting with little success as a barrister, he returned to his native
                    district, where he applied himself to the study of history. After the death of
                    his father, Ducange married at Amiens, on 19th July 1638, Catherine Du Bois,
                    daughter of a treasurer of France; and, in 1647, he purchased the office of his
                    father-in-law, the duties of which in no degree interfered with the great
                    literary works in which he had engaged. The plague, which in 1668 desolated
                    Amiens, forced him to leave that city. He established himself at Paris, where he
                    continued to reside until his death, which occurred on the 23d October 1688. In
                    the archives of Paris he was enabled to consult charters, diplomas, titles,
                    manuscripts, and a multitude of printed documents, which were not to be met with
                    elsewhere. His industry was exemplary and unremitting; and the number of his
                    literary works would be incredible, if the originals, all written in his own
                    hand, were not still extant. He was distinguished above nearly all the writers
                    of his time by his linguistic acquirements, his accurate and varied knowledge,
                    and his critical sagacity. Of his numerous published works noted below the most
                    important are the <hi rend="italic">Glossarium ad</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Scriptores</hi><hi rend="italic">mediae et infimae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Latinitatis</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Glossarium ad</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Scriptores</hi><hi rend="italic">mediae et infimae Graecitatis,</hi> which are
                    indispensable aids to the student of the history and literature of the Middle
                    Ages. To the three volumes of Ducange’s Latin glossary three supplementary
                    volumes were added by the Benedictines of St Maur (1733), and a further addition
                    of four volumes was made by Carpentier, a Benedictine, in 1766. The edition
                    published at Paris in that year accordingly consisted of ten volumes. The
                    edition by G. A. L. Henschel (8 vols., Paris, 1840-46) includes those
                    supplements and further additions by the editor.</p>
                <p>Ducange published the following works :—1. Histoire de ΓEm∙ {&gt;ire de
                    Constantinople sous les Empereurs François. Paris, 1657, olio. 2. Traité
                    Historique du Chef de S. Jean-Baptiste. Paris, 1666, 4to. 3. Histoire de S.
                    Louis, Roi de France, écrite par Jean, sire de Joinville. Paris, 1668, folio. 4.
                    Joannis Cinnaιni Historiarum de rebus gestis a Joanne et Manuele Comnenis libri
                    VI., Graece et Latine, cum Notis historicis et philologicis. Paris, 1670, folio.
                    5. Mémoire sur le projet d’un nouveau Recueil des Historiens de France, avec le
                    plan général de ce Recueil, inserted in the <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque
                    Historique de la France,</hi> by Père belong. 6. Glossarium ad Scriptores mediae
                    et infimae Latinitatis. Paris, 1678, 3 vols. fol. 7. Lettre du Sieur N.,
                    Conseiller du Roi, à son ami Μ. Ant. Wion d’Herouval, au sujet des Libelles qui
                    de temps en tempe se publient en Flandres contre les RR. PP. Henschenius et
                    Papebroch, Jésuites. Paris, 1682, 4to. 8. Historia Byzantina duplici Commentario
                    illustrata. Paris, 1680, fol. 9. Joannis Zonarae Annales ab exordio Mundi ad
                    mortem Alexii Comneni, Graece et Latine, cum Notis. Paris, 1686, 2 vols. fol.
                    10. Glossarium ad Scriptores mediae et infimae Graecitatis. Paris, 2 vols. fol.
                    11. Chronicon Paschale a Mundo condito ad Heraclii Imperatoris annum vigesimum.
                    Paris, 1689, fol. The last work was passing through the press when Ducange died;
                    and, on his decease, it was edited by Baluze, and published with an eloge of the
                    author prefixed.' His autograph manuscripts, and his extensive and valuable
                    library, passed to his eldest son, Philippe Dufresne, who died unmarried, four
                    years after. François Dufresne, the second son, and two sisters, then received
                    the succession and sold the library, when the greater part of the manuscripts
                    was purchased by the Abbé Du Champs, who handed them over to a bookseller called
                    Mariette, who re-sold part of them to Baron Hohendorf. The remaining part was
                    acquired by D’Hozier, the genealogist. But the French Government, aware of the
                    importance of all the writings of Ducange, succeeded, after much trouble, in
                    collecting the greater portion of these manuscripts, which were preserved in the
                    Imperial library of Paris. Among these manuscripts was one entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Gallia,</hi> a work of great erudition, being a history of France,
                    divided into seven epochs, with a number of dissertations.</p>
                <p>See Feugère’s Essai sur la vie et les ouvrages de Ducange (Paris, 1852).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
