<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0555-0536-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DUNDEE, John Graham of Claverhouse, Viscount</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 536</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1009087">Marching</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65f63">Soldiers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2md37">Missions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n555/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DUNDEE, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Graham of Claverhouse,
                    Viscount</hi></label> (1643-1689), born in or about the year 1643, was the elder
                    son of Sir William Graham ^nd Lady Jean Carnegie. Of his youth little record has
                    been kept; but in the year 1665 he appeared in St Andrews as a student of St
                    Leonard’s College. His education was upon the whole good, as appears from the
                    varied and valuable correspondence of his later years. Young Graham was destined
                    for a military career; and, having remained in St Andrews for about four years,
                    he proceeded abroad as a volunteer in the service of France. Thereafter, in
                    1672, he went to Holland, and obtained the post of comet in one of the cavalry
                    regiments of William, prince of Orange. In 1674 he was raised to the rank of
                    captain, as a reward for having rescued the prince from a marsh where his horse
                    had foundered during a retreat. Shortly afterwards, William having at his
                    disposal the command of one of the Scotch regiments in Holland, Graham made
                    application for the post. He was not appointed, and resigned his commission. In
                    the beginning of 1677 he returned to‘England, bearing, it is said, letters of
                    strong recommendation from William to Charles II. aud the duke of York.</p>
                <p>Early in 1678 he accepted a lieutenancy in a troop of horse under the command of
                    his relative the marquis of Montrose. Promotion immediately followed. He was ex
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n556/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0556-0537"/> pressly nominated by Charles II. to the command
                    of one of the newly raised troops of cavalry. From the time, indeed, of his
                    return to Scotland he assumed an influential position. His prestige as a
                    soldier, his uncompromising disposition, and his unmistakable capacity, at once
                    marked him out as a leader upon whom Government could rely. In the end of the
                    year he was despatched with his troop to Galloway to suppress the disorders
                    which prevailed in the district. He had a difficult and unpopular task,—that of
                    carrying out the policy of Lauderdale in the most disaffected part of Scotland.
                    The Act of 1670, imposing the punishment of death and confiscation of goods,
                    -was still in operation; and the Covenanters had for years before Graham’s
                    return to Scotland propounded the theory that opposition to the Government and
                    the actual slaughter of the king were not only just, but a religious duty.
                    Opposition to Lauderdale’s measures, however, was winked at by the duke of
                    Hamilton, and the recent authorized inroad of the Highlanders had widened the
                    area of dissatisfaction. It is not wonderful that the success of Graham in his
                    mission was smalL He entered, however, upon his occupation with zest, and
                    interpreted consistently the orders he received. There is evidence, also, that
                    his efforts were appreciated at headquarters, in his appointment, jointly with
                    the laird of Earls-hall, to the office of sheriff-depute of Dumfriesshire in
                    March 1679, with powers—specially narrated in his commission—anent “separation,”
                    conventicles, “disorderly baptisms and marriages,” and the like.</p>
                <p>For some years thereafter the position of Graham was perhaps as difficult and
                    delicate as one man was ever called upon to occupy. In the midst of enemies, and
                    in virtue of the most erroneous but direct orders of his Government, he combined
                    the functions of soldier, spy, prosecutor, and judge. Shortly after the murder
                    of Archbishop Sharp, on 5th May 1679, he was summoned to increased activity.
                    There were reports of an intended gathering in the neighbourhood of Glasgow, and
                    at the head of his dragoons Graham went in pursuit of the rebels. On Sunday the
                    1st of June, the Covenanters having removed from Loudon Hill to a well-protected
                    position upon the marshy ground of the farm of Drumclog, Graham, who had gone in
                    search of them, advanced. Hindered from the attack by the nature of the ground,
                    he had to wait till the impatience of his adversaries, who were under better
                    leadership than they ever afterwards enjoyed, induced them to commence an
                    impetuous attack. Headed by the youthful Clelland, the Covenanters charged the
                    cavalry, who in a little turned and fled. The loss of the victors was but three
                    men, while thirty-six dragoons were killed, Graham himself having a narrow
                    escape. This was the only regular engagement he had with the Covenanters. Small
                    as it was, the result raised an enthusiasm in the bosoms of the victors, and was
                    the beginning of an actual rebellion.</p>
                <p>On the 2 2d June Graham was present at the battle of Bothwell Bridge, at the head
                    of his own troop. Immediately thereafter he was commissioned to search the
                    southwestern shires for those who had taken part in the insurrection. In this
                    duty he seems to have been engaged till the early part of 1680, when he
                    disappears for a time from the record of these stringent measures. His powers
                    during these months were of the most sweeping description; and it appears that
                    his ample commission was most slenderly used. The gravest accusation against him
                    in reference to this period is that he was a robber.</p>
                <p>Graham had for some time been recognized as an adherent of the party who were
                    adverse to measures of leniency and conciliation. During these months he was
                    accordingly despatched to London along with Lord Linlithgow to influence the
                    mind of Charles II against the indulgent method adopted by Monmouth with the
                    extreme Covenanting party. It is perhaps not to his credit that he succeeded in
                    the object of his mission. He was then in the prime of life, was commandingly
                    handsome in appearance, a lover of sport, and a devoted royalist. Charles seems
                    to have been fascinated by his loyal supporter, and from that moment Graham was
                    destined to rise in rank and honours. On the 21st of April 1680 he obtained a
                    royal grant of the barony of the outlawed Macdowall of Freugh, and the grant was
                    confirmed by subsequent orders upon the Exchequer in Scotland. In April 1680 it
                    appears that his roving commission had been withdrawn by the Privy Council. He
                    is thus free from all concern with the severe measures which followed the
                    Sanquhar Declaration of 22d June 1680.</p>
                <p>The turbulence occasioned by the passing of the Test Act of 1681 required to be
                    quelled by a strong hand; and in the beginning of the following year Graham was
                    again commissioned to act in the disaffected districts. In the end of January he
                    was appointed to the sheriffships of Wigtown, Dumfries, Kirkcudbright, and
                    Annandale. He was besides acting captain of a troop of dragoons—the pernicious
                    combination of his offices being thus repeated. He appears further to have had
                    powers of life and death in virtue of a commission of justiciary granted to him
                    about the same time. In his despatches there are indications that he disapproved
                    of a system of indiscriminate punishment, and desired that severe vengeance
                    should only be executed upon ring-leaders and men of rank. This, however, appħed
                    solely to the harshest measures then known to the law, those of torture and
                    death. Where these were involved he preferred, after hunting out and seizing his
                    prisoners, to send them to Edinburgh for trial. But within these limits his
                    methods of procedure in the large districts over which he had control were
                    uncompromising, and, if we suppose him to have had sympathy with his orders,
                    most cruel. He quartered on the rebels, rifled their houses, and, to use his own
                    words, “endeavoured to destroy them by eating up their provisions.” The effect
                    of his policy, if we believe his own writ, is not overstated as</p>
                <p>“Death, desolation, nιin, and decay.”</p>
                <p>The result of a bitter quarrel with Sir John Dalrymple confirmed the prestige of
                    Graham, who was not only acquitted by the verdict of the Privy Council of the
                    grave charges of exaction and oppression preferred against him, but had the
                    satisfaction of seeing Sir John condemned to fine and imprisonment for
                    interference with his proceedings. On 25th December 1682 he was appointed
                    colonel of a new regiment raised in Scotland, and captain of its leading troop.
                    He had still greater honours in view, and in March 1683 he started for Newmarket
                    to demand an audience of the king. In the preceding January the case of the earl
                    of Lauderdale, late Maitland of Hatton, which involved the question of his
                    malversations with regard to the Scottish mint, was debated in the House of
                    Lords. Maitland was proprietor of the lands and lordship of Dundee and Dudhope,
                    and the decree of the lords against him was in March 1683 issued (or the sum of
                    .£72,000. Graham succeeded in having the property of the defaulter transferred
                    to him by royal grant, and in May the additional honour was conferred upon him
                    of nomination to the Privy Council of Scotland.</p>
                <p>Shortly afterwards Claverhouse was appointed to be present at the sittings of the
                    recently instituted Circuit Court of Justiciary in Stirling, Glasgow, Dumfries,
                    and Jedburgh. The notable objects of the circuit were the imposition of the test
                    and the punishment of rebels. Several were sentenced to death. During the rest
                    of the year he attended the meetings of council. As a statesman he was <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n557/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0557-0538"/> incapable of rising to an independent view of
                    affairs, and was unable to overcome his dutiful obedience to superior orders.
                    Although he had had experience of the most disaffected portions of the country,
                    there is but one record of his having interfered to prevent the accustomed
                    irritating measures. He declared decisively against the proposal to let loose
                    the Highland marauders upon the south of Scotland.</p>
                <p>In June 1684 he was again at his old employment—the inspection of the southern
                    shires; and in August, after the ambuscade of Enterkine-hill, he was
                    commissioned as second in command of the forces in Ayr and Clydesdale to search
                    out the rebels and report to head-quarters. By this time he was in possession of
                    Dudhope, having on the 10th of June married Lady Jean, daughter of Lord
                    Cochrane. As constable of Dundee it is recorded to his honour that he
                    recommended to the Privy Council the remission of extreme punishment in the case
                    of many petty offences. He issued from his retirement to take part in a
                    commission of lieutenancy which perambulated as a criminal court the southern
                    districts; and in the end of the year he was again in the same region on the
                    occasion of the disturbances in the town of Kirkcudbright.</p>
                <p>Shortly after the death of Charles II. (6th February 1685), Graham, through the
                    jealous efforts of Queensberry, incurred a temporary disgrace by his deposition
                    from the office of privy councillor; but in May he was reinstalled, although it
                    is to be observed that his commission of justiciary which had expired was not
                    renewed.</p>
                <p>In May 1685 he was ordered with his cavalry to guard the borders, and to scour
                    the south-west in search of rebels. By Act of Privy Council, a certificate was
                    required by all persons over sixteen years of age to free them from the hazard
                    of attack from Government officials. Without that they were at once liable to be
                    called upon oath to abjure the declaration of Renwick, which was alleged to be
                    treasonable. While on this mission he pursued and overtook two men—John Brown,
                    and a nephew whom he calls John Brownen. Brown, having refused the abjuration
                    oath, was shot dead. The order was within the authorized power of Graham.</p>
                <p>Until 1688 there is little more of note in his career. In 1686 he was promoted to
                    the rank of major-general, and had added to his position of constable the not
                    inconsiderable dignity of provost of Dundee. He appears, however, in the Privy
                    Council in 1688 opposing the proposal that Lieutenant-General Douglas should
                    have command of the whole army which had been ordered to England to aid the
                    falling dynasty.</p>
                <p>A week or two after his departure with the army his fascinating influence had
                    made itself felt upon James 11., and .amid the hurry of events he was created
                    viscount of Dundee on 12th November 1688. From York he went to Salisbury, where
                    he advised James to sterner measures than the feeble-hearted monarch had the
                    courage to adopt. Throughout the vexed joumeyings of the king, Dundee is found
                    accompanying or following him, endeavouring in vain to prompt him to make his
                    stand in England and fight rather than flee from the invader. At last J amés
                    announced his resolve, with the promise that he would send from France an
                    appointment in favour of Dundee to command the troops in Scotland, and
                    arrangements were entered into for communication with the voluntary exile.</p>
                <p>Dundee returned to Scotland in anticipation of the meeting of the Convention, and
                    at once exerted himself to increase the waning resolution of the duke of Gordon
                    with regard to holding Edinburgh Castle for the exiled king. He had conceived
                    the idea of forming a rival Convention at Stirling to sit in the name of James
                    IL, but the hesitancy of his associates rendered the design futile, and it was
                    given up. Dundee, however, boldly appeared at the first meeting of Convention on
                    16t h March 1686, and disclosed a plot which he declared he had discovered
                    against his own life, but the matter after some inquiry was departed from.</p>
                <p>On the 18th of March, despising the fears of his promised allies, he left
                    Edinburgh at the head of a company of fifty dragoons, who were strongly attached
                    to his person. He was not long gone ere the news was brought to the alarmed
                    Convention that he had been seen clambering up the west side of the castle rock
                    and holding conference with the duke of Gordon. In excitement and confusion
                    order after order was despatched in reference to the fugitive, and the
                    Convention sat with locked doors to prevent communication with traitors without.
                    Dundee retired to Dudhope. On the 30th of March he was publicly denounced as a
                    traitor, and in the latter half of April attempts were made to secure him at
                    Dudhope, and the residence in Glen Ogilvy to which he had retired. But the
                    secrecy and speed of his movements outwitted his pursuers, and he retreated to
                    the north. His career presents strange peculiarities. It was only in 1678 that
                    he had returned to Scotland from abroad. Yet in the short period of intervening
                    years he had, despite the opposition of his superiors in rank, risen from the
                    post of captain, and the social status of a small Scotch laird, to positions as
                    a soldier and statesman and the favourite of his sovereigns, of the greatest
                    dignity, influence, and wealth. Yet it was in this period that he committed
                    those acts on account of which his memory is loaded with reproach. When the
                    ruling dynasty changed, and he who had so often been commissioned to quell
                    insurrection had himself become an outlaw and a rebel, he supported the cause of
                    his exiled monarch with such skill and valour that his name and death are
                    recorded as heroic.</p>
                <p>On his march into the Highlands he commenced among the chieftains the diplomatic
                    policy in which he excelled. General Hugh Mackay was now in the field against
                    him, and what was simply a Highland chase began. Mackay started with a body of
                    cavalry, marched to the north, and having refused reinforcements from the
                    untrained peasantry of Aberdeenshire, pushed the pursuit further and further to
                    the west. Elgin, and latterly Inverness, were occupied by the Government troops.
                    Dundee had in the meantime been scouring the country from Perth, which on the
                    11th of May he had plundered, to the wilds of Lochaber, to which he had latterly
                    retired. The clans were assembled by the 28th of May, and on the 29th the castle
                    of Ruthven, near Kingussie, was seized. The army of Dundee was now much superior
                    in numbers to that of Mackay, and the prudent general beat a hasty retreat.
                    Having received reinforcements, however, he again advanced northward, and in
                    Strathdon, in the early part of June, it seemed likely that the opposing forces
                    would meet. But the Highland warriors, laden with plunder, were returning
                    homewards, and the army of Dundee was melting away. The outlawed leader again
                    retired, and Mackay conceived his mission at an end. He proceeded westward, and,
                    having garrisoned Inverness, marched to the south.</p>
                <p>Throughout the <hi rend="subscript"> ι</hi> whole of the campaign Dundee w;is
                    indefatigable in his exertions with the Highland chiefs and his communications
                    with his exiled king. To the day of his death he believed that formidable
                    succour for his cause was about to arrive from Ireland and France. He justly
                    considered himself at the head of the Stewart interest in Scotland, and his
                    despatches form a record of the little incidents of the campaign, strangely
                    combined with a revelation of the designs of the statesman. It mattered little
                    to him that on the 24th of July a price of .£20,000 had been placed upon his
                    head. The clans had begun to reassemble, and he was now in command of a
                    considerable force.</p>
                <p>Mackay, who had visited Edinburgh to report events, returned<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n558/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0558-0539"/> to Berth, whence, with an army now amounting to
                    about 4000 men, he proceeded to Dunkeld on the 26th of July. While in the
                    metropolis he had endeavoured to secure the Athole interest, and that the castle
                    of Blair should be held for King William. But he was as usual outwitted by
                    Dundee, who, after unsuccessful negotiations with Lord Murray, won over the
                    Athole factor by the presentation of a commission prepared for the occasion. The
                    castle was at once occupied, and at Dunkeld Mackay received intelligence that
                    the design of his march was frustrated. By ten <hi rend="smallcaps">a.m.</hi> of
                    the 27th of July 1689 he was at the entrance to the pass of Killiecrankie.</p>
                <p>Dundee had appointed a gathering of the clans at Blair for the 29th; and on the
                    27th he was at the head of at least 2000 men, including a contingent from
                    Ireland. The reports of scouts that 400 of the enemy had already threaded the
                    pass roused the impatience of the chiefs. But it was not until he received
                    intelligence that the whole army of Mackay had entered the defile that he gave
                    the order to march. With caution he disposed his troops on the hills to the
                    right of the opposing army, which, making its exit from the gully, was forming
                    on the haughs. On Mackay’s right and beyond the narrow plain were undulating
                    heights backed by Craig Culloch. On one of these Mackay was astonished to
                    observe the movement of the troops of Dundee. To prevent the enemy from gaining
                    an intervening eminence, he at once ordered a flank movement, and his army
                    marched up the face of the hillock, leaving the Garry in the rear. For several
                    hours the two armies faced each other, Dundee restraining the impatience of his
                    troops, but at eight in the evening the order was given to advance. Mackay had
                    formed his line three deep, while his opponent had arranged his men in
                    battalions with intervals wide enough to prevent the outflanking of superior
                    numbers. The Highlanders having discharged their firelocks threw them on the
                    ground, and rushed impetuously on the foe. The result was instantaneous;
                    Mackay’s line was broken and driven helplessly into the gorge. Dundee, at the
                    head of his cavalry, charged the enemy, but, confusion having arisen as to the
                    leadership of the troop, he was not at once followed. The gallant soldier,
                    waving on his men, was pierced beneath the breastplate by a bullet of the enemy,
                    and fell dying from his horse. Dundee asked “how the day went,” and, hearing the
                    answer and the expression of sympathy, replied that “it was the less matter for
                    him seeing the day went well for his master.” He was conveyed to the castle of
                    Blair, where within an hour or two of his death he was able to write a short
                    account of the engagement to King James. The battle, in which the Government
                    forces had lost 2000 men as against 900 of the enemy, was in truth the end of
                    the insurrection. The Highland camp was broken by jealousies, for the
                    controlling and commanding genius of the rebellion was no more.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Memorials and Letters of Graham of Claverhouse,</hi> by
                    Mark Napier, 1859-62, where the literature of the subject is referred to. The
                    work itself must be read with caution. (T. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
