<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0048-0039-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DELACROIX, Ferdinand Victor</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 39</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45x1d">Salons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4k931f29">Ruins</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qz22m9r">Giants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1104198">Salons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1004133">Luxembourgers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1137041">Success</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1211813">Luxembourg</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205592">Morocco</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n48/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DELACROIX, <hi rend="smallcaps">Ferdinand
                    Victor</hi></label>' <hi rend="smallcaps">Eug⅛ne,</hi> (1798- 1863), a French
                    painter of history, was born at Charenton-St-Maurice, near Paris, 26th April
                    1798. His father was a partisan of the most violent faction during the time of
                    the Revolution. The family affairs seem to have been conducted in the wildest
                    manner, and the accidents that befell the child, well authenticated as they are
                    said to be, make it almost a miracle that he survived. He was first nearly
                    burned to death in the cradle by a nurse falling asleep over a novel, and the
                    candle dropping on the coverlet; this left permanent marks on his arms and face.
                    He was next dropped into the sea by another <hi rend="italic">bonne,</hi> who
                    was climbing up a ship’s side to see her lover. He was nearly poisoned, and
                    nearly choked, and, to crown all, he tried to hang himself, without any thought
                    of suicide, in imitation of a print exhibiting a man in that position of final
                    ignominy. The prediction of a charlatan founded on his horoscope has been
                    preserved :—“Cet enfant deviendra un homme célèbre, mais sa vie sera des plus
                    laborieuses, des plus tourmentées, et toujours livrée à la contradiction.”</p>
                <p>Delacroix the elder died at Bordeaux when Eugene was seven years of age, and his
                    mother returned to Paris and placed him in the Lycée Napoléon. Afterwards, on
                    his determining to be a painter, he entered the <hi rend="italic">atelier</hi>
                    of Baron Guérin, who affected to treat him as an amateur. His fellow-pupil was
                    Scheffer, who was alike by temperament and antecedents the opposite of the <hi
                    rend="italic">bizarre</hi> Delacroix, and the two remained antagonistic to the
                    end of life. Delacroix’s acknowledged power and yet want of success with artists
                    and critics—Thiers being his only advocate—perhaps mainly resulted from his
                    bravura and rude dash in the use of the brush, at a time when smooth roundness
                    of surface was general. His first important picture, Dante and Virgil, was
                    painted in his own studio; and when Guérin went to see it he flew into a
                    passion, and told him his picture was absurd, detestable, exaggerated. “Why ask
                    me to come and see this? you knew what I must say.” Yet his work was received at
                    the Salon, and produced an enthusiasm of debate (1822). Some said Géricault had
                    worked on it, but all treated it with respect. Still in private his position,
                    even after the larger tragic picture, the Massacre of Scipio, had been deposited
                    in the Luxembourg by the Government, became that of an Ishmaelite The war for
                    the freedom of Greece then going on moved him deeply, and his next two
                    pictures—Marino Faliero Decapitated on the Giant’s Staircase of the Ducal Palace
                    (which has always remained a European success), and Greece Lamenting on the
                    Ruins of Missolonghi—with many smaller works, were exhibited for the benefit of
                    the patriots in 1826. This exhibition was much visited by the public, and next
                    year he produced another of his important works, Sardanapalus, from Byron’s
                    drama. After this, he says, “I became the abomination of painting, I was refused
                    water and salt,”—but, he adds with singularly happy naïveté, “J’étais enchanté
                    de moi-même !” The patrimony he inherited, or, perhaps it should be said, what
                    remained of it, was 10,000 <hi rend="italic">livres de rente,</hi> and with
                    economy he lived on this, and continued the expensive process of painting large
                    historical pictures. In 1831 he reappeared in the Salon with six works, and
                    immediately after left for Morocco, where <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n49/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0049-0040"/> he found much congenial matter. Delacroix never
                    went to Italy; he refused to go on principle, lest the old masters, either in
                    spirit or manner, should impair his originality and self-dependence. His
                    greatest admiration in literature was the poetry of Byron; Shakespeare also
                    attracted him for tragic inspirations; and of course classic subjects had their
                    turn on his easel.</p>
                <p>He continued his work indefatigably, having his pictures very seldom favourably
                    received at the Salon. These were sometimes very large, full of incidents, with
                    many figures. Drawing of Lots in the Boat at Sea, from Byron’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Don Juan,</hi> and the Taking of Constantinople by the Christians, were of that
                    character, and the first-named was one of his noblest creations. In 1845 he was
                    employed to decorate the library of the Luxembourg, that of the Chamber of
                    Deputies in 1847, the ceiling of the Gallery of Apollo in the Louvre in 1849,
                    and that of the Salon de la Paix in the Hotel de Ville in 1853. He died on the
                    13th August 1863; and in August 1864 an exposition of his works was opened on
                    the Boulevard des Italiens. It contained 174 pictures, many of them of large
                    dimensions, and 303 drawings, showing immense perseverance as well as energy and
                    versatility.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
