<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0040-0031-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DE GÉRANDO, Marie Joseph (9th edition, volume 7, page
                    31)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:881894">Cousins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095999">Restorationism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kk48">Arm</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n40/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DE GÉRANDO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Marie Joseph</hi></label>
                    (1772-1842), one of the most distinguished ethical and metaphysical philosophers
                    of France, was born at Lyons, February 29, 1772. When that city was besieged in
                    1793 by the armies of the republic, the young De Gérando took up arms in defence
                    of his native place, was made prisoner, and with difficulty escaped with his
                    life. He first took refuge in Switzerland, whence he afterwards fled to Naples.
                    In 1796, after an exile of three years, the establishment of the Directory
                    allowed him to return to France. Finding himself, at the age of twenty-five,
                    without a profession, he resolved to embrace the career of arms, and enlisted as
                    a private in a cavalry regiment. About this time the Institute had proposed as a
                    subject for an essay this question,—“What is the influence of symbols on the
                    faculty of thought!” De Gérando gained the prize, and heard of his success after
                    the battle of Zurich, in which he had distinguished himself. This literary
                    triumph was the first step in his upward career. In 1799 he was attached to the
                    ministry of the interior by Lucien Bonaparte; in 1804 he became general
                    secretary under Champagny; in 1805 he accompanied Napoleon into Italy; in 1808
                    he was nominated master of requests; in 1811 he received the title of councillor
                    of state; and in the following year he was appointed governor of Catalonia. On
                    the overthrow of the empire, De Gérando <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n41/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0041-0032"/> was allowed to retain this office; but having
                    been sent during the hundred days into the department of the Moselle to organize
                    the defence of that district, he was punished at the second Restoration by a few
                    months of neglect. He was soon after, however, readmitted into the council of
                    state, where he distinguished himself by the prudence and conciliatory tendency
                    of his views. In 1819 he opened at the law-school of Paris a class of public and
                    administrative law, which in 1822 was suppressed by Government, but was
                    re-opened six years later under theMartignac ministry. In 1837 the Government
                    acknowledged the long and important services which De Gérando had rendered to
                    his country by raising him to the peerage. He died in Paris, November 9, 1842,
                    at the age of seventy.</p>
                <p>De Gérando’s works are very numerous. That by which he is best known now, and
                    which constitutes his chief title to posthumous fame, is his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Histoire Comparée des Systèmes de Philosophie relativement aux principes
                        des Connaissances Humaines,</hi> of which the first edition appeared at
                    Paris in 1804, in 3 vols. 8vo. The germ of this work had already appeared in the
                    author’s <hi rend="italic">Mémoire de la Génération</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >des</hi><hi rend="italic">Connaissances Humaines,</hi> crowned by the
                    Academy of Berlin, and published at Berlin in 1802. In this work De Gérando,
                    after a rapid review of ancient and modern speculations on the origin of our
                    ideas, singles out the theory of primary ideas, which he endeavours to combat
                    under ail its forms. The latter half of the work, devoted to the analysis of the
                    intellectual faculties, is intended to show how all human knowledge is the
                    result of experience; and reflection is assumed as the source of our ideas of
                    substance, of unity, and of identity.</p>
                <p>De Gérando’s great work is divided into two parts, the first of which is purely
                    historical, and -devoted to an exposition of various philosophical systems; iu
                    the second, which comprises fourteen chapters of the entire work, the
                    distinctive characters and value of these systems are compared and discussed.
                    Great fault has been found with this plan, and justly, as it is impossible to
                    separate advantageously the history and critical examination of any doctrine in
                    the arbitrary manner which De Gérando has chosen for himself. Despite this
                    disadvantage, however, the work has great merits. It brought back the minds of
                    men to a due veneration for the great names in philosophical science,—a point
                    which had been utterly neglected by Condillac and his school. In correctness of
                    detail and comprehensiveness of view it was greatly superior to every work of
                    the same kind that had hitherto appeared in France. During the Empire and the
                    first years of the Restoration, De Gérando found time, despite his political
                    avocations, to recast the first edition of his <hi rend="italic">Histoire
                        Comparée,</hi> of which a second edition appeared at Paris in 1823, in 4
                    vols. 8vo. The plan and method of this edition are the same as in the first; but
                    it is enriched with so many additions that it may pass for an entirely new work.
                    The last chapter of the part published during the author’s lifetime ends with
                    the revival of letters and the philosophy of the 15th century. The second part,
                    carrying the work down to the close of the 18th century, was published
                    posthumously by his son in four vols. (Paris, 1847). Twenty-three chapters of
                    this had been left complete by the author in manuscript; the remaining three
                    were supplied from other sources, chiefly printed but unpublished memoirs.</p>
                <p>The next valuable work of De Gérando was his essay <hi rend="italic">Du</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">perfectionnement</hi><hi rend="italic">moral</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">V</hi><hi rend="italic">éducation de
                        soi-même,</hi> crowned by the French Academy in 1825. The fundamental idea
                    of this work is that human life is in reality only a great education, of which
                    perfection is the aim.</p>
                <p>Besides the works already mentioned, De Gérando left many others, of which we may
                    indicate the following :— <hi rend="italic">Considérations sur diverses méthodes
                        d’observation des peuples sauvages,</hi> 8vo, Paris, 1801; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Eloge</hi><hi rend="italic">de Dumarsais,—discours qui a remporté le prix
                        proposé par la seconde classe de l'institut National,</hi> 8vo, Paris, 1805;
                        <hi rend="italic">Le Visiteur du pauvre,</hi> 8vo, Paris, 1820; <hi
                        rend="italic">Institutes</hi><hi rend="italic">du Droit Administratif,</hi>
                    4 vols. 8vo, Paris, 1830; <hi rend="italic">Cours normal des instituteurs
                        primaires ou Directions relatives à Véducation physique, morale, et
                        intellectuelle dans les écoles primaires,</hi> 8vo, Paris, 1832; <hi
                        rend="italic">De Véducation des Sourds-Muets,</hi> 2 vols. Paris, 1832; <hi
                        rend="italic">De la Bienfaisance publique,</hi> 4 vols. 8vo, 1838. A
                    detailed analysis of the <hi rend="italic">Histoire Comparée des Systèmes</hi>
                    will he found in the <hi rend="italic">Fragments</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Philosophiques</hi> of Μ. Cousin.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
