<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0602-0591-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHESNEY, Charles Cornwallis (9th edition, volume 5,
                    page 591)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1046386">Operationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:959074">Home</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204739">Maryland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n87339t">Government</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n602/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHESNEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Cornwallis</hi></label>
                    (1826-1876), brevetcolonel in the corps of Royal Engineers, born 29th September
                    1826, was the third son of Charles Cornwallis Chesney, captain on the retired
                    list of the Bengal Artillery. Educated at Tiverton grammar school and Mount
                    Radford school, Exeter, and afterwards at the Royal Military Academy, Woolwich,
                    he obtained his first commission as second-lieutenant of engineers in 1845,
                    passing out of the academy with distinction at the head of his term. His early
                    service was spent in the ordinary course of regimental duty at home and abroad,
                    and being stationed in New Zealand during the Crimean War, he lost the
                    opportunity of serving in the only considerable military operations in Europe in
                    which the present generation of British soldiers has been engaged, while India,
                    the great school of war for the English army, was until lately closed to
                    officers of the Royal Artillery and Engineers. Among the various reforms in our
                    military system which followed from that war was the impetus given to military
                    education; military history was now for the first time introduced into the
                    course of instruction at our military colleges, and in 1858 Charles Chesney, who
                    had brought himself under notice by an essay on the subject, prepared under a
                    sort of competition invited by the authorities, was appointed professor of
                    military history at Sandhurst. In 1864 Captain Chesney succeeded Colonel Hamley
                    in the corresponding chair at the Staff College. To the admirable teaching of
                    these two officers may be ascribed in great measure the intelligent appreciation
                    of the relation of military history to the practical business of war now
                    manifested throughout the commissioned ranks of the British army; their
                    published writings have been received with great favour on the Continent and in
                    America.</p>
                <p>Chesney’s first published work was an account of the civil war in Virginia, which
                    went through several editions; and although written in the heat of the struggle,
                    and on the partial information then available, it may still be read with profit.
                    But the work which attained the greatest reputation was his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Waterloo Lectures,</hi> prepared from the notes of lectures orally delivered at
                    the Staff College. Up to this time the English literature on the Waterloo
                    campaign, although voluminous, was made up of personal reminiscences of actors
                    in the great scene, or of formal records such as Siborne’s accurate but tedious
                    narrative, useful materials for history rather than history itself; the French
                    accounts have mainly taken the form of fiction, the so-called history of
                    Lamartine being as much a work of fancy as the romance of Victor Hugo, while the
                    professedly sober pages of Thiers are not much more to be relied on. In
                    Chesney’s lucid and vigorous account of the momentous struggle, while it
                    illustrates both the strategy and tactics which culminated in the final
                    catastrophe, the mistakes committed by Napoleon are laid bare, and for the first
                    time an English writer is found to point out that the dispositions of the great
                    duke were not wholly faultless. Yet such criticism is in truth the sincerest
                    praise, since to those who, knowing anything of war, know that even the highest
                    combinations are at best a groping in partial darkness, the capacity of a great
                    leader will be more perfectly appreciated by a right estimate of his mistakes
                    than by a blind attribution of infallibihty. And in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Waterloo Lectures</hi> the Prussians are for the first time credited by an
                    English pen with their proper share in the victory. On this point there had
                    hitherto been an English as well as a Napoleonic legend. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Waterloo Lectures</hi> attracted much attention abroad as well as at home; on
                    the appearance of the French edition, published at Brussels, another account of
                    the campaign, written at the instance of the emperor Napoleon III., and quite in
                    the spirit of the Napoleonic legend, was published immediately afterwards in
                    Paris in a cover to correspond exactly with the Brussels edition, and with the
                    obvious intention that it should circulate in place of the other,—a delicate
                    test of the appreciation of the original on the part of the French
                    Government.</p>
                <p>Chesney was for many years a constant contributor to the newspaper press and to
                    periodic literature, devoting himself for the most part to the critical
                    treatment of military operations, and professional subjects generally. Some of
                    his essays on military biography, contributed mainly to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Edinburgh Review,</hi> were afterwards published separately. His style is
                    forcible, easy, and eminently clear, his judgment impartial and sagacious, and
                    although his mode of treating military operations may be open to the criticism
                    that it does not make sufficient allowance for the moral element in war—the
                    infirmities of troops and the blunders of generals,—it may be said on the other
                    hand that the whole truth is never told about battles at the time, and cannot be
                    found out afterwards, and that in the long run the less there is of the personal
                    in history, and the broader and more general the statement, the nearer will the
                    historian come to describing what happened.</p>
                <p>In 1868 Charles Chesney, who on promotion to field rank had returned to
                    regimental duty, was appointed a member of the Royal Commission on Military
                    Education which sat during that and the following year, under the presidency
                    first of Earl de Grey and afterwards of Lord Dufferin, and to whose
                    recommendations are due the improved organization of our military colleges, and
                    the development of military education throughout the principal military stations
                    of the British army. In 1871, immediately after the conclusion of the
                    Franco-German war, he was sent on a special mission to France and Germany, and
                    furnished to the Government a series of valuable reports on the different siege
                    operations which had been carried out during the war, including especially the
                    two sieges of Paris, and on the condition of the fortresses and military
                    condition and organization of the two powers. These reports were published in a
                    large volume, only a few copies of which have been issued confidentially.</p>
                <p>Never seeking regimental or staff preferment, Colonel Chesney never obtained any,
                    but he held at the time of his death a quite unique position in the army,
                    altogether apart from and above his actual place in it. Consulted by officers of
                    all grades on professional matters, his ready and vigorous pen was often placed
                    at the service of the Govern ment to illustrate and defend in the press the
                    different measures of reform lately adopted in military organization; while
                    probably few have done more to raise the intellectual standard of the English
                    army and its estimation in that respect among the more intelligent spirits of
                    foreign armies. Constantly engaged in literary pursuits, he was nevertheless
                    laborious and exemplary in the discharge of his public duties, while managing
                    also to devote a large part of his time to charitable and religious offices. He
                    was abstemious to a fault; and, overwork of both mind and body telling at last
                    on a frail constitution, he died after a short illness on the 19th March 1876,
                    at the age of forty-nine years, to the regret of the whole army, and of a very
                    large circle of friends both within and without the service, to whom he had
                    become endeared in a remarkable degree by his generous, self-denying, and
                    sympathetic disposition. At the time of his death he was serving as Commanding
                    Royal Engineer of the London district.</p>
                <p>Colonel Chesneys principal works were:— <hi rend="italic">A Military View of
                    Recent Campaigns in Virginia and Maryland,</hi> 1863; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Campaigns in Virginia and Maryland,</hi> 2d edition, 1865; <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Military Resources of Prussia and France, and Recent Changes in the Art of
                    War; Essays by Charles Chesney and Henry Reeve,</hi> republished jointly from
                    the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> 1870; <hi rend="italic">Waterloo
                    Lectures,</hi> 3d edition, 1874; <hi rend="italic">Essays in Modern Military
                    Biography,</hi> reprinted chiefly from the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh
                    Review,</hi> 1874. (G. C.) <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n603/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0603-0592"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
