<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0039-0030-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CANTERBURY (9th edition, volume 5, page 30)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1056939">Peninsulas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n39/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CANTERBURY</label>, a province of New Zealand, occupying the
                    central portion of the Middle Island on the eastern side of the great dividing
                    range of the Southern Alps. It is bounded on the E. by the sea, and on the N.,
                    W., and S. by the provinces of Nelson, Westland, and Otago respectively. The
                    area of Canterbury is about 8,693,000 acres.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n40/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0040-0031"/>
                <p>Physically, the province may be divided into two longitudinal sections, from
                    north to south. Of these the more westerly, which is considerably the larger, is
                    mountainous, sloping eastward into downs, while the other consists of a plain,
                    covering an area of 2,500,000 acres. To these two main divisions must be added
                    Banks Peninsula, an isolated hilly district on the eastern edge of the plain,
                    jutting into the sea, and with an area of 250,000 acres. Thus the surface of the
                    province is of the most diversified character, varying from the snow-clad peaks
                    of the Southern Alps, which culminate in Mount Cook (13,200.feet), the highest
                    mountain in New Zealand, to the dead level of the plain on which Christchurch
                    stands, only a few feet above the sea. In lakes Canterbury gives place to Otago
                    and Auckland, though Lakes Ohau and Coleridge are large sheets of water,
                    situated amid scenery of the most beautiful description. The rivers of
                    Canterbury are short and rapid, running with a direct course to the sea, and
                    quite useless for purposes of navigation. Apart from the Hurunui and Waitangi,
                    which divide Canterbury on the north-east and south-east from Nelson and Otago
                    respectively, and hence belong equally to those provinces, the principal rivers
                    of Canterbury are the Ashley, Waimakariri, Rakaia, Ashburton, and Rangitata.
                    They are all very liable to sudden and disastrous floods. The coast is poorly
                    supplied with good harbours, that of Akaroa, in Banks Peninsula, being the only
                    one safe in all kinds of weather. The harbour of Lyttelton is spacious, but
                    exposed to easterly winds. The capital of Canterbury is Christchurch, and the
                    other principal settlements are Lyttelton and Akaroa already mentioned, Kaiapoi
                    a few miles north of Christchurch, and Timaru, 110 miles south of the latter
                    place.</p>
                <p>The downs and great plain of Canterbury are devoid of forests, but the mountain
                    regions and Banks Peninsula yield abundance of excellent timber. The principal
                    trees are the totara <hi rend="italic">(Podocarpus Totara),</hi> rimu or red
                    pine <hi rend="italic">(Dacrydium</hi><hi rend="italic">cupressinum),</hi> and
                    kahikatea or white pine <hi rend="italic">(Podocarpus dacrydioides).</hi> Coal
                    well adapted for household and industrial purposes, though not of the first
                    quality, is found in the Malvern Hills, to the west of Christcl1ur3h, and beds
                    of clay ironstone exist in various localities, but are not yet worked. Gold is
                    found in the south-western angle of the province, near the Otago border, though
                    not in sufficient quantity to tempt many to search for it. The wealth of
                    Canterbury consists in its flocks and its yield of agricultural produce. In 1874
                    the province contained 2,965,000 sheep and 79,000 cattle. The number of
                    agricultural holdings was 3969, and the total area of land under crops of all
                    kinds, including cultivated grass, was about 390,000 acres, of which 112,000
                    acres were under cereals. The imports of Canterbury in 1874 amounted to
                    £1,568,826, and the exports to £1,108,531,—by far the greater proportion of the
                    latter consisting of wool, wheat, and oats. The export of phormium fibre (New
                    Zealand flax), from which much was at one time expected, has greatly declined,
                    but on the other hand the export of preserved meats is rapidly rising in
                    importance. The population of the province on 31st December 1874 was 71,316.
                    Besides possessing many good roads, Canterbury is fast being opened up by
                    railways. The first of these, from Lyttelton to Christchurch, a distance of
                    eight miles, was tunnelled at great expense through the hills at the back of the
                    former town. The line has since been continued on both sides of Christchurch—as
                    far south as the River Rangitata, and as far north as the River Ashley, while
                    branch lines have been, or are being, constructed to the settlements of
                    Southbridge, Malvern, and Oxford. The first railway having been of the 5-feet
                    3-inch gauge, the main line is for the most part of that width, while the
                    branches are of the narrow gauge of 3 feet 6 inches, which is almost universally
                    adopted in other parts of the colony.</p>
                <p>The educational system of Canterbury is comprehensive and efficient. In addition
                    to the New Zealand University (an examining institution, supported by the colony
                    as a whole, but having its headquarters at Christchurch), there are in the
                    capital several educational institutions of high standing. Spread over the
                    province there are also, in addition to schools maintained by private
                    enterprise, many Government schools. The number of these on 31st March 1875 was
                    93. They were conducted by 288 teachers and attended by 12,000 scholars.</p>
                <p>Canterbury was founded in December 1850 by an association headed by men of
                    influential position in England, and’ connected with the national church. It was
                    indeed sought for a time to prevent persons not members of the Church of England
                    from settling in Canterbury, but the attempt was a failure. In 1867 the portion
                    of the province west of the Southern Alps was formed into a separate province,
                    under the name of Westland. Further particulars regarding the history of
                    Canterbury will be found under the heading <hi rend="smallcaps">New
                    Zealand.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
