<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0229-0218-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CATANIA (9th edition, volume 5, page 218)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7c03z">Lava</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198504">Lava</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945091">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n229/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CATANIA</label>, the ancient <hi rend="italic">Catana,</hi> a
                    city and seaport of Sicily and the chief town of a province, is situated on the
                    east coast of the island, at the foot of the southern projections of Mount Etna,
                    about 60 miles by rail from Messina, in 37° 28' 20" N. lat. and 15° 5' 15" E.
                    long. It is one of the most important and attractive cities in the island, and
                    has a fine appearance from the sea. Its streets are wide, regular, and finely
                    paved with blocks of lava; and not only its public buildings but a large number
                    of its private mansions are spacious and handsome structures of lava and
                    limestone ornamented with marble. Among its churches, which number upwards of a
                    hundred, the first place is held by the cathedral, originally founded by Roger
                    I. in 1091, but for the most part rebuilt since the earthquake of 1693; and, at
                    the head of its monastic institutions stands the great Benedictine abbey of San
                    Nicolo, which occupies an area of about 21 acres, and has hardly more than two
                    or three buildings of the same kind in Europe to be compared withit. Its first
                    foundation dates from 1518, when the Benedictines removed from the town of
                    Nicolosi further up the slope of Mount Etna, where they had been settled since
                    1359; but the present buildings were erected in the beginning of the 18th
                    century by Contini of Rome. The church is principa∏y remarkable for a grand
                    organ, with seventy-two stops and 2916 pipes, built by Donato del Piano in 1760.
                    The chief educational institution is the university founded in 1445 by Alphonso
                    of Aragon; it has five faculties and thirty-eight professors, and was attended
                    in 1873 by 233 students. The library is of considerable extent; but its
                    collections of antiquities are surpassed by those in the Biscari Museum, founded
                    by Prince Ignazio Biscari in the end of the 18th century. The senate house, the
                    theatre, and the hospitals are the most important of the other buildings; and
                    among the associations may be mentioned an academy of sciences and a college of
                    the fine arts. Remains of the Roman period are numerous and extensive; they
                    include a theatre, an amphitheatre, an odeum, several baths known as the Bagni
                    Achillei, a number of tombs to the north-west of the town, and a few fragments
                    of a so-called temple of Ceres. The theatre is for the most part buried under
                    the <hi rend="italic">débris</hi> of volcanic disturbances; and it has at
                    different times served as a quarry for more modern buildings. Catania is the
                    seat of a bishop, a prefect, and a court of appeal, as well as the residence of
                    the grand prior of the Order of Malta. It is a place of great wealth, and is
                    remarkable for the display of its festivals, of which the most important is held
                    in August in honour of Santa Agata, the patroness of the city. Its industry and
                    commerce are of considerable importance; silk and linen are largely
                    manufactured, and there is a regular export of sulphur, grain, fruits, macaroni,
                    olives, and articles in amber and lava. In 1873 the sulphur shipped amounted to
                    57,383 tons. In 1871 there entered the port 2297 sailing and 434 steam ships,
                    with a respective tonnage of 97,442 and 162,387 tons. The value of the exports
                    to Great Britain in 1874 was £160,000. The harbour is small, and accessible only
                    to comparatively small craft, but another is in course of construction, which
                    will be capable of receiving vessels of the largest size. Population in 1871,
                    84,379.</p>
                <p>The ancient Catanawas founded (730 B.c.)by a colony from the neighbouring city of
                    Naxos, which was itself founded by the Chalcidians of Euboea. It maintained its
                    independence till 476 B.c., when it was taken by Hiero I., who removed its
                    inhabitants to Leontini, and repeopled the city with a new colony of 5000
                    Syracusans and an equal number of Peloponnesians, at the same time changing its
                    name to Aetna. Soon after the death of Hiero the former inhabitants obtained
                    possession of the town, when it again took the name of Catana. In 403 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> it was taken by Dionysius of Syracuse, who, after
                    plundering the city and selling the inhabitants for slaves, established there a
                    body of Campanian mercenaries. In the first Punic war it was one of the earliest
                    among the cities of Sicily to submit to the Romans, and it appears to have
                    afterwards continued on friendly terms with them. In the time of Cicero it was a
                    flourishing and wealthy city; but it suffered so severely from the ravages of
                    Sextus Pompeius, that Augustus afterwards sent a colony of veterans thither. In
                    its more modem history the principal events are its occupation by the Goths, its
                    deliverance by Belisarius, its sack by the Saracens, its conquest by the
                    Normans, its destruction by earthquake in 1169, and its devastation by Henry
                    VI., the erection of its fortress of Rocca Orsina by Frederick II., and several
                    sieges in the course of the 14th century, the partial ruin of its harbour in
                    1669 by the eruption of Mount Aetna, and its almost total overthrow by the
                    earthquake of 1693.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
