<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0207-0196-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CASTILLEJO, Christobal de (9th edition, volume 5, page
                    196)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc9k">Indexes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4000049q">Indexing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h10">Sermons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term ref="fast:968979">Indexing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:968971">Indexers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:968973">Indexes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947579">Green</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n207/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CASTILLEJO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Christobal de</hi></label>
                    (1494-1556), was born, according to Moratin, in Ciudad-Rodrigo. Attached at an
                    early age to the household of Ferdinand of Austria, afterwards king of Bohemia
                    and Hungary, and eventually emperor, Castillejo rose in the prince’s service to
                    the post of secretary, taking orders on the departure of his master from Spain,
                    in which country he remained some time. A letter written during this period
                    (1523) by Martin de Salinas to the treasurer Salamanca, in reply to one asking
                    him to provide the treasurer with a secretary, bears flattering witness to the
                    ability and temper of Castillejo, who is warmly recommended to the vacancy. It
                    is not known whether he obtained this post. Certain it is, however, that he soon
                    afterwards folowed Ferdinand, and resumed his secretaryship, with but little
                    profit, if we may judge from many passages in his verse, in which he deplores
                    his poverty and the forlorn position unaided merit, held at court. He was
                    several times in Venice, where certain of his opuscules were printed for
                    smuggling into Spain,—Castillejo, like Terres Naharro, whose comedies and
                    satires were also published in Italy, being on the <hi rend="italic">Index</hi>
                    of the Inquisition, on account of the strong anti clerical bias of his satirical
                    works. He died in a monastery near Vienna, two years before Ferdinand’s
                    recognition as emperor.</p>
                <p>Castillejo was a voluminous writer of verse. His poems are worthy of note, not
                    only on account of their intrinsic merit, but also as being the last
                    manifestation of importance of the older Spanish School of poetry against the
                    younger section under the leadership of Garcilaso de la Vega. That fine melodist
                    and brilliant rhetorician, the Ronsard of Spain, seconded by Boscan and Hurtado
                    de Mendoza, had introduced into his own land the rhythms and cadences employed
                    in Italy; through him the sonnet, the canzone, the octaves of the comic epics,
                    and even the <hi rend="italic">terza rima of</hi> the comedy itself had been
                    transplanted into Spanish soil; and he and his followers had created a
                    vocabulary of picked and exquisite terms which, passing through the hands of the
                    magniloquent Herrera, was to end in the monstrous dialect of Gongora and his
                    disciples. Against this revolution Castillejo set his face, fighting gallantly
                    and unavailingly in defence of the antique metrical forms and structures. The
                    use of these he never abandoned, save on one or two occasions when, for purposes
                    of parody, he produced sonnets and octaves. In the poetry of Castillejo, which
                    is written chiefly in “quintillas” and “copias de pié quebrado,” are all the
                    qualities that make the older verse of Spain such pleasant reading—the graceful
                    simplicity, the artless elegance, the fluency and spontaneity (which sometimes,
                    however, degenerates into garrulity), the keen and homely mother wit, often
                    gross but seldom offensive or cruel. He has, however, other qualities which are
                    peculiar to himself, and which give him a place apart even among the school that
                    may be said to end in him; his society verses are bright with a pleasant gossipy
                    amiability; his satires are quick with a certain cynical sprightliness that
                    makes them still amusing and attractive; while one at least of his poems, the
                    “Dialogue between Himself and his Pen,” overflows with a humorous tenderness
                    that is extremely effective. Writing on anything and everything—“On a Green and
                    Yellow Costume,” “On the Wood Guaiacum,” “On a Friend’s Horse called Tristram,”
                    —he of course produced a cloud of rhymes that are intolerable and to be avoided.
                    Some of his “Villancicos,” “Letras,” and “Motes,” however, are charming in
                    despite of years; a not infrequent note in them reminding the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n208/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0208-0197"/> reader somewhat of the quaint graces of Charles
                    of Orleans, with whom in this fondness for elaborate trifles Castillejo may be
                    said to have a certain affinity, though immeasurably his inferior in delicacy of
                    touch and artistic restraint. His principal satires, “The Sermon against Love”
                    and the “Dialogue of the Conditions of Women,” are amusing and witty enough;
                    while his “Galatea,” an imitation of Ovid, must be regarded as one of the
                    sweetest pieces of pastoral poetry in the whole range of Spanish letters, and,
                    with the exception of the exquisite little anacreontic to Love, as the best of
                    Castillejo’s many poems.</p>
                <p>The strong anti-clerical feelings of Castillejo, himself an ecclesiastic, have
                    been already remarked. His satires were treated exceedingly ill on this account
                    by the officers of the Inquisition, who did not scruple to excise large portions
                    of them, and to fill up the gaps thus caused with screeds of a contrary
                    tendency, the work of their own hack rhymesters, who had at this period a great
                    deal of work to do of the same sort. The poems themselves are divided into three
                    books, the first devoted to “Love,” and the second to “Conversation and Pastime
                    ;” while the third is composed of moral and religious verses. The best text is
                    that given in the <hi rend="italic">BibUoteca de Autores Españoles,</hi> vol.
                    xxxii., Madrid, 1832.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
