<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0791-0778-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CIMABUE, Giovanni (9th edition, volume 5, page
                    778)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q15g">Angels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93k3f">Madonna</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:808746">Angels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852215">Chapels</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n791/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CIMABUE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Giovanni</hi></label> (1240 to
                    about 1302), painter, was born in Florence of a creditable family, which seems
                    to have borne the name of Gualtieri, as well as that of Cimabue (Bullhead). He
                    took to the arts of design by natural inclination, and sought the society of men
                    of learning and accomplishment. Vasari, the historian of Italian painting,
                    zealous for his own native state of Florence, has left us the generally current
                    account of Cimabue, which later researches have to a great extent invalidated.
                    We cannot now accept his assertion that art, extinct in Italy, was revived
                    solely by Cimabue, after he had received some training from Grecian artists
                    invited by the Florentine Government to paint the chapel of the Gondi in the
                    church of S. Maria Novella; for native Italian art was not then a nullity, and
                    this church was only begun when Cimabue was already forty years old. Even
                    Lanzi’s qualifying statement that Grecian artists, although they did not paint
                    the chapel of the Gondi, did execute rude decorations in a chapel below the
                    existing church, and may thus have inspirited Cimabue, makes little difference
                    in the main facts. What we find as the general upshot is that some Italian
                    painters preceded Cimabue—particularly Guido of Siena and Giunta of Pisa; that
                    he worked on much the same principle as they, and to a like result; but that he
                    was nevertheless the most advanced master of his time, and, by his own works,
                    and the training which he imparted to his mighty pupil Giotto, he left the art
                    far more formed and more capable of growth than he found it. The undoubted
                    admiration of his contemporaries would alone demonstrate the conspicuous
                    position which he held, and deserved to hold. For the chapel of the Rucellai in
                    S. Maria Novellahe painted in tempera a colossal Madonna and Child with Angels,
                    the largest altarpiece produced up to that date; before its removal from the
                    studio it was visited with admiration by Charles of Anjou, with a host of
                    eminent men and gentle ladies, and it was carried to the church in a festive
                    procession of the people and trumpeters. Cimabue was at this time living in the
                    Borgo Allegri, then outside the walls of Florence; the legend that the name
                    Allegri (Joyous) was bestowed on the locality in consequence of this striking
                    popular display is more attractive than accurate, for the name existed already.
                    Of this celebrated picture, one of the great landmarks of modem and sacred art,
                    some details may be here given, which we condense from the <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of Painting in Italy</hi> by Messrs Crowe and Cavalcaselle. “The Virgin
                    in a red tunic and blue mantle, with her feet resting on an open-worked stool,
                    is sitting on a chair hung with a white drapery flowered in gold and blue, and
                    carried by six angels kneeling in threes above each other. A. delicately
                    engraved nimbus surrounds her head, and that of the infant Saviour on her lap,
                    who is dressed in a white tunic, and purple mantle shot with gold. A
                    dark-coloured frame surrounds the gabled square of the picture, delicately
                    traced with an ornament interrupted at intervals by thirty medallions on gold
                    ground, each of which contains the half-figure of a saint. In the face of the
                    Madonna is a soft and melancholy expression; in the form of the infant, a
                    certain freshness, animation, and natural proportion; in the group,
                    affection—but too rare at this period. There is sentiment in the attitudes of
                    the angels, energetic mien in some prophets, comparative clearness and soft
                    harmony in the colours. A certain loss of balance is caused by the overweight of
                    the head in the Virgin as compared with the slightness of her frame. The
                    features are the old ones of the 13 th century; only softened, as regards the
                    expression of the eye, by an exaggeration of elliptical form in the iris, and
                    closeness of the curves of the lids. In the angels, the absence of all true
                    notions of composition may be considered striking; yet their movements are more
                    natural and pleasing than hitherto. One indeed, to the spectator’s right of the
                    Virgin, combines more tender reverence in its glance that any that had yet been
                    produced. Cimabue gave to the flesh-tints a clear and carefully fused colour,
                    and imparted to the forms some of the rotundity which they had lost. With him
                    vanished the sharp contrasts of hard lights, half-tones, and shadows.” In a
                    general way, it may be said that Cimabue showed himself forcible in his
                    paintings, as especially in heads of aged or strongly characterized men; and, if
                    the then existing development of art had allowed of this, he might have had it
                    in him to express the beautiful as well. He, according to Vasari, was the first
                    painter who wrote words upon his paintings,—as, for instance, round the head of
                    Christ in a picture of the Crucifixion, the words addressed to Mary, <hi
                    rend="italic">Mulier</hi><hi rend="italic">ecce</hi><hi rend="italic">filius
                    tuus.</hi></p>
                <p>Other paintings still extant by this master are the following:—In the Academy of
                    Arts in Florence, a Madonna and Child, with eight angels, and some prophets in
                    niches,— better than the Rucellai picture in composition and study <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n792/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0792-0779"/> of nature, but more archaic in type, and the
                    colour now spoiled (this work was painted for the Badia of S. Trinita,
                    Florence); in the National Gallery, London, a Madonna and Child with Angels,
                    which came from the Ugo Baldi collection, and had probably once been in the
                    church of S. Croce, Florence; in the Louvre, a Madonna and Child, with
                    twenty-six medallions in the frame, originally in the church of S. Francesco,
                    Pisa. In the lower church of the Basilica of S. Francesco at Assisi, Cimabue,
                    succeeding Giunta da Pisa, probably adorned the south transept,— painting a
                    colossal Virgin and Child between four Angels, above the altar of the
                    Conception, and a large figure of St Francis. In the upper church, north
                    transept, he has the Saviour Enthroned and some Angels; and, on the central
                    ceiling of the transept, the Four Evangelists with Angels. Many other works in
                    both the lower and the upper church have been ascribed to Cimabue, but with very
                    scanty evidence; even the above-named can be assigned to him only as matter of
                    probability. Numerous others which he indisputably did paint have perished,—for
                    instance, a series (earlier in date than the Rucellai picture) in the Carmine
                    church at Padua, which were destroyed by a fire.</p>
                <p>From Assisi Cimabue returned to Florence. In the closing years of his life he was
                    appointed capomaestro of the mosaics of the Cathedral of Pisa, and was
                    afterwards, hardly a year before his death, joined with Arnolfo di Lapo as
                    architect for the Cathedral of Florence. In Pisa he executed a Majesty in the
                    apse,—Christ in glory between the Virgin and John the Evangelist, a mosaic, now
                    much damaged, which stamps him as the leading artist of his time in that
                    material. This was probably the last work that he produced.</p>
                <p>The debt which art owes to Cimabue is not limited to his own performances. He was
                    the master of Giotto, whom he found a shepherd boy of ten, in the pastures of
                    Vespignano, drawing with a coal on a slate the figure of a lamb. Cimabue took
                    him to Florence, and instructed him in the art; and after his death Giotto
                    occupied a house which had belonged to his master in the Via del Cocomero.
                    Another painter with whom Cimabue is said to have been intimate was Gaddo
                    Gaddi.</p>
                <p>It had always been supposed that the bodily semblance of Cimabue is preserved to
                    us in a portrait-figure by Simon Memmi painted in the Cappella degli Spagnuoli,
                    in S. Maria Novella,—a thin hooded face in profile, with small beard, reddish
                    and pointed. This is now extremely dubious. Simone Martini of Siena (commonly
                    called Memmi) was bom in 1283, and would therefore have been about nineteen
                    years of age when Cimabue died; it is not certain that he painted the work in
                    question, or that the figure represents Cimabue. The Florentine master is spoken
                    of by a nearly contemporary commentator on Dante (the so-called Anonimo, who
                    wrote about 1334) as <hi rend="italic">arrogante</hi><hi rend="italic">e
                    disdegnoso</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> sc “arrogant and passionate” that, if
                    any one, or if he himself, found a fault in any work of his, however cherished
                    till then, he would abandon it in disgust. This, however, to a modem mind, looks
                    more like an aspiring and fastidious desire for perfection than any such form of
                    “arrogance and passion” as blemishes a man’s character. Giovanni Cimabue was
                    buried in the cathedral of Florence, 8. Maria del Fiore, with an epitaph written
                    by one of the Nini :—</p>
                <p>’ ∙ Credidit ut Cimabos picturae castra tenere Sic tenuit vivens; nunc tenet
                    astra poli</p>
                <p>Here we recognize distinctly the suggestion of the first clause in the famous
                    triplet of Dante:</p>
                <p>“Credette Cimabue nella pintura</p>
                <p>Tener lo campo; ed ora ha Giotto il grido, 81 ehe la fama di colui s’oscura.” (W.
                    Μ. R.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
