<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0595-0584-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHERBOURG (9th edition, volume 5, page 584)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150792">Tides</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:875388">Conquerors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n595/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHERBOURG</label>, a naval station, fortified town, and
                    seaport of France, in the department of La Manche, on the northern shore of the
                    peninsula of Cotentin, at the mouth of the small River Divette, in 49° 38' N.
                    lat., l <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 38' W. long. It stands on a bay formed by
                    Cape Levi on the E. and Cape La Hogue on the W.,and is distant 75 miles from the
                    Isle of Wight, 41 miles W. by N. from St Lo, and 212 in the same direction from
                    Paris. The town in itself is small and unimportant. Its houses are built of
                    stone and roofed with slate; but the streets are narrow, and the only public
                    buildings of any interest are the tower (a remnant of the old fortifications),
                    the church of La Trinité, in front of which is the colossal statue of Napoleon
                    I. by Level; the Chapelle de Nôtre Dame du Voeu, formerly part of the abbey
                    founded by the Empress Maude in the 12th century; the Hôtel de Ville, which
                    contains the Henry Museum and the library; the bathing establishments, opened in
                    1827; and the theatre. The town is supplied with water <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n596/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0596-0585"/> from a reservoir completed in 1874 at Château
                    d’Eau, about three quarters of a mile distant, and capable of containing upwards
                    of 500,000 gallons. Cherbourg derives its chief importance from its naval and
                    commercial harbours, which are distant from each other about half a mile. The
                    former is cut out of the rock, and is capable of accommodating fifty men-of-war
                    of the largest size. The depth of water at full tide is 50 feet, at low tide 25
                    feet. Connected with the harbour are the dry docks, the yards where the largest
                    ships in the French navy are constructed, the magazines, the rope walks, and the
                    various workshops requisite for a naval arsenal of the first class. The works
                    are carefully guarded on every side by redoubts and fortifications, and are
                    commanded by batteries on the surrounding hills <hi rend="smallcaps">sq</hi>
                    completely that the harbour of Cherbourg may be pronounced one of the strongest
                    in the world. The commercial harbour at the mouth of the Divette communicates
                    with the sea by a canal 650 feet in length and 54 in width. It consists of two
                    parts, an outer harbour 262 yards long by 218 wide, and a basin 446 yards long
                    and 138 wide, in which the depth of water is 19 feet at low tide, and will be
                    increased by the dredging operations commenced in 1874. Outside these harbours
                    is the triangular bay, which forms the roads of Cherbourg. This bay is admirably
                    sheltered by the land on every side but the north. To protect the shipping from
                    the violence of the north winds the great <hi rend="italic">digue,</hi> or
                    breakwater, has been constructed. This immense work is 2½ miles in length; its
                    breadth at the base is 262 feet, and at the summit 101 feet. Its foundation was
                    formed by massy wooden frames, which were sunk and filled with stones; and it is
                    now protected from the waves by a parallel line of large blocks weighing each 44
                    tons. The industrial activity of Cherbourg is considerable, its principal
                    products being cotton yarn, refined sugar, soda, leather, and chemicals. A lace
                    factory gives employment to nearly 400 women. The chief articles of export are
                    farm and dairy produce, more especially potatoes, butter, and pigs; and the
                    imports consist mainly of coal, iron, timber, and cotton. The population in 1846
                    was 22,460; in 1872 it amounted to 34,785.</p>
                <p>Cherbourg is supposed by some investigators to occupy the site of the Roman
                    station of <hi rend="italic">Coriallum,</hi> but nothing definite is known about
                    its origin. The name was long regarded as a corruption of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Caesaris</hi><hi rend="italic">Burgus,</hi> or Caesar’s Borough, but there is
                    at least as much probability that it is the same as the English Scarborough. The
                    castle is mentioned in the 11th century, and the town certainly existed in the
                    10th. William the Conqueror supplied it with a hospital and a church; and Henry
                    II. on several occasions chose it as his residence. In 1295, it was pillaged by
                    an English fleet from Yarmouth; and in the 14th century it frequently suffered
                    during the invasions of Normandy. Captured by the English in 1418 after a four
                    months’ siege, it was recovered by Charles VII. of France in 1450. An attempt
                    was made under Louis XIV. to construct a military port; but the fortifications
                    were dismantled in 1689, and further damage was inflicted by the English in 1758
                    Louis XVI. commenced the construction of the breakwater, and his plans were
                    afterwards carried out and extended by Napoleon I., who is said to have declared
                    that he would renew at Cherbourg the wonders of Egypt, and raise his pyramid in
                    the sea. It was left, however, to Louis Philippe, and particularly to Napoleon
                    III., to complete his designs; and their successful realization was celebrated
                    in 1858, in the presence of the Queen of England, against whose dominions they
                    had at one time been mainly directed. Between 1783 and the close of 1857,
                    66,862,000 francs had been expended on the works.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
