<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0441-0430-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHARRON Pierre (9th edition, volume 5, page
                    430)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n873131">Carthusians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n441/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHARRON <hi rend="smallcaps">Pierre</hi></label> (1541-1603),
                    a French philosopher, born in Paris in 1541, was one of the twenty-five children
                    of a bookseller of that city. After studying law at Orleans and Bourges, and
                    obtaining the degree of doctor from the latter university, he settled at Paris
                    to practise as an advocate. But, having met with no great success during five or
                    six years, he entered the church, and soon gained the highest popularity as a
                    preacher, rising to the dignity of canon, and being appointed preacher in
                    ordinary to Queen Margaret. At length, when about forty-seven years of age, he
                    determined to fulfil a vow which he had once made to enter the cloister; but,
                    being rejected by the Carthusians and by the Celestines, and having taken the
                    advice of some professed casuists, he held himself absolved, and continued to
                    follow his old profession. He delivered a course of sermons at Angers, and in
                    the next year passed <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n442/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0442-0431"/> to Bordeaux, where he formed his short but famous
                    and important friendship with Montaigne. Its intimacy is shown by the fact that
                    at the death of Montaigne, in 1592, Charron was requested in his will to bear
                    the arms of his family.</p>
                <p>In 1594 Charron published (at first anonymously, afterwards under the name of
                    “Benedict Vaillant, Advocate of the Holy Faith,” and also, in 1594, in his own
                    name) <hi rend="italic">Les</hi><hi rend="italic">Trois Vérités,</hi> in which,
                    by methodical and orthodox argument, he seeks to prove that there is a God and a
                    true religion, that the true religion is the Christian, and that the true church
                    is the Roman Catholic. The last book (which is three-fourths of the whole work)
                    is chiefly an answer to the famous Protestant work entitled <hi rend="italic">Le
                    Traité</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">l’</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Église</hi> by Du Plessis Momay; and in the second edition (1595) there is an
                    elaborate reply to an attack on the third <hi rend="italic">Vérité</hi> which
                    had been published anonymously by a Protestant writer. <hi rend="italic">Les
                    Trois Vérités</hi> gained considerable popularity, ran through several editions,
                    and obtained for its author the favour of the bishop of Cahors, who appointed
                    him grand vicar and theological canon. It also led to his being chosen deputy to
                    the general assembly of the clergy, of which body he became chief secretary. It
                    was followed in 1600 by <hi rend="italic">Discours</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Chrestiens,</hi> a book of sermons, similar in tone, half of which treat of the
                    Eucharist.</p>
                <p>In the following year (1601) Charron published at Bordeaux his third and most
                    remarkable work—the famous <hi rend="italic">De la Sagesse,</hi> a complete
                    popular system of moral philosophy. Usually, and so far correctly, it is coupled
                    with the Essays of Montaigne, to which the author is under very extensive
                    obligations; but though it is avowedly composed in great part of the thoughts
                    and evea the words of others, there is distinct individuality in the book. It is
                    specially interesting from the time when it appeared, and the man by whom it was
                    written. Conspicuous as a champion of orthodoxy against atheists, Jews, and
                    Protestants—without resigning this position, and still upholding practical
                    orthodoxy—Charron suddenly stood forth as the representative of the most
                    complete intellectual scepticism.</p>
                <p>His psychology is sensationalist. With sense all our knowledge commences, and
                    into sense all may be resolved. The soul, located in the ventricles of the
                    brain, is affected by the temperament of the individual; the dry temperament
                    produces acute intelligence; the moist, memory; the hot, imagination. Dividing
                    the intelligent soul into these three faculties, he shows—after the manner which
                    Bacon subsequently adopted—what branches of science correspond with each. With
                    regard to the nature of the soul he merely quotes opinions. The belief in its
                    immortality, he says, is the most universal of beliefs, but the most feebly
                    supported by reason. As to man’s power of attaining truth his scepticism is
                    decided; and he plainly declares that none of our faculties enable us to
                    distinguish truth from error. In comparing man with the lower animals, Charron
                    insists that there are no breaks in nature. “Those parts which approach and
                    touch one another are more or less similar. So between man and the other animals
                    there is much nearness and kindred.” The latter have reason; nay, they have
                    virtue; and, though inferior in some respects, in others they are superior. The
                    estimate formed of man is not, indeed, flattering. His five most essential
                    qualities are vanity, weakness, inconstancy, misery, presumption. Upon this view
                    of human nature and the human lot Charron founds his moral system. Equally
                    sceptical with Montaigne, and decidedly more cynical, he is distinguished by a
                    deeper and sterner tone. Man comes into the world to endure; let him endure
                    then, and that in silence. To be grieved by others’ sorrows is a weakness; our
                    compassion should be like that of God, who succours the suffering without
                    sharing in their pain. Avoid vulgar errors; cherish universal sympathy. Let no
                    passion or attachment become too powerful for restraint. Follow the customs and
                    laws which surround you. Such are the maxims he lays down.</p>
                <p>Special interest attaches to Charron’s treatment of religion. He has been lauded
                    for his piety, and condemned for his infidelity; but he is justly to be regarded
                    as a sceptic of the school of Montaigne. He insists on the diversities in
                    religions; he dwells also on what would indicate a common origin. All grow from
                    small beginnings and increase by a sort of popular contagion; all teach that God
                    is to be appeased by prayers, presents, vows, but especially, aud most
                    irrationally, by human suffering. Each is said by its devotees to have been
                    given by inspiration. In fact, however, a man is a Christian, Jew, or Mahometan,
                    before he knows he is a man. One religion is built upon another; the Jewish, for
                    instance, on the Egyptian and other Gentile religions, the Christian on the
                    Jewish, the Mahometan on the Jewish and Christian combined. But while he openly
                    declares religion to be “strange to common sense,” the practical result at which
                    Charron arrives is that one is not to sit in judgment on his faith, but to be
                    “simple and obedient,” and to allow himself to be led by public authority. This
                    is one rule of wisdom with regard to religion; and another equally important is
                    to avoid superstition. What superstition is he boldly ventures to define. It is
                    the belief that God is like a hard judge who, eager to find fault, narrowly
                    examines our slightest act, that He is revengeful and hard to appease, and that
                    therefore He must be flattered and importuned, and won over by pain and
                    sacrifice. True piety, which is the first of duties, is, on the other hand, the
                    knowledge of God and of one’s self, the latter knowledge being necessary to the
                    former. It is the abasing of man, the exalting of God,—the belief that what He
                    sends is all good, and that all the bad is from ourselves. It leads to spiritual
                    worship; for external ceremony is merely for our advantage, not for His
                    glory.</p>
                <p>Charron’s political views are neither original nor independent. He pours much
                    hackneyed scorn on the common herd, declares the sovereign to be the source of
                    law, and asserts that popular freedom is dangerous.</p>
                <p>At once the <hi rend="italic">De la Sagesse</hi> brought upon its author the most
                    violent attacks, the chief being by the Jesuit Garasse. A second edition was
                    nevertheless soon called for. In 1603, notwithstanding much opposition, it began
                    to appear; but only a few pages had been printed when Charron died suddenly in
                    the street. A summary and defence of the <hi rend="italic">Sagesse,</hi> written
                    shortly before his death, appeared in 1606. In 1604 his friend Michel de la
                    Rochemaillet prefixed to an edition of the <hi rend="italic">Sagesse</hi> a
                    Life, which depicts Charron as a man of the most amiable disposition and purest
                    character. His complete works, with this Life, were published in 1635. An
                    excellent abridgment of the <hi rend="italic">Sagesse</hi> is given in
                    Tennemann’s <hi rend="italic">Philosophie,</hi> vol. ix.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
