<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0031-0022-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CANONIZATION (9th edition, volume 5, page 22)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:843075">Butlers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010918">Martyrs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw1m">Martyrs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46t0gw81">Belief</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n31/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CANONIZATION</label>, a ceremony in the Church of Rome, by
                    which persons deceased are ranked in the catalogue of the saints. This act is
                    preceded by beatification; and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n32/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0032-0023"/> after the merits of the individual have been duly
                    tested and approved, the Pope decrees the canonization.</p>
                <p>The term was not introduced till the 12th century. The first person who availed
                    himself of it was Udalric, bishop of Constance, in his letter to Pope Calixtus
                    II. relative to the canonization of Bishop Conrad. The act, however, dates from
                    a much more remote antiquity. The ceremony was originally only a commemoration
                    of the martyrs, whose assistance was invoked in the name of the church militant
                    to which they had belonged. Originally bishops decided whether or not the
                    candidate had fairly vindicated his claim to the honour; but they only acted as
                    the organ of public opinion. Orthodoxy was certainly considered of great
                    importance, as may be seen from the fact of the exclusion of Origen and
                    Tertullian, those great though erratic geniuses of the early church, from the
                    title. As soon as the power of Rome was once more upon the ascendant in Europe,
                    the popes naturally appropriated to themselves the important privilege of
                    canonization. None but martyrs were at first admitted into the category of
                    saints, but in course of time the privilege was extended to some of those pious
                    men who, without having sealed their testimony with their blood, had evinced the
                    sincerity of their belief by the purity of their practice. In later times,
                    however, the Pope assumed the right of admitting into the sacred catalogue
                    potentates whose claim seems to have largely consisted in their support of his
                    temporal interests. Notable instances of this are the names of the emperor Henry
                    I., canonized by Eugenius III., and Edward the Confessor of England, canonized
                    by Alexander III.</p>
                <p>So long as the right of according the honours of canonization was vested in the
                    bishops, there was no public guarantee that it had been exercised with rigour or
                    discretion. But when it passed into the hands of the popes, means were taken to
                    prevent any but really meritorious persons from being enrolled in the holy
                    category. Even then, however, a very simple ordeal sufficed. A few miracles
                    reported to have happened at a tomb were enough to give its inmate a claim to
                    have his name inscribed in the canon of the mass among the number of the happy.
                    A Roman Catholic writer, the editor of Butler’s <hi rend="italic">Lives of the
                    Saints</hi> (ed. 1866) states that “the proceedings of a beatification or
                    canonization are long, rigorous, and expensive.” It has been asserted that the
                    discovery of the last-named feature of the process prevented the somewhat
                    parsimonious Henry VII. of England from carrying out his desire for the
                    canonization of King Henry VI.; Bacon, however <hi rend="italic">(History of
                    Henry VJI.),</hi> inclines rather to the belief that the obstacle here was the
                    pope’s fear it would “diminish the estimation of that kind of honour” to give it
                    to such “a simple man.” At a later period, when the ceremony was only performed
                    after a considerable lapse of time, reasons were always hard to be found why the
                    saintly candidate should be rejected. In modern times the court of Rome has
                    shown itself extremely averse to promiscuous canonization; and since the days of
                    Benedict XIV., the promoter of the faith, popularly known as the <hi
                    rend="italic">advocatus diaboli,</hi> or devil’s advocate, has exercised extreme
                    severity in sifting the claims of aspirants. It is further necessary that a
                    period of a hundred years should elapse between the death of the saint and his
                    admission into the calendar. But the more pious men of every country in Europe
                    have of late evinced so little ambition to secure this posthumous compliment,
                    that it may now be considered to have gone fairly out of fashion. It is also
                    probable that the far more stringent rules of evidence and the growth of
                    physical science have tended to render proof of the supernatural much more
                    difficult than it seemed to be to our mediaeval forefathers. It may be observed
                    that the Lutheran divines of the century after the Reformer’s decease frequently
                    refer to him as B. (i.e., <hi rend="italic">Beatu«)</hi> Lutherus.</p>
                <p>On the day of canonization the Pope and cardinals officiate in white; while St
                    Peter’s church is illuminated and hung with rich tapestry, upon which the arms
                    of the Pope, and of the prince or state requiring the canonization, are
                    embroidered in gold and silver.</p>
                <p>Beatification, which frequently precedes canonization, gives an inferior <hi
                    rend="italic">status</hi> to the deceased person, and appears rather to
                    recommend him as a fit object for the <hi rend="italic">cultus</hi> of his
                    co-religionists than to enjoin it.</p>
                <p>See Du Cange <hi rend="italic">Glossarium,</hi><hi rend="italic">s. v.</hi>
                    “Canonizare,” and the references there given to St Augustine on St John, ths
                    Bull of Pope John XV., and (for the ceremonies) to th© <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ceremonialβ</hi><hi rend="italic">Romanum,</hi> lib. i. sect. 16. Compare
                    Milman, <hi rend="italic">Lat. Christianity,</hi> bk. xiv. chap il, and preface
                    to Forbes’s <hi rend="italic">Kalendlar of Scottish Saiιds,</hi> 1872. For the
                    Roman Catholic statement of the case see Alban Butler’s <hi rend="italic">Lives
                    of the Saints,</hi> preface to edition of 1866, and an <hi rend="italic">Essay
                    on Beatification, Canonization, &lt;Lc.,</hi> by F. W. Faber (London, 1848). But
                    the great authorities on the subject to which all Roman Catholics refer are the
                    decrees of Pope Urban VIII., and a treatise on the entire subject by Pope
                    Benedict XIV.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
