<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0274-0263-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAVAN (9th edition, volume 5, page 263)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:863821">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914304">Episcopalians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j960b1w">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n274/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAVAN</label>, an inland county in the province of Ulster, in
                    Ireland, situated between 53° 43' and 54° 7' N. lat,, and 6° 45' and 7° 47' W.
                    long., is bounded N. by Fermanagh and Monaghan, E. by Monaghan and Meath, S by
                    Meath, Westmeath, and Longford, and W. by Longford and Leitrim. It has an area
                    of 746 square miles, or 477,394 acres.</p>
                <p>The surface of the country is uneven, consisting of hill and dale, without any
                    great extent of level ground, but only in its northern extremity attaining a
                    mountainous elevation. The barony of Tullyhaw, bordering on Fermanagh, a wild
                    dreary mountain district, known as the kingdom of Gian or Glengavlin, contains
                    the highest land in the county, called Slieve Russell. In the same barony is
                    Quilca Mountain, the place of inauguration for the Macquires, chieftains of
                    Fermanagh, held in veneration by the peasantry, in connection with legends and
                    ancient superstitions. The remainder of the county is not deficient in wood, and
                    contains numerous lakes, generally of small dimensions, but of much interest for
                    their picturesque beauty, more especially Lough Oughter, which lies between the
                    towns of Cavan and Killashandra. The chief river in the county is the Erne,
                    which originates in the Lake of Scrabby, one of the minor sheets of water
                    communicating with Lough Gowna on the borders of Longford. The river takes a
                    northerly direction by Killeshandra and Belturbet, being enlarged during its
                    course by the Annalee and other smaller streams, and finally enters Lough Erne
                    near the northern limit of the county. The other waters, consisting of numerous
                    lakes and their connecting streams, are mostly tributary to the Erne. A copious
                    spring called the Shannon Pot, at the foot of the Cuilagh Mountain, in the
                    barony of Tullyhaw, is regarded as the source of the River Shannon. The
                    Blackwater, a tributary of the Boyne, also rises in this county, near
                    Bailieborough.</p>
                <p>Branch lines of the Midland, Great Western, and Great Northern railways traverse
                    the county.</p>
                <p>The climate is not very genial owing to the dampness arising from its numerous
                    lakes and the nature of the soil, and to the boisterous winds which frequently
                    prevail, more especially in the higher districts.</p>
                <p>The south-eastern portion of Cavan rests upon clay-slate, and the remainder of
                    the county upon the Carboniferous limestone formation. A rich iron ore was
                    formerly raised from Quilca Mountain. Indications of lead, silver, and sulphur
                    have been observed; and fullers’ earth, pipe-clay, potters’ clay, and brick clay
                    are frequently met with in Tullyhaw barony, in which there are also indications
                    of coal. Several mineral springs exist in this county, the chief of which is
                    near the once-frequented village of Swanlinbar. In the neighbourhood of
                    Belturbet, near the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n275/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0275-0264"/> small lake of Annagh, is a carbonated chalybeate.
                    There are several other springs of less importance; and the small Lough Leighs,
                    or Lough-an-Leighaghs, which signifies the healing lake, on the summit of a
                    mountain between Bailieborough and Kingscourt, is celebrated for its
                    antiscorbutic properties. The level of this lake never varies. It has no visible
                    supply nor vent for its discharge; neither is it jver frozen during the severest
                    winters.</p>
                <p>The soil is generally a stiff clay, cold and watery, but capable of much
                    improvement by drainage, for which its undulating surface affords facilities.
                    Agriculture has made little progress within the last twenty years; the extent of
                    the farms being generally small. In the mountainous parts, however, where the
                    land is chiefly under grazing, the farms are larger, and in stock raising the
                    county has made considerable progress.</p>
                <p>From the Owners of Land Return (1876) it appears that in 1875 Cavan was divided
                    among 1044 proprietors, 328 of whom owned less than 1 acre, and 716 one acre and
                    upwards. The largest estates were those of Lord Farnham (29,455 acres), Earl
                    Annesley (24,221), and E. J. Saunderson (12,362). The average rateable value of
                    the land was Ils. 10|d. per acre, while that of all Ulster was 15s. 8∣d.; and
                    the average extent of the properties was 435 acres per owner, or nearly double
                    the average size for Ulster, which was 239.</p>
                <p>The following tables give comparative statements of the agriculture acreage in
                    the years in 1853 and 1875, and of the live stock in 1852 and 1875 respectively
                    :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Oats.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Wheat, Barley, Flax, &lt;fcc.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Turnips Potatoes, <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> " <hi
                            rend="superscript"> d</hi> ° <hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> ' <hi
                            rend="superscript"> ler</hi> Green Crops.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Meadow.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Under crops.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1853.. .89,929</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>2,883 12,106 27,734</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8,368</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31,921</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>176,591</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1875...52,826</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>665 5,298 28,823</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6,754</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6!,946</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>156,312</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Horses. Mules, <hi rend="subscript"> f</hi>, ... and
                            Asses. <hi rend="superscript"> cattlβ</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Sheep.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Γigs,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Goats.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Poultry.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1852 19,381</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>92,690</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16,167</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24,715</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>14,024</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>328,241</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1875 19,439</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>120,399</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>27,322</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>42,263</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>15,800</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>422,501</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The number of goats raised here greatly exceeds that in the other counties, with
                    the exception of Kerry and Cork.</p>
                <p>Cavan is not a manufacturing county. The bleaching of linen and the distillation
                    of whisky are both carried on to a small extent; but the people are chiefly
                    employed in agricultural pursuits and in the sale of home produce. The soil in
                    those districts not well adapted for tillage is peculiarly favourable for trees.
                    The woods were formerly very considerable, and the timber found in the bogs is
                    of large dimensions; but plantations are now chiefly found in demesnes, where
                    they are extensive.</p>
                <p>The population is less mixed in race than most parts of Ulster, being generally
                    of Celtic extraction. The dwellings of the peasantry are poor in accommodation.
                    There are in the county only four towns with upwards of 1000 inhabitants, viz.,
                    Cavan, Cootehill, Belturbet, and Bailieborough. The population in 1851 amounted
                    to 174,064, and in 1871 to 140,735 (with an excess of 223 males), showing a
                    decrease in twenty years of 33,329 persons, being an average of 1666 per annum,
                    or 19 per cent., on the population of 1851. This is considerably above the
                    average decrease of Ulster. At the census of 1871 there were 113,174 Catholics,
                    21,223 Episcopalians, 15,004 Presbyterians, and 1334 of other denominations,
                    showing that 80 per cent, of the inhabitants professed the Catholic faith.</p>
                <p>With regard to emigration, it appears that 11,129 persons left the county within
                    the five years ending 1875, being at the rate of 2226 per annum, which is about
                    the average of the rest of the province. The poor law is administered by a
                    subdivision of the county and parts of the adjacent district into four unions,
                    and these relieved 5126 paupers in 1874. Education is dispensed by means of 8
                    superior and 340 primary schools. In 1871 the number of persons of five and
                    upwards who could read and write was 55,773; 31,438 could read hut could not
                    write, and 48,104 could neither read nor write.</p>
                <p>The county is divided into eight baronies—Castlerahan, Clanmahon, Clankee, Lough
                    tee Lower and Upper, Tully-garvey, Tullyhaw, and Tullyhunco, and contains
                    thirty-six parishes and parts of parishes. It is almost entirely within the
                    diocese of Kilmore. In military arrangements it is in the Belfast district; and
                    there are barracks for cavalry at Belturbet, and for infantry at Cavan, where
                    also the staff of the county militia is stationed. The assizes are held at
                    Cavan, where the county prison and the county infirmary are situated. Prior to
                    the Union it returned six members to the Irish parliament, two for the county at
                    large, and two for each of the boroughs of Cavan and Belturbet; but since that
                    period it has been represented in the imperial parliament by two county members
                    only.</p>
                <p>The most ancient geographers describe this and the adjacent counties of Leitrim
                    and Fermanagh as occupied by the tribe of the Erdini. At the period of the
                    English settlement, and for some centuries afterwards, it was known by the name
                    of the Brenny, or O’Reilly’s country; and its inhabitants, protected by the
                    nature of the country, long maintained their independence. In 1584 Cavan was
                    formed into a county of Ulster by Sir John Perrott, lorddeputy of Ireland, and
                    subdivided into seven baronies, two of which were assigned to Sir John O’Reilly,
                    free of all contributions, and three to other members of the family; while the
                    two remaining baronies, possessed by the septs of Mackernon and Macgauran, and
                    situated in the mountains bordering on O’Rourke’s country, were left subject to
                    their ancient tenures and the exactions of their Irish lord, the Crown reserving
                    200 beeves upon the whole county for the lord-deputy’s provision. There was also
                    an ancient subdivision, peculiar to this county, into polls, each of which
                    contained about 25 acres. Early in the reign of James I., a commission of
                    inquiry was issued concerning all lands in several counties of Ulster, escheated
                    to the Crown by attainder, outlawry, or actual death in rebellion, by which the
                    greater portion of this county was deemed to be vested in the Crown, and its
                    exact state thereupon investigated. Under the consequent project for the new
                    plantation of Ulster, the county was distributed among the undertakers, British
                    planters, servitors, natives, ecclesiastics, &amp;c. The principal English and
                    Scotch families settled in Cavan were the Auchmuties, Bailies, Butlers,
                    Hamiltons, Lamberts, Parsons, and Ridgeways. Some few remains of antiquity
                    remain in the shape of cairns, raths, and the ruins of small castles.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Cavan,</hi> the capital of the above county, and, previous
                    to the Union, a parliamentary borough, but now placed under the Towns
                    Improvement Act, is situated near the centre of the county. It is 68 miles N.W.
                    from Dublin (85½ by rail), on one of the tributary streams of the Annalee River,
                    in a large valley surrounded on every side by elevated ground, with picturesque
                    environs, adorned by the mansions and demesnes of Lord Farnham and the bishop of
                    Kilmore. The town, which in 1871 contained 3380 inhabitants, is of unpretending
                    and rather humble appearance. The court-house, erected at an expense of £11,000,
                    is elegant in its proportions and convenient in its internal arrangements. The
                    parish church, built on an elevated site, is also a graceful structure. The most
                    conspicuous building is the grammar-school, founded by Charles I. It was rebuilt
                    in 1819, at an expense of £9000, on an eminence overlooking one of the main
                    entrances into the town, and is capable of accommodating one hundred resident
                    pupils. The other public buildings are the Roman Catholic chapel and Dissenters’
                    meeting-houses, the county gaol and in-fîrmary<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n276/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0276-0265"/>, barracks, and the union workhouse. Cavan has
                    still some linen trade, and a considerable retail business is transacted in the
                    town. It is the seat of a presbytery of the Presbyterian church, but the great
                    majority of the inhabitants are Roman Catholics. A monastery of Dominican
                    friars, founded by O’Reilly, chieftain of the Brenny, formerly existed here, and
                    became the burial-place of the celebrated Irish general, Owen O’Neal, who died
                    as is supposed by poison, in 1649, at Cloughoughter. This monastery, and all the
                    other antiquities of the town, have been swept away during the violent and
                    continuous feuds to which the country has been subjected. Even so late as the
                    year 1690 the chief portion of the town was burned by the Enniskilleners under
                    General Wolseley.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
