<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0384-0373-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHALMERS, George (9th edition, volume 5, page
                    373)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18t91">Churchyards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100852">Royalists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204739">Maryland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n384/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHALMERS, <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi></label>
                    (1742-1825), an antiquarian and political writer of considerable eminence, was
                    born at Fochabers, a village in the county of Moray, in the year 1742. His
                    father, James Chalmers, was a grandson of George Chalmers of Pittensear, a small
                    estate in the parish of Lhanbryde, now St Andrews-Lhanbryde, in the same county,
                    possessed by the main line of the family from about the beginning of the 17th to
                    the middle of the 18th century. After completing the usual course at King’s
                    College, Aberdeen, young Chalmers studied law in Edinburgh for several years.
                    Two uncles on the father’s side having settled in America, he visited Maryland
                    in 1763, with the view, it is said, of assisting to recover a tract of land of
                    some extent about which a dispute had arisen, and was in this way induced to
                    commence practice as a lawyer at Baltimore, where for a time he met with much
                    success. Having, however, espoused the cause of the Royalist party on the
                    breaking out of the American war of Independence, he found it expedient to
                    abandon his professional prospects in the New World, and return to his native
                    country. For the losses he had sustained as a colonist he received no
                    compensation, and several years elapsed before he obtained an appointment that
                    placed him in a state of comfort and independence.</p>
                <p>In the meantime Chalmers applied himself with great diligence and assiduity to
                    the investigation of the history and establishment of the English colonies in
                    North America; and enjoying free access to the state papers and other documents
                    preserved among what were then termed the plantation records, he became
                    possessed of much important information. His work entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Politisai</hi><hi rend="italic">Annals of the present United Colonies from
                    their Settlement to ths Peace of</hi> 1763, 4to, London, 1780, was to have
                    formed two volumes; but the second, which should have contained the period
                    between 1688 and 1763, never appeared. The first volume, however, is complete in
                    itself, and traces the original settlement of the different American colonies,
                    and the progressive changes in their constitutions and forms of government as
                    affected by the state of public affairs in the parent kingdom. Independently of
                    its value as being compiled from original documents, it bears evidence of great
                    research, and has been of essential benefit to later writers. Continuing his
                    researches, he next gave to the world <hi rend="italic">An Estimate oj the
                    Comparative Strength of Britain during the Present and Four Preceding
                    Reigns,</hi> Lond. 1782, which passed through several editions. At length, in
                    August 1786, Chalmers, whose sufferings as a Royalist must have strongly
                    recommended him to the Government of the day, was appointed chief clerk to the
                    committee of Privy Council on matters relating to trade, a situation which he
                    retained till his death in 1825, a period of nearly forty years. As his official
                    duties made no great demands on his time, he had abundant leisure to devote to
                    his favourite studies,—the antiquities and topography of Scotland having
                    thenceforth special attractions for his busy pen.</p>
                <p>Besides biographical sketches of De Foe, Sir John Davies, Allan Ramsay, Sir David
                    Lyndsay, Churchyard, and others, prefixed to editions of their respective works,
                    Chalmers wrote a life of Paine, the author of the <hi rend="italic">Rights of
                    Man,</hi> which he published under the assumed name of Francis Oldys, A.M., of
                    the University of Pennsylvania; and a life of Ruddiman, in which considerable
                    light is thrown on the state of literature in Scotland during the earlier part
                    of the last century. His life of Queen Mary, in two quarto volumes, was first
                    published in 1818. It is founded on a MS. left by Whitaker the historian of
                    Manchester; but Chalmers informs us that he found it necessary to rewrite the
                    whole. The history of that ill-fated queen occupied much of his attention, and
                    his last work, <hi rend="italic">A Detection of ths Love-Letters lately
                    attributed in Hugh Campbell's work to Mary Queen of Scots,</hi> is an exposure
                    of an attempt to represent as genuine some fictitious letters said to have
                    passed between Mary and Bothwell, which had fallen into deserved oblivion. In
                    1797 appeared his <hi rend="italic">Apology for the Believers in the Shakespeare
                    Papers which were exhibited in Norfolk Street,</hi> followed by other tracts on
                    the same subject. These contributions to the literature of Shakespeare are full
                    of curious matter, but on the whole display a great waste of erudition, in
                    seeking to show that papers which had been proved forgeries might nevertheless
                    have been genuine. Chalmers also took part in the J unius controversy, and in
                    <hi rend="italic">The Author of Junius A scertained, from a Concatenation of
                    Circumstances amounting to Moral Demonstration,</hi> Lond. 1817, 8vo, sought to
                    fix the authorship of the celebrated letters on Hugh Boyd. In 1824 he published
                    <hi rend="italic">The Poetical Remains of some of the Scottish Kings, now first
                    collected</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and the same year he edited and presented
                    as a contribution to the Bannatyne Club <hi rend="italic">Rdbene and Makyne and
                    the Testament of Cresseid, by Robert Henry son.</hi> His political writings are
                    equally numerous. Among them may be mentioned <hi rend="italic">Collection of
                    Treaties between Great Britain and other Powers,</hi> Lond. 1790, 2 vols. 8vo;
                    <hi rend="italic">Vindication of the Privileges of ths People in respect to ths
                    Constitutional Right of Free Discussion,</hi> &lt;fcc., Lond. 1796, 8vo,
                    published anonymously; <hi rend="italic">A Chronological account of Commerce and
                    Coinage in Great Britain from ths Restoration till</hi> 1810, Lond. 1810, 8vo;
                    <hi rend="italic">Opinions of Eminent Lawyers on various points of English
                    Jurisprudence, chiefly concerning ths Colonies, Fishsries, and Commerce of Great
                    Britain,</hi> Lond. 1814, 2 vols. 8vo; <hi rend="italic">Comparative Views of
                    the State of Great Britain before and since the ĬVar,</hi> Lond. 1817, 8vo.</p>
                <p>But Chalmers’s greatest work is his <hi rend="italic">Caledonia,</hi> which,
                    however, he did not live to complete. The first volume appeared in 1807, and is
                    introductory to the others. It is divided into four books, treating successively
                    of the Roman, the Pictish, the Scottish, aud the Scoto-Saxon periods, from 80 to
                    1306 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> In these we are presented, in a condensed
                    form, with an account of the people, the language, and the civil and
                    ecclesiastical history, as well as the agricultural and commercial state of
                    Scotland during the first thirteen centuries of our era. Unfortunately the
                    chapters on the Roman period are entirely marred by the author’s having accepted
                    as genuine Bertram’s forgery <hi rend="italic">De Situ Britanniae;</hi> but
                    otherwise his opinions on controverted topics are worthy of much respect, being
                    founded on a laborious investigation of all the original authorities that were
                    accessible to him. The style both of this and.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n385/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0385-0374"/>
                <p>of the succeeding volumes is redundant, the scholarship is often defective, and
                    hastily-drawn conclusions are asserted with the utmost confidence in their
                    accuracy; yet, notwithstanding all these drawbacks, such were the industry and
                    perseverance of Chalmers that his <hi rend="italic">Caledonia</hi> contains a
                    mass of information on all subjects connected with early Scottish history and
                    topography that has been of the highest value to subsequent writers. The second
                    volume, published in 1810, gives an account of the seven southeastern counties
                    of Scotland—Roxburgh, Berwick, Haddington, Edinburgh, Linlithgow, Peebles, and
                    Selkirk, each of them being treated of as regards name, situation and extent,
                    natural objects, antiquities, establishment as shires, civil history,
                    agriculture, manufactures and trade, and ecclesiastical history. In 1824, after
                    an interval of fourteen years, the third volume appeared, giving, under the same
                    headings, a description of the seven southwestern counties—Dumfries,
                    Kirkcudbright, Wigtown, Ayr, Lanark, Renfrew, and Dumbarton. In the preface to
                    this volume the author states that the materials for the history of the central
                    and northern counties were collected, and that he expected the work would be
                    completed in two years. This expectation, however, was not destined to be
                    realized. It is much to be regretted that, instead of a!l but wasting his time
                    on profitless and acrimonious controversies about Shakespearian forgeries and
                    the character of Queen Mary, Chalmers did not direct his whole energies to his
                    <hi rend="italic">magnum opus,</hi> and give to the world the matured fruits of
                    all the labour he had bestowed on it; for it is on <hi rend="italic"
                    >Caledonia</hi> that his fame must chiefly rest.</p>
                <p>While thus fully occupied, Chalmers had for many years been engaged in laying the
                    foundation for other works of a not less important and laborious nature. One of
                    these is said to have been a history of Scottish poetry, another, a history of
                    printing in Scotland. Each of them he thought likely to extend to two large
                    quarto volumes, and on both he expended an unusual amount of enthusiasm and
                    energy. He had also prepared for the press an elaborate history of the life and
                    reign of David I. In his later researches he was assisted by his nephew James,
                    son of Alexander Chalmers, writer in Elgin.</p>
                <p>George Chalmers died at his house, James Street, Buckingham Gate, London, May 31,
                    1825, after a few days’ illness, in the eighty-third year of his age. His
                    valuable and extensive library he bequeathed to his nephew, at whose death in
                    1841 it was sold and dispersed. Chalmers was a member of the Royal and
                    Antiquarian Societies of London, an honorary member of the Antiquarian Society
                    of Scotland, and a member of other learned societies. In private life he was
                    undoubtedly an amiable man, although the dogmatic tone that disfigures portions
                    of his writings procured him many opponents. He is besides chargeable with a
                    want of taste, which appears too prominently in his keen attempts to silence, at
                    all hazards, those whom he considered the detractors of Mary. Among his avowed
                    antagonists in literary warfare the most distinguished were Malone and Steevens,
                    the Shakspeare editors; Mathias, the author of the <hi rend="italic">Pursuits of
                    Literature;</hi> Dr Jamieson, the Scottish lexicographer; Pinkerton, the
                    historian; Dr Irving, the biographer of the Scottish poets; and Dr Currie of
                    Liverpool. But with all his failings in judgment, Chalmers was a valuable
                    writer. He uniformly had recourse to original sources of information; and he is
                    entitled to great praise for his patriotic and self-sacrificing endeavours to
                    illustrate the history, literature, and antiquities of his native country. (j.
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">m‘d.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
