<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0129-0118-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CARNARVON, County of (9th edition, volume 5, page
                    118)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1173757">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106523">Scapula</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134302">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sn8w">Pool</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sn3j">Pools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n129/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CARNARVON, <hi rend="smallcaps">County of</hi></label>,
                    (Welsh <hi rend="italic">Caer-yn-arfon},</hi> a maritime county of North Wales,
                    is bounded on the N. by Beaumaris Bay, on the E. by Denbigh, on the S.E. by
                    Merioneth; on the S.W. by Cardigan Bay, and on the W. by the Irish Sea and fhe
                    Menai Strait. There is a small detached portion of the county on the N. coast of
                    Denbighshire. The greatest length of this county is from north-east to
                    south-west, and measures about 55 miles; while its greatest breadth from
                    south-east to north-west is about 23 miles. Nearly one-half of its whole length
                    forms a spur-like peninsula, varying from five to nine miles in width,
                    projecting in a south-west direction into the Irish Sea, and forming Cardigan
                    Bay on the south, and Carnarvon Bay on the north. The county possesses an area
                    of 579 square miles, or 370,273 acres, and contains 10 hundreds and 76
                    parishes.</p>
                <p>The Lower Silurian and Cambrian beds may be termed the basis of the geological
                    features of this county; but they are so completely penetrated in every
                    direction by intrusive igneous rocks that there is hardly a square mile of
                    surface in the whole county free from their presence. These consist chiefly of
                    compact felspar, felspathic traps, greenstone, quartz porphyries, and syenite.
                    On the west, along the shore of the Menai Strait, there is a narrow belt of
                    carboniferous limestone; of this the Great Orme’s Head is also composed; and on
                    the western side of the peninsular part of the county is a broad band of
                    chlorite and mica schist with serpentine interspersed. Carnarvon is rich in
                    mineral treasures; for, besides lead and copper lodes and an appreciable amount
                    of gold, its numerous slate quarries are amongst the most valuable mineral
                    properties in the United Kingdom, and yield princely incomes to the fortunate
                    possessors, besides furnishing employment to many thousands of workmen,</p>
                <p>Carnarvon is the most mountainous of all the Welsh counties, and its mountains
                    are the grandest of any in the British islands south of the Forth. The Snowdon
                    range fills up the whole of the centre of the county; and, with its lofty
                    summits rising to the height of between 3000 and 4000 feet, throws an air of
                    grandeur and sublimity over scenery which is of the most romantic and beautiful
                    description. The summit of Snowdon itself is 3570 feet above the level of the
                    sea, and it is surrounded by a phalanx of giants, many of them but little lower
                    that itself. Among the more important of these, within the county, are the
                    Carnedd Llewelyn, 3482 feet; the Carnedd Dafydd, 3430 feet; the Glyder Fawr,
                    3275 feet; the Elidyr-fawr, 3033 feet; the Moel Siabod. 2863 feet; Moel Hebog,
                    2578 feet; and Drum, 2527 feet in height. The rocks of which the Snowdonian
                    range is composed are for the most part of a very bold and rugged description,
                    which adds to the impressiveness of their immense masses.</p>
                <p>Some of the valleys are characterized by the extreme of wild and rugged grandeur,
                    being walled in by the naked <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n130/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0130-0119"/> rocks, and traversed by foaming torrents; while
                    others are marked by soft and smiling beauty. Among the former may be mentioned
                    the gorge at Pont Aberglaslyn, while Nant Gwynant, with its placid lake and
                    verdant meadows, will serve as an illustration of the latter. The vales of
                    Beddgelert and Llanberis, the former at the southern, and the latter at the
                    northern base of Snowdon, have a world-wide reputation for beauty; and the vale
                    of the Conway, from Llanrwst to Conway, is a noble piece of scenery, backed as
                    it is on its southern border by the Snowdon range.</p>
                <p>The only river of importance is the Conway, which rises in Llyn Conway, in the
                    S.E. corner of the county, and after separating Carnarvon from Denbigh in a
                    nearly due north course of about 30 miles, falls into the sea at Conway. It is a
                    tidal river, and is navigable for about 10 miles from Conway. The Seoint, a
                    small stream, rises in Snowdon, and falls into the sea at Carnarvon.</p>
                <p>The lakes are very numerous, and some of them of considerable size. The more
                    important are the lakes of Llanberis (Llyn Peris and Llyn Padarn), to the north
                    of Snowdon; Llyn Ogwen, to the north of the Glyder Fawr; Llyn Cwlyd and Llyn
                    Eigiau, both to the north of Capel Curcg; Llyn Llydau on Snowdon; Llyn Cwellyn
                    to the west, and Llyn Gwynant to the east of that mountain; Llyniau Nant-y-Llef
                    or Nautile Pools, near Llanllyfni; and Llyn Conway, already referred to.</p>
                <p>The climate is cold and severe during the winter, except in the peninsular part
                    of the county and on the sea-coast, where it is very mild. The arable land
                    occupies not more than a third part of the whole surface; and this is mostly in
                    the vale of Conway, or in the neighbourhood of the sea. A small quantity of
                    wheat is raised; but the principal cultivated crops are oats, barley, and
                    potatoes. The alluvial deposit in some of the valleys forms a rich and fertile
                    soil, which is chiefly employed as meadow land. Dairy and sheep-farming form the
                    chief employment of the agricultural population; and on the hills numbers of
                    diminutive ponies are reared, which at two years old find a steady sale in the
                    English market. Agriculture is not in a forward state, and has not been advanced
                    by the success attending the mining industries of the county. In 1873 Carnarvon
                    was divided among 6240 separate proprietors, 4610 of these owning holdings of
                    less than an acre; eleven holdings consisted of more than 5000 acres, and none
                    exceeded 42,000 acres. On an average each holding contained 48 acres, the
                    average of all Wales being 74½; and the average rental of properties amounting
                    to an acre and upwards was as high as 19s. 9d. per acre, owing to the presence
                    of so many valuable mines.</p>
                <p>The following tables will show the state of agriculture in the county in the
                    years 1872 and 1875, and from these it will be observed that there is a general
                    diminution of the acreage of crops but an increase in the numbers of live stock
                    :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Year.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Oats. Barley Wheat Green crops. <hi rend="superscript">
                            G</hi> ^ <hi rend="subscript"> t</hi> “<hi rend="subscript"> o</hi><hi
                            rend="superscript"> n</hi><hi rend="subscript"> n</hi><hi
                            rend="superscript"> der</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1872</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13,786 9,101 2,033 9,134</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>35,418</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1875</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12,849 8,459 1,626 9,101</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>37,006</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Yeaι</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Horses. cattle. Sheep</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Pigs.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1872.</p><p>1875.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7,064 46,981 218,881</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>21,002</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>7.363 51,352 223,804</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19,273</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The county is as well served with railways as the mountainous character of the
                    district will allow. The Chester and Holyhead line runs along the northern
                    coast, and crosses to Anglesey by means of the Britannia Bridge over the Menai
                    Strait. From this line branches diverge up the valley of the Conway, and across
                    the peninsula by Carnarvon to Pwllheli, &amp;c. The Cumbrian line enters from
                    the south at Portmadoc.</p>
                <p>These means of communication and the numerous ports on its coasts, afford very
                    great facilities for the transport of the important mineral products of the
                    county.</p>
                <p>Copper, lead, and slate are worked very largely, particularly the last, which is
                    of the most valuable quality. For roofing, paving, and ornamental purposes it is
                    exported in large quantities. In 1871, 4370 men were employed in the slate
                    quarries. The chief owners are Lord Penrhyn, Mr Duff Smith, and the Welsh Slate
                    Company.</p>
                <p>The inhabitants, who all speak Welsh more or less, numbered in 1851 87,870; in
                    1871 they had increased 20½ per cent., amounting to 106,121, of whom 51,874 were
                    males and 54,247 females. Nearly the whole of Carnarvonshire is in the diocese
                    of Bangor. It has a court of quarter sessions. It is represented in Parliament
                    by one member for the county and one for the Bangor group of boroughs.</p>
                <p>The principal towns are Bangor, population (1871) 9859; Carnarvon, 9449;
                    Pwllheli, 3009; and Llandudno, 2762.</p>
                <p>Carnarvonshire was occupied by the important tribe of the Segontiaci, who were
                    with difficulty subdued by Ostorius Scapula and Suetonius Paulinus. During the
                    Roman period it formed part of Britannia Secunda, and Conovium and Segontium
                    have been identified as Caer Rhyn and Carnarvon (Caer Seoint). Later it was part
                    of the kingdom of Gwynnedd until Edward I. in 1277 restricted that division to
                    the land of Snowdon proper. The early fortresses at Diganwy, Dinorwig, &lt;fcc.,
                    as well as the later castles at Conway, Carnarvon, and other places, attest the
                    warlike character of its inhabitants.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Carnarvon,</hi> the capital of the above county, a
                    parliamentary and municipal borough, occupies an area of 1897 acres, and is
                    pleasantly situated on the eastern shore of Carnarvon Bay, in the Irish Sea, at
                    the mouth of the Seoint, 210 miles north-west of London. It stands very nearly
                    upon the site of Caer Seoint, the ancient capital of the Segontiaci, and owes
                    its origin to Hugh Lupus, earl of Chester, who in 1098 fortified the place. The
                    noble castle was commenced in 1284, and the common tradition that Edward II. was
                    born in that year within its walls is now known to be unfounded, as they were at
                    the date of his birth scarcely in existence. It occupies a large area on the
                    west side of the town and is in the form of an irregular oblong, surrounded by
                    walls and defended by thirteen polygonal towers. The Eagle Tower (Edward’s
                    reputed birthplace) is at the extreme west, and is of conspicuous beauty and
                    dominant height. A considerable portion of the town-wall near the castle is
                    still entire. The parish church is nearly half a mile from the town. In the town
                    itself there is a chapel of ease, and several large and commodious dissenting
                    chapels. There are also a town and county hall, a training college for teachers,
                    and handsome schools. The town also possesses assembly rooms and a theatre, and
                    is resorted to as a sea-bathing place in summer. The port is used for the export
                    of slates and copper ore from the quarries of Llanberis and Llanllyfni, but
                    there is little manufacturing in the town itself. The borough has formed part of
                    a district which has returned a member to Parliament since 1536. The Reform Bill
                    added Bangor to the district, which now includes Carnarvon, Conway, Criccieth,
                    Pwllheli, Bangor, and Nevin. The population of Carnarvon in 1851 was 8674, and
                    in 1871, 9449 (males 4357, females 5092); the inhabited houses numbered 1975.
                    There is a weekly market on Saturdays, and four fairs are held in the course of
                    the year. The quarter sessions and assizes are held in the town.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
