<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0351-0340-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CENTIPEDES and (9th edition, volume 5, page
                    340)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884440">Crustacea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:995621">Leggings</term>
                    <term ref="fast:995328">Leg</term>
                    <term ref="fast:974074">Insects</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047771">Organisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047777">Organization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fb21">Crustacea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vd0k">Leg</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vs35">Naturalists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26q375">Myriapoda</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qh88">Insects</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4br8mh3x">Organ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vf0v">Jaws</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n351/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CENTIPEDES <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi></label> MILLEPEDES,
                    the popular names of the two orders of Articulate animals which until lately
                    formed the entire class <hi rend="italic">Myriapoda.</hi> They were formerly
                    classed with insects, which they resemble in their jointed limbs and antennae,
                    and in their respiratory system, but they have also points of contact with
                    annelid worms, with crustaceans, and with spiders, by which they are marked as a
                    transition group, intermediate between the lower and higher Articulata.
                    Myriapods (∕x,υpιαs, ten thousand, and που?, a foot) are elongated worm-like
                    creatures, cylindrical or flattened, and composed of numerous segments, each
                    bearing one or two pairs of jointed legs,—those on the anterior segments being
                    modified, as in the Crustacea, so as to form the organs of the mouth. The
                    fang-like, prehensile jaws of the centipede, perforated at their extremities to
                    allow of the passage of the liquid venom into the wound they have inflicted, are
                    thus simply modifications of a pair of legs. The eyes consist of a number of <hi
                    rend="italic">ocelli,</hi> congregated together on the head, aud, with a single
                    exception, are never compound, as in insects. Like the latter, they breathe by
                    means of tracheal tubes, opening by stigmata placed on both sides, behind the
                    insertion of the legs, and kept permanently open by a spiral chitinous fibre.
                    They are unisexual, the organs of generation being, however, differently placed
                    in the two groups, occurring anteriorly in millepedes, and posteriorly in
                    centipedes. The young of many species closely resemble their parents from the
                    time they leave the egg, only with fewer limbs and segments; these, however,
                    increase with each successive moulting until the normal number of the adult is
                    reached. Other species, as those of the family <hi rend="italic">Julidoe,</hi>
                    undergo, during their period of growth, modifications closely resembling the
                    metamorphoses of insects. Their larvae at first either are destitute of legs, or
                    have only three pairs situated anteriorly; and it is only after a long series of
                    moultings, extending in some cases over two years, that their maturity is
                    signalized by the appearance of sexual organs.</p>
                <p>Myriapods have been usually divided into the two orders <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ckilognatfιa</hi> or Millepedes and <hi rend="italic">Chiloρoda</hi> or
                    Centipedes; but recently a small myriapod, ∙ <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> ⅛th of
                    an inch in length, was discovered by Sir J. Lubbock, among decomposing vegetable
                    matter, differing from the other members of the class in the absence of
                    tracheae, apparently absorbing air through its semi-transparent skin, in the
                    smaller number of its legs (nine pairs), and in the bifid character of its
                    antennae; and this has been made the type of a third order— <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pauropidae. Pauropus Huxleyi</hi> Lubbock describes as an active, cleanly
                    little creature, with a look of cheerful intelligence, in marked contrast to the
                    dull stupidity of the <hi rend="italic">Julidoe,</hi> or the melancholy ferocity
                    of the centipede. Millepedes, or “Thousand-Legs,” are readily distinguished from
                    the other group by their antennae, which are always six or seven jointed, by the
                    generally cylindrical shape of the body, and by the possession of two pairs of
                    legs on each segment—the last posterior segments and a few anterior excepted.
                    Each segment also bears a pair of stigmata or tracheal openings, instead of
                    every alternate one, as in centipedes; and this fact, taken in connection with
                    the double quantity of legs, has led to the belief that each segment in the
                    millepede has been formed by the union of two, a view further strengthened by
                    the presence of a <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n352/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0352-0341"/> distinct transverse groove down the centre of
                    each. The legs of millepedes though numerous are exceedingly weak, and in moving
                    they appear to glide along like footless worms. They are most frequently found
                    among damp moss, and beneath masses of decaying vegetable matter on which they
                    feed; and when in danger they roll themselves into a ball. The British species
                    are few, and the largest of these does not exceed 2 inches in length; but there
                    is an American form which attains a length of 8 inches, All are equally
                    harmless, the prehensile jaws being rudimentary, while the other parts of the
                    mouth are modified to suit their purely vegetable diet.</p>
                <p>Centipedes, or “Hundred-Legs,” have their segments flattened, and covered with a
                    leathery skin, and have one pair of legs on each segment, the posterior pair
                    being directed backwards and elongated so as to resemble a couple of jointed
                    tails. Their antennae have not less than fourteen and rarely more than forty
                    joints, while the body segments do not usually exceed twenty. The organs of the
                    mouth are masticatory, and are admirably adapted to the carnivorous habits of
                    the centipede. It feeds principally on insects, seizing them with its powerful
                    prehensile organs, and injecting at the same time its venom into the wound. The
                    bite of the larger forms, as <hi rend="italic">Scolopendra morsitαns,</hi>
                    occurring in tropical countries, is exceedingly painful, and is described by
                    those who have suffered from it “as similar to what might be produced by contact
                    with a red-hot iron,” giving rise to swelling, throbbing pains, and febrile
                    symptoms (Dr Collingwood’s <hi rend="italic">Naturalist’s Rambles in the China
                    Seas).</hi> These, however, yield readily to an application of ammonia.
                    Centipedes seldom exceed a foot in length. They are exceedingly active in
                    pursuit of their prey, insinuating their many-jointed and flattened bodies under
                    stones, beneath the bark of trees, and wherever insects usually lurk. <hi
                    rend="italic">Lithobius forcipatus,</hi> the commonest British species, is 2
                    inches long, and quite harmless, although when seized it attempts to fix its
                    jaws into the skin of its captor. The species belonging to the genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Geophilus</hi> are said to be luminous in the dark. Upwards of
                    twenty species of fossil Myriapoda are known,— the oldest from the Coal Measures
                    of North America, and belonging to the millepede or vegetable-eating division.
                    One of these, <hi rend="italic">Xylobius</hi><hi rend="italic">sigillaria,</hi>
                    was found in the hollow trunks of the fossil <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sigillaria.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
