<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0768-0755-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHRYSOSTOM, St John (9th edition, volume 5, page
                    755)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025507">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4610vs0f">Archbishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n768/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHRYSOSTOM, <hi rend="smallcaps">St John</hi></label>
                    (Χρυσόστομος, golden-mouthed), the most famous of the Greek fathers, was born of
                    a noble family at Antioch, the capital of Syria, most probably about 347. At the
                    school of Libanius the sophist he gave early indications of his mental powers,
                    and would have been the successor of his heathen master, had he not been, to use
                    the expression of his teacher, stolen away to a life of piety (like Augustine,
                    Gregory of Nazianzus, and Theodoret), by the influence of his pious mother
                    Anthusa. Immediately after his baptism by Meletius, the bishop of Antioch, he
                    gave up all his forensic prospects, and buried himself in an adjacent desert,
                    where for six years he spent a life of ascetic self-denial and study. His
                    infirmities, however, compelled him to return to the world; and the authority of
                    Meletius gained his services to the church. On his arrival he was ordained
                    deacon in his thirty-fifth year (381), and afterwards presbyter at Antioch. On
                    the death of Nectarius he was appointed archbishop of Constantinople by
                    Eutropius, the favourite minister of the Emperor Arcadius. He had, ten years
                    before this, only escaped promotion to the episcopate by a very questionable
                    stratagem,—which, however, he defends in his instructive and eloquent treatise
                    <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Sacerdotio.</hi> As a presbyter, he
                    won high reputation by his preaching at Antioch, more especially by his homilies
                    on <hi rend="italic">The Statues,</hi> a course of sermons delivered when the
                    citizens were justly alarmed at the prospect of severe measures being taken
                    against them by the Emperor Theodosius, whose statues had been demolished in a
                    riot.</p>
                <p>On the archiépiscopal throne Chrysostom still persevered in the practice of
                    monastic simplicity. The ample re <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n769/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0769-0756"/> venues which his predecessors had consumed in
                    pomp and luxury he diligently applied to the establishment of hospitals; and the
                    multitudes who were supported by his charity preferred the eloquent discourses
                    of their benefactor to the amusements of the theatre or of the circus. His
                    homilies, which are still preserved, furnish ample apology for the partiality of
                    the people, exhibiting the free command of an elegant and copious language, an
                    inexhaustible fund of metaphors and similitudes, giving variety and grace to the
                    most familiar topics, with an almost dramatic exposure of the folly and
                    turpitude of vice. His zeal as a bishop and eloquence as a preacher, however,
                    gained him enemies both in the church and at the court. The ecclesiastics who
                    were parted at his command from the lay-sisters (whom they kept ostensibly as
                    servants), the thirteen bishops whom he deposed for simony and licentiousness at
                    a single visitation, the idle monks who thronged the avenues to the court and
                    found themselves the public object of his scorn—all conspired against the
                    powerful author of their wrongs. Their resentment was inflamed by a powerful
                    party, embracing the magistrates, the ministers, the favourite eunuchs, the
                    ladies of the court, and Eudoxia the empress herself, against whom the preacher
                    thundered daily from the pulpit of St Sophia. A favourable pretext for
                    gratifying their revenge was discovered in the shelter which Chrysostom had
                    given to four Nitrian monks, known as the tall brothers, who, on being
                    excommunicated by their bishop, had fled to Constantinople; and a ready tool was
                    found in Theophilus, bishop of the rival city of Alexandria, who had driven them
                    from their diocese, and had long circulated in the East the charge of Origenism
                    against Chrysostom. By his instrumentality a synod was called to try or rather
                    to condemn the archbishop; butfearing the violence of the mob in the metropolis,
                    who idolized him for the fearlessness with which he exposed the vices of their
                    superiors, it held its sessions in the suburb of Chalcedon, named the Oak, where
                    Rufinus had erected a stately church and monastery. A bishop and a deacon were
                    sent to accuse the archbishop, and presented to him a list of charges, in which
                    pride, inhospitality, and Origenism were brought forward to procure the votes of
                    those who hated him for his austerity, or were prejudiced against him as a
                    suspected heretic. Four successive summonses were signified to Chrysostom, but
                    he indignantly refused to appear until four of his notorious enemies were
                    removed from the council. Without entering into any examination of the charges
                    brought before them, the synod condemned him on the ground of contumacy; and,
                    hinting that his audacity merited the punishment of treason, called on the
                    emperor to ratify and enforce their decision. He was immediately arrested and
                    hurried to Nicaea in Bithynia. As soon as the news of his banishment spread
                    through the city, the astonishment of the people was quickly exchanged for a
                    spirit of irresistible fury. In crowds they besieged the palace, and had already
                    begun to take vengeanae on the foreign monks and sailors who had come from
                    Chalcedon to the metropolis, when, at the entreaty of Eudoxia, the emperor
                    consented to his recall. His return was graced with all the pomp of a triumphal
                    entry, but in two months after he was again in exile. His fiery zeal could not
                    blind him to the vices of the court; and heedless of personal danger he
                    thundered against the profane honours that were addressed almost within the
                    precincts of St Sophia to the statue of the empress. The haughty spirit of
                    Eudoxia was inflamed by the report of a discourse commencing with the
                    words,—“Herodias is again furious; Herodias again dances; she once more demands
                    the head of John ;” and though the report was false, it sealed the doom of the
                    archbishop. A new council was summoned, more numerous and more subservient to
                    the wishes of Theophilus; and troops of barbarians were quartered in the city to
                    overawe the people. Without examining it, the council confirmed the former
                    sentence, and condemned him afresh for having resumed his functions without
                    their permission. He was hurried away to the desolate town of Cucusus, among the
                    ridges of Mount Taurus, with a secret hope, perhaps, that he might be a victim
                    to the Isaurians on the march, or to the more implacable fury of the monks. He
                    arrived at his destination in safety; and the sympathies of the people, which
                    had roused them to fire the cathedral and senatehouse on the day of his exile,
                    followed him to his obscure retreat. His influence, however, became more
                    powerfully felt in the metropolis than before. In his solitude he had ample
                    leisure for forming schemes of missionary enterprise; and by his correspondence
                    with the different churches, he at once baffled his enemies, and gave greater
                    energy to his friends. This roused the emperor to visit him with a severer
                    punishment. An order was despatched for his instant removal to the extreme
                    desert of Pityus; and his guards so faithfully obeyed their cruel instructions
                    that, before he reached the sea coast of the Euxine, he expired at Comana in
                    Pontus, in the sixtieth year of his age. His exile gave rise to a schism in the
                    church, and the Johannists (as they were called) did not return to communion
                    with the archbishop of Constantinople till the relics of the saint were, 30
                    years after, brought back to the Eastern metropolis with great pomp, and the
                    emperor publicly implored forgiveness from Heaven for the guilt of his
                    ancestors. The festival of St Chrysostom is kept in the Greek Church, November
                    13, and in the Latin Church, January 27.</p>
                <p>In his general teaching Chrysostom elevates the ascetic element in religion, and
                    in his homilies he inculcates the need of personal acquaintance with the
                    Scriptures, and denounces ignorance of them as the source of all heresy. If on
                    one or two points, as for instance the invocation of saints, some germs of
                    subsequent Roman teaching may be discovered, there is a want of anything like
                    the doctrine of indulgences or of compulsory private confession. Moreover, in
                    writing to Innocent, bishop of Rome, he addresses him as a brother metropolitan,
                    and sends the same letter to Venerius, bishop of Milan, and Chromatins, bishop
                    of Aquileia. His correspondence breathes a most Christian spirit, more
                    especially in its tone of charity towards his persecutors; and his line of
                    exegesis, if not acutely metaphysical or mystical, is full of good sense and
                    right feeling.</p>
                <p>His works are exceedingly voluminous, and consist chiefly of homilies,
                    commentaries, smaller treatises, epistles, and liturgies. Their excellence is
                    powerfully shown in the history of the times, for the illustration of which they
                    afford highly valuable materials. The school of 'exegesis formed by him, and
                    especially illustrated by such works as his commentaries on the Gospel of St
                    Matthew, the Book of Acts, the Epistle to the Romans, and other parts of the New
                    Testament, is sound, practical, and may (as Dr Newman has justly remarked)
                    almost be called “English.” It was subsequently adorned by the justly honoured
                    names of Theodoret, Theophylact, Euthymius, and Nicephorus. The best edition is
                    that of Bernard de Montfaucon in 13 vols, fol., 1718-1738, reproduced with some
                    improvements by the Abbé Migne (Paris, 1863); but this edition is greatly
                    indebted to the one issued more than a century earlier (1612) by one of the
                    foremost English scholars of his age, Sir Henry Savile, provost of Eton College,
                    from a press established at Eton by himself. It is in eight volumes, and is said
                    to have cost its editor £8000. Hallam <hi rend="italic">(Lit. of Europe,</hi>
                    iii. 10,11) calls it “the first work of learning, on a great scale, published in
                    England.” Numerous MSS. still remain unedited. Some of the homilies and
                    commentaries are translated in the <hi rend="italic">Library</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n770/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0770-0757"/><hi rend="italic">of the Fathers,</hi> published
                    at Oxford, and the Greek text has been in part re-edited by a scholar who has
                    shown a very special aptitude for the work, the Rev. F. Field of King’s College,
                    Cambridge. As authorities for the facts of his life, the most valuable are the
                    ecclesiastical histories of Socrates, Sozomen, and Theodoret; and amongst the
                    moderns, Erasmus, Cave, Lardner, and Tillemont, with the more recent church
                    history of Neander, and his monogram on the <hi rend="italic">Life and Times of
                    Chrysostom,</hi> translated by J. C. Stapleton. There has also appeared a
                    valuable German biography by Dr Förster; and a narrative, full of interest and
                    told with life-like animation, has been given by the late Μ. Amedée Thierry in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Revue</hi><hi rend="italic">des Deux Mondes,</hi> and
                    since republished (Paris, 1860) in one volume, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Récits</hi><hi rend="italic">de l</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Histoire Romaine au
                    cinquième Siècle.</hi> A graceful and interesting sketch of the concluding
                    scenes of St Chrysostom’s life may be found in Dr Newman’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historical Sketches</hi> (London, 1873), though that eminent writer seems not
                    very favourable to the theology of the Antiochene school, or even of Chrysostom
                    himself. Valuable information is given in Professor Bright’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of the Church</hi> (Oxford, 1864), and in Canon Robertson’s <hi
                    rend="italic">History of the Christian Church</hi> (vol. ii,, London, 1874). But
                    the best special contribution to English literature on the subject is <hi
                    rend="italic">St Chrysostom</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi><hi rend="italic">His
                    Life and Times,</hi> by the Rev. W. R. W. Stephens (London, 1872).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
