<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0082-0071-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAPITAL (9th edition, volume 5, page 71)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1172973">Wealth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1078608">Profit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1078633">Profiteering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025265">Money</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:976135">Interest</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7712k">Wealth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87p69">Profit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sc8g">Money</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tg7r">Rates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49g99c">Wages</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w744">Progress</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n82/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAPITAL</label>, in social discussions sometimes treated as
                    antithetical to Labour, is in reality the accumulated savings of labour and of
                    the profits accruing from the savings of labour. It is that portion of the
                    annual produce reserved from consumption to supply future wants, to extend the
                    sphere of production, to improve industrial instruments and processes, to carry
                    out works of public utility, and, in short, to secure and enlarge the various
                    means of progress necessary to an increasing community. It is the increment of
                    wealth or means of subsistence analogous to the increment of population and of
                    the wants of civilized man. Hence Mr Mill and other economists, when seeking a
                    graphic expression of the service of capital, have called it “abstinence.” The
                    labourer serves by giving physical and mental effort in order to supply his
                    means of consumption. The capitalist, or labourer-capitalist, serves by
                    abstaining from consumption, by denying himself the present enjoyment of more or
                    less of his means of consumption, in the prospect of a future profit. This
                    quality, apparent enough in the beginnings of capital, applies equally to all
                    its forms and stages; because whether a capitalist stocks his warehouse with
                    goods and produce, improves land, lends on mortgage or other security, builds a
                    factory, opens a mine, or orders the construction of machines or ships, there is
                    the element of self-deprival for the present, with the risk of ultimate loss of
                    what is his own, and what, instead of saving and embodying in some productive
                    form, he might choose to consume. On this ground rests the justification of the
                    claims of capital to its industrial rewards, whether in the form of rent,
                    interest, or profits of trade and investment.</p>
                <p>To any advance in the arts of industry or the comforts of life, a rate of
                    production exceeding the rate of consumption, with consequent accumulation of
                    resources, or in other words, the formation of capital, is indispensable. The
                    primitive cultivators of the soil, whether those of ancient times or the modern
                    pioneers who have formed settlements in the forests of the New World, soon
                    discovered that their labour would be rendered more effective by implements and
                    auxiliary powers of various kinds, and that until the produce from existing
                    means of cultivation exceeded what was necessary for their subsistence, there
                    could be neither labour on their part to produce such implements and
                    auxiliaries, nor means to purchase them. Every branch of industry has thus had a
                    demand for capital within its own circles from the earliest times. The flint
                    arrow heads, the stone and bronze utensils of fossiliferous origin, and the rude
                    implements of agriculture, war, and navigation, of which we read in Homer, were
                    the forerunners of that rich and wonderful display of tools, machines, engines,
                    furnaces, and countless ingenious and costly appliances, which represent so
                    large a portion of the capital of civilized countries, and without the
                    pre-existing capital cou!d not have been developed. Nor in the cultivation of
                    land, or the production simply of food, is the need of implements, and of other
                    auxiliary power, whether animal or mechanical, the only need immediately
                    experienced. The demands on the surplus of produce over consumption are various
                    and incessant. Near the space of reclaimed ground, from which the cultivator
                    derives but a bare livelihood, are some marshy acres that, if drained and
                    enclosed, would add considerably in two or three years to the produce; the
                    forest and other natural obstructions might also be driven farther back with the
                    result, in a few more years, of profit; fences are necessary to allow of pasture
                    and field crops, roads have to be made and farm buildings to be erected; as the
                    work proceeds more artificial investments follow, and by these successive
                    outlays of past savings in improvements, renewed and enhanced from generation to
                    generation, the land, of little value in its natural state either to the owner
                    and cultivator or the community, is at length brought into a highly productive
                    condition. The history of capital in the soil is substantially the history of
                    capital in all other spheres. No progress can be made in any sphere, small or
                    large, without reserved funds possessed by few or more persons, in small or
                    large amounts, and the progress in all cases is adventured under self-deprival
                    in the meanwhile of acquired value, and more or less risk as to the final
                    result.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n83/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0083-0072"/>
                <p>Capital is necessarily to be distinguished from money, with which in ordinary
                    nomenclature it is almost identical. It is impossible to draw any line where
                    capital may not operate actively without the intervention of money. A farmer,
                    manufacturer, or artisan, who has saved from his consumption and expenses of the
                    past year an amount of product-value, may in the following year either employ
                    more labour to direct production or divert a portion of the labour hitherto
                    employed to an improvement of his process, which in either case would be an
                    investment of capital. Money, strictly speaking, is the gold and silver coins in
                    circulation and banking reserve, and its sum in the United Kingdom may amount to
                    over 100 millions sterling. But when the bank deposits of the kingdom are taken
                    into account, they are found to be fives of hundreds of millions sterling, all
                    active as money, and forming what is called the “floating capital” of the
                    country. The explanation is that the farmer, manufacturer, and artisan already
                    supposed, having a surplus produce to dispose of, sell it at what they deem the
                    proper time for their advantage and put the proceeds in bank; or the domestic
                    servant or labouring man having a surplus from his wages, or the investor or
                    speculator iu stocks and shares having realized a profit, or the owner of a
                    thousand acres, or the millionaire embarrassed with the returns of a capital so
                    large that he can only add to it year after year, do the same thing—the money
                    employed in these multiplied transactions being merely the vehicle of their
                    notation in money-value, and after accomplishing one series of transactions
                    being available for another series following. The deposits thus made to the
                    banks may be recalled soon or late, in whole or in part, or may go on increasing
                    under the same names for a generation; but, in any case, they are the realized
                    moneyvalues of commodities, wages, rents, interest, and profits, of which the
                    owners had no present need, and which they placed at the service of the public
                    in this social form at some rate of interest until such time as they might
                    choose or need to recall them. This is capital in its most vitalized form,
                    because it is offered through the banks to all who want capital and can give the
                    requisite securities of document or character for its repayment. In proportion
                    as this fund increases a country may be safely deemed richer in resource for the
                    extended employment of labour in all profitable branches of industry, and for
                    coping with every exigency in its industrial and commercial condition. It is a
                    necessary element of all great enterprises, such as railways, telegraphs, lines
                    of ocean steamers, and the like, as well as of operations in foreign commerce
                    where there is a long train of outlays in materials, wages, and charges before
                    there can be any return. Still the idea of capital cannot be confined to money
                    and bank deposits of money. The indefinite extent to which, in the practical
                    conduct of trades and industries, the capital is insensibly increased out of the
                    resources of the business itself, without loans or contribution of new capital
                    shares, and the facility with which property and commodities command the energy
                    of free and active capital, forbid any narrow definition. The capital of a
                    country can scarce be said to be less than the whole sum of its investments in a
                    productive form, and possessing a recognized productive value.</p>
                <p>The distinction of “fixed” and “circulating” capital by the author of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Wealth of Nations</hi> (book ii. c. i.) cannot fail to be always
                    useful in exhibiting the various formsand conditions under which capital is
                    employed. Yet the principal phenomena of capital are found to be the same,
                    whether the form of investment be more or less permanent or circulable. The
                    machinery in which capital is “fixed,” and which yields a profit without
                    apparently changing hands, is in reality passing away day by day, until it is
                    worn out, and has to be replaced. So also of drainage and other land
                    improvements. When the natural forests have been consumed and the landowners
                    begin to plant trees on the bare places, the plantations while growing are a
                    source of health, shelter, and embellishment—they are not without a material
                    profit throughout their various stages to maturity—and when, at the lapse of
                    twenty or more years, they are ready to be cut down, and the timber is sold for
                    useful purposes, there is a harvest of the original capital expended as
                    essentially as in the case of the more rapid yearly crops of wheat or oats. The
                    chief distinction would appear to rest in the element of time elapsing between
                    the outlay of capital and its return. Capital may be employed in short loans or
                    bills of exchange at two or three months, in paying wages of labour for which
                    there may be return in a day or not in less than a year or more, or in
                    operations involving within themselves every form of capital expenditure, and
                    requiring a few years or ninety-nine years for the promised fructification on
                    which they proceed. But the common characteristic of capital is that of a fund
                    yielding a return and reproducing itself whether the time to this end be long or
                    short. The division of expenditure or labour (all expenditure having a
                    destination to labour of one kind or another) into “productive” and
                    “unproductive " by the same distinguished authority (book ii. c. 3) is also
                    apposite both for purposes of political economy and practical guidance, though
                    economists have found it difficult to define where “productive expenditure” ends
                    and “unproductive expenditure” begins. Adam Smith includes in his enumeration of
                    the “fixed capital” of a country “the acquired and useful abilities of all the
                    inhabitants ;” and in this sense expenditure on education, arts, aud sciences
                    might be deemed expenditure of the most productive value, and yet be wanting in
                    strict commercial account of the profit and loss. It must be admitted that there
                    is a personal expenditure among all ranks of society, which, though not in any
                    sense a capital expenditure, may become capital and receive a productive
                    application, always to be preferred to the grossly unproductive form in the
                    interest both of the possessors and of the community.</p>
                <p>These remarks have probably indicated with sufficient clearness the origin,
                    nature, and uses of capital. The subject in its details is full of
                    controversies, on which it would be out of place here to enter. It may be enough
                    to indicate simply some conclusions which appear to be fully established. 1.
                    Capital is not a prerogative or monopoly of any class, but embraces both in its
                    actual form and its future possibilities all classes of men from the humblest
                    labourer to the millionaire. 2. In proportion as capital increases the rate of
                    profit falls, the competition of capital with capital being fully more close and
                    active than that of labour with labour (J. S. Mill’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Principles of Political Economy,</hi> book iv. c. 4). 3. The amount of the
                    annual produce falling to capital is necessarily larger in proportion to the
                    amount falling to labour in countries w here the capital is large than in those
                    where it is relatively small, in old than in new countries, though the rate of
                    profit may be lower in the former than in the latter. The rate of profit may
                    fall over the whole capital of a country, and yet from the increase of capital
                    employed the aggregate profit be undiminished or even increased. Μ. Bastiat puts
                    this conclusion in the following formula:—“In proportion to the increase of
                    capital the <hi rend="italic">absolute</hi> share of the total product falling
                    to the capitalist is augmented and his <hi rend="italic">relative</hi> share is
                    diminished; while, on the contrary, the labourer’s share is increased both
                    absolutely and relatively” <hi rend="italic">(Harmonies of Political
                    Economy,</hi> vii.) 4. Capital, so far from being the antagonist, is the ally of
                    labour, the indispensable means of all extended employment and reward of labour,
                    as well <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n84/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0084-0073"/> as of all increase of population and civilized
                    well-being <hi rend="italic">(Some Leading Principles of Political Economy,</hi>
                    by Professor Cairnes, part ii. c. 3).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
