<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0303-0292-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CELIBACY (9th edition, volume 5, page 292)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kn07">Priests</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1076268">Priests</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888378">Deacons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n303/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CELIBACY</label> is the condition of those who are living a
                    single life. The word is derived from <hi rend="italic">ccelebs,</hi> which
                    means, not necessarily, as is very commonly supposed, a bachelor, but one who
                    has no existing wife, whether he be a bachelor or a widower. (For authorities on
                    this point, see Facciolati, <hi rend="italic">Totius Latinitatis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Lexicon.)</hi> Scaliger and Voss derive the word from <hi
                    rend="italic">κοίτη,</hi> a bed, and λείπω, to leave. Some more fanciful
                    etymologists, imagining that <hi rend="italic">ccelebs</hi> leads a <hi
                    rend="italic">celestial</hi> life, have suggested a derivation from <hi
                    rend="italic">coelum.</hi> The word is sometimes written <hi rend="italic"
                    >coelebs,</hi> but the better authorities are in favour of the diphthong <hi
                    rend="italic">oe.</hi></p>
                <p>From the remotest times, those who have given their attention to the study of the
                    conditions of human life in this world have deemed the married state to be a
                    better thing both for the individual and the society to which he belongs than
                    celibacy; while from an equally early period those who have professed to
                    understand man’s destinies in a future world, and the most proper means of
                    preparing for them, have, though in no wise condemning marriage, conceived that
                    celibacy is the better, purer, nobler, and higher condition of life. Lawgivers,
                    sociologists, statesmen, philosophers, and physiologists have held the former
                    view; devotees, ascetics, priests, the latter.</p>
                <p>The lawgivers of various countries and ages have striven to discourage celibacy,
                    &lt;as far as it was in the power of law to do so. The mention by Dionysius of
                    Halicarnassus of an ancient law by which all persons of mature age were obliged
                    to marry, may be cited. More authentic is the Roman law of the time of Augustus
                    known as the <hi rend="italic">Lex Julia de</hi><hi rend="italic">maritandis
                    Ordinibus.</hi> It was afterwards called <hi rend="italic">Papia Poppoea,</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">Julia</hi><hi rend="italic">Papia,</hi> from some new
                    sanctions and amendments under the consuls Papius and Poppaeus. Modern
                    legislation has with increased wisdom shrunk from such direct attempts to coerce
                    those subjected to it. But various provisions have in many European countries
                    been enacted or proposed with the view of favouring the prevalence of
                    marriage.</p>
                <p>Any endeavour to give a satisfactory account of the investigations of
                    physiologists, as bearing on this subject would lead us too far afield into the
                    discussion of topics which fall more conveniently and appropriately under other
                    headings. But it appears from recent statistics that married persons,—women in a
                    considerable but men in a much greater degree,—have at all periods of life a
                    greater probability of living than the single.</p>
                <p>The ideas which, in the absence of or in opposition to the deductions of social
                    philosophers and legislators, have found expression in the religious or
                    ecclesiastical observances and theories of various ages aud creeds, require and
                    are fitted to be treated, though with the utmost brevity, in a somewhat more
                    historical manner. Beausobre, in his <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Critique</hi><hi rend="italic">du Manichéisme,</hi> lib. vii. cap.
                    3, shows <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n304/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0304-0293"/> that it was a prevalent opinion among the
                    earliest Christians that if Adam had not fallen by disobedience, he would have
                    lived for ever in a state of virgin purity, and that a race of sinless beings
                    would have peopled Paradise, produced by some less objectionable means than the
                    union of the first pair of mortals. Marriage was considered by them as a
                    consequence of the Fall, the brand of the imperfection it had entailed, and a
                    tolerated admission of an impure and sinful nature. To abstain from it,
                    therefore, was the triumph of sanctity and at the same time the proof and the
                    means of spiritual perfection. The earliest aspirants to this perfection among
                    the Christians were not ecclesiastics as such, but hermits and. anchorites, who
                    adopted this among other means of attaining to recognizedly exceptional
                    sanctity. It is not true, as is often stated, that the official expositors of
                    Romanist theology and ecclesiastical law maintain that a vow of perpetual
                    celibacy was required as a condition of ordination in the earliest ages of the
                    church. It is fully admitted by them that, “although celibacy is preferable to
                    matrimony, the divine law does not make it necessary for the reception of holy
                    orders, or forbid cither the ordination of married men or the marriage of those
                    already in orders.” In fact it would be impossible to maintain the reverse
                    without denying the truth of many portions of ecclesiastical history, which the
                    church cannot afford to spare, as to the conduct and lives of many of the early
                    bishops, confessors, and martyrs, and without running very serious risk of
                    damaging the favourite claim of the church to uninterrupted apostolical
                    succession.</p>
                <p>It was proposed in the second Council of Carthage (251) that celibacy should be
                    required in candidates for the priesthood; but it cannot be pretended that even
                    from that time it was always considered necessary. Moroni <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Diet. Storico Eccles.,</hi> vol. ii. p. 58) makes a very much modified
                    statement :—“As regards the usage and laws of the church,” he says, “it has
                    never been permitted to priests or to bishops to take wives, <hi rend="italic"
                    >when they had declared</hi> at the time of their ordination that they would
                    persevere in celibacy.” It must be observed, however, with regard to the
                    citations of the cases of bishops and priests of the early Greek Church, that
                    Romanist ecclesiastical writers have never pretended that the practice of the
                    Greek Church was not much more lax in this respect than that of the Latin or
                    Western Church. The difference between the discipline of the one and the other
                    was this. In the Greek Church no objection was made to the ordination of married
                    men purposing to continue living with their wives, if these wives were their
                    first wives, and had not before their marriage been widows; whereas, as is
                    claimed by Romanist writers, in the Latin Church neither priests’ nor bishops’
                    orders were ever conferred on married men without requiring from them and from
                    their wives reciprocal consent, and a solemn promise, that they would live
                    separately during the remainder of their lives. As regards <hi rend="italic"
                    >bishops,</hi> however, the practice in the Greek Church was the same as in the
                    Latin. The decrees of various councils, however, show that the practice of the
                    Greek Church in this respect was by no means settled and uniform. That of Ancyra
                    in 313 permitted marriage only to such deacons as had protested against
                    accepting the obligation of celibacy at the time of their ordination. The
                    Council of Nice thought that the ancient tradition of the church should be
                    re-established in conformity with the 26th apostolical canon, which permitted
                    marriage only to those who held the office of readers or chanters in the
                    churches.</p>
                <p>The principal Papal decrees which have been issued by the popes on the subject of
                    sacerdotal celibacy are the following. It is said that Calixtus I., who was
                    elected in 221, renewed a constitution forbidding the marriage of priests. It is
                    said, too, that Lucius I., elected in 255, reenacted the same prohibition. We do
                    not, however, reach any certainty on the subject till we come to the Council of
                    Elvira, the first of those on matters of discipline the decrees of which are
                    extant. It is doubtful whether this council was held in the year 300 or 313. The
                    thirty-third and thirty-sixth canons of this council command bishops, priests,
                    deacons, and subdeacons to live apart from their wives. The council further
                    prohibited ecclesiastics from having any female in their houses save a sister or
                    a daughter, and those only when virgins, who had consecrated their virginity to
                    God. The ecclesiastical writers maintain that these constitutions were but the
                    confirmation by authoritative sanction of the practice which had been
                    immemυrially observed, rather as an apostolic tradition than a positive command.
                    From that time to the time of Gregory VII. (the great Hildebrand, elected 1073),
                    a series of popes issued decrees commanding bishops, priests, and deacons to
                    observe celibacy. But all of them are couched in terms, and put forth under
                    circumstances, which indicate that the regulation was by no means universally,
                    perhaps even it may be said generally, observed. Gregory VII., in the council
                    held at Rome in the year 1074, determined more decisively and vigorously that,
                    according to the sacred canons and the decrees of his predecessors, no
                    ecclesiastic could be a married man, that the sacrament of ordination should be
                    conferred on none except those who professed perpetual celibacy, and that no
                    wived priest should celebrate or even assist at the Mass.</p>
                <p>Upon the whole it is clear that the pretensicn advanced by the Church of Rome to
                    insist on the celibacy of its clergy was at first put forward tentatively and
                    gradually, as a thing desirable and tending to higher perfection, rather than as
                    a thing absolutely necessary; that, like so much else in that church, it was an
                    encroachment on Christian liberty, originating in a mystic idea of the greater
                    purity of a state of celibacy, which was a natural product of the working of the
                    human intellect in the earliest centuries of Christianity, and became fixed and
                    consolidated into a rigid law, as the rulers of the church, and especially
                    Gregory VII., came to perceive that it was a potent engine of ecclesiastical
                    power. It is probable that Hildebrand, the nature of whose intellect and temper
                    was such as eminently to qualify him for perceiving, appreciating at its true
                    value, and utilizing the doctrine of the universal celibacy of the clergy, was
                    the first ruler of the church who clearly saw the incalculably enormous pow er
                    which this rule placed in the hands of the hierarchy as a body, yet more notably
                    than it tended to increase that of each individual priest. To this and to this
                    alone it has been and is due that a Catholic priest is the citizen of no
                    country, and acknowledges or at least feels no allegiance, unless perhaps a
                    subordinate and secondary one, save to his church, and that to him his order is
                    in the place of family and country; and the greatness, the power, the glory, and
                    the supremacy of the church constitutes that for which the best minds among the
                    priesthood labour and live. But while churchmen were becoming more and more
                    alive to the vast importance of celibacy as a <hi rend="italic">sine qua
                    non</hi> of the priesthood, minds which were fitted to estimate that institution
                    with a larger view to its ultimate results and consequences became at an early
                    period aware of its veritable consequences. Erasmus, in his 19th Epistle (lib.
                    29) gives us at once his own and Augustine’s views of the subject in the
                    following remarkable passage :—“Miruιn vero si procus amans laudat nuptias,
                    dicitque castum conjugium non multum abesse a laude virginitatis, quum
                    Augustinus patriarcharum polygamiam anteponat nostro caelibatui.”</p>
                <p>But when the church stood at the diverging of the ways, fabled in the apologue,
                    and at the Council of Trent decided <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n305/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0305-0294"/> once and for ever which of the two paths open
                    before her she should follow, whether that of progressive reformation and
                    amelioration, or that of a <hi rend="italic">sint-ut sunt-autmon-sint</hi>
                    persistence in her old ways and policies, the abolition of the celibacy of the
                    clergy was discussed among other proposed measures of reform, and more
                    peremptorily rejected than almost any other suggestion brought forward. The
                    church understood too well what was around her, and too little what was ahead of
                    her; was too clear-sighted, yet too shortsighted; and determined to retain the
                    terrible engine of her power, which makes of her a caste, with a gulf between
                    her ministers and the rest of humanity.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
