<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0811-0798-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CLACKMANNAN (9th edition, volume 5, page 798)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wm7s">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9h942">Coaling</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j960b1w">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp1v">Dollar</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865087">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865671">Coaling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="fast:863821">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1744651">Dollarization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n811/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CLACKMANNAN</label>, a county of Scotland, on the north bank
                    of the River Forth, situated between 56° 5' and 56° 14' N. lat., and 3° 33' and
                    3° 56' W. long., is bounded on the S.W. by the Forth, W. by Stirlingshire, N.
                    and N.W. by Perthshire and a detached portion of Stirling, E. by Fife, and N.E.
                    by a detached portion of Perth. It is the smallest county in the United Kingdom,
                    is irregular in form, and occupies an area of 47½ square miles, or 30,477 acres.
                    The surface of the county is varied in its character. An elevated ridge rises on
                    the west, and, running through the middle of the county, spreads itself
                    gradually till it reaches the eastern boundary, skirting the alluvial or carse
                    lands in the valleys of the Forth and of the Devon. Still further to the north,
                    the Ochil Hills (the highest of which is Bencleuch, 2363 feet, above
                    Tillicoultry) form a very picturesque landscape, having their generally verdant
                    surface broken by bold projecting rocks and deeply indented ravines. The range
                    forms a great igneous mound, developing itself in amygdaloid felspar and
                    porphyry, and occasionally in pentagonal columns of basaltic greenstone. It is
                    used almost entirely for sheep farming.</p>
                <p>The only streams worthy of notice which traverse the county are the Devon and the
                    Black or South Devon. The former, remarkable in the upper parts of its course
                    for its romantic scenery, runs through the county near the base of the Ochils,
                    and falls into the Forth at the village of Cambus. The Black Devon flows
                    westward in a direction nearly parallel to the Devon, and falls into the Forth
                    near Clackmannan. It supplies motive power to numbers of mills and coal engines;
                    and its whole course is over coal strata. The Forth is navigable as far as it
                    forms the boundary of this county, and ships of 500 tons burden can run up as
                    far as Alloa.</p>
                <p>The soils of the arable land of Clackmannanshire are in general productive and
                    well cultivated; though the greater part of the elevated range which is
                    interposed between the carse lands on the Forth and the vale of Devon at the
                    base of the Ochils on the north consists of inferior soils, often incumbent on
                    an impervious clay. All the crops commonly raised in Scotland grow luxuriantly
                    on both sides of this tract, which also contains within itself a considerable
                    proportion of valuable soil. According to the agricultural returns for 1875 the
                    area of land under cultivation in Clackmannan is considerably above the average
                    for Scotland, and the average under corn is 7 per cent, above the average of
                    other counties. In minerals the county is rich. Iron-ore (haematite), copper,
                    silver, lead, cobalt, and arsenic have all been discovered in small quantity in
                    the Ochils, between Airthry and Dollar. Iron-stone is wrought to a considerable
                    extent for the Devon iron-works, near Clackmannan. It is found either in beds,
                    or in oblate balls imbedded in slaty clay, and yields from twenty-five to thirty
                    per cent, of iron. Coal has been wrought for upwards of two hundred years in
                    this county. A considerable proportion of the quantity obtained is shipped at
                    Alloa for foreign ports. It is all bituminous or common coal of a good quality;
                    no smithy or caking coal has yet been discovered. In 1871 there were 2137
                    persons engaged in coal mining and its adjuncts. The strata which compose the
                    coal-field are varieties of sand-stone, shale, fire-clay, and argillaceous
                    ironstone. The great coal-field of Scotland, which passes in a diagonal line
                    from the mouths of the Forth and Tay to the Irish Sea, is bounded by the Ochils;
                    no coal has been found to the north of them, except at Brora, in
                    Sutherlandshire.</p>
                <p>There is a considerable manufacturing industry in the county. Woollens are made
                    extensively at Tillicoultry; and at other parts distilling, brewing, coopering,
                    tanning, glass-blowing, and ship-building are carried on. In 1871 there were
                    4952 persons engaged in connection with the woollen manufacture, or more than a
                    fifth of the whole population.</p>
                <p>Among the antiquities of Clackmannan may be mentioned the ruins of Castle
                    Campbell, an old seat of the Argyll family, occupying a singularly wild and
                    almost inaccessible situation, above the village of Dollar. It was burned by
                    Montrose in 1644. The tower of Alloa, built prior to the year 1300, the
                    residence of the Erskines, earls of Mar, now belonging to the representative of
                    that noble family, is in good preservation. The tower of Clackmannan was long
                    the seat of a lineal descendant of the Bruce family after the failure of the
                    male line.</p>
                <p>According to the parliamentary return for 1873 Clackmannan county was divided
                    among 1227 proprietors, the average size of the properties amounting to 24½
                    acres (that of all Scotland being 143), while the average value of the land was
                    &lt;£3, 4s. 6d. per acre (that of Scotland being £1). There were in the same
                    year 1137 properties of less than 1 acre, 52 of 1 and under 10∙ acres, 20 of 10
                    and under 100, and 5 above 2000—the largest amounting to 6163 acres, the
                    property of the earl of Kellie.</p>
                <p>Clackmannanshire sends a member to Parliament conjunctly with the county of
                    Kinross and certain adjoining parishes. By the Reform Bill, the parishes of
                    Culross and Tulliallan, formerly comprehended in the county of Perth, Alva,
                    formerly belonging to Stirling, and the Perthshire portion of Logie were
                    included in the parliamentary group. The population of the county in 1861 was
                    21,450, and in 1871, 23,747, consisting of 11,555 males and 12,192 females. The
                    principal towns are—Alloa, population 9000; Tillicoultry, 3700; Dollar, 2100;
                    and Clackmannan, 1300.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
