<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0357-0346-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CERINTHUS (9th edition, volume 5, page 346)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35664">Baptism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q15g">Angels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zd0b">Ghosts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827229">Baptism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:808746">Angels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942434">Ghosts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:901244">Ebionism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n357/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CERINTHUS</label> was the founder of one of the earliest
                    heretical sects of the Christians. He was brought up in Egypt (Theod. <hi
                    rend="italic">Hoer. Fαb.</hi> ii. 3), but removed to Asia Minor, where he
                    propagated his doctrines. He flourished, according to Eusebius <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Hist. Ecd.</hi> iii. 28) in the time of Trajan (98-117). Irenaeus relates a
                    story which represents him as a contemporary of the apostle John <hi
                    rend="italic">(Contra Hoer.</hi> iii. 3, 4). He says that John, the disciple of
                    the Lord, when in Ephesus went to bathe, and when he saw Cerinthus inside, he
                    leapt from the bath without bathing, crying out, “Let us flee, lest the bath
                    fall, for Cerinthus the enemy of the truth is within.” Irenaeus heard this story
                    from some people who heard it from Polycarp, who may have heard it directly, or
                    more likely at second-hand, from some of the friends of St John. The same story
                    is told in regard to Ebion, but not on so good authority. We know nothing of the
                    death of Cerinthus.</p>
                <p>We possess three different authorities for the opinions of Cerinthus, to some
                    extent inconsistent with each other,— Irenaeus, Caius the Roman presbyter, and
                    the third unknown. Lipsius has tried to prove that the third was Hippolytus.</p>
                <p>According to Irenaeus <hi rend="italic">(Contra Hoer.</hi> i. 26), Cerinthus
                    taught “that the world was not made by the supreme God, but by a certain power
                    which was separated and distant from the supreme authority, which is over all,
                    and which was ignorant of the God over all.” He also maintained “that Jesus was
                    not born of a virgin, but was the offspring of Joseph and Mary, born like all
                    other human beings, and that he was juster and wiser and more prudent than all.”
                    He affirmed also “that after his baptism the Christ came down into him in the
                    form of a dove from the Lord, who is above all, and that then he proclaimed the
                    unknown Father and performed miracles, but towards the end the Christ flew away
                    from Jesus, and that Jesus suffered and was raised up, but that the Christ
                    remained impassible, being spiritual.” The same information is given in the
                    treatise <hi rend="italic">The Refutation of Heresies,</hi> first ascribed to
                    Origen, and now to Hippolytus (lib. vii. c. 33), in the very words of Irenaeus,
                    and the writer repeats it in his summary (x. 21), with the addition that it was
                    by an angelic power that the world was made. Irenaeus (iii. xi. 7, see also
                    Jerome, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Viris</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >III.</hi> c. 9) also informs us that the gospel of St John contained statements
                    which were specially intended to remove the error of Cerinthus, and of the
                    Nicolaitanes who held the opinion before him, that the maker of the world and
                    the supreme God were different.</p>
                <p>From Caius the Roman presbyter our information is as follows. “Cerinthus, by
                    means of revelations which pretend to be written by a great apostle, speaking
                    falsely, introduces wonders which he speaks of as if they had been shown to him
                    by angels, saying that after the resurrection the kingdom of Christ was to be on
                    earth, and that again men in bodily form would live in Jerusalem and be subject
                    to lusts and pleasures. And being an enemy to the Scriptures, and wishing to
                    lead astray, he affirms that a thousand years will be spent in marriage
                    feasting” (Eus. <hi rend="italic">Hist. Eccl.</hi> iii. 28). It is plain from
                    this passage that Caius derived his opinion of the character of the millennium
                    in which Cerinthus believed from the revelations which Cerinthus wrote in the
                    name of a great apostle. Dionysius, bishop of Alexandria, affirms that some
                    maintained that the Apocalypse was not the production of the apostle John, not
                    even of a saint, but of Cerinthus, who established the sect called Cerinthian
                    from him, and who wished to give a respectable name to his own fiction (Eus. <hi
                    rend="italic">Hist. Ecd.</hi> vii. 25). The context proves conclusively that
                    Dionysius refers specially to Caius, whose words he partly quotes <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n358/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0358-0347"/> and partly paraphrases. The paraphrase shows how
                    easy it is to invent a discreditable character and doctrine for a heretic. He
                    says that Cerinthus believed “that the kingdom of Christ would be on earth, and
                    that being fond of the body and altogether carnal, he dreamt that he would revel
                    in these delights for which he longed—the satisfaction of the stomach and the
                    parts below it, that is. in foods, and drinks, and marriages, and the means by
                    which he thought that he could more decently procure these, namely, feasts and
                    sacrifices and the slaying of victims.” It is barely possible that Dionysius may
                    have had access to other sources of information than the statement of Caius, but
                    the probability is all on the other side. He was a determined antagonist of
                    millenarianism, and was prepared to see gross sensuality in the adherents of the
                    doctrine; but there is no good evidence that Cerinthus was sensual. We cannot
                    even affirm that he was a millenarian, for Caius evidently formed his opinion on
                    this matter in consequence of his belief that Cerinthus wrote the Revelation
                    ascribed to St John—a belief which others seem to have shared with him (Epiph.
                    <hi rend="italic">Haer.</hi> li., 3).</p>
                <p>Our third source is not extant in its original form, but is to be traced in
                    Epiphanius <hi rend="italic">(Haer.</hi> xxviii.), and in almost all the Latin
                    writers on heresy contained in Oehler’s first volume of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Corpus Hoeresiologicum,</hi> but most markedly in Philastrius (c. 36) and
                    Pseudo-Augustinus (c. 8). According to Irenaeus, Cerinthus carefully
                    distinguished between the historical man Jesus and the aeon Christ. This source
                    evidently represented Jesus and Christ as the same, and it was the descent of
                    the Holy Ghost after his baptism that rendered Jesus Christ capable of
                    performing miracles. Jesus Christ was the son of Joseph and Mary, and was for
                    the short time of his ministry miraculously endowed through the descent of the
                    Holy Ghost, but the Holy Ghost left him before he suffered, and he died and did
                    not rise again, but will rise again when the general resurrection takes
                    place.</p>
                <p>Cerinthus, according to these authorities, affirmed that the world was made by
                    angels, and that the law and the prophets were given by one of the angels who
                    made the world. Philastrius thus sums up the other features of the heresy. “He
                    taught circumcision and the observance of the Sabbath . . . He does not receive
                    the apostle Paul, he honours Judas the traitor, he receives the gospel according
                    to Matthew, he despises three gospels, he rejects the Acts of the Apostles, he
                    blasphemes the blessed martyrs.” Epiphanius makes him accept only a portion of
                    the gospel of St Matthew. He thinks that he was one of those Judaic Christians
                    referred to in Acts xv. 24, that he also found fault with the apostle Peter for
                    going to Cornelius (Acts xi. 3) and created a commotion against Paul in
                    connection with Titus (Acts xxi. 28), and that St Paul alludes to a practice of
                    Cerinthians in noticing baptism for the dead.</p>
                <p>Most of these statements are probably incorrect, and some of them are to be
                    rejected without hesitation for chronological reasons. Some of the writers
                    mention a Merinthus, who was either the same as Cerinthus or was confounded with
                    him. It is likely that this is not the only confusion in these accounts, and we
                    may well doubt whether either Justin or Hippolytus could be the source from
                    which they were drawn, or that the account contained in it was more accurate
                    than that of Irenaeus.</p>
                <p>Cerinthus is mentioned in nearly all the historians of early Christianity, but
                    special reference may be made to Lardner’s works, vol. viii. (Kippis’s edition);
                    ManseΓs <hi rend="italic">Gnostic Heresies</hi> (London, 1875); Lipsius’s
                    “Gnosticismus,” in Erseh and Graber, p. 257; his <hi rend="italic">Zur
                    Quellenkritik des Epiphanias</hi> (Vienna, 1865), p. 115, and his <hi
                    rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Quellen der ältesten
                    Ketzergeschichte</hi> (Leipsic, 1875), p. 39; and Adolf Harnack’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Zur Quellenkritik der Geschichte des Gnosticismus</hi> (Leipsic,
                    1873), p. 46. (J. D.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
