<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0826-0813-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CLARKSON, Thomas (9th edition, volume 5, page
                    813)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825039">Bachelors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166263">Vices</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933481">Foxes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206005">Guinea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n826/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CLARKSON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi></label>
                    (1760-1846), was born on the 28th March 1760, at Wisbeach, in Cambridgeshire,
                    where his father was head-master of the free grammar school. He was educated at
                    St Paul’s School and at St John’s College, Cambridge. Having taken the first
                    place among the middle bachelors as Latin essayist, he succeeded in 1785 in
                    gaining a similar honour among the senior bachelors. The subject appointed by
                    the vice-chancellor, Dr Peckhard, was one in which he was himself deeply
                    interested— <hi rend="italic">Anne</hi><hi rend="italic">liceat invitos</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">servitutem</hi><hi rend="italic">dare
                    ì</hi> (Is it right to make men slaves against their will?) In preparing for
                    this essay Clarkson consulted a number of works on African slavery, of which the
                    chief was Benezet’s <hi rend="italic">Historical Survey of New Guinea</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> and the atrocities of which he read affected him so deeply
                    that he determined to devote all his energies to effect the abolition of the
                    slave trade, and gave up his intention of entering the church. His first measure
                    was to publish, with additions, an English translation of his prizeessay (June
                    1786). He then commenced to search in all quarters for information concerning
                    slavery. He soon discovered that the cause had already been taken up to some
                    extent by others, most of whom belonged to the Society of Friends, and among the
                    chief of whom were William Dillwyn, Joseph Wood, and Granville Sharp. With the
                    aid of these gentlemen, a committee of twelve was formed in May 1787 to do all
                    that was possible to effect the abolition of the slave trade. Meanwhile Clarkson
                    had also gained the sympathy of Wilberforce, Whitbread, Sturge, and several
                    other men of influence. Travelling from port to port, he now commenced to
                    collect a large mass of evidence; and much of it was embodied in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Summary View of the Slave Trade, and the Probable Consequences of
                    its Abolition,</hi> which, with a number of other anti-slavery tracts, was
                    published by the committee. Pitt, Grenville, Fox, and Burke looked favourably on
                    the movement; in May 1788 Pitt introduced a parliamentary discussion on the
                    subject, and Sir W. Dolben brought forward a bill providing that the number of
                    slaves carried in a vessel should be proportional to its tonnage. A number of
                    Liverpool and Bristol merchants obtained permission from the House to be heard
                    by council against the bill, but on the 18th June it passed the Commons. Soon
                    after Clarkson published an <hi rend="italic">Essay on the Impolicy of the Slave
                    Trade;</hi> and for two months he was continuously engaged in travelling that he
                    might meet men who were personally acquainted with the facts of the trade. From
                    their lips he collected a considerable amount of evidence; but only nine could
                    be prevailed upon to promise to appear before the privy council. Meanwhile other
                    witnesses had been obtained by Wilberforce and the committee, and on the 12th
                    May 1789 the former led a debate on the subject in the House of Commons, in
                    which he was seconded by Burke and supported by Pitt and Fox. It was now the
                    beginning of the French Revolution, and in the hope that he might arouse the
                    French to sweep away slavery with other abuses, Clarkson crossed to Paris, where
                    he remained six months. He found Necker head of the Government, and obtained
                    from him some sympathy but little help. Mirabeau, however, with his assistance,
                    prepared a speech against slavery, to be delivered before the National Assembly,
                    and the Marquis de la Fayette entered enthusiastically into his views. During
                    this visit Clarkson also met a deputation of negroes from St Domingo, who had
                    come to France to present a petition to the National Assembly, desiring to be
                    placed on an equal footing with the whites; but the storm of the Revolution
                    permitted no substantial success to be achieved. Soon after his return home he
                    engaged in a search, the apparent hopelessness of which finely displays his
                    unshrinking laboriousness and his passionate enthusiasm. He desired to find some
                    one who had himself witnessed the capture of the negroes in Africa; and a friend
                    having met by chance a man-of-war’s-man who had done so, Clarkson, though
                    ignorant both of the name and of the residence of the sailor, at once set out in
                    search of him, and after many disappointments actually discovered him. His last
                    tour was undertaken in order to form anti-slavery committees in all the
                    principal towns. At length, in the autumn of 1794, his health, which had long
                    been impaired by his uninterrupted exertions, gave way, and he was obliged to
                    cease active work. He did not, however, entirely give up the cause. At the
                    suggestion of Wilberforce and others, he occupied his time in writing a <hi
                    rend="italic">History of the Abolition of the Slave Trade,</hi> which appeared
                    in 1808. In 1818 he had an interview at Paris with the emperor of Russia, to
                    whom he presented an address against the negro slave trade. He again visited the
                    emperor during the conference of the European monarchs which was held at
                    Aix-la-Chapelle, and, through him, the address was also presented to the emperor
                    of Austria and the king of Prussia. In 1823, the slave trade having been
                    abolished in 1807, the Anti-Slavery Society was formed, and Clarkson was one of
                    its vice-presidents. He was for some time blind from cataract; but several years
                    before his death his sight was restored. He died at the age of eighty-six, at
                    his patrimonial house, Playford Hall, Suffolk.</p>
                <p>Besides the works already mentioned, he published <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n827/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0827-0814"/> the <hi rend="italic">Portraiture of
                    Quakerism</hi> (1806), <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of William Penn</hi> (1813),
                    <hi rend="italic">Researches, Antediluvian, Patriarchal, and Historical</hi>
                    (1836), intended as a history of the interference of Providence for man’s
                    spiritual good, and <hi rend="italic">Strictures</hi> on several of the remarks
                    concerning himself made in the <hi rend="italic">Life of Wilberforce,</hi> in
                    which his claim as originator of the anti-slavery movement is denied. See his
                    <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> by Thomas Elmes and Thomas Taylor.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
