<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0230-0219-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CATECHISM (9th edition, volume 5, page 219)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z99h">Age</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800130">Age</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800293">Aging</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025507">Monks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n230/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CATECHISM</label>, a word which originally signified
                    instruction by word of mouth, being derived from the Greek <hi rend="italic"
                    >κατηχίω.</hi> But, as it was necessarily by oral instruction that, in the early
                    church, catechumens (or converts in preparation for baptism) were instructed in
                    the essential doctrines of Christianity, and as the catechist usually sought to
                    produce clear comprehension by means of questioning, several distinct uses of
                    the word have sprung from its original employment, and it has come to
                    signify—(1) instruction by means of question and answer; (2) elementary
                    instruction, whether oral or written, in any branch of knowledge; and (3), in
                    common language, a book of elementary instruction by means of question and
                    answer,— either secular, as, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> the science catechisms
                    of the Middle Ages, or, as usually, religious.</p>
                <p>Catechetical instruction was doubtless common among the ancient Jews, and the
                    modern Jews possess several catechisms. The earliest with which we are
                    acquainted are the <hi rend="italic">Thirteen Articles of Belief</hi> of the
                    famous Maimonides, which belongs to the 12th century, and Rabbi Levi’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Book of Education,</hi> which belongs to the 13th. Among those
                    used at the present day in England may be mentioned Leser’s and Pixiotto’s.</p>
                <p>The most important and authoritative of the catechisms of the Roman Catholic
                    Church is that of the Council of Trent, which was published in 1566. It was
                    prepared under the superintendance of the archbishop of Milan, by Leonardo
                    Marini, Francisco Fureiro, Aegidius Foscorari, and Mugio Calini; and the style
                    was polished by Pogianus. It is not a catechism in the ordinary sense, for it is
                    not in the interrogative form, and it can scarcely be called elementary. It is,
                    in fact, a very careful and complete system of Roman Catholic doctrine,
                    extending over 500 8vo pages of closely-printed Latin. By command of the
                    council, it was translated into French, German, Spanish, and Italian, and there
                    is also an English version. The earliest of the catechisms of this church appear
                    to be that of Kero, a monk of St Gall, who lived in the 8th century, and that
                    which is ascribed to Otfried, a monk of Weissen burg of the 9th century. Others
                    worthy of mention are the <hi rend="italic">Summa</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Doctrinarum</hi> of Peter Canisius, which was authorized in 1566; that of
                    Bellarmine (1603), and that of Bossuet (1687). In 1870, the Oecumenical Council
                    recommended the general use of the <hi rend="italic">Schema de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Parvo,</hi> a small catechism, which is little more than an
                    abstract of Bellarmine’s.</p>
                <p>Catechisms were also very common among the Christian sects which, during the
                    Middle Ages, opposed themselves to the dominant church, as the Albigenses and
                    the Wickliffites.</p>
                <p>The Greek Church has two principal catechisms, the earlier of which is that of
                    Peter Mogilas, patriarch of Kieff, which was published in 1542, and sanctioned
                    by the church in 1572. The other is that of Plato, patriarch of Moscow, of which
                    an abstract has been made for purposes of education. This work is divided into
                    two parts, of which the first treats of natural religion, the second of
                    revealed.</p>
                <p>Of the larger Protestant sects, each has a separate catechism. The Lutherans are
                    represented by the two smaller catechisms of their founder, published in 1520
                    and 1529, and by his larger catechism, published in the latter year. In
                    Switzerland, France, the Low Countries, Hungary, and Scotland, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Geneva Catechism</hi> of Calvin (1536) was for some time the
                    standard of the Reformed Church. The <hi rend="italic">Heidelberg</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Catechism,</hi> which appeared in 1563, compiled' by Caspar
                    Olevian and Zacharias Ursinus, and revised by the Synod of Dort, became the
                    standard of the Swiss Church; and upon it was founded the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Zurich Catechism</hi> (1639). ASocinian catechism appeared at Rakov in
                    1574.</p>
                <p>The first prayer-book of Edward VI., published in the year 1549, contained what
                    now forms the first part of the catechism of the English Church»</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n231/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0231-0220"/>
                <p>ĭt consists of no more than two or three pages, and contains only the Ten
                    Commandments, the Creed, the Lord’s Prayer, and an expression of the doctrine of
                    baptism held by the English Church. In the reign of James I. an explanation of
                    the Anglican doctrine of the sacraments was added by Bishop Overall.</p>
                <p>The first catechism produced by the Scottish Presbyterians was that known as
                    Craig’s, which was laid before the General Assembly in 1592. It embodied, in
                    twelve chapters, the Calvinistic doctrine of the church with regard to original
                    sin, redemption, the sacraments, and ecclesiastical discipline; and after each
                    chapter was a number of questions and answers. This catechism, together with
                    some of those used on the Continent, served the British Presbyterians till 1647.
                    In that year the Westminster Assembly of Divines appointed committees to draw up
                    the famous <hi rend="italic">Larger</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Shorter
                    Catechisms.</hi></p>
                <p>Besides these catechisms, which profess to be the symbols of various churches, a
                    large number of private catechisms have been published. In the English Church
                    the most important are Cranmer’s and Noel’s (1570). Among the English Protestant
                    dissenters, who, of course, do not possess an authoritative catechism, there
                    have been several, of which the most famous are those of Dr Watts. A
                    considerable number have also been produced by German theologians; but many of
                    the works which they have published under the name have no claim to it
                    whatever.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
