<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0905-0444-0433-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHARTISM (9th edition, volume 5, page 433)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:852538">Charters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852540">Chartism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1092555">Reformation</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1092647">Reformers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1032344">Names</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sf3s">Charters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698d4f">Chartism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086357g">Stars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bv7b36b">Reformers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wk9g">Reformation</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gh4j">Names</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n444/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CHARTISM</label> was a movement for radical reform in English
                    politics, which originated in 1838, reached its culminating point in 1848, and
                    collapsed the same year; it took its name from the “People’s Charter” or
                    “National Charter,” the document in which the scheme of reform was embodied. The
                    Reform Bill of 1832 left a large class of the population, especially the
                    working-men, dissatisfied. Accordingly, in 1838, after an unsuccessful attempt
                    to initiate a scheme of more radical reform in the House of Commons, six of the
                    most advanced members of the House had a consultation <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit05newyrich/page/n445/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0905-0445-0434"/> with the deputies of the “Working-men’s
                    Association,” the result being the appearance of the People’s Charter, which
                    embodied in the six following points the programme of their party:—(1) annual
                    parliaments; (2) universal suffrage; (3) vote by ballot; (4) abolition of the
                    property qualification for membership of the House of Commons; (5) payment of
                    members; (6) equal electoral districts. The most influential of the six members
                    of the House who took part in the drawing up of the charter was O’Connell, and
                    the methods adopted for the propagation of their views were those practised by
                    the great agitator with such success. Monster meetings were held, at which
                    seditious language was occasionally spoken, and slight collisions with the
                    military took place. Petitions of enormous size, signed in great part with
                    fictitious names, were presented to Parliament; and a great many newspapers were
                    started, of which the <hi rend="italic">Northern Star,</hi> conducted by Feargus
                    O’Connor, the active leader of the movement, had a circulation of 50,000. In
                    1840 the Chartist movement was still further organized by the inauguration at
                    Manchester of the National Charter Association, which rapidly became powerful,
                    being the head of about 400 sister societies, which are said to have numbered
                    40,000 members. Some time after, efforts were made towards a coalition with the
                    more moderate radicals, but these failed; and a land scheme was started by
                    O’Connor, which prospered for a few years. In 1844 the fanatical spirit of some
                    of the leaders was only too well illustrated by their attitude towards the
                    Anti-Corn-Law League. O’Connor, especially, entered into a public controversy
                    with Cobden and Bright, in which he was worsted; and he even endeavoured to
                    defeat the purpose of the League. But it was not till 1848, during a season of
                    great suffering among the working classes, and under the influence of the
                    revolution at Paris, that the real strength of the Chartist movement was
                    discovered, and the prevalent discontent became known. Early in March
                    disturbances occurred in Glasgow which required the intervention of the
                    military, while in the manufacturing districts all over the West of Scotland the
                    operatives were ready to rise, in the event of the main movement succeeding.
                    Some agitation, too, took place in Edinburgh and in Manchester, but of a milder
                    nature; in fact, while there was a real and wide-spread discontent, men were
                    indisposed to resort to decided measures. The principal scene of intended
                    Chartist demonstration was London. An enormous gathering of half a million was
                    announced for the 10th April on Kennington Common, from which they were to march
                    on the Houses of Parliament to present a petition signed by nearly six million
                    names, in order by this imposing display of numbers to secure the enactment of
                    the six points. Probably some of the more violent members of the party thought
                    to imitate the Parisian mob by taking power entirely into their own hands. The
                    announcement of the procession excited great alarm, and the most decided
                    measures were taken by the authorities to prevent a rising. The procession was
                    forbidden. The military was called out under the command of the Duke of
                    Wellington, and by him concealed near the bridges and other points where the
                    procession might attempt to force its way. Even the Bank and other public
                    buildings were put in a state of defence, and special constables, to the number,
                    it is said, of 170,000, were enrolled, one of whom was destined shortly after to
                    be the emperor of the French. After all these gigantic preparations on both
                    sides the Chartist demonstration proved to be a very insignificant affair.
                    Instead of half a million, only about 50,000 assembled on Kennington Common, and
                    their leaders, Feargus O’Connor and Ernest Jones, shrank from the responsibility
                    of braving the authorities by conducting the procession to the Houses of
                    Parliament. The monster petition was duly presented, and scrutinized, with the
                    result that the number of signatures was found to have been grossly exaggerated,
                    and that the most unheard of falsification of names had been resorted to.
                    Thereafter the movement specially called Chartism soon died out. The return of
                    national prosperity relieved the working classes of their most pressing
                    grievances; and subseqent legislative changes have in great measure removed the
                    causes that existed for discontent among the classes which mainly supported the
                    charter.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
