<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0816-0787-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MONTFORT, Simon de, Earl of Leicester</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 16, page 787</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1133321">Stewards</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1119758">Sisters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n816/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MONTFORT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Simon de, Earl of
                    Leicester</hi></label> (<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1200- 1265), a great political
                    leader, and sometimes even referred to as the “founder of the English House of
                    Commons,” born in France about the beginning of the 13th century, was the fourth
                    and youngest son of Simon IV. de Montfort and of Alice de Montmorency. Of his
                    early life and education nothing is known, the first definitely recorded fact
                    about him being that in April 1230 he was in England and had attached himself to
                    the service of Henry III., who granted him a temporary pension of 400 marks,
                    with a promise of the earldom which his father had held.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Simon IV. de Montfort, the well-known
                    Albigensian crusader, in right of his mother, Amicia de Beaumont, sister and
                    co-heiress of Robert Fitz-Pernell, earl of Leicester, succeeded to that earldom
                    in 1204, and in 1207 was confirmed in the high stewardship of England,
                    hereditary in connexion with the title. Soon afterwards he was deprived of his
                    English possessions under some pretext, the real reason doubtless being his
                    position as captain-general of the French forces against the Albigenses (1208).
                    He received them again towards the end of John’s reign, their custody, however,
                    being committed to his nephew, the earl of Chester. The long hostility between
                    England and France during the early years of Henry III. made it practically
                    impossible for the alien De Montforts to maintain any hold upon their English
                    earldom on the death of Simon IV. in 1218; in 1231, after the peace, the eldest
                    son Anιaury (now constable of France) renounced all claim to it, thus leaving
                    the field clear to his next surviving brother Simon.</p></note> In the following
                    year he did homage for the honour of Leicester, and in 1232 the king confirmed
                    to him all the land with appurtenances which had belonged to the late earl in
                    England. But, though thus formally admitted to the ranks of the English
                    baronage, he did not for several years succeed in making way against the strong
                    dislike in which “aliens” were now held, and until 1236 most of his time was
                    spent, in considerable poverty, abroad. In that year, however, he attended the
                    king’s marriage to Eleanor of Provence as lord high steward, and thenceforward
                    began to take part in the business of the royal council. Handsome, talented, and
                    brave, he gained the love of Eleanor, widow of the earl of Pembroke, and sister
                    of the king, to whom he was privately married at Westminster on 7th January
                    1238, Henry himself giving away the bride. When the fact became known, the
                    indignation of the baronage and of the people had almost broken out in open
                    rebellion, and, after Simon had with difficulty averted this by propitiating his
                    brother-in-law, Richard, earl of Cornwall, he found it necessary to go to Rome
                    to meet the objections which the church had raised on the ground of an alleged
                    previous vow made by Eleanor. Having succeeded in obtaining (by bribery, it
                    would seem) the papal sanction to his marriage, he returned to England in
                    October, and early next year, still in the enjoyment of the royal favour, he had
                    the earldom of Leicester formally conferred upon him in presence of the
                    assembled barons. In June (1239) he assisted as godfather and high steward at
                    the baptism of Prince Edward; but the machinations of his enemies were soon
                    afterwards successful in bringing about a change in the fickle humour of Henry,
                    and when Simon came back to Westminster in August to attend the churching of the
                    queen the king met him with the information that he was an excommunicated
                    person, and ordered him to leave the church.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>There is no evidence that Simon actually had been
                    excommunicated, but it seems clear that certain payments he had agreed to make
                    to the Roman curia had not been punctually attended to, and that some annoyance
                    had been in this way caused to the king. The charge of immoral relations with
                    Eleanor was probably only a conveniently coarse way of restating the
                    ecclesiastical offence for which De Montfort had already purchased
                    absolution.</p></note> Along with his wife he forthwith went into voluntary
                    exile in France; but in April 1240 he returned to England, and was received by
                    the king on a footing of at least outward friendship. Of his private and public
                    life during the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n817/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0817-0788"/> next eight years very few facts» have been
                    preserved. There is some ground for believing that he went to the Holy Land in
                    1240, and a letter is still extant in which the nobility of the kingdom of
                    Jerusalem ask Frederick II. (June 1241) to allow Simon de Montfort, earl of
                    Leicester, to act as regent till the arrival of his son Conrad. In 1242 he
                    accompanied Henry’s unsuccessful expedition to France. In the parliamentary
                    history of these years his name appears but seldom, but where he is mentioned he
                    is invariably found on the side of the people, resisting alike the arbitrary
                    wastefulness of the king and the rapacious exactions of the pope. In 1248 De
                    Montfort was appointed for six years the king’s “seneschal,” or “locum-tenens,”
                    in Gascony. In this capacity he was very inadequately supported from home with
                    either men or money; he more than once subdued the rebellious provinces, indeed,
                    but meanwhile his enemies at home gained strength and encouraged the Gascons in
                    repeated accusations and complaints against the seneschal. These resulted in
                    one-sided inquiries, but ultimately in his acquittal, and led to a demand on his
                    part for reparation, and a consequent quarrel with the king. Towards the end of
                    1252 De Montfort retired into France, where such was the reputation he enjoyed
                    as a statesman that, on the death of the queen-regent and in the absence of
                    Louis IX., he was offered the office of high steward and a place among the
                    guardians of the crown. This, however, he declined, “being unwilling to prove a
                    renegade;” and, after a partial reconciliation with Henry, he returned to
                    England in 1254. In the following year he was sent on a secret mission into
                    Scotland, and in 1257 he was one of the king’s ambassadors to France; but his
                    chief activity between 1254 and 1258, if we are to judge by the prominent place
                    he took in the revolution of the last-named year, must have been in the meetings
                    of parliament. At the Westminster parliament in April 1258 it was significantly
                    upon the earls of Gloucester and Leicester that the king’s half-brother, William
                    de Valence, laid the blame of all the evils under which the country was
                    groaning, De Montfort in particular being called by him “an old traitor and a
                    liar.” At Leicester’s suggestion the barons leagued for the defence of their
                    rights, and presented themselves armed at the meeting, which extorted the
                    appointment of the committee of twenty-four to meet at Oxford and proceed at
                    once with the reform of the realm. The Provisions of Oxford having been signed
                    (October 1258), De Montfort received the custody of the castle of Winchester,
                    where the parliament continued its session, he meanwhile apparently holding the
                    position of military commander-in-chief; and, after the removal of the barons to
                    London, he was appointed member of an embassy to Scotland. In the early part of
                    1259 he was chiefly busied with the task of adjusting the terms of a peace with
                    France, which was not settled until the end of that year. From the date of the
                    conclusion of that peace, owing to divisions in the reforming party, the king
                    began to regain his lost power, and in 1262 he felt himself strong enough to
                    repudiate the Provisions of Oxford, thus giving the signal for civil war. The
                    successes of the barons, led by De Montfort, in the west, and his victorious
                    entry into London again reduced the king to submission, but only to bring once
                    more also into prominence the divided state of Leicester’s supporters. Louis’s
                    one-sided Mise of Amiens (1264), however, rendered another appeal to arms on the
                    part of the barons inevitable, and by the victory of Lewes (14th May 1264) De
                    Montfort for the time became master of England. Taking Henry, his prisoner,
                    along with him to London, he summoned thither the parliament, which met in June,
                    and drew up the constitution or scheme of government associated with his name,
                    of which the most striking feature is the new development it gives to the
                    representative system. A still further advance in the development took place in
                    1265, when borough members, as distinguished from county members, were for the
                    first time summoned. Meanwhile troubles in the west required De Montfort’s
                    presence in the field, and, by the alliance of his rival Gloucester with Roger
                    Mortimer, as well as by the escape of Prince Edward, who put himself at the head
                    of the royalist opposition, the great parliamentary leader was placed in serious
                    straits. At Evesham, where he had halted on his march to join his son at
                    Kenilworth, he was surprised by the army of Prince Edward, and after a struggle
                    of about two hours was slain on the field of battle (4th August 1265). As
                    regards the personal character of De Montfort, it is not surprising to find that
                    contemporary opinion was divided; but of his determination, constancy, and
                    energy there can be no question, while much is revealed by the fact that, though
                    in an unauthorized way, his memory was revered in England as a saint and martyr,
                    offices were drawn up in his honour, his intercession invoked, and miraculous
                    virtues attributed to his relics. The painstaking labours of recent
                    investigators have tended to bring into clearer light the purity and nobleness
                    of purpose of Simon de Montfort as a consistent defender of the rights of the
                    governed; on the other hand, it has also become obvious that the representative
                    institutions of England, though largely helped forward by him, can hardly be
                    claimed as his creation. Thus on both sides the statement of Hume that the House
                    of Commons was planted by the inauspicious hand of this bold and artful
                    conspirator must be rejected as inconsistent with the facts.</p>
                <p>Compare <hi rend="smallcaps">England,</hi> vol. viii. p. 310 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sqq.,</hi> and see the monographs of Pauli <hi rend="italic">{Simon von
                    Montfort, Graf von Leicester,</hi><hi rend="italic">Der Schöpfer des</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Hauses</hi><hi rend="italic">der Gemeinen,</hi> Tübingen, 1867)
                    and Prothero <hi rend="italic">{The Life of</hi><hi rend="italic">Simon de
                    Montfort,</hi> 1877), and the literature there referred to.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
